第四章　白教堂[28]

/

“今天早上，阿拉贝尔和我带着他，”巴雷特小姐写道，“坐马车去维尔街办点事。跟往常一样，他跟着我们进出店里。从店里出来上马车时，他还在我脚边。我转过身便唤道：‘弗勒希。’阿拉贝尔也四处找他。可弗勒希踪影全无！就在那一瞬间，他被人从车轮底下抓走了，你明白吗？”勃朗宁先生非常明白。巴雷特小姐忘了拴狗链，弗勒希就这样被偷走了。这便是一八四六年时温波尔街及附近街区的法则。

诚然，没有任何东西可以打破温波尔街表面的稳固和安宁。体弱多病者步力所及或巴思椅能被推到之处，放眼望去，皆是四层洋楼、大玻璃窗和桃花心木大门构成的赏心悦目的景致。哪怕乘坐双驾马车，只要马车夫小心谨慎，在下午的兜风行程中也不会越过礼仪与体面的边界。然而，如果你并非病弱之人，如果你不坐双驾马车，如果你—跟很多人一样—体格健全、充满活力—喜欢步行，那么你很可能会在距离温波尔街几步之遥的地方看到各种景象，听到各种用语，闻到各种味道，甚至开始疑虑温波尔街本身的安稳。在这一时期，当托马斯·比姆斯[29]先生打算到伦敦逛逛，见到的恰是此景。他感到惊讶，事实上他深受震动。威斯敏斯特区富丽堂皇的建筑鳞次栉比，然而其后便是破败的棚屋，人们成群地挤在屋内，屋子下方便是一群群牛—“每七英尺就挤着两个人”。他自感有责任把所见公之于众。然而一个人该如何不失文雅地描述一间位于牛棚之上、合住着两三个家庭的卧室，况—这牛棚甚至没有通风设备，牛就在卧室底下遭人挤奶、屠宰和烹食？当比姆斯先生尝试这么做时，他却发现，这项任务穷尽了英语语言中的所有词语。他还是认为自己有义务把下午散步经过伦敦最具贵族气派的几个教区时的见闻如实陈述。斑疹伤寒的感染概率是如此之高，富人不会知道自己面临何种危险。对于自己在威斯敏斯特、帕丁顿及马里波恩区的所见所闻，他根本做不到三缄其口。譬如，有一幢本来属于某位贵族的老宅邸，昔日的大理石壁炉台依然存在。房间皆由木头嵌板，楼梯扶栏上皆雕刻着花，然而地板已经腐烂，墙壁上沾满了污秽，成群的衣不蔽体的男男女女栖身于此，占据了古老的宴会厅。接着他继续往前走。这块儿某个有商业头脑的建筑商将一幢老宅夷平，取而代之的是一栋偷工减料的廉价公寓。雨沿着屋顶渗入室内，风则从墙缝中钻了进去。他看见有个孩子拿着个铁罐在条鲜绿色的溪流里舀水，便问他这里的人喝不喝那溪里的水。是的，他们喝，还在里面洗澡，因为房东每周只肯供应两次水。这类景象之所以尤其令人吃惊，是因为在伦敦最安静、最文明的街区里—“最上流的教区也在所难免”—竟也能遇到此般场景。再比方说，就在巴雷特小姐卧室的后方，便是伦敦最不堪入目的贫民窟之一。肮脏败坏和体面富贵在那里交会。当然，还有些区域早已由穷人接管，无人干扰。在白教堂区，或托特纳姆考特路下面的那块三角地带，几个世纪以来，贫穷、罪恶与苦难一直在那里滋长繁衍、生生不息，无人干预。又好比圣贾尔斯区里大量密集的老房子，“俨然是罪犯的流放地，是一座不折不扣的贫民都市”。这流放地被称为“白嘴鸦”，称呼十分恰当，因为贫民们就是这般聚集在一起的。区内人挤人，户户相叠，仿佛黑压压地挤在树梢上的一群白嘴鸦。只不过这里的房子并非树木建成，甚至都不再是房子了。它们是由砖块砌成的牢房，由流满了脏污的巷道分隔开来。从早到晚，衣衫不整的各路人马在小巷里熙来攘往；入夜后，白天赴伦敦西区讨生活的盗贼、乞丐和娼妓又源源不断地涌回区内。警方对此束手无策。过路行人只能加快脚步，不敢稍停，或许只会和比姆斯先生一样，在一堆旁征博引、托词规避和委婉客气的辞藻中悄悄暗示天下未必像理想中那样处处太平。霍乱有可能降临，而—即便有霍乱降临的征兆，也不至于这般躲闪。

不过那个征兆在一八四六年的夏天尚未出现。对于居住在温波尔街及附近街区的人来说，确保安全的唯一方法便是决不越雷池一步，而—带狗出门一定得系狗链。如果你跟巴雷特小姐一样一时疏忽，那就只好付出代价，正像巴雷特小姐此刻必须付出代价一样。温波尔街与圣贾尔斯区比邻而居的法则简单明了：圣贾尔斯区尽管偷，温波尔街必须乖乖付钱。因此，阿拉贝尔立刻“开始安慰我，告诉我顶多花十英镑，肯定能把他赎回来”。据估计，十英镑差不多是泰勒先生给可卡犬开的价。泰勒先生是这个地区的地头蛇，温波尔街的贵妇人只要一丢了狗，就会去找泰勒先生。由他开个价码，狗主人赶紧付钱，如果不付，几天之后温波尔街便会收到一个牛皮纸袋，里面装着狗头和狗爪—至少这是街坊上某位女士企图跟泰勒先生讨价还价之后的下场。不过巴雷特小姐当然愿意付钱，一回家便告知了兄弟亨利。亨利当天下午去见了泰勒先生，发现泰勒先生“坐在一间挂了油画的房间里抽雪茄”—据说泰勒先生仅靠温波尔街的狗，年收入便达两千到三千英镑。泰勒先生一口答应出面和他的“社区”交涉，狗第二天就会归还。这件事很伤脑筋，尤其眼下她正急着用钱，所以更让人恼火；可要是在一八四六年忘记给自己的狗拴狗链，这就是不可避免的后果！

但是对弗勒希，情况却很不一样。巴雷特小姐想到，弗勒希“并不知道我们可以把他赎回来”；他从来没有精通过人类社会的游戏法则。“这下他肯定要哭号一整个晚上了，我很了解他。”九月一日星期二的下午，巴雷特小姐在给勃朗宁写信时这样说道。就在巴雷特小姐给勃朗宁写信的同时，弗勒希正经历着他这辈子最恐怖的遭遇。他困惑极了，不明究竟，前一秒钟还在维尔街，置身于彩缎蕾丝之间，下一秒便整个儿地栽进布袋里，颠颠簸簸地被拎着迅速穿过几条街，最后终于被倒了出来—倒在这里！他发现自己在一片漆黑之中，又冷又湿。头晕脑涨过去之后，他渐渐分辨出自己身处一间低矮阴暗的房间—几把破椅子，一张破烂的床垫。接着有人捉住他的一条腿，把他紧紧拴在某样东西上。有什么东西趴在地板上—是人是兽，他辨别不出。巨大的靴子和曳地的长裙不断地进进出出，苍蝇嗡嗡嗡地围着地上几片腐烂的臭肉。孩子们从黑暗的角落里爬出来，拧他的耳朵。他哀号一声，他的脑袋挨了重重的一击。他靠着墙蜷缩在只有几英寸的潮湿砖块上。这会儿，他能看见地板上挤满了形形色色的动物：一群狗你争我抢地嘶咬着一根腐臭的骨头，他们瘦得肋骨都快戳破肚皮了—他们饥不择食、又脏又病、毛发蓬乱。然而弗勒希看得出来，其实他们全都是血统最高贵的犬类，是系狗链的狗，是仆役养的狗—就像他自己一样。

他趴在那儿，连哼都不敢哼一声，一小时接着一小时过去了。渴是他最大的煎熬。他舔了一口身旁水桶里那深绿色的水，这一舔让他作起呕来，他宁愿渴死也不会再喝第二口。可是一只威风高贵的灵缇正贪婪地喝个不停。每次房门被踢开，他都抬头看：巴雷特小姐—是巴雷特小姐吗？她终于来了吗？但进来的是一个毛发浓密的恶棍，他把动物们全踢到旁边，踉踉跄跄地走到一把破椅子前，瘫坐了下去。然后夜色愈来愈浓，他几乎分辨不清地板上、床垫上、破椅子上都是些什么东西。有人将一小截蜡烛插在壁炉架上。外边的排水沟里燃着一团火。借着那团闪烁不定的微弱火光，弗勒希能看到从窗外经过的可怕脸庞不怀好意地睥睨着屋内。然后他们进到屋来，本来就满满当当的小房间愈加拥挤，他只好缩成一团，更加紧贴着墙趴着。这群可怕的怪物—有些衣衫褴褛，有些涂满胭脂、身插羽毛—要么蹲在地上，要么弓背围坐在桌旁。他们喝起酒来，不时恶言相向，拳脚相对。从扔到地板上的口袋里滚出更多的狗—小型宠物犬、塞特犬、指示犬……个个脖子都还套着项圈。还有一只巨大的凤头鹦鹉，一边振翅疾飞，从一个角落冲向另一个角落，一边尖叫着：“漂亮宝莉！漂亮宝莉！”那口音足以吓坏它的女主人，一位住在梅达韦尔区的寡妇。接下来女人们也打开了口袋，手镯、戒指和胸针倒了满桌，这些首饰跟弗勒希看巴雷特小姐及亨丽埃塔小姐戴的那些一样。那群牛鬼蛇神伸出爪子在首饰堆里乱抓，咒骂着，争吵着。狗儿乱吠，孩子们尖叫，色彩斑斓的凤头鹦鹉（温波尔街的一扇窗子里挂有鸟笼，弗勒希常在其中看到类似的一只鸟）也厉声叫着：“漂亮宝莉！漂亮宝莉！”一声急过一声，直到被一只忽然飞过来的拖鞋打中，它才住了口，狂乱地拍击着那对带有黄色斑点的鸽灰色大翅膀。于是蜡烛突然一歪，倒了下来，房里一片漆黑。屋里也越来越热，那气味、那热度让人难以忍受。弗勒希的鼻子火烧火燎，皮毛抽搐起来。可是巴雷特小姐还是没有来。

巴雷特小姐躺在她位于温波尔街的沙发上。她很恼火，又很担忧，但并没有特别紧张。弗勒希当然会遭点罪，他会整夜哀号吠叫，不过只是几个小时的事情。泰勒先生会开个价，她只要照付，弗勒希就会被归还了。

九月二日星期三，白教堂区的贫民窟里晨曦微露。七零八落的玻璃窗渐渐变成灰色。光线爬上仰天躺在地板上的众多恶棍那毛发浓厚的脸上。弗勒希从遮蔽双眼的迷离之境中醒来，再一次面对现实。此刻眼前的一切便是现实—这个房间，这些恶棍，这群哀号着、乱咬着、被拴牢的狗，这片黑暗，这股潮湿。就在昨天，他还跟着高贵的女士们置身于彩缎环绕的商店里，可那是真的吗？温波尔街这个地方又真的存在吗？真有那么一个房间吗？那个房间里摆着盛满清水的紫色罐子，他曾经趴在那个房间的软垫上，还被赏过一块烤得恰好的鸡翅膀，他还出于嫉妒和愤怒咬了一位戴黄手套的男士，这样的房间真的有过吗？那样的生活与感情飘远了，消解了，变得虚幻起来。

在这里，光线穿过飞扬的尘土透进来，一个女人吃力地从一团麻袋里爬起来，跌跌撞撞地走出去拿啤酒。酗酒与咒骂再度开始。一个胖女人揪住弗勒希的两只耳朵，把他拎了起来，捅戳他的肋骨，拿他开了一个恶心的玩笑。她又把他扔回地上，引来众人爆笑。门被踢开又砰地关上。他每回都会抬头观望。是威尔逊吗？有没有可能是勃朗宁先生，或巴雷特小姐？但不是！只是另一个贼，另一个杀人犯。仅仅瞅一眼那些曳地的长裙，那些粗硬的靴子，他就愈加往角落里缩。有一次，有人朝他丢过来一根骨头，他试着去啃，但他的牙齿咬不动硬得像石头似的肉，那股恶臭也让他作呕。他更加口渴了，不得不舔舔从桶里洒出来的绿水。星期三慢慢过去，趴在破木地板上的他觉得越来越热，越来越渴，全身越来越酸痛，所有感受全都搅和在了一起。他对发生了什么也漠不关心，唯有门被打开时，他才会抬起头来看。可惜，每次都不是巴雷特小姐。

躺在温波尔街家里沙发上的巴雷特小姐愈加焦虑起来。显然事情进展多有不顺。泰勒答应过星期三下午到白教堂区去跟他的“社区”交涉。但星期三下午、星期三晚上都已过去，泰勒一直没有现身。她估摸这大概只是意味着价码抬高了—碰上这个节骨眼，实在很麻烦。然而，她当然还是要照付，“我不能没有弗勒希，你知道的。”她写信跟勃朗宁先生说，“我不能冒任何风险去讨价还价。”于是，她继续躺在沙发上一边写信给勃朗宁，一边竖着耳朵等待敲门声。但是只有威尔逊前来送信，前来送热水。上床睡觉时间都到了，弗勒希还没有归来。

九月三日星期四，白教堂区东方欲晓。那扇门开了又关。趴在弗勒希身边哼唧了整个晚上的红色塞特犬被一个穿鼠皮背心的恶汉一把抱走了—命运会是如何呢？被宰杀和存活于此，哪一种更幸运？这般苟活与那样死掉，哪一样更糟？喧嚣嘈杂、又饿又渴、臭气熏天—弗勒希想起自己曾经非常讨厌古龙水的味道—这一切迅速抹去了任何清醒的意念，驱走了所有的欲望。往昔的记忆碎片开始在他脑海里翻腾。那是年老的米特福德博士在田野里高声呼唤的声音吗？那是克伦哈波克在门口跟面包师傅说长道短吗？屋子里一阵嘎吱声，他还以为那是米特福德小姐捆扎一束天竺葵发出的声响。可那只是风—因为今天风雨交加—吹打着糊在破窗框上的牛皮纸；那只是阴沟里的醉鬼在胡言乱语；那只是角落里的老太婆一边在火上用平底锅烤鲱鱼，一边咕咕哝哝个不停。他被遗忘了，他被抛弃了。不会有人来救他，不会有人跟他说话—鹦鹉大叫着：“漂亮宝莉！漂亮宝莉！”而金丝雀没完没了地发出愚蠢的啁啾。

夜色再一次笼罩室内，托盘上竖起蜡烛，室外黯淡的光线闪烁不定。扛着布袋的凶恶之徒和涂脂抹粉的俗艳女人成群结队、拖拖拉拉地从门口进到屋里，纷纷栽倒在破床破桌上。又一个夜晚的黑暗降临在白教堂区。雨水持续而规律地从屋顶的一个漏洞滴下来，滴答滴答敲击着摆在下面接水的水桶。巴雷特小姐没有出现。

星期四，温波尔街晨光熹微，却不见弗勒希的踪影—也没有泰勒先生的消息。巴雷特小姐惊恐万分，四下打听。她把兄弟亨利叫来仔细盘问，这才发现被他给骗了。“魔头”泰勒前天晚上如约前来，并给出了条件：给“社区”六个几尼，再付他半个几尼。可是亨利没有告诉她，却禀报了巴雷特先生，结果当然是巴雷特先生吩咐亨利不许给钱，也不许向她透露这次会面。巴雷特小姐“极为恼怒”，恳求亨利立刻去找泰勒先生，付钱给他。亨利拒绝了，并“把爸爸搬出来做挡箭牌”。但这个时候把爸爸搬出来有什么用，她抗议道。他们在这里说爸爸如何如何的同时，弗勒希可能就被宰掉了。她下定决心，如果亨利不肯去，那她就自己去：“……如果他们不照我的话做，明天一早我就亲自去把弗勒希接回来。”她在信中如是告诉勃朗宁先生。

然而，巴雷特小姐发现此事说来容易做起来难。她去接弗勒希，就跟弗勒希回到她身边一样艰难，整条温波尔街都在跟她对着干。弗勒希被偷、泰勒索求赎金这件事现在已是尽人皆知。温波尔街坚决表明立场，反对白教堂区。失明的博伊德先生传话过来，表示他认为支付赎金将是“一桩可怕的罪行”。她的父亲及兄弟都联合起来反对她，—为了维护他们那个阶层的利益，出卖什么都在所不惜。可糟糕的是—尤其糟糕的是—勃朗宁先生凭借他的影响力、口才、学养和逻辑，选择站在温波尔街，而不是弗勒希一边。他写道：倘若巴雷特小姐对泰勒屈服，不啻于对暴政屈服，对敲诈勒索者让步，她在助长邪恶压倒正义，助力恶行侵害无辜。倘若她满足了泰勒的要求，“……那些没有足够的钱支付赎金的穷困的狗主人，又该如何是好”？他的想象力大迸发，他想象如果泰勒哪怕只问他要五先令的赎金，他会怎么说。他会说：“‘你’必须对你那帮走狗的所作所为负责！我重申：‘你’别跟我说些什么砍狗头剁狗爪的废话。就像我实实在在地站在你眼前跟你说话一样，我将实实在在地穷毕生之力来打倒你，打倒你所代表的恶势力；我将实实在在地想尽办法揭发你和你的同谋共犯，送你们上绝路—我现在已经发现了‘你’，我再也不会放过……”如果勃朗宁先生有幸见到泰勒先生的话，他就准备这样当面回应泰勒。事实上，他意犹未尽，在同一个星期四下午赶上稍晚的邮车，又送来了第二封信，信里说：“……想到各阶层的压迫者在发现沉默弱者的秘密之后，是如何随心所欲、无所不用其极地操纵宰控他们时，真是让人毛骨悚然。”他并不是责备巴雷特小姐—对他而言，她所做的一切，没有一件不是完美的，没有一件是不可接受的。只是，他在星期五早晨继续写道：“……我认为这是令人惋惜的懦弱表现……”倘若她助长了泰勒的偷狗行为，便是在助长巴纳德·格雷戈里[30]盗取德行的行径。所以，对于那些被巴纳德·格雷戈里一类勒索之徒从名录上挑中，遭到恣意抹黑而刎颈自尽或逃亡国外的可怜虫，她也负有间接责任。“其实何必对世上最浅显易懂的道理发上这样一通陈词滥调呢？”就这样，勃朗宁先生每天在伦敦新十字区振振有词地写满两封信，并送过来。

巴雷特小姐躺在沙发上读那些信。让步本该是一件多么容易的事—说一句“在我看来你的见解比一百只可卡犬更有价值”本该是一件很容易的事。她大可往枕头上一靠，叹口气说：“我只是一名弱女子，对法律和正义一窍不通，你替我做决定吧！”这该多么容易啊。只要她拒付赎金，只要她反抗泰勒和以他为首的“社区”，那么即使弗勒希被杀，即使那可怕的包裹送到，被她打开，然后掉出他的脑袋和脚爪，罗伯特·勃朗宁也会站在她身边，向她保证她做了正确的事并赢得他的尊敬。可巴雷特小姐就是不甘示弱，她拿起笔，反驳罗伯特·勃朗宁。这都很有道理，她写道，引用多恩[31]的话、举格雷戈里为例，并想象自己正义凛然地回答泰勒先生—如果泰勒攻击的是她，如果格雷戈里诋毁的是她的名誉，她也会这么做—只要他们敢！可是，倘若那一群盗贼绑架的是她，倘若落在他们手里的是她，他们威胁要割掉她的耳朵并邮寄到新十字区，勃朗宁先生会怎么做呢？不管他会作何反应，反正她心意已决。弗勒希孤立无助，她有义务去救他。“可是弗勒希，可怜的弗勒希，他如此忠诚地爱我，我难道有权牺牲无辜的他，就为了表示我反对人世间如泰勒先生之流的罪恶吗？”不论勃朗宁先生可能会说什么，她都要去救弗勒希，哪怕她必须深入白教堂的虎穴去接他，哪怕罗伯特·勃朗宁因此而鄙夷她。

于是，星期六那天，她开始穿衣打扮，而勃朗宁先生的信就展开着摆在她面前的桌上。她读了他信上所言：“再说一句—在这整个事件当中，我所致力反对的是在这个父权世界里所有当家的丈夫、父兄及统治者制定的一切可憎的规矩。”所以，要是她去了白教堂区，那就是站到了罗伯特·勃朗宁的对立面，就是反对了那些当家的丈夫、父兄及统治者。然而，她继续穿衣打扮。马车房里有条狗在嚎，它被拴了起来，孤苦无助地被残酷的人们掌控。那狗似乎在嚎着提醒她：“别忘了弗勒希！”她穿上鞋子，披上披风，戴上帽子。她又瞥了一眼勃朗宁先生的那封信。“我将娶你为妻。”她读道。但那条狗嚎个不停。她离开房间下了楼。

亨利·巴雷特迎向她，表示她若真的去做她扬言要做的事，就很有可能遭人抢劫甚至被谋害。她吩咐威尔逊去叫马车。尽管威尔逊吓得浑身筛糠，但还是顺从地照做了。马车到了。巴雷特小姐让威尔逊上车。威尔逊虽然认定自己死期将至，仍然上了车。巴雷特小姐告诉车夫去肖尔迪奇区的曼宁街。待巴雷特小姐自己也登车后，马车出发了。他们很快便将大玻璃窗、桃花心木大门与地下室采光井的栅栏甩在身后，进入了一个巴雷特小姐闻所未闻、想所未想的世界。他们在一个卧室地板下方就是牛群的世界，那里的人家都睡在窗户破了的房间里；这是一个每周只供水两次的世界，一个罪恶与贫穷滋养着罪恶与贫穷的世界。他们已经来到了正派体面的马车夫一无所知的区域。马车停住，车夫去一家酒馆问路。“里面出来两三个男人，‘噢，我敢说你们是来找泰勒先生的！’”一辆马车载着两位淑女出现在这个神秘的世界，只会为了一桩事，而那桩事已经无人不晓，就是那邪恶至极的事。其中一个男人跑进一栋屋子，出来后表示泰勒先生：“不在家！”“问我愿不愿意下车。威尔逊在一边害怕得要命，哀求我千万别做这种傻事。”一大群男人和男孩紧紧包围了马车。“那你愿不愿意见泰勒太太？”那男人问。巴雷特小姐一丁点见泰勒太太的意愿都没有，可这会儿一个肥硕超群的女人已从那屋子里走了出来，“一辈子的心宽养出来的体胖”。她告诉巴雷特小姐，她丈夫外出不在，“可能几分钟就回来，也可能几个小时后才回来—问我愿不愿意下车等他”。威尔逊使劲拉她的外衣。想象一下在那个女人的家里等人！坐在被一大群男人和男孩包围的马车里已经够糟了。于是巴雷特小姐便坐在马车里与那位“硕大的女匪”谈判。泰勒先生手上有她的狗，她说，泰勒先生答应会归还她的狗，能否请泰勒先生当天一定把狗送回温波尔街。“噢，当然可以！”胖女人堆着一脸无比亲切的笑容答道。她相信泰勒先生正是为此事才出门的。她一边说，一边“轻松愉快地左右摇晃着脑袋”。

就这样，马车掉头，离开了肖尔迪奇区的曼宁街。威尔逊认为“我们简直是虎口脱险”，巴雷特小姐自己则忧虑万分。“显然帮派在那里势力庞大，这些社区、这些‘千奇百怪的人’……的存在早已根深蒂固。”她写道。她的脑海中思潮汹涌，眼前充斥着各种影像。原来温波尔街的另一边是这副模样—这些面孔，这些屋子。她在酒馆外的马车里所看到的东西，比过去五年躺在温波尔街后面卧房里看到的东西加起来都多。“那些男人的脸！”她感叹道。那些面孔烙印在她的眼球上，刺激着她的想象力，即便是“圣洁的大理石神灵”—书架上那几尊半身像—也从未让她产生这么多灵感。在这里生活着跟她一样的女子；当她躺在沙发上阅读、写作时，那群人却在这个世界里如此活着。然而马车此时已再度行驶在两排四层的房屋中间，两侧熟悉的大门与窗户回归视线—有棱有角的砖道，黄铜门环，整齐划一的窗帘。终于到温波尔街五十号了。威尔逊飞快地跳下车—可以想象她意识到自己平安无事该有多么如释重负，但巴雷特小姐却似乎迟疑了片刻。她仍然看得见“那些男人的面孔”。多年后，当她坐在意大利阳光灿烂的阳台上写作时，那些面孔还会再次浮现于她的眼前[5]。它们将激发她的灵感，让她写下《奥罗拉·利》长诗中最生动的章节。不过男管家已经打开了前门，她走上楼再次回到了自己的房间。

星期六是弗勒希遭囚禁的第五天。他竭尽力气，几乎不再抱有希望，气喘吁吁地趴在拥挤地板上的那个黑暗角落里。门猛地被摔开又砰地关上。粗哑的声音大喊着。女人们尖声叫着。鹦鹉喋喋不休，仿佛从未对梅达韦尔区的寡妇们说过话似的，然而现在邪恶的老妇也基本上不会咒骂它们。虫子在弗勒希的毛皮里爬来爬去，但他实在太虚弱了，太茫然麻木了，以至于他都懒得甩动自己的毛发。弗勒希之前的生活及其中的无数场景—雷丁、温室、米特福德小姐、凯尼恩先生、书架、半身像、遮光帘上的农人—全似一片片掉进大锅里的雪花一般融化得无影无踪。倘若他心中仍有一线希望，那也是寄托于某种无名无形的东西上—是一张他依然称作“巴雷特小姐”的模糊脸庞。她仍旧存在；世界上其他的一切都消失了，但她仍旧存在，尽管他们之间存在的道道鸿沟让她几乎不可能来解救他。黑暗再度降临，几乎快要碾碎他最后的一线希望—巴雷特小姐。

事实上，纵然到了这最后关头，温波尔街的各方势力仍在奋力阻止弗勒希与巴雷特小姐团圆。星期六下午，她躺着等待泰勒到来，正如那肥硕超群的女人允诺的。他终于来了，却没有带狗。他传话说，只要巴雷特小姐当场付他六个几尼，他“以自己的名誉发誓”，必定直奔白教堂区去把狗接过来。泰勒这个“大魔头”的名誉到底值多少，巴雷特小姐不敢说，可是“似乎也没有其他法子了”，弗勒希的性命可是危在旦夕。她数了六个几尼，派人送下去给等在楼下走廊里的泰勒。只不过倒霉的是，当泰勒在走廊里等待，置身于雨伞堆、雕刻品、厚毛地毯和其他珍贵物品之间时，艾尔弗雷德·巴雷特走了进来。眼见大魔头泰勒居然登堂入室出现在自己家里，他不禁大发脾气，暴跳如雷。他咒骂泰勒是“诈骗犯、骗子、贼”！泰勒先生于是反唇相讥。更糟的是，泰勒竟发誓“就算狗儿正一心期盼救援，你们也永远别想再见到他了！”说完他便冲出了房子。也就是说，第二天一早，血迹斑斑的包裹便会送到。

巴雷特小姐又一次飞快地更衣，冲下了楼。威尔逊在哪儿？让她去叫马车。她打算立马回肖尔迪奇区。全家人都跑来劝阻她：天色已晚，她已筋疲力尽。就算一个健康的男人这么做都是在冒险，她这么做简直是疯狂。他们就是这么对她说的。她的兄弟姐妹全都围着她，吓唬她，阻止她，“大骂我‘疯了’，执拗又任性—我也像泰勒先生一样被他们冠上了无数头衔”。但她坚持自己的立场。最后，他们终于明白了她疯狂的程度，无论冒什么样的风险，他们都非让步不可。塞普蒂默斯保证，只要白白[32]肯回到自己的房间，并“控制好自己的脾气”，他愿意亲自去见泰勒，付清赎金，把狗接回来。

九月五日，白教堂区的暮光渐渐没入漆黑的夜色。房门又一次被踢开，一个毛茸茸的男人一把揪住弗勒希的脖子，把他从角落里拎了出来。弗勒希抬头看见宿敌那张令人惊骇的脸，不知等待自己的是死亡还是自由。其实除了鬼魂般萦绕不去的记忆之外，他什么都不在乎了。那男人弯下腰。他粗壮的手指为什么要在他的喉咙下摸索呢？是一把刀，还是一条链子？弗勒希跌跌撞撞，被半遮着眼，摇摇晃晃地带到了户外。

在温波尔街，巴雷特小姐咽不下晚餐。弗勒希是死是活，她完全没数。八点钟，敲门声响起，是勃朗宁先生的信像往常一样送来了。但门打开，信被送进来时，有什么东西也冲了进来—是弗勒希。他直冲向自己的紫色水罐。罐子里的水加满了三次，他却依旧喝个不停。巴雷特小姐观望着那条失魂落魄、晕头转向的脏狗一刻不停地喝水。“他见到我远不如我想象的那样热忱。”她评论道。是的，此刻这个世界上他渴望的东西只有一样—洁净的水。

话说回来，巴雷特小姐只是瞥了那些男人几眼，那些脸便让她终生难忘。弗勒希却任由他们摆布了整整五天。此刻他再度趴在软垫上，清凉的水似乎是唯一有存在感、有真实性的东西了。他一直在喝水。卧房里昔日的神祇—书架、衣橱、半身像—似乎失去了存在感。这间卧室不再代表全世界，它只是一个庇护所，只是在毒蛇猛兽潜行的森林中由一棵颤巍巍的酸模树遮蔽的一小片幽谷，每一棵树后面都藏着一个伺机出击的凶手。当他茫然而疲惫不堪地趴在巴雷特小姐脚边的沙发上时，耳畔依然回响着被拴住的狗的号叫和饱受惊吓的鸟的尖叫。每当门一打开，他都吓一跳，总以为会有个毛发浓重的男人带着刀进来—那不过是带了一本书来的凯尼恩先生，或是戴着黄手套的勃朗宁先生。可现在，见到凯尼恩先生和勃朗宁先生，他就往回缩。他不再信任他们。在那些堆满笑容的友善面孔之后，隐藏着背叛、残忍与欺骗。他们的抚摸是空洞的。他甚至不敢跟威尔逊一起走着去邮筒寄信。不用狗链拖，他是绝对不动的。每当他们说：“可怜的弗勒希，是不是有坏人把你偷走了？”他便抬起头来悲鸣或哀号。一记鞭响会让他闪电一般冲向地下室通风井的台阶，逃到安全地带。在屋里的时候，他会在沙发上更挨近巴雷特小姐。只有她一个人没有抛弃他。他对她仍葆有些许信念。渐渐地，她身上的存在感越来越强烈了。精疲力竭、浑身战栗、肮脏不堪、骨瘦如柴的他就趴在她脚边的沙发上。

时光荏苒，白教堂的记忆也渐渐褪色，紧贴着巴雷特小姐趴在沙发上的弗勒希比以往更能读懂她的心思。他们曾经被迫分离，如今再度聚首；事实上，他俩从未如此心灵相通过。她的每一举每一动也都传递给了他。她现在似乎无时无刻不在有所动作。一个包裹的送达甚至让她跳了起来。她打开包裹，用颤抖的双手拿出一双厚皮靴，然后立刻把它们藏进橱柜的角落里。然后她躺下来，仿佛什么事都没发生似的，尽管事实并非如此。只剩他俩独处时，她起身，从抽屉里拿出一条钻石项链。她还拿出装勃朗宁先生信件的那个盒子。她把那双皮靴、那条项链和那盒信全都放进一个绒毡制的箱子里，接着—似乎听见有人上楼—迅速把箱子推到床底下，匆忙躺下，用披肩把自己盖好。这些偷偷摸摸的迹象，弗勒希预感，肯定暗示着某种危机的临近。难道他们要一起远走高飞？莫非他们将一起逃离这个充斥着偷狗贼和暴君的可怕世界？噢，若果真如此，该有多好！他兴奋得颤抖呜咽起来，但巴雷特小姐轻声命令他保持安静，他立刻就安静了下来，她也异常安静。她的兄弟姐妹进门来的时候，她总是安安静静地躺在沙发上；她也躺着跟巴雷特先生说话，一如往常。

可是到了星期六，即九月十二日那天，巴雷特小姐做了一件弗勒希从来没见她做过的事。她梳妆打扮，似乎准备早餐后直接出门。更不同寻常的是，当弗勒希看着她换衣服时，他从她脸上的表情就清楚地知道她不会带他一起去，她要独自去办一件秘密的事。十点钟，威尔逊进了房间。她也穿戴整齐，仿佛准备出门散步。她们俩一起出去了，而弗勒希趴在沙发上等待她们回来。约摸一个小时之后，巴雷特小姐自个儿回来了。她没有看向他—她仿佛什么都看不见。她把手套脱了下来，在那么一瞬间，他看见一枚金戒指在她左手的一根手指上闪着光芒。然后他看着她摘下那枚戒指，把它藏进一个抽屉的最深处。接着她跟往常一样，在沙发上躺下。他趴在她身边，几乎不敢呼吸，因为他知道，无论发生了什么事，他们都必须不惜一切代价去保守那个秘密。

卧房内的生活也必须不惜一切代价地照常进行下去，然而一切都不一样了。在弗勒希看来，就连每次拉开和关上遮光帘都像是在打信号。在那几尊半身像上移动的光影也在提醒、昭示着什么。房间里的每样东西似乎都意识到变化即将到来，都在准备迎接某件大事；可是一切又恭默守静、秘而不宣。兄弟姐妹们一如既往地进进出出，巴雷特先生一如既往地晚间来探视，一如既往地检查肉排是否吃完了，葡萄酒是否喝光了。有其他人在房间里的时候，巴雷特小姐一如既往地谈笑风生，丝毫不露有所隐瞒的蛛丝马迹。但那些人一旦离去，她会一边竖起耳朵留着神，一边匆匆忙忙、偷偷摸摸地拉出床底下的箱子，往里面装东西。这些紧张的迹象是确定无疑的。星期日，教堂的钟声响起。“那是什么钟声？”有人问。“是马里波恩教堂的钟声。”亨丽埃塔小姐回答。弗勒希看见巴雷特小姐的脸色突然一片惨白。但其他人似乎什么都没有注意到。

就这样，星期一过去了，星期二、星期三、星期四也过去了。一如既往地吃喝、谈话和静卧于沙发上，这就像给他们覆盖了一块静默之毯。弗勒希在不安稳的睡梦中辗转反侧，他梦见他们在广袤的森林里，摸着黑一起蹲伏于蕨类植物和绿叶中，接着绿叶被拨开，他醒了过来。周围漆黑一片，可是在黑暗里，他看见威尔逊偷偷溜进房间，取出床底下的那个箱子，不声不响地拎了出去。那是九月十八日星期五的晚上。整个星期六早晨，他就那样趴在那儿，好像知道有条手帕随时会落地，有声低低的口哨随时会响起，这发出的可是生死攸关的信号。他看着巴雷特小姐自己穿好了衣服。四点差一刻，房门打开了，威尔逊走了进来。接着信号发出了—巴雷特小姐把他抱进怀里。她站了起来，走到门边。他俩驻足片刻，环顾房内：那是沙发，旁边摆着勃朗宁先生的扶手椅，那是几尊半身像和桌子。阳光透过常春藤的叶缝洒了进来，印有散步农人的遮光帘轻轻飘向窗外。一切都一如既往。一切似乎都等待着成千上万个类似的动作照旧进行，可是对巴雷特小姐和弗勒希来说，这却是最后一次。巴雷特小姐悄无声息地把门关上了。

他们悄无声息地溜下楼去，走过客厅、图书室、餐厅。每个房间看起来都习如往常，味道也和平日里并无二致；四下一片静谧，仿佛在炎热的九月午后沉睡着。卡蒂利内也趴在大厅的地毯上睡觉。他们走到前门，悄没声儿地转动门把手。一辆马车等在门外。

“去霍奇森旅馆。”巴雷特小姐说道。她的声音就像是耳语一般。弗勒希一动也不动地坐在她的膝盖上。世界上没有任何东西能让他打破此刻浩瀚无际的静默。

[28]过去曾为伦敦的贫民区，最早即从一座白教堂开始发展，因而得名。

[29]托马斯·比姆斯（Thomas Beames，1814或1815-1864），牧师，著有《伦敦的贫民窟：过去、现在与未来》一书。

[30]巴纳德·格雷戈里（Barnard Gregory，1796-1852），英国记者、出版人兼演员。于1831年至1849年间发行《讽刺家》报，并利用这份报纸发表伦敦社交界人士的丑闻，以勒索对方。这种行为引发了几起著名的诽谤诉讼，他也因此多次入狱。

[31]多恩（Donne，1572-1631），17世纪英国玄学派诗人、教士。诗作大多在去世后才印行。

[32]白（Ba），即伊丽莎白（Elizabeth）的昵称。

第五章　意大利

/

连续数小时、数天、数周，周遭似乎只剩黑暗与颠簸，只有乍现的光亮，随后进入漫长阴暗的隧道，被甩东甩西，又被仓促地拎到亮光下，看到巴雷特小姐靠近的脸颊，随后是纤细的树木、线条、铁轨和光影斑驳的高耸房屋—因为当时铁路运输有野蛮的规定，行程中狗必须关在狗箱里。然而弗勒希并不害怕，他们逃离了，他们把暴君和偷狗贼远远地甩在身后。尽情颠簸、尽情咔嚓吧，火车不断把他东摔西撞时，他喃喃自语道：“只要能让我们远离温波尔街和白教堂区就行。”最后，光线变得充足了，颠簸也停止了。他听见鸟儿在唱歌，树儿在风中叹息。抑或是水流的奔腾声吗？他终于睁开了眼睛，抖抖身上的毛皮。他看见了可以想见的最令人讶异的景象。巴雷特小姐身处湍急水流当中的一块岩石之上。树木向她探下身来，河水在她周围激荡。她危在旦夕。弗勒希纵身一跃，水花飞溅。他穿过河流，来到她身旁。“……他以彼得拉克的名义受洗了。”当他爬上石头到她身边时，巴雷特小姐如是言。原来他们来到了沃克吕兹[33]，而她正栖身于彼得拉克之泉当中的岩石上。

随后是更多的颠簸，更多的咔嚓声，接下来他又一次在平稳的地面上站定了。黑暗被分开，光线倾泻而下，洒满他全身。这是一间阳光普照的巨大的空屋子，他站在房间的红色瓷砖上，发觉自己还活脱脱的，如梦初醒，又满怀困惑。他跑过来跑过去，这里嗅嗅，那里摸摸。这儿没有地毯和壁炉。这儿没有沙发，没有扶手椅，没有书架，也没有半身像。呛人的陌生气味刺激着他的鼻孔，让他打起喷嚏。光线极其强烈、澄澈，令他目眩神迷。他从未身处过这样的房间—如果这真是一个房间的话—如此坚硬、如此明亮、如此巨大，又如此空旷。巴雷特小姐坐在屋子中央一张桌子旁的椅子上，看上去比以往更加娇小。然后威尔逊带他出了门，他发现自己几乎啥也看不见，先是因为阳光，再是因为阴影。街道的一半仿佛燃烧般炙热，另一半却寒气逼人。路过的女人们身上裹着毛皮大衣，却又都打着阳伞遮阴。那条街异常干燥。尽管眼下已是十一月中旬，地面上却没有会弄湿他脚掌或黏结他脚毛的烂泥和水坑。这里没有地下室的采光井，也没有栏杆，更没有那浓烈的混杂气味，那气味总令他沿着温波尔街或牛津街散步时心有旁骛。话说回来，从尖锐的石头角落和干燥的黄色墙壁散发出来的新奇气味也异常刺鼻而古怪。接着，一股香甜得让人震惊的气味从一幅舞动的黑色帘布后面传出来，像云朵般飘荡。他停住，抬起前爪，品味着；他尝试跟着气味往里走，从帘布下方往里钻。他一眼瞥见一个有低沉回响的、光影斑驳的大厅，大厅非常高，非常空旷。随后威尔逊惊恐地尖叫一声，利落地把他猛拉了回去。他们再度沿街道而行。街上的喧闹声震耳欲聋，仿佛所有人都在同一时刻高声吼叫。有别于伦敦那一成不变、催人入眠的嗡嗡声，这里咔嚓声、尖叫声、叮当声、吼嚷声、噼啪的鞭子声和当啷的铃铛声不绝于耳。弗勒希蹦这边跳那边，威尔逊也一样。为了避开运货马车、一头小牛、一队士兵和一群山羊，他们被迫上上下下人行道二十次。他感觉，和过去这么些年相比，自己反而更年轻、更敏捷了。他眼花缭乱却乐不可支，趴倒在红色地砖上，虽然以前他可以睡在温波尔街后面卧室的软枕头上，却从未睡得如此香甜。

不过没多久，弗勒希便意识到还有更深层次的差异，那便是比萨—他们如今居住的城市—有别于伦敦。两城的狗不相同。在伦敦，哪怕只是小跑到邮筒附近，他也不可避免地会碰到哈巴狗、寻回犬、斗牛犬、獒犬、柯利牧羊犬、纽芬兰犬、圣伯纳犬、猎狐犬或西班牙猎犬家族最著名的七种狗之一。他给每种狗都取了不同的名字，排了不同的等级。但是在比萨，尽管狗的数量大，却毫无等级之分。全都是—这可能吗？—杂种狗。他放眼望去，他们只是狗而已—灰狗、黄狗、斑纹狗、斑点狗，可无法从中辨认出哪只是西班牙猎犬、柯利牧羊犬、寻回犬或獒犬。难道犬业俱乐部在意大利毫无势力吗？难道西班牙猎犬俱乐部不为人知吗？难道这里没有法律规定冠毛是致命缺陷，有卷耳者为珍物，脚上的羽状毛必须予以保护，眉骨必须呈拱形—不可凸出？显然没有。弗勒希感觉自己像一位流亡在外的王子，是一群下里巴人中唯一的贵族。他是整个比萨城里唯一的纯种可卡犬。

弗勒希多年来一直被教导要将自己视为一条贵族狗。紫色水罐与狗链的法则深深浸透了他的灵魂。他失去了心理平衡一点儿也不足为奇。一个姓霍华德或卡文迪什的人落魄到泥屋里，混迹于一帮当地人当中，如果他时不时缅怀查茨沃思[34]，惆怅地怀念起夕阳照耀彩绘玻璃时的红地毯和饰满冠冕的长廊，这也情有可原。我们必须承认，弗勒希有势利的一面。很多年前米特福德小姐便已察觉到这一点。在伦敦，置身同级别以及更优秀的犬类当中，这个特性被压抑住了。如今再度抬头，他认为自己举世无双。他变得飞扬跋扈、放肆无礼。“弗勒希变成了一个十足的大王，想叫人开门的时候便吠个不停，让你心烦意乱。”勃朗宁夫人写道。“罗伯特，”她接着说，“宣称弗勒希认为他—我的丈夫—被创造出来是—门为他效劳的，看上去还真像是那么回事。”

“罗伯特”，“我的丈夫”—如果说弗勒希变了，那巴雷特小姐也一样。不仅仅是因为她现在自称勃朗宁夫人，还在阳光底下炫耀手上的金戒指；她的变化和弗勒希的变化一样巨大。弗勒希一天能听到她说五十遍“罗伯特”和“我的丈夫”，而—语气当中的得意总让他颈毛倒竖、心跳加速。发生变化的不只是她的语言，她整个人都焕然一新了。比方说，以前她只能呷一小口波尔图葡萄酒，还抱怨头痛，现在却不同了，她能将基安蒂红葡萄酒一饮而尽—睡得更为香甜。餐桌上摆着的是一大串连枝带叶的橙子，而非一小颗去了皮、又酸又黄的果子。她不再坐带顶篷的四轮大马车去摄政公园，而是穿上厚靴子去攀岩。她不再乘着双驾马车辘辘地驶过牛津街，而是登上快散架的出租马车，一路颠簸到湖边欣赏山景。疲惫了，她不会挥手再叫另一辆马车，而是在石头上坐下观察蜥蜴。阳光普照时她满心欢喜，天寒地冻时她也欢喜满心。在滴水成冰的日子里，她会把从公爵森林里捡来的松枝丢进火里。他们一起坐在噼里啪啦的火苗前，闻着那股强烈的松香味儿。她总是不厌其烦地赞美意大利，批判英国。“……我们这些可怜的英国人，”她惊叹道，“需要学会享乐。他们需要经过阳光净化而非炉火的淬炼。”在意大利，太阳孕育了自由、生命与喜悦。你看不见任何男人打架，也听不见他们对骂；你也绝对看不到意大利人喝得烂醉—肖尔迪奇区“那群男人的脸”又浮现于她的眼前。她总是拿伦敦来跟比萨进行比较，说自己是多么地喜欢比萨。漂亮的女人可以独自行走于比萨街头。尊贵的女士们先倒空了自己的夜壶，再带着“无可否认的光鲜亮丽”去到宫廷。拥有铃声、杂种狗、骆驼、松树林的比萨，比拥有桃花心木大门及羊肩肉的温波尔街不知要好上多少倍。就这样，勃朗宁夫人每天一边将基安蒂红葡萄酒一饮而尽，再从橙子树枝上扯下一个橙子，一边赞美意大利，并为可怜、乏味、潮湿、阴霾、抑郁、昂贵、保守的英国悲叹。

诚然，威尔逊还将四平八稳的英式作派保持了一段时间。有关管家和地下室、前门与窗帘的记忆可没那么容易从心头抹去。“惊骇于维纳斯的有失体统”，她心有余悸地走出美术馆。后来，由于朋友的好意允许，她得以从门外瞥见大公爵宫廷的富丽堂皇，但她依然忠诚地坚持认为圣詹姆士教堂更胜一筹。“跟我们英国的宫廷比起来，”她报告说，“那地方……简直半零不落。”然而在她观赏的同时，一名大公爵侍卫绝佳的体格却吸引了她的注意。她的幻想被点燃，她的看法有点儿动摇，她的标准倾塌了。莉莉·威尔逊跟侍卫里吉先生陷入热恋[6]。

正如勃朗宁夫人探索着她的新自由，欣喜于她的新发现，弗勒希也忙于进行他的发现，探索他的自由。他们离开比萨之前—一八四七年春，他们迁居佛罗伦萨—弗勒希就坦然面对了这新奇—起初令他心烦意乱的事实，即犬业俱乐部的律法并非放诸四海而皆准。他设法让自己接受了淡色冠毛并非致命缺陷这一事实。他也相应地修正了自己的行为准则。他依照犬类社会的新观念行事，刚开始时还有点儿瞻前顾后的，接下来便一日比一日平易起来。就算在比萨，勃朗宁夫人也注意到：“……他每天都出去跟小狗们说意大利话。”现在到了佛罗伦萨，昔日束缚他的最后一副镣铐也从他身上脱落了。解放的那一刻降临在去卡施奈公园的那一天。当弗勒希冲过“翡翠般”的草地，惊起“野鸡四下飞蹿”时，他突然忆起摄政公园及其规定：狗必须系狗链。可现在“必须”在哪里呢？狗链又在哪里呢？公园管理员和警棍又去哪儿了？全都消失不见了！和腐朽贵族社会的偷狗贼、犬业俱乐部及西班牙猎犬俱乐部一起消失了！和四轮马车、双驾马车一起消失了！和白教堂、肖尔迪奇一起消失了！他驰骋，他飞奔，他的毛皮闪亮，他的眼睛放光。他现在是全世界的朋友，每一条狗都是他的兄弟。在这个新世界里，他不需要狗链，也不需要保护。如果勃朗宁先生迟迟不肯出去散步—他跟弗勒希现在成了最好的朋友—他会大胆地叫唤他。“在他面前站起来，用无法想象的骄横腔调吠叫。”勃朗宁夫人有点儿气恼地观察着—因为眼下她和弗勒希的关系远不如往昔亲昵。她不再需要他的红色毛皮、明朗双目来弥补自己缺失的体验。她已在葡萄园及橄榄树丛中找到了属于自己的牧神潘，他还出现在夜幕下的松木篝火旁。就这样，如果勃朗宁先生磨磨蹭蹭，弗勒希便会站起来吠叫；可要是勃朗宁先生宁愿待在家里写作，也没关系。弗勒希现在很独立了。爬满墙的紫藤和金链花正在盛开，花园中的紫荆怒放欲燃，野郁金香缀满田野。他为什么要等呢？他自己就跑了。如今他是自己的主人了。“……他独自跑出去，一去就是几个小时。”勃朗宁夫人写道，“……他对佛罗伦萨的每一条街都了如指掌—凡事都要有自己的主张了。我不再因为他不在就担心受怕。”她补充道，面带微笑地回忆起在温波尔街的痛苦时刻，只因她一时疏忽在维尔街忘拴狗链了，那帮贼便躲在马腿下面，伺机把他偷走。在佛罗伦萨，人们不知畏惧为何物；这里没有偷狗贼，她或许还叹口气想到，这里也没有—制的父亲。

但是坦白地讲，但凡圭迪府邸的门开着便要往外窜的弗勒希，可不是为了要观赏名画、探索黝暗的教堂或仰望模糊的壁画。他是为了享受某样东西，为了找寻这些年来他久违的某样东西。曾经，维纳斯的号角吹起狂野的音乐，在伯克郡的大地萦绕，他爱过帕特里奇先生的狗，她还给他生过一个孩子。现在，他又听见同样的声音响彻佛罗伦萨狭窄的街巷，而—经过这么多年的沉寂，那声音变得更为紧迫，更为猛烈了。此刻，弗勒希理解了人类永远不会理解的东西—纯粹的爱，简单的爱，彻底的爱，在清醒时分不会带来无尽忧虑的爱，问心无愧，无怨无悔；来了又去，仿若那采花的蜜蜂来了又去。今天的花儿是玫瑰，明天的花儿是百合；此刻是沼泽地里的野蓟，下一刻是温室里矫揉造作的套袋兰花。如此博爱，如此无忧无虑，弗勒希将小巷深处有斑点的西班牙猎犬、斑纹狗和黄狗一一拥入怀中—无论是谁，都没有关系。对弗勒希来说，全都一样。号角声起，随风飘送，飘到哪里，他追随到哪里。爱是一切，有爱便足够了。没有人责备他的放浪。每当弗勒希深夜迟归，甚至翌日清晨返家，勃朗宁先生只是大笑着说：“对于像他这么体面的狗来说实在丢人！”当弗勒希扑倒在卧室地板上，在用人造大理石镶嵌的圭迪家族纹章上沉沉睡去时，勃朗宁夫人也笑了。

圭迪府邸内的房间都很空旷。所有在他与世隔绝的那段日子里被遮罩覆盖的家具全都消失了。床就是床，盥洗台就是盥洗台，每样东西都呈现本来的面目而非其他。巨大的客厅零零散散放了几把旧式乌木雕花椅，壁炉上方挂了一面镜子，两旁有丘比特举着灯。勃朗宁夫人自己也把印度披肩扔到一边。她戴着一顶用颜色鲜艳的丝绸制成的无边小帽，这是她丈夫喜欢的。她的头发梳成了新的发式。夕阳西下，遮光板拉起时，她穿着白色薄棉裙在阳台上踱步。她喜欢坐在那儿观望并聆听街上的人们。

迁居佛罗伦萨没多久，有一天夜晚街上沸反盈天、脚步杂沓，他们冲上阳台一看究竟。一大群人从下面奔涌而过。他们举着横幅，又叫又唱。每扇窗子里都探满人头，所有的阳台都挤满了人。窗子里的人朝街上的人抛撒鲜花和月桂叶，而街上的人—庄严的男人，快活的年轻女子—彼此亲吻，对着阳台上的人高举起他们的宝宝。勃朗宁先生和夫人倚在栏杆上，不停地鼓掌。一条又一条的横幅经过。火把的光把它们照亮。其中一条写着“解放”，另一条写着“意大利统一”，还有“纪念烈士”“庇护九世万岁”及“莱奥波尔多二世万岁”—长达三个半小时，横幅不断经过，人们不停欢呼，勃朗宁和夫人站在点了六支蜡烛的阳台上不停挥手。弗勒希也跟着挤在他俩中间，前脚搭在基石上，努力地跟着欢呼了好久。但是最终—他装不下去了—他打起了哈欠。“他终于坦白了，他认为那群人闹得过久了。”勃朗宁夫人观察到。疲惫和疑虑将他占据，他生出一股下流的欲望。这究竟在干啥？他自问。这位大公爵是何许人物，他又许诺了什么？他们为什么都激动得如此离谱？—因为每当有横幅经过，勃朗宁夫人便热情地挥手再挥手，不知何故，这令他有点儿恼怒。他觉得，如此殷勤地对待一位大公爵未免过于夸张了。接着，就在大公爵本人经过时，他留意到有一条小狗停在门口。趁勃朗宁夫人沉浸在反常的兴奋中，他赶紧抓住机会，溜下阳台跑了。他穿过横幅和群众，一路尾随着她。她则越跑越远，跑入了佛罗伦萨的中心地带。大呼小叫声愈来愈遥远，人群的欢呼声渐渐隐没于岑寂当中。火把的光亮也熄灭了，只剩下一两点星光在阿尔诺河的涟漪中闪烁，弗勒希便和那条斑点西班牙猎犬并肩趴在河畔，蜷缩着依偎在泥地上的一个旧篮子里。他们迷失于爱情中，一直到旭日东升。弗勒希直到第二天上午九点才回到家。勃朗宁夫人满怀嘲讽地跟他打招呼—她想着，他至少应该记得今天是她第一个结婚周年纪念日吧。不过她料想“他一定是找到乐子了”。的确如此。当她从四万人的大游行、大公爵的种种许诺及横幅上迎风招展的愿望中生发出无法言说的满足感时，弗勒希无比欢喜的却是门边的那条小狗。

毋庸置疑，勃朗宁夫人与弗勒希在各自的发现之旅中抵达了截然不同的目的地—她发现的是大公爵，他发现的则是斑点西班牙猎犬。然而不可否认的是，将他们俩维系在一起的纽带依然牢固。弗勒希摒弃了那些“必须”的陈规，在卡施奈公园那翡翠般的草地上自由自在地驰骋起来，惊起的野鸡掠过一道红光或金光。只是他刚开始这么做，就感到了一种牵制，让他再度回归到蛰居家中的状态。起初也没什么—只是一点儿蛛丝马迹—一八四九年的春天，勃朗宁夫人开始忙着做起针线活儿来了。可眼前这幅景象之中总有什么令弗勒希觉得蹊跷。她向来不事女红。他注意到威尔逊移动了一张床，她还在一个抽屉里放了许多白色的衣物。他从地砖上仰起头，凝神观看，—心倾听。又有什么事情即将发生吗？他焦虑地寻找皮箱与打包的迹象。是要再一次远走高飞，再一次逃离吗？可这一回要逃往哪里，又躲避什么呢？这儿没什么可怕的，他向勃朗宁夫人保证。在佛罗伦萨，他们俩谁都不用忧心忡忡，不用害怕泰勒先生，或看到被包在棕色纸袋里的狗头。他困惑不解，这种种变动的迹象，据他的解读，并不意味着逃亡。这些迹象，以一种极其神秘的方式，象征着某种期待。当他观望着勃朗宁夫人如此泰然自若、安静沉稳地端坐于她那张矮椅上飞针走线时，他体味出即将发生的事不可避免。这也令人畏惧。时间一周一周地过去，勃朗宁夫人几乎足不出户。她坐在那儿，看上去在期盼某件盛事。难道她准备跟某个像泰勒一样的恶棍正面交锋，孤绝而无助地任他拳打脚踢？想到这个，弗勒希感同身受地颤抖起来。她绝计没有逃离的意图，没有收拾好的箱盒，也没有迹象显示有谁准备离开这栋房子—反倒像是有什么人即将抵达。嫉妒而焦虑的弗勒希严密监视着每个新来的访客。现在来拜访的人很多—布莱格登小姐、兰多尔先生、哈蒂·霍斯默、利顿先生—来圭迪府邸的绅士淑女实在太多了。勃朗宁夫人日复一日地坐在扶手椅里安静地穿针引线。

然后，在三月初的一天，勃朗宁夫人一整天都没有在客厅现身。其他人进进出出，勃朗宁先生和威尔逊也进进出出。看到他们进出时如此心烦意乱，弗勒希自个儿躲到了沙发底下。大伙儿在楼梯上咚咚咚地上上下下，奔来奔去，压低嗓门用各种陌生的语调呼来唤去。他们在楼上的卧室里走动，他则愈来愈往沙发的暗影深处钻。他身体里每一根神经都能感应到某种变化正在发生—某件可怕的事情正在进行。多年前，他曾经这样等候过，等着神秘蒙面人上楼梯的脚步声。最终门打开了，巴雷特小姐高喊：“勃朗宁先生！”现在来的是谁？是哪一位神秘人？日长似岁，他彻底被遗忘，没有人进客厅来。他趴在客厅里，没有吃的也没有喝的；现在纵然有一千只长着斑点的西班牙猎犬在门口嗅来嗅去，他也只会躲开她们。因为随着时间一小时一小时地过去，他越发强烈地感觉有外物强行入侵家里。他从沙发罩的荷叶边底下往外偷瞄。两个举着灯的丘比特、乌木柜、法式椅子看上去都像被戳得七零八落；他感觉为了给那个看不见的东西腾出空间，自己似乎也给挤到了墙边。他看到过勃朗宁先生一次，但他不再是以前那个勃朗宁先生了；他也看到过威尔逊一次，可她也变了—就好像他们都看到了那个他感觉到的无形之物。他们的眼睛里闪耀着奇特的光芒。

终于，看上去红光满面、衣衫不整却得意扬扬的威尔逊把他抱在怀里上了楼。他们进入卧房。笼罩在阴影中的房间里传来一阵如小羊叫唤般微弱的声音—枕头上有东西在挥动，是个活物。勃朗宁夫人完全没依靠旁人，连前门都没打开，仅凭一己之力就从一个人变成了两个人。那可怕的东西就在她身边挥舞手臂，呜呜叫着。无法掩饰的愤怒、嫉妒以及强烈的嫌恶涌上弗勒希的心头，他用力挣脱了威尔逊的怀抱，冲下了楼。威尔逊和勃朗宁夫人唤他回去；她们用爱抚引诱他，给他吃好吃的东西，却一点儿用也没有。他试图躲开那令人厌恶的景象，那让人反感的存在，直往沙发的阴影中和黑暗的角落里钻。“……整整两个星期，他陷入了深深的忧郁之中，无论大家如何费尽心力哄他都没有用。”—就算千头万绪忙得无法分身，勃朗宁夫人也不得不注意到这一点。倘若我们把人类的时间换算成狗的时间—我们也必须如此—想象一分钟如何膨胀成一小时，一小时又如何膨胀成一天，那么以人类的时间计算，弗勒希的“严重抑郁症”持续了足足六个月，这一结论毫不夸张。许多男男女女在不到六个月的时间就能将自己的爱恨情仇抛到九霄云外了。

但弗勒希不再是温波尔街时代那条不懂世故、未经教化的狗了。他早已吸取了教训。威尔逊揍过他。他被迫吞咽过陈腐变质的蛋糕，而他本可以在其新鲜时享用的。他曾发誓去爱勃朗宁先生而不去咬他。当他趴在沙发底下时，所有这些往事在他的心头翻腾；他终于想通了。他再一次得到了奖赏。必须承认的是，刚开始那个奖赏不具有实体性，甚至让人难以接受。宝宝被放到弗勒希的背上，这边宝宝揪扯着他的耳朵，那边他得驮着宝宝走来走去。可他如此温文尔雅，哪怕耳朵被揪，也只是转过头去“亲亲那双肥嘟嘟的浅凹进去的小光脚”，以至于三个月后，那团无助弱小、只会乱扯和哭闹的小肉球竟然开始对他青睐有加，“总的来说”—勃朗宁夫人是这么说的—比起别人，更喜欢他。然后，令人感到奇妙的是，弗勒希发现自己也喜欢上了宝宝。难道他们俩没有共通之处吗？难道宝宝不是有很多地方像弗勒希吗？难道他们不是对很多事有一致的看法和品位吗？就比如，欣赏风景这件事。对弗勒希而言，所有风景都是索然无趣的。这么多年来，他从来没学会正眼看看山峦。他们带他去瓦隆布罗萨[35]时，那里森林的壮美却只让他感到无聊至极。宝宝几个月大的时候，他们再次乘坐马车进行长途旅行。宝宝躺在保姆的大腿上，弗勒希则坐在勃朗宁夫人的膝盖上。马车走啊走啊走个不停，费劲地登上亚平宁山脉的高峰。勃朗宁夫人简直喜不自禁，几乎离不开窗口。即便穷尽所有的英语词汇，她也找不到合适的表达来抒发自己的千万感触。“……亚平宁山脉的景色毓秀，几近梦幻。其形其色千变万化，精彩纷呈；山势突变，峰峦各异。栗树林因自身之重朝万丈深谷倾落，湍急的激流劈剁、撕扯着岩石。层峦叠嶂，竞相攀越，仿佛是彼此挤压形成，尽力绽放色彩。”—亚平宁山脉之美催生出诸多词句，这些词句竞相涌现，彼此倾轧，彼此吞没。然而宝宝和弗勒希却一点儿也没感受到这种激动，体会到这种心余力绌。他们俩都默不作声。弗勒希“把头从窗口收回来，不认为那值得一看……他对树木山川之类的极其不屑”。勃朗宁夫人如是总结。马车继续辘辘地行驶着。弗勒希睡着了，宝宝也睡着了。终于，窗外有了灯光与房舍，男男女女来来往往。他们进入了一个村落。弗勒希顿时醒了，全神贯注起来。“……他如饥似渴，弹眼落睛，东看看西瞅瞅，让你觉得他在做笔记或是准备做笔记。”让他兴奋的是人类的生活场景。至少从这点看来，若想打动弗勒希的感官，美必须先通过结晶作用化成绿色或蓝紫色的粉末，再由某种神圣的注射器注入弗勒希的鼻孔，渗入他鼻孔深处的毛细血管才行；随后产生的反应也不是以文字的形式出现，而是沉寂的狂喜。勃朗宁夫人目力之所及，是他鼻子之所闻；她笔触之所记，是他嗅吸之所得。

至此，作传者迫不得已，须暂—搁笔。两三千字不足以形容我们眼前之所见—勃朗宁夫人便不得不坦言自己被亚平宁山脉击败了：“我实在无法向你描绘这一切。”她承认道—但用来形容我们闻到的气味的词儿却不过两三个。人类的鼻子几乎相当于不存在。世界上最伟大的诗人，也只能一边闻到玫瑰的味道，另一边闻到粪便的味道而已。至于二者之间的无穷变化，则从来没有人记录过。然而弗勒希却基本上活在这个嗅觉的世界里。爱首先是气味，形状与颜色也是气味，音乐、建筑、法律、政治和科学都是气味。对他而言，气味即宗教本身。光是描绘每天排骨或饼干带给他的最单纯的体验，都超出了我们的能力范围。就算是斯温伯恩先生[36]也无法形容出六月一个炎热的午后温波尔街上的味道对弗勒希而言意味着什么。至于描摹混杂在火把、月桂叶、熏香、横幅、蜡烛，以及被一只摆在樟脑堆里的丝缎高跟鞋踩碎的玫瑰花环等气味当中的一只西班牙猎犬的味道，或许只有莎士比亚才能办得到，前提是他能在写《安东尼和克莉奥佩特拉》时，中途停下来细细推敲—但莎士比亚并没有停住。在此承认我们能力有限后，只能认识到，对弗勒希来说，在他一生最充实、最自由、最快乐的那几年里，意大利主要意味着一连串的气味。爱情，想必会逐渐丧失吸引力；但气味长存。如今他们一家再度在圭迪府邸安顿下来，所有人都各得其所。勃朗宁先生通常在一个房间里写作，勃朗宁太太则通常在另一个房间里写作，宝宝在儿童房里玩耍。而弗勒希则迷失于佛罗伦萨的大街小巷，享受气味的盛宴。他追随气味的指引，穿梭在大路与后街、广场与小巷之间，嗅闻着一种又一种味道：浓烈的、温和的、神秘的、美好的。他进进出出、上上下下—有人在打制铜器，有人在烘焙面包，女人们坐着梳理头发，鸟笼高高垒在堤道上，洒落在人行道上的葡萄酒留下深红的污渍，皮革、马具与大蒜各发其味，布匹被拍打着，藤叶在颤动，男人们坐下来喝酒吐痰掷骰子—他跑进跑出，或是鼻子贴着地面，畅饮所有的精华，或是抬头让鼻子在风中随气味共舞。他睡在被太阳晒热的地上—阳光让石头发出臭味！他在隧道的阴影里探查—阴影让石头发出酸味！他狼吞虎咽地吃下一整串一整串的熟葡萄，只因为那紫色的味道；意大利家庭主妇从阳台扔出来的硬山羊骨头或通心面之类的，他都会嚼嚼再吐出来—羊骨头和通心面的气味都是粗粝的、猩红的。他跟随令人沉迷的香甜气味，进入昏暗的大教堂里蓝紫色的迷宫中，一边嗅闻，一边企图舔舐镶有彩绘玻璃的墓穴上的金子。这并不意味着他的触觉就不灵敏了。他熟知佛罗伦萨大理石的光滑，还有沙砾与卵石的粗糙。帷幔陈旧的褶皱、光滑的石制手指和脚掌，都接受过他舌头的舔舐，以及他颤抖着的口鼻部的轻触。至于他无比敏感的脚掌肉垫，则清晰地拓印上了令人骄傲的拉丁语铭文。简言之，他对佛罗伦萨的熟悉程度，没有一个人类可与之抗衡，就连拉斯金[37]及乔治·艾略特[38]也无法企及。唯有不能说话的人方能领略弗勒希的感觉。他所有数不清的感觉，没有一样可用简陋的文字传达出来。

作传者虽然很乐意就此推断弗勒希的后半辈子是一场笔墨无法形容的快乐狂欢，并乐观地秉持这样一种观点：当小宝宝一天比一天多学会一个字，却因此日益远离感官知觉时，弗勒希将注定永远留在所有本质皆永葆至纯的天堂里，在这里万事万物皆以袒露的精神紧贴其赤诚的灵魂—可惜这并不是真的。弗勒希并没有活在这样的天堂里。只有在星际间遨游的神灵，像飞行距离远至冰雪极地与热带森林却从未见到过人类家园和人间袅袅烟火的鸟儿，或许—就我们所知—才能获得豁免，享受如此完满的幸福。可是弗勒希睡过人类的膝头，听过人类的声音，他的体内遍布属于人类的热情；他了解各种层次的嫉妒、愤怒和绝望。眼下正值盛夏，他饱受跳蚤之苦[7]。太阳能催熟葡萄，同样也带来了跳蚤，这种讽刺显得十分残酷。“……在佛罗伦萨，萨沃纳罗拉[39]的殉道，”勃朗宁夫人写道，“并不比弗勒希在夏季受到的折磨惨烈多少。”跳蚤在佛罗伦萨房舍的每个角落里活蹦乱跳。它们从古老石头的每一条裂隙中，从陈旧帷幔的每一道皱褶里，从每一件斗篷、每一顶帽子和每一条毛毯里悄悄跃出。它们在弗勒希的皮毛里筑巢，一路啮咬到他皮毛的最深处。他又抓又搔，健康状况江河日下，变得阴郁、瘦弱而狂乱。米特福德小姐收到求救信。勃朗宁夫人焦急地在信中询问：长跳蚤有何疗方？依然坐在三英里十字标的温室里写悲剧的米特福德小姐将笔放下，开始查阅老药方—要用什么样的五月花，什么种类的玫瑰花蕾。只是雷丁的跳蚤一掐就死了，佛罗伦萨的跳蚤却色泽鲜红、强壮有力。对它们来说，米特福德小姐的药粉大概只是鼻烟。绝望之下，勃朗宁先生和夫人只能跪在水桶旁，用上肥皂和刷子，竭尽全力清除这害虫，结果却徒劳无功。终于有一天，带弗勒希出去散步的勃朗宁先生注意到别人在指指点点，他听见有人指着弗勒希的鼻子低声说：“兽疥癣！”时至今日，“罗伯特已和我一样爱弗勒希”，带一位朋友下午出门散步，却听见他遭受这般侮辱，实在无法忍受。罗伯特，他太太写道，“对此忍无可忍”。现在只剩下一个办法了，但这一治疗方法与疾病本身一样极端。尽管弗勒希已变得十分亲民，对身份地位的象征物不再那么重视，但他依旧像菲利普·西德尼所宣称的那样，是一位天生的绅士。他的纯正血统不言自明；那一身毛皮对他而言，好比穷困潦倒的乡绅怀中那枚镌刻着家族纹章的金表—曾有万亩良田，如今缩水到只剩这小表一圈。勃朗宁此刻提议牺牲的正是他的皮毛。他把弗勒希唤到跟前，“抄起一把剪刀，把他全身上下剪得像头狮子”。

随着罗伯特·勃朗宁一刀一刀地剪，可卡犬的荣耀掉落于地，一个迥然不同、拙劣的动物模样从他的颈部渐渐生成。弗勒希觉得自己遭了阉割，受了轻贱，挨了羞辱。我现在是什么？他瞪着镜子思忖。镜子用一以贯之的残忍和坦率回答道：“你什么都不是。”他谁也不是。他显然不再是一条可卡犬了。然而当他对着镜子端详时，他的耳朵现在光秃秃的，不再卷曲，似乎在抽搐，就好像真理与欢笑这两位非凡的精灵在对着它们絮语似的。毕竟，什么也不是，不正是世界上最令人满足的状态吗？他又看了看。那是他的环状颈毛。戏仿那些自以为是的家伙的浮夸行径—从某种方面来看不也是一种经历吗？无论如何，不管他是如何解决这件事的，他毫无疑问摆脱了跳蚤的烦恼。他甩甩自己的颈毛，用他那无毛瘦弱的腿蹦跶起来，精神随之大振，仿若一位刚从病床上起身的大美人，发现自己已菊老荷枯、韶华不再，于是将衣裳和化妆品付之一炬，又想到自己再也不必对镜自怜，或为爱人情薄、情敌貌美而担惊受怕，便开怀大笑起来；或像一位穿了二十年浆硬了的绒面呢袍的牧师，把硬领子扔进垃圾桶里，再从橱柜里抽出伏尔泰的著作一般。就这样，弗勒希蹦蹦跳跳地跑走了，尽管被剪得像只秃狮子，却再也不必为跳蚤而苦恼了。“弗勒希，”勃朗宁夫人写信给她姐妹说，“非常有智慧。”或许当时她想到了希腊人所说的只有历经痛苦的磨炼才能获得快乐。他是真正的哲学家，虽然失去了皮毛，却不再受跳蚤之苦了。

可没过多久，弗勒希刚刚获得的哲学便受到了考验。一八五二年夏天，圭迪府邸内即将降临危机的种种迹象再度无声无息地聚集：抽屉被拉开，绳头在箱子外晃荡……对狗而言，这份凶险就好比预示闪电的云之于牧羊人，预示战争的谣言之于政客。直指又一次变化、又一趟旅行。但所为何来呢？皮箱被拖下来捆扎好，宝宝被保姆抱在怀里带出来，勃朗宁先生和夫人穿着旅行装束现身，出租马车停在门口。弗勒希达观地等在大厅。他们万事俱备之时，他也整装待发。现在所有人都坐进了马车，弗勒希轻盈地纵身一跃跟着跳上车。威尼斯、罗马或巴黎—他们这是要去哪儿呢？现在所有国家对他而言都毫无二致，四海之内皆兄弟。他已经吸取了教训。但当他终于从茫然中走出来时，却发现再多的哲学也不够用—他居然身处伦敦。

房子左右排列在以方方正正的砖头砌成的整洁道路的两旁。他脚底下的人行道冰冷坚硬。从镶着黄铜门环的桃花心木大门里出来一位盛装淑女，身着一袭紫色毛绒拖地长裙，头别一顶缀饰着花朵的小花冠。她撩起大堆裙摆，带着倨傲的表情朝街上来回扫了两眼。马夫正弯腰将四轮大马车的踏脚放下。整条韦尔贝克街—这里正是韦尔贝克街—笼罩在豪华气派的红光中。这光不似意大利的光线那般澄澈凶猛，而是呈黄褐色，—因数以百万计的车轮不断碾过和数以百万计的马蹄不停践踏而尘土弥漫。伦敦正当盛季。人声鼎沸，嗡嗡声交织如云，会合而成的喧嚣覆盖住整个城市。一条威武的猎鹿犬由小侍童用链子牵着迎面走来。一位警察大摇大摆地踏着极有节奏的阔步经过，瞪着大牛眼左右察看。炖煮的味道、牛肉的味道、炙烤的味道、牛肉烧卷心菜的味道从上千个地下室里飘出来。一名穿制服的仆役将一封信投入邮箱。

为大都会的繁华所震慑，弗勒希踏上门阶的脚步踟蹰了片刻，威尔逊也顿住了。意大利的文明、宫廷、革命、大公爵和大公爵的侍卫们，此刻显得多么微不足道！当那名警察经过时，威尔逊不禁感谢上苍，还好她没嫁给里吉先生。接着，从街角一家酒馆里走出来一个邪恶的身影。一个男人不怀好意地睨视着。弗勒希一跃而上，冲进屋内。

一连几个星期，他都被严密地禁闭于韦尔贝克街一套寄宿公寓的起居室里。与外界隔离仍然是必要的，因为霍乱正在肆虐，贫民窟内的状况确实因霍乱而有了些许改善，可惜程度不大，狗儿被偷仍层出叠见，温波尔街的狗出入仍须系链。弗勒希当然有他的社交生活，他会在邮筒旁和酒馆外碰见其他的狗，他们以狗族与生俱来的优良教养欢迎他的回归。就像一位长年生活在东方，并沾染上若干当地习惯的英国贵族—谣传他确已皈依伊斯兰教，还跟一位中国洗衣女工育有一子—当他返回宫廷社交圈时，发现昔日老友们都宁愿忘记他曾误入歧途，还邀请他去查茨沃思，没人会提及他的妻子，而—大家都理所当然地认为他会加入家庭祷告—温波尔街上的那些指示犬及塞特犬也同样欢迎弗勒希加入他们，—对他的皮毛状态视若无睹。但眼下在弗勒希看来，伦敦的狗似乎都有一定的病态。众所周知，卡莱尔夫人[40]的狗尼禄从顶楼窗口跳了出去[8]，企图自杀。据说，这是因为他无法承受住在切尼洛的压力。重返韦尔贝克街的弗勒希对此确实深信不疑。禁足，满满当当的小物什，晚上的蟑螂，白天的苍蝇，萦绕不去的羊膻味，餐具柜上永不缺席的香蕉—所有这些，再加上跟好几位穿着隆重却不常或根本不洗澡的男男女女耳鬓厮磨，都令他脾气暴躁、神经紧张。他经常在寄宿公寓的小衣橱下一趴就是几个小时。溜出门是不可能的，因为前门永远锁着；他必须等着谁给他系上狗链，带他出去。

只有两件事打破了他客居伦敦数周一成不变的单调生活。晚夏的一天，勃朗宁一家前往法汉姆拜访查尔斯·金斯利牧师[41]。此时的意大利，土地早已赤裸坚硬得像块砖，跳蚤也开始肆虐，有气无力的狗儿拖着步子从一个阴影挪到另一个阴影里，甚至为碰上的某尊多纳泰罗[42]的雕像抬起的手臂投下的细条影子而心怀感激。可在法汉姆，这里的田野绿草如茵，池塘碧波荡漾，树林絮絮低语。草皮细软得脚掌踏上去都会弹起来似的。勃朗宁一家与金斯利一家共度了一整天。又一次，当弗勒希跟在他们身后踱步时，往昔的号角突然响起，旧日的狂喜再度现身—那是只野兔，还是只狐狸？弗勒希驰骋在萨里郡[43]的田野上，仿佛在三英里十字标那段旧日时光之后再没有这样痛快地跑过了。一只野鸡嗖地腾起，划出紫色和金色的光芒。他差一点儿就咬住野鸡的尾羽了，但恰在此刻，有人大喝一声。皮鞭猛然抽响。是查尔斯·金斯利牧师在厉声唤他跟上吗？反正，他停止了奔跑。法汉姆的树林没有遭到一丝破坏。

几天后，他正趴在韦尔贝克街的客厅里，勃朗宁夫人穿着散步的衣服走了进来，把他从小衣橱底下唤出来。她将狗链套在他的项圈上。自一八四六年九月以来，他们第一次一起走向温波尔街。等来到五十号门前，他们如往昔一样停下了脚步。他们如往昔一样静静地等待。男管家如往昔一样应门缓慢。过了好些时候门终于打开。蜷在地垫上的是卡蒂利内吗？那只没有牙的老狗打了个哈欠，伸了个懒腰，对他们视若无睹。就像当年离家下楼时一样，他们悄无声息、偷偷摸摸地爬上楼。勃朗宁夫人轻手轻脚地打开一扇又一扇房门，似乎害怕会在里面看到什么，从一间房走到另一间。她看着看着就神情忧伤起来。“……那些房间在我看来，”她写道，“不知道怎么回事，又小又阴暗，家具既不合适，也不方便。”常春藤依然轻叩着后面卧房的窗玻璃，彩绘遮光帘依然遮蔽着光线。什么都没有改变。这么多年来仿佛什么都没有发生过似的。就这样，她从一个房间走到另一个房间，悲伤地回忆着。但还没等她结束探视，弗勒希就万分焦虑起来。万一巴雷特先生忽然进来，发现了他们该怎么办？万一他眉头一皱，转动钥匙，把他们永远锁在后面的卧室里该怎么办？勃朗宁夫人终于把所有的房门都关好，再一次悄没声儿地下了楼。没错，她说，在她看来，这栋房子需要好好打扫。

自那之后，弗勒希心中唯有一个愿望—永远离开伦敦，永远离开英国。直到发现自己身处穿越海峡、驶往法国的轮船甲板，他才快活起来。那是一趟波涛汹涌的航行。横穿海峡花费了八个小时。随着轮船颠簸摇晃，弗勒希那些骚动不安的混杂记忆也在他的心头翻来滚去—身穿紫色毛绒裙的淑女，拎着大包小包、衣衫褴褛的男人，摄政公园，在骑马侍卫簇拥下浩荡而过的维多利亚女王，翠绿的英国草地，恶臭的英国人行道—他躺在甲板上任这一幕幕场景滑过脑海。他抬起头，看见一位严肃、高大的男士倚栏而立。

“卡莱尔先生！”他听见勃朗宁夫人喊道，就在那一瞬间—可别忘了这次横渡很是艰险—弗勒希狂吐起来。水手们拎着水桶和拖把冲了过去。“……可怜的狗儿，他被特别下令驱逐下了甲板。”勃朗宁夫人说。因为甲板仍属英国领地，而狗是不可以在甲板上呕吐的。这便是他对故国海岸的最后致意。

[33]沃克吕兹（Vaucluse），位于法国东南部，是法国最大的罐头番茄、西瓜、苹果、葡萄和樱桃产地。

[34]查茨沃思（Chatsworth），位于英格兰德文郡，自1549年以来，一直为德文郡公爵的庄园。德文郡公爵的姓氏即为卡文迪什。建筑内收藏有众多珍贵的绘画、家具等文物，如17世纪之前欧洲画家的绘画、新古典主义雕塑和书籍。查茨沃思庄园多次被选为英国最受欢迎的庄园。

[35]瓦隆布罗萨（Vallombrosa），意大利中北部村镇，建于11世纪，是著名的修道院所在地和避暑胜地。

[36]斯温伯恩（Swinburne，1837-1909），英国维多利亚时代最后一位重要的诗人。在艺术手法上，他追求形象的鲜明华丽与大胆新奇、声调的和谐优美与婉转轻柔，对20世纪以来的诗人产生了深远的影响。

[37]拉斯金（Ruskin，1819-1900），英国作家、艺术家、艺术评论家，还是哲学家、教师和业余的地质学家。他的重要作品有《现代画家》《建筑的七盏灯》《威尼斯之石》等。

[38]乔治·艾略特（George Eliot，1819-1880），19世纪英国著名作家，与萨克雷、狄更斯、勃朗特姐妹齐名。主要作品有《弗洛斯河上的磨坊》《米德尔马契》等。

[39]萨沃纳罗拉（Savonarola，1452-1498），多明我会修士，佛罗伦萨宗教改革家。从1494年到1498年担任佛罗伦萨的精神和世俗领袖。他以反对文艺复兴艺术和哲学，焚烧艺术品和非宗教类书籍，毁灭他认为不道德的奢侈品，以及严厉的布道著称。

[40]此处的卡莱尔夫人，应为托马斯·卡莱尔（Thomas Carlyle，1795-1881）的妻子。托马斯·卡莱尔是一位作家、历史学家、哲学家和极具影响力的社会评论家。他的妻子简（Jane Welsh Carlyle）也是位著名的作家。当时的许多文学泰斗是他们家的常客，比如查尔斯·狄更斯、勃朗宁夫妇和约翰·拉斯金等。

[41]查尔斯·金斯利（Charles Kingsley，1819-1875），英国文学家、学者与神学家。早年曾先后就学于皇家学院、伦敦大学以及剑桥大学，后常年担任牧师、教授，并开始发表作品。他擅长儿童文学创作，作品具有世界声誉。

[42]多纳泰罗（Donatello，1386？-1466），意大利文艺复兴初期佛罗伦萨雕塑家，写实主义雕塑的奠基人之一，研究过人体结构，代表作有《大卫》《加塔梅拉塔骑马像》等。

[43]萨里郡（Surrey），英格兰东南部的郡，位于伦敦西南。

第六章　结局

/

弗勒希现在老了。英格兰之旅以及由此激发的种种回忆毫无疑问使他身心俱疲。大家都注意到，自从返回后，他总是宁可待在阴影里，而不是阳光下，即便佛罗伦萨的阴影热过温波尔街的阳光。他在雕像下面伸展四肢趴着，在喷泉出水口下方蜷着，只为享受几滴不时溅在毛皮上的水珠，他就这样趴着打上好几个小时的盹。年轻的狗儿会来到他近旁，他会给他们讲白教堂和温波尔街的故事，他会描绘苜蓿的气味和牛津街的味道，他会将记忆中一场接一场的革命生动演绎—大公爵们上位又垮台，可左边巷子里那只带斑点的西班牙猎犬—她却生生不息，始终都在，他会这么说。接着，脾气暴躁的兰多尔先生会急匆匆走过，假装愤怒地对他挥挥拳头；好心的艾莎·布莱格登小姐会停下来，从手提袋里掏出一块甘甜的饼干。市场里的农妇在菜篮子的阴影处用树叶给他铺了张床，还时不时给他扔串葡萄。整个佛罗伦萨—不论身份高贵还是平凡，不论是人还是狗—都认识他，喜欢他。

可他却渐渐变得老态龙钟了，连喷泉下面都懒得去趴了—因为鹅卵石地面对他这身老骨头来说太硬了—而是趴在勃朗宁夫人卧室的地板上，那块用人造大理石镶成的圭迪家族的纹章特别平滑；或者躲在客厅桌子底下的阴影里。从伦敦返回后没多久，一天他摊开四足趴在那儿很快就睡沉了。他深陷于年老者那种无梦的酣睡中。事实上今天他睡得比往日更沉，在他熟睡之际，黑暗仿佛在他周围变得更为浓稠。倘若他真能梦到什么，也很可能是梦见自己睡在原始森林的最深处，远离所有的阳光，与人类的声响隔绝—虽然他偶尔会梦见自己听见某只睡梦中的鸟儿正发出喃喃的啁啾，或是风儿拂过枝头时一只沉思的小猴儿发出柔声的轻笑。

树枝被猛然分开，光线涌入—到处洒落着一道道炫目的光束。猴儿们吱吱唧唧，鸟儿惊起，高声啼警。他腾地起身，睡意全消。他的周围泛起一场惊天动地的骚乱。他原是躺在客厅一张普通桌子的桌脚中间睡着了，现在却被众多翻腾的裙摆和起伏的裤脚包围，连桌子本身都开始剧烈地左右摇晃。他不知道该往哪个方向跑。究竟发生了什么？天知道这桌子到底中了什么邪。他抬高嗓音长号一声以示询问。

可弗勒希的问题没有得到满意的答案。仅能在此罗列几项最单调乏味的事实。简言之，似乎在十九世纪初，布莱辛顿伯爵夫人从一位魔术师那儿购买了一个水晶球，但伯爵夫人“从来不明白它的用途”。事实上，除了水晶本身之外，她从没在那个球里看到过任何别的东西。然而，在她去世后，她的私人物件被拍卖，于是这个球落到了那些“眼力更深邃，目光更澄澈”的人手里，这些人在球里看到了水晶之外的东西。至于这位买家是否为斯坦厄普大人，“目光更澄澈”的人是不是他，无从查证。但可以确定的是，到了一八五二年，斯坦厄普大人确实拥有一个水晶球，而—他可以在球里看到“太阳的精灵”。显而易见的是，热情好客的贵族当然不会独享此等景观，斯坦厄普大人就习惯在午宴时展示他的水晶球，邀请朋友也来看看太阳的精灵。球内的景象拥有某种令人愉悦的奇特性质—但乔利先生对此免疫。水晶球开始风靡一时。幸运的是，一位伦敦的眼镜制造商很快发现自己能够制造出同样的水晶球，尽管他既不是埃及人，也不是魔术师。可想而知，英国产的水晶价格不菲。因此，在十九世纪五十年代初，很多人都开始痴迷水晶球。然而，“绝大多数人，”斯坦厄普大人说，“会使用水晶球，却没有承认这件事的道德勇气。”精灵在伦敦的流行程度变得如此明目张胆，以至于触发了某种警报。斯坦利大人向爱德华·利顿[44]爵士提议，“政府应当指派调查委员尽可能深入地发掘事实真相”。不知即将成立官方调查委员会的传言是否使精灵们大为警惕，也不知精灵是否也跟肉身一样，倾向于在幽闭空间内大量繁殖，但毋庸置疑的是，精灵开始显现不安分的迹象，并—成群结队地逃出水晶球，在桌腿里重寻安身之所。—不论动机为何，总之这个策略是成功的。水晶球价格昂贵，而桌子却几乎人人有之。因此，一八五二年冬天勃朗宁夫人回到意大利时，发现精灵已先行抵达；佛罗伦萨的桌子差不多全都被精灵占领了，无一幸免。“从公使馆人员到英籍药剂师，”她写道，“大家都在‘伺候’桌子……无处不是。人们围坐在桌旁，可不是为了玩惠斯特牌。”不，那是在破译桌腿传达的信息。比如，如果被问及某个孩子的岁数，桌子便会“极智慧地用桌腿敲击地面表达自己，并根据字母表的次序一一作答”。既然一张桌子能说出你的孩子已经四岁了，那么它岂非无所不能？旋转桌在商店里做起了广告。墙上贴满宣传神奇的“里窝那[45]的发现”的海报。到一八五四年，这股潮流蔓延速度如此之快，“美国有四十万个家庭表示……曾经亲身享受过与精灵沟通的乐趣”。而在英国则有消息称，爱德华·布尔沃-利顿爵士进口了“数个美国敲击精灵”到内布沃思，结果喜人—当小阿瑟·拉塞尔在用早餐时看见“一个身着破旧晨衣、相貌怪异的老绅士”瞪着他时，他被告知布尔沃-利顿爵士相信自己可以隐身了[9]。

勃朗宁夫人首次在午餐会上朝斯坦厄普大人的水晶球里探望时，什么都没看见—只不过看出它的确是个极能象征那个时代精神的东西。太阳的精灵也的确告诉她，她就要去罗马了；但由于她并不打算去罗马，她违背了太阳精灵的话。“话说回来，”她坦诚地补充说，“我喜欢不可思议。”如果不爱冒险，那就不是她了。她曾经冒着生命危险前去曼宁街，在距离温波尔街不到半小时车程的地方，发现了一个她想象之外的世界。所以，为什么佛罗伦萨附近就不应该存在这样一个须臾可至的世界呢—一个更好、更美丽的世界，死者在那儿栖身，徒劳地想触及我们的世界？无论如何，她愿意冒这个险。于是她也在桌旁就座。在座的有利顿先生—那位隐身老先生的聪明儿子，弗雷德里克·坦尼森先生，鲍尔斯先生，以及维拉里先生—他们每个人都坐在桌旁。待桌腿踢够了后，他们继续坐在桌旁喝着茶吃着奶油草莓侃侃而谈，而“佛罗伦萨隐入紫色群山，群星闪耀”。“……我们讲述了何等奇妙的故事，我们发誓见到了何等的奇迹！噢，艾莎，我们这群人全是信徒，只有罗伯特除外……”随后，胡子花白又耳背的柯卡普先生突然冲了进来。他特意过来只为宣告：“神灵世界的确存在—未来之国度也一样。我承认。我终于确信了。”向来自诩“离无神论者仅一步之遥”的柯卡普先生之所以改变了信仰，仅仅是因为他尽管耳聋，却听见了“三声响亮的叩击，令他惊跳起来”！勃朗宁夫人还怎能跟桌子保持距离呢？“要知道我是个沉溺于幻想的人，期望敲遍现实世界的每一扇门，只为逃离。”她写道。因此，她召集那些信徒来圭迪府邸。他们坐在那儿把手放在客厅的桌子上，试图逃离。

弗勒希在极度的忧惧中惊起。裙裾和裤腿翻滚在他四周。桌子靠一条腿立着。可是无论围坐桌旁的那些绅士淑女听见或看到了什么，弗勒希却什么也没听见，什么也没看见。的确，桌子单腿站立着，但只要你用力压住一边，任何一张桌子都能如此。他自己就曾经掀翻过桌子，还为此被臭骂。不过，勃朗宁夫人此刻大眼圆睁瞪视着，似乎看见外面有什么不可思议的东西。弗勒希冲向阳台，四下张望。是不是又有一位大公爵在横幅和火把的簇拥下骑马经过？弗勒希看到的只有街角的老丐妇，她蜷伏在自己的一篮甜瓜旁。可勃朗宁夫人显然看见了什么，看见了某样非常美妙的东西。就像以前在温波尔街时，有一次她无端抽泣起来，他瞧不出其中的缘由；还有一次她举起一张满是涂鸦的纸开怀大笑。但这次不一样，她此刻表情当中的某种东西吓到了他。这个房间，这张桌子，这些裙裾和裤腿里的某种东西，是他极其不喜欢的。

数个星期过去了，勃朗宁夫人越发全心沉溺于窥视隐形之物。遇上晴朗的大热天，她不去看蜥蜴在石头里爬进爬出，而是在桌前坐下；遇到满天星斗的黑夜，她并不读书或在纸上书写，而是趁勃朗宁先生外出时召唤威尔逊。威尔逊打着哈欠来了。接着，她们会一起坐在桌旁，一直等到那件主要用来遮阴的家具开始踢地板，勃朗宁夫人宣告说，这是在告诉威尔逊她马上就要生病了。威尔逊回答说自己只是很困。但没多久，不依不饶、正直—非常英派的威尔逊尖叫着陷入了晕厥，勃朗宁夫人满屋子乱转，忙着找“卫生醋”。在弗勒希看来，如此虚度一个宁静的晚上让人无比心塞，坐着读书岂不更好。

毋庸置疑，这些悬疑，无法形容的难闻气味，桌腿踢地，人的尖叫和醋味儿，全都令弗勒希神经紧张。小宝宝佩尼尼祈祷“请让弗勒希的毛再长回来”，这完全没问题，这个愿望弗勒希可以理解。可是像那样非要有臭烘烘、粗鄙长相的人在场，以及让那张明明只是桃花心木做的结实桌子做出古怪动作的祈祷方式，却触怒了他，也同样触怒了他那位强壮睿智、衣衫考究的男主人。然而，对弗勒希来说，比任何气味、任何古怪动作都要糟糕得多的，是勃朗宁夫人凝视窗外时脸上的表情。她似乎看见了什么美妙的事物，而其实那里什么也没有。弗勒希就活生生地站在她跟前，她的视线却穿透他，好像他不存在似的。这是她给予他的最残酷的表情，比她当初看到他咬了勃朗宁先生的腿时所表现出的冷漠与愤怒更残忍，比那次在摄政公园看见他的爪子被门夹住时发出的嘲讽的笑声更伤人。有些时刻，他还真有点儿怀念温波尔街和那里的桌子。至少温波尔街五十号的桌子从来没有单腿站立过。那张周围箍了一道铁圈，搁着她心爱装饰品的小桌总是默默地纹丝不动。在那些远远逝去的日子里，他只要一跳上巴雷特小姐的沙发，她就会立马清醒过来，注视着他。而如今，他再一次跳上她的沙发，她对他却置若罔闻。她在写作，完全忽视了他。她继续写道—“同时，应灵媒的要求，精灵之手从桌上拿起一个花环，把它戴到我的头上。做此事的那只手若以人手的尺寸来看，非常巨大，白皙如雪，非常美丽。它离我很近，就和此刻我正在写字的手一样近，我看得一清二楚。”弗勒希用力抓抓她。她的目光依旧穿透他，好似他不存在。他跳下沙发，冲下楼梯，跑到街上去了。

这是个酷热的午后。街角那位年老的女乞丐趴在她的甜瓜上睡着了。阳光似乎在空中嗡嗡作响。弗勒希贴着街道阴凉的一侧，沿早就熟稔于心的道路，小跑着往集市而去。整个广场到处都是遮阳篷、货摊和鲜艳的太阳伞，色彩斑斓。卖东西的妇人坐在一篮篮水果旁，鸽子扑扇着翅膀，钟声轰鸣，鞭子抽得啪啪响。佛罗伦萨那些五颜六色的杂种狗跑进跑出，嗅嗅刨刨。无处不是繁忙如蜂巢，热闹似火炉。弗勒希搜寻着阴影，投身于老朋友卡特琳娜身侧，在她大篮子的阴影里趴了下来。一个插着红色和黄色花朵的棕色罐子在旁边投下另一片阴影。一座雕像矗立于他们的上方，右臂向外伸展，使阴影的颜色变成更深的紫色。弗勒希趴在这块阴凉处，看着年轻的狗狗忙活自己的事。他们龇牙低吼，拉扯嘶咬，伸着懒腰打着滚，纵情享受着青春年少的快乐。他们互相追逐，进进出出，猛绕圈子，就像当年他在巷子里追逐那只有斑点的西班牙猎犬。他的思绪一度回到了雷丁—想起了帕特里奇先生的那条西班牙猎犬，想起了自己的初恋，想起了年少的痴狂与纯真。没错，他也曾经风华正茂。他并不嫉妒正享受当下的他们。他已经知道这个世界是个生活的好地方。他现在与世无争了。集市上的妇人挠了挠他的耳根。以前她经常因为他偷葡萄或做其他小小的坏事而打他，可现在他老了，她也老了。他看着她的甜瓜，她挠着他的耳朵；她织着她的毛衣，他打着他的盹。苍蝇围着切开露出果肉的粉色大甜瓜嗡嗡个不停。

阳光炙烤着百合花的叶子和绿白相间的太阳伞，散发着宜人的气息。大理石雕像慢慢升温，变得如香槟般新鲜。弗勒希趴在那儿，让阳光烤着皮毛，直透裸露的肌肤。等烤完一边，他翻了个身，再继续烤另一边。市场里的人始终叽叽喳喳个不停，讨价还价；妇人来来往往，不时停下来用手指捏一捏蔬菜和水果。嗡嗡作响的人声不绝于耳，弗勒希就爱听这声音。不一会儿，他便在百合花的阴影里睡着了。他睡着了，就像狗在做梦时那样。眼下他的腿抽搐起来—他是梦到自己在西班牙猎兔吗？当兔子从灌木丛中飞蹿而出，他是不是正沿着炽热的山坡向上奔跑，而黝黑的男人大喊着：“Span！Span！”然后他又一动不动地趴着。接着他吠了起来，又快又轻，连着叫了好几声。或许他听见雷丁的米特福德博士正在催促他的灵缇前去狩猎。后来他又温顺地摇摇尾巴。他是听见米特福德小姐喊道“坏狗！坏狗！”，遂夹着尾巴回到站在芜菁田里猛挥雨伞的米特福德小姐身旁了吗？接下来他趴着打了一会儿鼾，陷入老者愉悦的沉睡当中。突然，他身上的每一块肌肉都开始抽搐。他猛地被吓醒了。他以为自己身处何方，白教堂区的坏蛋之中？是不是又有一把刀架在他的脖子上？

无论如何，他在惊恐中从梦里醒来。他匆匆飞奔而去，仿佛在冲向安全地带，仿佛在搜寻庇护之所。集市上的妇人们大笑起来，拿烂葡萄丢他，唤他回来，但他没有理会。他穿过街道，差点被运货马车碾压到—站着驾车的男人诅咒他，抄起皮鞭想抽他。光着半截身子的小孩在他飞逃而过时朝他扔鹅卵石，嚷嚷着“疯狗！疯狗！”[46]。他们的母亲跑到门口，惊慌地把孩子们拉回家。那么他疯掉了？是不是太阳把他的脑袋烤坏了？还是他再一次听见了维纳斯狩猎的号角？抑或是某个美国敲击精灵—那些住在桌腿里的精灵之一，最终附身于他？不管是何原因，他抄近路穿过一条又一条街道，直抵圭迪府邸的大门口。他直接蹿上楼，径直冲进客厅。

勃朗宁夫人正躺在沙发上看书。他冲进去时，她抬起头来，吓了一跳。不，不是精灵—只是弗勒希罢了。她笑了。接着，当他跃上沙发，把脸贴上她的脸时，她曾经写过的一首诗突然浮现于脑海：

你看此狗。就在昨日

忘记他存在于斯的我沉入冥想

直到思绪联翩招来泪珠串串

泪湿双颊的我倚枕而卧

一个如福纳斯[47]般毛茸茸的脑袋，径直

突然探近我的脸——两只清澈的

金色大眼让我的眼睛一亮——一片垂耳

轻抚我的双颊，将泪痕擦干！

我先是讶异，仿若那阿卡狄亚人，

惊艳于暮色树林里的似羊之神；

可是，当蓄满虬髯的脸庞再贴近，

我的泪一扫而光，我知道那是弗勒希，

从惊讶与悲伤中脱身——感恩真正的潘神

虽是低等生物，却是他引我上爱的高峰。

多年以前的某一天，她在温波尔街写下这首诗，当时的她很不快乐。而如今她是幸福的。她日渐苍老，弗勒希亦是如此。她弯下腰，与他依偎了一会儿。她脸上的宽嘴、大眼，再加上浓密鬈发，依旧与他怪异地相似。尽管她与弗勒希各不相同，却又像是从一个模子里铸出来的，或许他俩彼此唤醒了对方身上蛰伏的个性，使对方更加完整了。然而她是个女人，他却是条狗。勃朗宁夫人接着看书。随后，她又看了看弗勒希。可他却没有回应。他身上发生了一种异乎寻常的变化。“弗勒希！”她叫道。但他阒然无声。他曾经活过，现在他死了[10]。仅此而已。说来也怪，客厅里的桌子静立着，纹丝未动。

[44]爱德华·利顿（Edward Lytton，1803-1873），英国政治家、诗人和批评家。

[45]原文为意大利语。里窝那为意大利地名。

[46]原文为意大利语。

[47]福纳斯（Faunus），古罗马神话当中的畜牧农林神，相当于古希腊神话中的潘。

原文注释

/

[1]彩绘织物—巴雷特小姐说：“我在打开的窗户前挂了一块透明的遮光帘。”她补充道，“爸爸取笑我说像糖果店的后窗，然而当阳光点燃城堡，他显然有所触动。”有人认为城堡及其他图样皆绘制在一片薄金属上，也有人认为那是一幅绣工精细的薄纱帘，但尚无确切定论。

[2]凯尼恩先生由于缺了两颗门牙而有些口齿不清。—这里有夸大及臆测的成分。米特福德小姐为始作俑者。据称她在与霍恩先生的对话中曾说过：“你要知道，我们那位亲爱的朋友，除了自己的家人和一两位朋友外，从不见外人。她高度评价某某先生的‘朗读’技巧和出色品位，常请他为自己大声朗读新诗……于是某某先生便站在壁炉前的地毯上，举起手稿，抬高音量，而我们亲爱的朋友则裹着印度披肩躺在沙发上，又厚又密的深色长发遮住低垂的头，全神贯注。现在，亲爱的某某先生掉了一颗门牙—其实不是门牙，而是门牙旁边的一颗牙—你看，这让发音出了问题……一种讨喜的口齿不清、音节含混，所以‘silence’和‘ilence’听起来真的并无二致……”毫无疑问，这位某某先生便是凯尼恩先生，因为维多利亚时代的人们对牙齿相关的话题出奇地敏感，因此必须隐去其名。只不过此事牵涉英国文学中更重要的问题。长久以来，巴雷特小姐被指耳朵有毛病。米特福德小姐则认为，凯尼恩先生牙齿的问题更值得诟病。但另一方面，巴雷特小姐本人却坚称自己作诗押韵跟他牙齿的缺失或她听力的低下，都没有关系。她写道：“我对韵文主题的重视，远甚于押韵的正确性，因此冷酷地决定孤注一掷，尝试多项实验。”因此她才会“冷酷地”把“angels”和“candles”、“heaven”和“unbelieving”、“islands”和“silence”当成同一个韵脚。当然，此事还待学者们定夺。然而任何一位研究过勃朗宁夫人性格及行为的人，想必都会认为无论对于艺术还是爱情，她都是一位刻意打破规则的人，因此才成为促成现代诗发展的“同谋共犯”。

[3]黄手套—据奥尔夫人的《勃朗宁生平》记载，他戴柠檬黄的手套。布里德尔·福克斯夫人曾在一八三五至一八三六年见过他，她说过：“那时的他修长黝黑，非常帅气，而——容我在此暗示—有一点点纨绔子弟的味道，特别喜欢穿戴柠檬黄小山羊皮手套之类的东西。”

[4]“他被偷走了。”—事实上，弗勒希被偷了三次，但为求结构紧凑，这里将三次浓缩为一次。巴雷特小姐付给偷狗贼的赎金合计为二十英镑。

[5]多年后，当她坐在意大利阳光灿烂的阳台上写作时，那些面孔还会再次浮现于她的眼前。—长诗《奥罗拉·利》中的人物皆为虚构，想必当勃朗宁夫人写这首诗时，部分最生动的诗行描写的就是伦敦的一个贫民窟（尽管对于一个艺术家而言，它自然是扭曲的，更何况她只是坐在一辆四轮马车上见过一次，威尔逊还拽着她的衣角）。显然，勃朗宁夫人对人类生活的满满好奇心，单靠卧室盥洗台上的荷马、乔叟半身像是满足不了的。

[6]莉莉·威尔逊跟侍卫里吉先生陷入热恋。—莉莉·威尔逊的一生鲜为人知，亟须传记作者给予—注。勃朗宁夫妇信札中所提及的人物，除主要人物外，没有谁比威尔逊更能激发好奇心并心生困惑了。她的教名为莉莉，姓威尔逊。这就是我们知道的跟她的出身和成长背景相关的一切了。她可能是霍普恩德附近一位农场主的女儿，因为举止端庄、围裙洁净而受到巴雷特府邸厨师的赏识，得以来到府邸当差。那时候巴雷特夫人找了个借口进到那个房间观察，认为她相当不错，于是指派她担任伊丽莎白小姐的女仆。又或者因为她是个伦敦佬，或是来自苏格兰—都有可能。无论如何，一八四六年时，她在服侍巴雷特小姐，而—是个“报酬不菲的仆人”—年薪十六英镑。由于她几乎跟弗勒希一样沉默寡言，所以她的性格几乎不为人知；又由于巴雷特小姐从未为她写过诗，她的面目远不如弗勒希清晰。不过从信札当中的各种暗示判断，显然她从一开始便属于严肃端庄到非人性化地步的英国女仆类型，在当时是英国地下室用人区的荣耀。同样显而易见的是，威尔逊对于权力及仪典也严格遵守。她极端尊敬“那个房间”；她肯定是第一个坚持下级仆役和上级仆役必须在不同的地方吃布丁的人。所有这些都隐匿在她用手打弗勒希后说的那句话当中—“因为他该打”。自不待言的是，如此推崇传统，势必催生对反传统的极端恐惧，因此当威尔逊面对曼宁街的下层社会时，她比巴雷特小姐更为惊骇，更为确定那些偷狗贼都是杀人犯。与此同时，她战胜恐惧，陪同巴雷特小姐登上马车的英雄行为，显示出对女主人的忠诚在她心中是多么地根深蒂固。巴雷特小姐去哪儿，威尔逊一定跟着去哪儿。私奔事件发生时，她成功地践行了这一原则。巴雷特小姐曾对威尔逊的勇气有所怀疑，但她的疑虑毫无根据。“威尔逊，”她写道—这些是她以巴雷特小姐的身份写给勃朗宁先生的最后一些文字—“对我不能再好了，而我……却指责她‘胆小’，怕她会胆怯！我开始认为胆小的人一旦受到适当的激励，会比谁都更勇猛。”顺便说一句，此处值得我们花费一秒钟关注一下仆役极不稳定的生活状态。如果威尔逊不跟巴雷特小姐走，就巴雷特小姐所知，肯定会“在日落前流落街头”，只怀揣着几个先令，或许还是从十六英镑年薪里攒下来的积蓄。接下来她将遭遇何种命运？由于十九世纪四十年代的英国小说鲜少讨论小姐贴身女仆的生活，传记作者的探照灯又从未探寻至如此低的阶层，这个问题恐怕永远无解。但威尔逊决定冒险，宣称将“跟随我到天涯海角”。她抛弃了地下室，抛弃了“那个房间”，还抛弃了温波尔街所代表的整个世界—这个世界对威尔逊意味着一切文明礼教，一切正确思想和体面生活—投身异国他乡的道德败坏与反宗教。再没有比观察威尔逊到了意大利之后，在英国式的礼教和与生俱来的热情之间所进行的挣扎更有意思的事了。她嘲笑意大利的宫廷，因意大利的名画而震惊。然而，“惊骇于维纳斯的有失体统”的她，却难得地没有忘记一项事实：任何女人脱光衣服之后，都是赤裸的。或许她曾经想过：就连我，每天也免不了得赤裸两三秒钟吧。所以，“她觉得自己应该再尝试一次，或许那令人心烦的端庄会消退，谁知道呢”？它显然是迅速消失了！没多久，她不仅喜欢上意大利，还和大公爵的贴身侍卫里吉先生坠入爱河。这些侍卫都是既高尚又有道德的男士，—有人身高达六英尺。她戴起了订婚戒指，打发了一位来自伦敦的追求者，还开始学习意大利语。然而好景不长，待拨云散雾之后，我们看到威尔逊被抛弃了—“背信弃义的里吉解除了和威尔逊的婚约”。从中作梗的似乎是里吉的兄弟，他是普拉托的男子服饰用品批发商。里吉辞去大公爵贴身侍卫一职，采纳了兄弟的建议，在普拉托做起了男子服饰用品的零售买卖。或许是因为他的新工作需要一位对男子服饰用品有—业知识的妻子，或许是因为普拉托有个女孩具备了这类—业知识，可以肯定的是，他不再经常写信给威尔逊，尽管他本应该写。到底这位既高尚又有道德的男士干了什么坏事，令勃朗宁夫人在一八五〇年慨叹道：“（威尔逊）已经完全想开了，多亏她头脑清楚、个性稳健。她怎么能再继续爱这样的男人呢？”—里吉为何在如此短的时间里便被贬为“这样的男人”，我们无从猜测。被里吉抛弃的威尔逊与勃朗宁一家关系愈来愈密切。她不仅担任贴身女仆，还烘烤蛋糕、缝制衣裳，并—成为宝宝佩尼尼的慈爱保姆；宝宝就此认定她属于家庭成员之一，不叫她别的，而是直呼其名莉莉。一八五五年，威尔逊嫁于勃朗宁家的男仆—罗马尼奥利，“一位心地善良的好人”；两人共同照料勃朗宁宅邸一段时间。然而，一八五九年，罗伯特·勃朗宁“接下兰多尔监护人一职”，这个职位责任重大，—顾虑甚多，因为兰多尔的种种习惯让人头疼。“完全不懂得克制自己，”勃朗宁夫人写道，“却极善猜忌。”在种种状况下，威尔逊被指派做“他的保姆”，“除他的配额所余之外”，再领年薪二十二英镑。后来她的薪水一直加到了三十英镑，因为“老狮子”兰多尔“冲动如老虎”，他若对晚餐不满意，二话不说便把盘子扔出窗外或摔在地上；又常怀疑仆人偷偷打开桌子抽屉。担任他的保姆，诚如勃朗宁夫人所说：“须冒若干危险，换作是我，宁愿躲得远远的。”但对见识过巴雷特先生及各种精灵的威尔逊来说，几个扔出窗外或摔在地上的盘子不过是小菜一碟—诸如此类的危险充斥着日常工作。

我们能够了解到的是，那一天确乎是不同寻常的一天。无论它是否始于某偏远的英国乡村，总之它是在威尼斯的雷佐尼科府邸结束的。至少到一八九七年她还住在那儿，当时她已经成了一名寡妇，而男主人正是她曾经挚爱并喂养长大的小男孩—巴雷特·勃朗宁先生。当她这位老妇人坐在威尼斯通红的夕阳前浮想联翩时，她大概也觉得这是不同寻常的一天吧。她那些嫁给农场帮工的朋友至今仍为买一品脱的啤酒而在英国的小巷间踉跄前行。而她却跟随巴雷特小姐私奔到了意大利，见识了林林总总的怪事—革命、侍卫、精灵，还有老把盘子扔出窗外的兰多尔先生。那时勃朗宁夫人已过世—坐在雷佐尼科府邸夕照窗前的老威尔逊心中想必感触良多。但我们若想假装猜得出她的心思，那可就太自不量力，因为她正是昔日那一大批高深莫测、守口如瓶、隐而不显的优良女仆的典范。—让我们引用她女主人的一句话替她盖棺定论吧：“天底下再也找不到比威尔逊更诚实、更真诚、更重感情的人了。”

[7]他饱受跳蚤之苦。—显然十九世纪中叶的意大利因其跳蚤而闻名。事实上，这些跳蚤让他们打破了不可逾越的传统。比方说，一八五八年在罗马，纳撒尼尔·霍桑去跟布雷默小姐喝茶时：“我们谈到跳蚤—这种小昆虫在罗马无孔不入，入侵每个人的私生活，如此司空见惯，在所难免，以至于大家聊起蚤患之苦毫不避讳。可怜了娇小的布雷默尔小姐，替我们倒茶时就因一只跳蚤而不堪其扰……”

[8]尼禄从顶楼窗口跳了出去。—据卡莱尔所说，尼禄（1849-1860）是条“毛发浓密的小古巴犬（可能是马耳他狗或是杂种狗），毛色主要为白色，是一条情深意重、充满活力的小狗，除此之外优点甚少，而—几乎毫无训练”。关于它的一生资料丰富，却不适用于此。只需提及它曾被偷，它的脖子上被绑了一张支票带回给卡莱尔，那金额足够买一匹马；而—“我把它抛进阿伯道尔的海里不止两三次，它一点儿都不喜欢”。一八五〇年，它从图书室的窗口跳出去，避开了通风井栏杆的尖顶，“啪嗒”一声摔在人行道上。“那是早餐后，”卡莱尔夫人说，“它一直站在敞开的窗户旁看小鸟……我躺在床上，突然听见伊丽莎白在松木隔板后面尖叫：噢，上帝！噢，尼禄！然后像狂风般冲下楼梯，跑出门外，来到街上……我穿着睡衣跟着冲出去找她……卡莱尔先生从卧室里下来，下巴上满是肥皂泡泡，问道：‘尼禄出什么事了？’—‘噢，先生，它肯定四条腿全摔断了！它刚从你的窗口跳出去！’—‘上帝保佑！’卡莱尔先生说完后便转身回去继续把胡子刮完。”然而，尼禄一根骨头都没摔断，活得好好的。后来他被一辆屠夫的运货马车碾过，终于在一八六〇年二月一日因那次车祸的后遗症去世，被埋在切尼洛花园内的一块小石碑下面。

它是否真的想自杀，还是诚如卡莱尔夫人暗示的，只是想跃起捉鸟而已，或许值得我们写一篇相当有意思的犬类心理学论文。有人认为拜伦的狗因为同情拜伦，也跟着他一起发了疯；还有人认为尼禄是因为卡莱尔先生的缘故，罹患不可救药的抑郁症。关于狗与时代精神的关系—譬如我们是否能形容某条狗是伊丽莎白时期的，或奥古斯都时期的，或维多利亚时期的—以及狗主人之诗作和哲学思想对他们的狗所造成的影响，这些主题值得大书特书，在此篇幅有限，无法深谈。我们只能说，尼禄跳楼的动机扑朔迷离。

[9]布尔沃-利顿爵士相信自己可以隐身了。—休思·杰克逊夫人在《维多利亚时代的童年》中写道：“阿瑟·拉塞尔爵士告诉我，多年以前，他还是个小孩子的时候，他母亲带他去内布沃思。第二天早晨他在大餐厅里吃早饭，一个身着破旧晨衣、相貌怪异的老绅士走了进来，缓缓绕餐桌而行，轮流瞪视每一位客人。他听见母亲的邻座对其耳语：‘不必理会，他以为自己可以隐身。’那便是利顿爵士本尊。”（第十七至十八页）

[10]现在他死了。—弗勒希当然是死了，但是他死亡的日期及方式都不为人知。唯一相关的记载是：“弗勒希寿终正寝，葬于圭迪府邸地穴。”勃朗宁夫人葬于佛罗伦萨的英国公墓，罗伯特·勃朗宁则葬于威斯敏斯特教堂。因此，弗勒希至今仍躺在勃朗宁夫妇曾经生活过的那幢宅邸之下。

Chapter 1　THREE MILE CROSS

It is universally admitted that the family from which the subject of this memoir claims descent is one of the greatest antiquity. Therefore it is not strange that the origin of the name itself is lost in obscurity. Many million years ago the country which is now called Spain seethed uneasily in the ferment of creation. Ages passed; vegetation appeared; where there is vegetation the law of Nature has decreed that there shall be rabbits; where there are rabbits, Providence has ordained there shall be dogs. There is nothing in this that calls for question or comment. But when we ask why the dog that caught the rabbit was called a Spaniel, then doubts and difficulties begin. Some historians say that when the Carthaginians landed in Spain the common soldiers shouted with one accord ‘Span! Span!' - for rabbits darted from every scrub, from every bush. The land was alive with rabbits. And Span in the Carthaginian tongue signifies Rab-bit. Thus the land was called Hispania, or Rabbit-land, and the dogs, which were almost instantly perceived in full pur-suit of the rabbits, were called Spaniels or rabbit dogs.

There many of us would be content to let the matter rest; but truth compels us to add that there is another school of thought which thinks differently. The word Hispania, these scholars say, has nothing whatever to do with the Carthagin-ian word span. Hispania derives from the Basque word españa, signifying an edge or boundary. If that is so, rabbits, bushes, dogs, soldiers - the whole of that romantic and pleasant picture, must be dismissed from the mind; and we must simply suppose that the Spaniel is called a spaniel because Spain is called España. As for the third school of antiquaries which maintains that just as a lover calls his mistress monster or monkey, so the Spaniards called their favourite dogs crooked or cragged (the word españa can be made to take these meanings) because a spaniel is notori-ously the opposite - that is too fanciful a conjecture to be seriously entertained.

Passing over these theories, and many more which need not detain us here, we reach Wales in the middle of the tenth century. The spaniel is already there, brought, some say, by the Spanish clan of Ebhor or Ivor many centuries previ-ously; and certainly by the middle of the tenth century a dog of high repute and value. ‘The Spaniel of the King is a pound in value,' Howel Dha laid it down in his Book of Laws. And when we remember what the pound could buy in the year AD 948 - how many wives, slaves, horses, oxen, turkeys and geese - it is plain that the spaniel was already a dog of value and reputation. He had his place already by the King' s side. His family was held in honour before those of many famous monarchs. He was taking his ease in pal-aces when the Plantagenets and the Tudors and the Stuarts were following other people' s ploughs through other people' s mud. Long before the Howards, the Cavendishes or the Russells had risen above the common ruck of Smiths, Joneses and Tomkins, the spaniel family was a family distinguished and apart. And as the centuries took their way, minor branches broke off from the parent stem. By degrees, as English history pursues its course, there came into existence at least seven famous Spaniel families - the Clumber, the Sussex, the Norfolk, the Black Field, the Cocker, the Irish Water and the English Water, all deriving from the original spaniel of prehistoric days but show-ing distinct characteristics, and therefore no doubt claiming privileges as distinct. That there was an aristocracy of dogs by the time Queen Elizabeth was on the throne Sir Philip Sidney bears witness: ‘ …… greyhounds, Spaniels and Hounds', he observes, ‘whereof the first might seem the Lords, the second the Gentlemen, and the last the Yeomen of dogs', he writes in the Arcadia.

But if we are thus led to assume that the Spaniels followed human example, and looked up to Greyhounds as their superiors and considered Hounds beneath them, we have to admit that their aristocracy was founded on better reasons than ours. Such at least must be the conclusion of anyone who studies the laws of the Spaniel Club. By that august body it is plainly laid down what constitute the vices of a spaniel, and what constitute its virtues. Light eyes, for example, are undesirable; curled ears are still worse; to be born with a light nose or a topknot is nothing less than fatal. The merits of the spaniel are equally clearly defined. His head must be smooth, rising without a too-decided stoop from the muzzle; the skull must be comparatively rounded and well developed with plenty of room for brain power; the eyes must be full but not gozzled; the general expression must be one of intelligence and gentleness. The spaniel that exhibits these points is encouraged and bred from; the span-iel who persists in perpetuating topknots and light noses is cut off from the privileges and emoluments of his kind. Thus the judges lay down the law and, laying down the law, impose penalties and privileges which ensure that the law shall be obeyed.

But, if we now turn to human society, what chaos and confusion meet the eye! No Club has any such jurisdiction upon the breed of man. The Heralds' College is the nearest approach we have to the Spaniel Club. It at least makes some attempt to preserve the purity of the human family. But when we ask what constitutes noble birth - should our eyes be light or dark, our ears curled or straight, are topknots fatal, our judges merely refer us to our coats of arms. You have none perhaps. Then you are nobody. But once make good your claim to sixteen quarterings, prove your right to a coronet, and then they say you are not only born, but nobly born into the bargain. Hence it is that not a muffineer in all Mayfair lacks its lion couchant or its mermaid rampant. Even our linendrapers mount the Royal Arms above their doors, as though that were proof that their sheets are safe to sleep in. Everywhere rank is claimed and its virtues are asserted. Yet when we come to survey the Royal Houses of Bourbon, Hapsburg and Hohenzollern, decorated with how many coronets and quarterings, couchant and rampant with how many lions and leopards, and find them now in exile, deposed from authority, judged unworthy of respect, we can but shake our heads and admit that the Judges of the Spaniel Club judged better. Such is the lesson that is enforced directly we turn from these high matters to consider the early life of Flush in the family of the Mitfords.

About the end of the eighteenth century a family of the famous spaniel breed was living near Reading in the house of a certain Dr Midford or Mitford. That gentleman, in con-formity with the canons of the Heralds' College, chose to spell his name with a t, and thus claimed descent from the Northumberland family of the Mitfords of Bertram Castle. His wife was a Miss Russell, and sprang, if remotely, still decidedly from the ducal house of Bedford. But the mating of Dr Mitford' s ancestors had been carried on with such wanton disregard for principles that no bench of judges could have admitted his claim to be well bred or have allowed him to perpetuate his kind. His eyes were light; his ears were curled; his head exhibited the fatal topknot. In other words, he was utterly selfish, recklessly extravagant, worldly, insincere and addicted to gambling. He wasted his own fortune, his wife' s fortune, and his daughter' s earnings. He deserted them in his prosperity and sponged upon them in his in firmity. Two points he had in his favour indeed, great personal beauty - he was like an Apollo until gluttony and intemperance changed Apollo into Bacchus - and he was genuinely devoted to dogs. But there can be no doubt that, had there been a Man Club corresponding to the Span-iel Club in existence, no spelling of Mitford with a t instead of with a d, no calling cousins with the Mitfords of Bertram Castle, would have availed to protect him from contumely and contempt, from all the penalties of outlawry and ostra-cism, from being branded as a mongrel man unfitted to carry on his kind. But he was a human being. Nothing therefore prevented him from marrying a lady of birth and breeding, from living for over eighty years, from having in his possession several generations of greyhounds and span-iels and from begetting a daughter.

All researches have failed to fix with any certainty the exact year of Flush' s birth, let alone the month or the day; but it is likely that he was born some time early in the year 1842.It is also probable that he was directly descended from Tray (c.1816), whose points, preserved unfortunately only in the untrustworthy medium of poetry, prove him to have been a red cocker spaniel of merit. There is every reason to think that Flush was the son of that ‘real old cocking spaniel' for whom Dr Mitford refused twenty guineas ‘on account of his excellence in the field'. It is to poetry, alas, that we have to trust for our most detailed description of Flush himself as a young dog. He was of that particular shade of dark brown which in sunshine flashes ‘all over into gold'. His eyes were ‘startled eyes of hazel bland'. His ears were ‘tasselled'; his ‘slender feet' were ‘canopied in fringes' and his tail was broad. Making allowance for the exigencies of rhyme and the inac-curacies of poetic diction, there is nothing here but what would meet with the approval of the Spaniel Club. We cannot doubt that Flush was a pure-bred Cocker of the red variety marked by all the characteristic excellences of his kind.

The first months of his life were passed at Three Mile Cross, a working man' s cottage near Reading. Since the Mitfords had fallen on evil days - Kerenhappock was the only servant - the chair-covers were made by Miss Mitford herself and of the cheapest material; the most important article of furniture seems to have been a large table; the most important room a large greenhouse - it is unlikely that Flush was surrounded by any of those luxuries, rain-proof kennels, cement walks, a maid or boy attached to his person, that would now be accorded a dog of his rank. But he throve; he enjoyed with all the vivacity of his temperament most of the pleasures and some of the licences natural to his youth and sex. Miss Mitford, it is true, was much confined to the cottage. She had to read aloud to her father hour after hour; then to play cribbage; then, when at last he slumbered, to write and write and write at the table in the greenhouse in the attempt to pay their bills and settle their debts. But at last the longed-for moment would come. She thrust her papers aside, clapped a hat on her head, took her umbrella and set off for a walk across the fields with her dogs. Span-iels are by nature sympathetic; Flush, as his story proves, had an even excessive appreciation of human emotions. The sight of his dear mistress snuffing the fresh air at last, letting it ruffle her white hair and redden the natural freshness of her face, while the lines on her huge brow smoothed them-selves out, excited him to gambols whose wildness was half sympathy with her own delight. As she strode through the long grass, so he leapt hither and thither, parting its green curtain. The cool globes of dew or rain broke in showers of iridescent spray about his nose; the earth, here hard, here soft, here hot, here cold, stung, teased and tickled the soft pads of his feet. Then what a variety of smells interwoven in subtlest combination thrilled his nostrils; strong smells of earth, sweet smells of flowers; nameless smells of leaf and bramble; sour smells as they crossed the road; pungent smells as they entered bean-fields. But suddenly down the wind came tearing a smell sharper, stronger, more lacerating than any - a smell that ripped across his brain stirring a thousand instincts, releasing a million memories - the smell of hare, the smell of fox. Off he flashed like a fish drawn in a rush through water further and further. He forgot his mistress; he forgot all human kind. He heard dark men cry ‘Span! Span!' He heard whips crack. He raced; he rushed. At last he stopped bewildered; the incantation faded; very slowly, wagging his tail sheepishly, he trotted back across the fields to where Miss Mitford stood shouting ‘Flush! Flush! Flush!' and waving her umbrella. And once at least the call was even more imperious; the hunting horn roused deeper instincts, summoned wilder and stronger emotions that transcended memory and obliterated grass, trees, hare, rabbit, fox in one wild shout of ecstasy. Love blazed her torch in his eyes; he heard the hunting horn of Venus. Before he was well out of his puppyhood, Flush was a father.

Such conduct in a man even, in the year 1842,would have called for some excuse from a biographer; in a woman no excuse could have availed; her name must have been blotted in ignominy from the page. But the moral code of dogs, whether better or worse, is certainly different from ours, and there was nothing in Flush' s conduct in this respect that requires a veil now, or unfitted him for the society of the purest and the chastest in the land then. There is evidence, that is to say, that the elder brother of Dr Pusey was anxious to buy him. Deducing from the known character of Dr Pusey the probable character of his brother, there must have been something serious, solid, promising well for future excellence whatever might be the levity of the present in Flush even as a puppy. But a much more significant testi-mony to the attractive nature of his gifts is that, even though Mr Pusey wished to buy him, Miss Mitford refused to sell him. As she was at her wits' end for money, scarcely knew indeed what tragedy to spin, what annual to edit, and was reduced to the repulsive expedient of asking her friends for help, it must have gone hard with her to refuse the sum off ered by the elder brother of Dr Pusey. Twenty pounds had been offered for Flush' s father. Miss Mitford might well have asked ten or fifteen for Flush. Ten or fifteen pounds was a princely sum, a magnificent sum to have at her dis-posal. With ten or fifteen pounds she might have re-covered her chairs, she might have re-stocked her greenhouse, she might have bought herself an entire wardrobe, and ‘I have not bought a bonnet, a cloak, a gown, hardly a pair of gloves', she wrote in 1842, ‘for four years'.

But to sell Flush was unthinkable. He was of the rare order of objects that cannot be associated with money. Was he not of the still rarer kind that, because they typify what is spiritual, what is beyond price, become a fitting token of the disinterestedness of friendship; may be offered in that spirit to a friend, if one is lucky enough to have one, who is more like a daughter than a friend; to a friend who lies secluded all through the summer months in a back bedroom in Wimpole Street, to a friend who is no other than Eng-land' s foremost poetess, the brilliant, the doomed, the adored Elizabeth Barrett herself? Such were the thoughts that came more and more frequently to Miss Mitford as she watched Flush rolling and scampering in the sunshine; as she sat by the couch of Miss Barrett in her dark, ivy-shaded London bedroom. Yes; Flush was worthy of Miss Barrett; Miss Barrett was worthy of Flush. The sacrifice was a great one; but the sacrifice must be made. Thus, one day, probably in the early summer of the year 1842, a remarkable couple might have been seen taking their way down Wimpole Street - a very short, stout, shabby, elderly lady, with a bright red face and bright white hair, who led by the chain a very spirited, very inquisitive, very well-bred golden cocker spaniel puppy. They walked almost the whole length of the street until at last they paused at No.50.Not without trepi-dation, Miss Mitford rang the bell.

Even now perhaps nobody rings the bell of a house in Wimpole Street without trepidation. It is the most august of London streets, the most impersonal. Indeed, when the world seems tumbling to ruin, and civilisation rocks on its foundations, one has only to go to Wimpole Street; to pace that avenue; to survey those houses; to consider their uni-formity; to marvel at the window curtains and their consistency; to admire the brass knockers and their regu-larity; to observe butchers tendering joints and cooks receiving them; to reckon the incomes of the inhabitants and infer their consequent submission to the laws of God and man - one has only to go to Wimpole Street and drink deep of the peace breathed by authority in order to heave a sigh of thankfulness that, while Corinth has fallen and Messina has tumbled, while crowns have blown down the wind and old Empires have gone up in flames, Wimpole Street has remained unmoved, and, turning from Wimpole Street into Oxford Street, a prayer rises in the heart and bursts from the lips that not a brick of Wimpole Street may be re-pointed, not a curtain washed, not a butcher fail to tender or a cook to receive the sirloin, the haunch, the breast, the ribs of mutton and beef for ever and ever, for as long as Wimpole Street remains, civilisation is secure.

The butlers of Wimpole Street move ponderously even to-day; in the summer of 1842 they were more deliberate still. The laws of livery were then more stringent; the ritual of the green baize apron for cleaning silver; of the striped waistcoat and swallow-tail black coat for opening the hall door, was more closely observed. It is likely then that Miss Mitford and Flush were kept waiting at least three minutes and a half on the door-step. At last, however, the door of number fifty was flung wide; Miss Mitford and Flush were ushered in. Miss Mitford was a frequent visitor; there was nothing to surprise, though something to subdue her, in the sight of the Barrett family mansion. But the effect upon Flush must have been overwhelming in the extreme. Until this moment he had set foot in no house but the working man' s cottage at Three Mile Cross. The boards there were bare; the mats were frayed; the chairs were cheap. Here there was nothing bare, nothing frayed, nothing cheap - that Flush could see at a glance. Mr Barrett, the owner, was a rich merchant; he had a large family of grown-up sons and daughters, and a retinue, pro-portionately large, of servants. His house was furnished in the fashion of the late' thirties, with some tincture, no doubt, of that Eastern fantasy which had led him when he built a house in Shropshire to adorn it with the domes and crescents of Moorish architecture. Here in Wimpole Street such extravagance would not be allowed; but we may suppose that the high dark rooms were full of ottomans and carved mahogany; tables were twisted; filigree ornaments stood upon them; daggers and swords hung upon wine-dark walls; curious objects brought from his East Indian property stood in recesses, and thick rich carpets clothed the floors.

But as Flush trotted up behind Miss Mitford, who was behind the butler, he was more astonished by what he smelt than by what he saw. Up the funnel of the staircase came warm whiffs of joints roasting, of fowls basting, of soups simmering - ravishing almost as food itself to nostrils used to the meagre savour of Kerenhappock' s penurious fries and hashes. Mixing with the smell of food were further smells - smells of cedarwood and sandalwood and mahogany; scents of male bodies and female bodies; of men servants and maid servants; of coats and trousers; of crinolines and mantles; of curtains of tapestry, of curtains of plush; of coal dust and fog; of wine and cigars. Each room as he passed it - dining-room, drawing-room, library, bedroom - wafted out its own contri-bution to the general stew; while, as he set down first one paw and then another, each was caressed and retained by the sen-suality of rich pile carpets closing amorously over it. At length they reached a closed door at the back of the house. A gentle tap was given; gently the door was opened.

Miss Barrett's bedroom - for such it was - must by all accounts have been dark. The light, normally obscured by a curtain of green damask, was in summer further dimmed by the ivy, the scarlet runners, the convolvuluses and the nastur-tiums which grew in the window-box. At first Flush could distinguish nothing in the pale greenish gloom but five white globes glimmering mysteriously in mid-air. But again it was the smell of the room that overpowered him. Only a scholar who has descended step by step into a mausoleum and there finds himself in a crypt, crusted with fungus, slimy with mould, exuding sour smells of decay and antiquity, while half-obliterated marble busts gleam in mid-air and all is dimly seen by the light of the small swinging lamp which he holds, and dips and turns, glancing now here, now there - only the sensations of such an explorer into the buried vaults of a ruined city can compare with the riot of emotions that flooded Flush' s nerves as he stood for the first time in an invalid' s bedroom, in Wimpole Street, and smelt eau-de-Cologne.

Very slowly, very dimly, with much sniffing and pawing, Flush by degrees distinguished the outlines of several articles of furniture. That huge object by the window was perhaps a wardrobe. Next to it stood, conceivably, a chest of drawers. In the middle of the room swam up to the surface what seemed to be a table with a ring round it; and then the vague amorphous shapes of armchair and table emerged. But everything was disguised. On top of the wardrobe stood three white busts; the chest of drawers was surmounted by a bookcase; the bookcase was pasted over with crimson merino; the washing-table had a coronal of shelves upon it; on top of the shelves that were on top of the washing-table stood two more busts. Nothing in the room was itself; every-thing was something else. Even the window-blind was not a simple muslin blind; it was a painted fabric with a design of castles and gateways and groves of trees, and there were several peasants taking a walk. Looking-glasses further dis-torted these already distorted objects so that there seemed to be ten busts of ten poets instead of five; four tables instead of two. And suddenly there was a more terrifying confusion still. Suddenly Flush saw staring back at him from a hole in the wall another dog with bright eyes flashing, and tongue lolling! He paused amazed. He advanced in awe.

Thus advancing, thus withdrawing, Flush scarcely heard, save as the distant drone of wind among the tree-tops, the murmur and patter of voices talking. He pursued his inves-tigations, cautiously, nervously, as an explorer in a forest softly advances his foot, uncertain whether that shadow is a lion, or that root a cobra. At last, however, he was aware of huge objects in commotion over him; and, unstrung as he was by the experiences of the past hour, he hid himself, trembling, behind a screen. The voices ceased. A door shut. For one instant he paused, bewildered, unstrung. Then with a pounce as of clawed tigers memory fell upon him. He felt himself alone - deserted. He rushed to the door. It was shut. He pawed, he listened. He heard footsteps descending. He knew them for the familiar footsteps of his mistress. They stopped. But no - on they went, down they went. Miss Mit-ford was slowly, was heavily, was reluctantly descending the stairs. And as she went, as he heard her footsteps fade, panic seized upon him. Door after door shut in his face as Miss Mitford went downstairs; they shut on freedom; on fields; on hares; on grass; on his adored, his venerated mistress - on the dear old woman who had washed him and beaten him and fed him from her own plate when she had none too much to eat herself - on all he had known of happiness and love and human goodness! There! The front door slammed. He was alone. She had deserted him.

Then such a wave of despair and anguish overwhelmed him, the irrevocableness and implacability of fate so smote him, that he lifted up his head and howled aloud. A voice said ‘Flush'. He did not hear it. ‘Flush', it repeated a second time. He started. He had thought himself alone. He turned. Was there something alive in the room with him? Was there something on the sofa? In the wild hope that this being, whatever it was, might open the door, that he might still rush after Miss Mitford and find her - that this was some game of hide-and-seek such as they used to play in the greenhouse at home - Flush darted to the sofa.

‘Oh, Flush!' said Miss Barrett. For the first time she looked him in the face. For the first time Flush looked at the lady lying on the sofa.

Each was surprised. Heavy curls hung down on either side of Miss Barrett's face; large bright eyes shone out; a large mouth smiled. Heavy ears hung down on either side of Flush's face; his eyes, too, were large and bright: his mouth was wide. There was a likeness between them. As they gazed at each other each felt: Here am I - and then each felt: But how different! Hers was the pale worn face of an invalid, cut off from air, light, freedom. His was the warm ruddy face of a young animal; instinct with health and energy. Broken asunder, yet made in the same mould, could it be that each completed what was dormant in the other? She might have been - all that; and he - But no. Between them lay the widest gulf that can separate one being from another. She spoke. He was dumb. She was woman; he was dog. Thus closely united, thus immensely divided, they gazed at each other. Then with one bound Flush sprang on to the sofa and laid himself where he was to lie for ever after - on the rug at Miss Barrett' s feet.

Chapter 2　THE BACK BEDROOM

The summer of 1842 was, historians tell us, not much differ-ent from other summers, yet to Flush it was so different that he must have doubted if the world itself were the same. It was a summer spent in a bedroom; a summer spent with Miss Barrett. It was a summer spent in London, spent in the heart of civilisation. At first he saw nothing but the bedroom and its furniture, but that alone was surprising enough. To identify, distinguish and call by their right names all the different articles he saw there was confusing enough. And he had scarcely accustomed himself to the tables, to the busts, to the washing-stands - the smell of eau-de-Cologne still affected his nostrils disagreeably, when there came one of those rare days which are fine but not windy, warm but not baking, dry but not dusty, when an invalid can take the air. The day came when Miss Barrett could safely risk the huge adventure of going shopping with her sister.

The carriage was ordered; Miss Barrett rose from her sofa; veiled and muffled, she descended the stairs. Flush of course went with her. He leapt into the carriage by her side. Couched on her lap, the whole pomp of London at its most splendid burst on his astonished eyes. They drove along Oxford Street. He saw houses made almost entirely of glass. He saw windows laced across with glittering streamers; heaped with gleaming mounds of pink, purple, yellow, rose. The carriage stopped. He entered mysterious arcades filmed with clouds and webs of tinted gauze. A million airs from China, from Arabia, wafted their frail incense into the remotest fibres of his senses. Swiftly over the counters flashed yards of gleaming silk; more darkly, more slowly rolled the ponderous bombazine. Scissors snipped; coins sparkled. Paper was folded; string tied. What with nodding plumes, waving streamers, tossing horses, yellow liveries, passing faces, leaping, dancing up, down, Flush, satiated with the multiplicity of his sensations, slept, drowsed, dreamt and knew no more until he was lifted out of the carriage and the door of Wimpole Street shut on him again.

And next day, as the fine weather continued, Miss Barrett ventured upon an even more daring exploit - she had her-self drawn up Wimpole Street in a bath-chair. Again Flush went with her. For the first time he heard his nails click upon the hard paving-stones of London. For the first time the whole battery of a London street on a hot summer' s day assaulted his nostrils. He smelt the swooning smells that lie in the gutters; the bitter smells that corrode iron railings; the fuming, heady smells that rise from basements - smells more complex, corrupt, violently contrasted and com-pounded than any he had smelt in the fields near Reading; smells that lay far beyond the range of the human nose; so that while the chair went on, he stopped, amazed; defining, savouring, until a jerk at his collar dragged him on. And also, as he trotted up Wimpole Street behind Miss Barrett' s chair he was dazed by the passage of human bodies. Petti-coats swished at his head; trousers brushed his flanks; sometimes a wheel whizzed an inch from his nose; the wind of destruction roared in his ears and fanned the feathers of his paws as a van passed. Then he plunged in terror. Mer-cifully the chain tugged at his collar; Miss Barrett held him tight, or he would have rushed to destruction.

At last, with every nerve throbbing and every sense sing-ing, he reached Regent's Park. And then when he saw once more, after years of absence it seemed, grass,flowers and trees, the old hunting cry of the fields hallooed in his ears and he dashed forward to run as he had run in the fields at home. But now a heavy weight jerked at his throat; he was thrown back on his haunches. Were there not trees and grass? he asked. Were these not the signals of freedom? Had he not always leapt forward directly Miss Mitford started on her walk? Why was he a prisoner here? He paused. Here, he observed, the flowers were massed far more thickly than at home; they stood, plant by plant, rigidly in narrow plots. The plots were intersected by hard black paths. Men in shiny top-hats marched ominously up and down the paths. At the sight of them he shuddered closer to the chair. He gladly accepted the protection of the chain. Thus before many of these walks were over a new conception had entered his brain. Setting one thing beside another, he had arrived at a conclusion. Where there are flower-beds there are asphalt paths; where there are flower-beds and asphalt paths, there are men in shiny top-hats; where there are flower-beds and asphalt paths and men in shiny top-hats, dogs must be led on chains. Without being able to decipher a word of the placard at the Gate, he had learnt his lesson - in Regent' s Park dogs must be led on chains.

And to this nucleus of knowledge, born from the strange experiences of the summer of 1842,soon adhered another; dogs are not equal, but different. At Three Mile Cross Flush had mixed impartially with tap-room dogs and the Squire' s greyhounds; he had known no difference between the tinker' s dog and himself. Indeed it is probable that the mother of his child, though by courtesy called Spaniel, was nothing but a mongrel, eared in one way, tailed in another. But the dogs of London, Flush soon discovered, are strictly divided into different classes. Some are chained dogs; some run wild. Some take their airings in carriages and drink from purple jars; others are unkempt and uncollared and pick up a living in the gutter. Dogs therefore, Flush began to sus-pect, differ; some are high, others low; and his suspicions were confirmed by snatches of talk held in passing with the dogs of Wimpole Street. ‘See that scallywag? A mere mongrel! …… By gad, that' s a fine Spaniel. One of the best blood in Britain! …… Pity his ears aren' t a shade more curly …… There' s a topknot for you!'

From such phrases, from the accent of praise or derision in which they were spoken, at the pillar-box or outside the public-house where the footmen were exchanging racing tips, Flush knew before the summer had passed that there is no equality among dogs: some dogs are high dogs; some are low. Which, then, was he? No sooner had Flush got home than he examined himself carefully in the looking-glass. Heaven be praised, he was a dog of birth and breeding! His head was smooth; his eyes were prominent but not gozzled; his feet were feathered; he was the equal of the best-bred cocker in Wimpole Street. He noted with approval the purple jar from which he drank - such are the privileges of rank; he bent his head quietly to have the chain fixed to his collar - such are its penalties. When about this time Miss Barrett observed him staring in the glass, she was mistaken. He was a philosopher, she thought, meditating the difference between appearance and reality. On the con-trary, he was an aristocrat considering his points.

But the fine summer days were soon over; the autumn winds began to blow; and Miss Barrett settled down to a life of complete seclusion in her bedroom. Flush' s life was also changed. His outdoor education was supplemented by that of the bedroom, and this, to a dog of Flush' s tempera-ment, was the most drastic that could have been invented. His only airings, and these were brief and perfunctory, were taken in the company of Wilson, Miss Barrett' s maid. For the rest of the day he kept his station on the sofa at Miss Barrett' s feet. All his natural instincts were thwarted and contradicted. When the autumn winds had blown last year in Berkshire he had run in wild scampering across the stub-ble; now at the sound of the ivy tapping on the pane Miss Barrett asked Wilson to see to the fastenings of the window. When the leaves of the scarlet runners and nasturtiums in the window-box yellowed and fell she drew her Indian shawl more closely round her. When the October rain lashed the window Wilson lit the fire and heaped up the coals. Autumn deepened into winter and the first fogs jaundiced the air. Wilson and Flush could scarcely grope their way to the pillar-box or to the chemist. When they came back, nothing could be seen in the room but the pale busts glimmering wanly on the tops of the wardrobes; the peasants and the castle had vanished on the blind; blank yellow filled the pane. Flush felt that he and Miss Barrett lived alone together in a cushioned and firelit cave. The traffic droned on per-petually outside with muffled reverberations; now and again a voice went calling hoarsely, ‘Old chairs and baskets to mend', down the street: sometimes there was a jangle of organ music, coming nearer and louder; going further and fading away. But none of these sounds meant freedom, or action, or exercise. The wind and the rain, the wild days of autumn and the cold days of mid-winter, all alike meant nothing to Flush except warmth and stillness; the lighting of lamps, the drawing of curtains and the poking of the fire.

At first the strain was too great to be borne. He could not help dancing round the room on a windy autumn day when the partridges must be scattering over the stubble. He thought he heard guns on the breeze. He could not help running to the door with his hackles raised when a dog barked outside. And yet when Miss Barrett called him back, when she laid her hand on his collar, he could not deny that another feeling, urgent, contradictory, disagreeable - he did not know what to call it or why he obeyed it - restrained him. He lay still at her feet. To resign, to control, to suppress the most violent instincts of his nature - that was the prime lesson of the bedroom school, and it was one of such por-tentous difficulty that many scholars have learnt Greek with less - many battles have been won that cost their generals not half such pain. But then, Miss Barrett was the teacher. Between them, Flush felt more and more strongly, as the weeks wore on, was a bond, an uncomfortable yet thrilling tightness; so that if his pleasure was her pain, then his pleas-ure was pleasure no longer but three parts pain. The truth of this was proved every day. Somebody opened the door and whistled him to come. Why should he not go out? He longed for air and exercise; his limbs were cramped with lying on the sofa. He had never grown altogether used to the smell of eau-de-Cologne. But no - though the door stood open, he would not leave Miss Barrett. He hesitated half-way to the door and then went back to the sofa. ‘Flushie', wrote Miss Barrett, ‘is my friend - my companion - and loves me better than he loves the sunshine without.' She could not go out. She was chained to the sofa. ‘A bird in a cage would have as good a story', she wrote, as she had. And Flush, to whom the whole world was free, chose to forfeit all the smells of Wimpole Street in order to lie by her side.

And yet sometimes the tie would almost break; there were vast gaps in their understanding. Sometimes they would lie and stare at each other in blank bewilderment. Why, Miss Barrett wondered, did Flush tremble suddenly, and whimper and start and listen? She could hear nothing; she could see nothing; there was nobody in the room with them. She could not guess that Folly, her sister' s little King Charles, had passed the door; or that Catiline the Cuba bloodhound had been given a mutton-bone by a footman in the base-ment. But Flush knew; he heard; he was ravaged by the alternate rages of lust and greed. Then with all her poet' s imagination Miss Barrett could not divine what Wilson' s wet umbrella meant to Flush; what memories it recalled, of forests and parrots and wild trumpeting elephants; nor did she know, when Mr Kenyon stumbled over the bell-pull, that Flush heard dark men cursing in the mountains; the cry, ‘Span! Span!' rang in his ears, and it was in some muf-fled, ancestral rage that he bit him.

Flush was equally at a loss to account for Miss Barrett's emotions. There she would lie hour after hour passing her hand over a white page with a black stick; and her eyes would suddenly fill with tears; but why? ‘Ah, my dear Mr Horne', she was writing. ‘And then came the failure in my health …… and then the enforced exile to Torquay …… which gave a nightmare to my life for ever, and robbed it of more than I can speak of here; do not speak of that any-where. Do not speak of that, dear Mr Horne.' But there was no sound in the room, no smell to make Miss Barrett cry. Then again Miss Barrett, still agitating her stick, burst out laughing. She had drawn ‘a very neat and characteristic portrait of Flush, humorously made rather like myself', and she had written under it that it ‘only fails of being an excel-lent substitute for mine through being more worthy than I can be counted'. What was there to laugh at in the black smudge that she held out for Flush to look at? He could smell nothing; he could hear nothing. There was nobody in the room with them. The fact was that they could not com-municate with words, and it was a fact that led undoubtedly to much misunderstanding. Yet did it not lead also to a peculiar intimacy? ‘Writing', Miss Barrett once exclaimed after a morning' s toil, ‘writing, writing …… ' After all, she may have thought, do words say everything? Can words say anything? Do not words destroy the symbol that lies beyond the reach of words? Once at least Miss Barrett seems to have found it so. She was lying, thinking; she had forgotten Flush altogether, and her thoughts were so sad that the tears fell upon the pillow. Then suddenly a hairy head was pressed against her; large bright eyes shone in hers; and she started. Was it Flush, or was it Pan? Was she no longer an invalid in Wimpole Street, but a Greek nymph in some dim grove in Arcady? And did the bearded god himself press his lips to hers? For a moment she was transformed; she was a nymph and Flush was Pan. The sun burnt and love blazed. But suppose Flush had been able to speak - would he not have said something sensible about the potato disease in Ireland?

So, too, Flush felt strange stirrings at work within him. When he saw Miss Barrett' s thin hands delicately lifting some silver box or pearl ornament from the ringed table, his own furry paws seemed to contract and he longed that they should fine themselves to ten separate fingers. When he heard her low voice syllabling innumerable sounds, he longed for the day when his own rough roar would issue like hers in the little simple sounds that had such mysterious meaning. And when he watched the same fingers for ever crossing a white page with a straight stick, he longed for the time when he too should blacken paper as she did.

And yet, had he been able to write as she did? - The ques-tion is superfluous happily, for truth compels us to say that in the year 1842-43 Miss Barrett was not a nymph but an invalid; Flush was not a poet but a red cocker spaniel; and Wimpole Street was not Arcady but Wimpole Street.

So the long hours went by in the back bedroom with nothing to mark them but the sound of steps passing on the stairs; and the distant sound of the front door shutting, and the sound of a broom tapping, and the sound of the post-man knocking. In the room coals clicked; the lights and shadows shifted themselves over the brows of the five pale busts, over the bookcase and its red merino. But sometimes the step on the stair did not pass the door; it stopped out-side. The handle was seen to spin round; the door actually opened; somebody came in. Then how strangely the furni-ture changed its look! What extraordinary eddies of sound and smell were at once set in circulation! How they washed round the legs of tables and impinged on the sharp edges of the wardrobe! Probably it was Wilson, with a tray of food or a glass of medicine; or it might be one of Miss Barrett' s two sisters - Arabel or Henrietta; or it might be one of Miss Barrett' s seven brothers - Charles, Samuel, George, Henry, Alfred, Septimus or Octavius. But once or twice a week Flush was aware that something more important was about to happen. The bed would be carefully disguised as a sofa. The armchair would be drawn up beside it; Miss Barrett herself would be wrapped becomingly in Indian shawls; the toilet things would be scrupulously hidden under the busts of Chaucer and Homer; Flush himself would be combed and brushed. At about two or three in the afternoon there was a peculiar, distinct and different tap at the door. Miss Barrett flushed, smiled and stretched out her hand. Then in would come - perhaps dear Miss Mitford, rosy and shiny and chattering, with a bunch of geraniums. Or it might be Mr Kenyon, a stout, well-groomed elderly gentleman, radi-ating benevolence, provided with a book. Or it might be Mrs Jameson, a lady who was the very opposite of Mr Kenyon to look at - a lady with ‘a very light complexion - pale, lucid eyes; thin colourless lips …… a nose and chin projective without breadth'. Each had his or her own man-ner, smell, tone and accent. Miss Mitford burbled and chattered, was fly-away yet substantial; Mr Kenyon was urbane and cultured and mumbled slightly because he had lost two front teeth; Mrs Jameson had lost none of her teeth, and moved as sharply and precisely as she spoke.

Lying couched at Miss Barrett's feet, Flush let the voices ripple over him, hour by hour. On and on they went. Miss Barrett laughed, expostulated, exclaimed, sighed too, and laughed again. At last, greatly to Flush's relief, little silences came - even in the flow of Miss Mitford' s conversation. Could it be seven already? She had been there since midday! She must really run to catch her train. Mr Kenyon shut his book - he had been reading aloud - and stood with his back to the fire; Mrs Jameson with a sharp, angular movement pressed each finger of her glove sharp down. And Flush was patted by this one and had his ear pulled by another. The routine of leave-taking was intolerably prolonged; but at last Mrs Jameson, Mr Kenyon, and even Miss Mitford had risen, had said good-bye, had remembered something, had lost something, had found something, had reached the door, had opened it, and were - Heaven be praised - gone at last.

Miss Barrett sank back very white, very tired on her pil-lows. Flush crept closer to her. Mercifully they were alone again. But the visitor had stayed so long that it was almost dinner-time. Smells began to rise from the basement. Wilson was at the door with Miss Barrett's dinner on a tray. It was set down on the table beside her and the covers lifted. But what with the dressing and the talking, what with the heat of the room and the agitation of the farewells, Miss Barrett was too tired to eat. She gave a little sigh when she saw the plump mutton chop, or the wing of partridge or chicken that had been sent up for her dinner. So long as Wilson was in the room she fiddled about with her knife and fork. But directly the door was shut and they were alone, she made a sign. She held up her fork. A whole chicken' s wing was impaled upon it. Flush advanced. Miss Barrett nodded. Very gently, very cleverly, without spilling a crumb, Flush removed the wing; swallowed it down and left no trace behind. Half a rice pudding clotted with thick cream went the same way. Nothing could have been neater, more effect-ive than Flush' s co-operation. He was lying couched as usual at Miss Barrett' s feet, apparently asleep, Miss Barrett was lying rested and restored, apparently having made an excel-lent dinner, when once more a step that was heavier, more deliberate and firmer than any other, stopped on the stair; solemnly a knock sounded that was no tap of enquiry but a demand for admittance; the door opened and in came the blackest, the most formidable of elderly men - Mr Barrett himself. His eye at once sought the tray. Had the meal been eaten? Had his commands been obeyed? Yes, the plates were empty. Signifying his approval of his daughter' s obedience, Mr Barrett lowered himself heavily into the chair by her side. As that dark body approached him, shivers of terror and horror ran down Flush' s spine. So a savage couched in flowers shudders when the thunder growls and he hears the voice of God. Then Wilson whistled; and Flush, slinking guiltily, as if Mr Barrett could read his thoughts and those thoughts were evil, crept out of the room and rushed down-stairs. A force had entered the bedroom which he dreaded; a force that he was powerless to withstand. Once he burst in unexpectedly. Mr Barrett was on his knees praying by his daughter' s side.

Chapter 3　THE HOODED MAN

Such an education as this, in the back bedroom at Wimpole Street, would have told upon an ordinary dog. And Flush was not an ordinary dog. He was high-spirited, yet reflect-ive; canine, but highly sensitive to human emotions also. Upon such a dog the atmosphere of the bedroom told with peculiar force. We cannot blame him if his sensibility was cultivated rather to the detriment of his sterner qual-ities. Naturally, lying with his head pillowed on a Greek lexicon, he came to dislike barking and biting; he came to prefer the silence of the cat to the robustness of the dog; and human sympathy to either. Miss Barrett, too, did her best to refine and educate his powers still further. Once she took a harp from the window and asked him, as she laid it by his side, whether he thought that the harp, which made music, was itself alive? He looked and listened; pon-dered, it seemed, for a moment in doubt and then decided that it was not. Then she would make him stand with her in front of the looking-glass and ask him why he barked and trembled. Was not the little brown dog opposite himself? But what is ‘oneself' ?Is it the thing people see? Or is it the thing one is? So Flush pondered that question too, and, unable to solve the problem of reality, pressed closer to Miss Barrett and kissed her ‘expressively'. That was real at any rate.

Fresh from such problems, with such emotional dilemmas agitating his nervous system, he went downstairs, and we cannot be surprised if there was something - a touch of the supercilious, of the superior - in his bearing that roused the rage of Catiline, the savage Cuba bloodhound, so that he set upon him and bit him and sent him howling upstairs to Miss Barrett for sympathy. Flush ‘is no hero', she concluded; but why was he no hero? Was it not partly on her account? She was too just not to realise that it was for her that he had sacrificed his courage, as it was for her that he had sacrificed the sun and the air. This nervous sen-sibility had its drawbacks, no doubt - she was full of apologies when he flew at Mr Kenyon and bit him for stum-bling over the bell-pull; it was annoying when he moaned piteously all night because he was not allowed to sleep on her bed - when he refused to eat unless she fed him; but she took the blame and bore the inconvenience because, after all, Flush loved her. He had refused the air and the sun for her sake. ‘He is worth loving, is he not?' she asked of Mr Horne. And whatever answer Mr Horne might give, Miss Barrett was positive of her own. She loved Flush, and Flush was worthy of her love.

It seemed as if nothing were to break that tie - as if the years were merely to compact and cement it; and as if those years were to be all the years of their natural lives. Eighteen-forty-two turned into eighteen-forty-three; eighteen-forty-three into eighteen-forty-four; eighteen-forty-four into eighteen-forty-five. Flush was no longer a puppy; he was a dog of four or five; he was a dog in the full prime of life - and still Miss Barrett lay on her sofa in Wimpole Street and still Flush lay on the sofa at her feet. Miss Bar-rett' s life was the life of ‘a bird in its cage'. She sometimes kept to the house for weeks at a time, and when she left it, it was only for an hour or two, to drive to a shop in a car-riage, or to be wheeled to Regent' s Park in a bath-chair. The Barretts never left London. Mr Barrett, the seven brothers, the two sisters, the butler, Wilson and the maids, Catiline, Folly, Miss Barrett and Flush all went on living at 50 Wim-pole Street, eating in the dining-room, sleeping in the bedrooms, smoking in the study, cooking in the kitchen, carrying hot-water cans and emptying the slops from Janu-ary to December. The chair-covers became slightly soiled; the carpets slightly worn; coal dust, mud, soot, fog, vapours of cigar smoke and wine and meat accumulated in crevices, in cracks, in fabrics, on the tops of picture-frames, in the scrolls of carvings. And the ivy that hung over Miss Barrett' s bedroom window flourished; its green curtain became thicker and thicker, and in summer the nasturtiums and the scarlet runners rioted together in the window-box.

But one night early in January 1845 the postman knocked. Letters fell into the box as usual. Wilson went downstairs to fetch the letters as usual. Everything was as usual - every night the postman knocked, every night Wilson fetched the letters, every night there was a letter for Miss Barrett. But to-night the letter was not the same letter; it was a different letter. Flush saw that, even before the envelope was broken. He knew it from the way that Miss Barrett took it; turned it; looked at the vigorous, jagged writing of her name. He knew it from the indescribable tremor in her fingers, from the impetuosity with which they tore the flap open, from the absorption with which she read. He watched her read. And as she read he heard, as when we are half asleep we hear through the clamour of the street some bell ringing and know that it is addressed to us, alarmingly yet faintly, as if someone far away were trying to rouse us with the warning of fire, or burglary, or some menace against our peace and we start in alarm before we wake - so Flush, as Miss Barrett read the little blotted sheet, heard a bell rousing him from his sleep; warning him of some dan-ger; menacing his safety and bidding him sleep no more. Miss Barrett read the letter quickly; she read the letter slowly; she returned it carefully to its envelope. She too slept no more.

Again, a few nights later, there was the same letter on Wilson's tray. Again it was read quickly, read slowly, read over and over again. Then it was put away carefully, not in the drawer with the voluminous sheets of Miss Mitford' s letters, but by itself. Now Flush paid the full price of long years of accumulated sensibility lying couched on cushions at Miss Barrett' s feet. He could read signs that nobody else could even see. He could tell by the touch of Miss Barrett' s fingers that she was waiting for one thing only - for the postman' s knock, for the letter on the tray. She would be stroking him perhaps with a light, regular movement; suddenly - there was the rap - her fingers constricted; he would be held in a vice while Wilson came upstairs. Then she took the letter and he was loosed and forgotten.

Yet, he argued, what was there to be afraid of, so long as there was no change in Miss Barrett's life? And there was no change. No new visitors came. Mr Kenyon came as usual; Miss Mitford came as usual. The brothers and sisters came; and in the evening Mr Barrett came. They noticed nothing; they suspected nothing. So he would quieten him-self and try to believe, when a few nights passed without the envelope, that the enemy had gone. A man in a cloak, he imagined, a cowled and hooded figure, had passed, like a burglar, rattling the door, and finding it guarded, had slunk away defeated. The danger, Flush tried to make himself believe, was over. The man had gone. And then the letter came again.

As the envelopes came more and more regularly, night after night, Flush began to notice signs of change in Miss Barrett herself. For the first time in Flush' s experience she was irritable and restless. She could not read and she could not write. She stood at the window and looked out. She questioned Wilson anxiously about the weather - was the wind still in the east? Was there any sign of spring in the Park yet? Oh no, Wilson replied; the wind was a cruel east wind still. And Miss Barrett, Flush felt, was at once relieved and annoyed. She coughed. She complained of feeling ill - but not so ill as she usually felt when the wind was in the east. And then, when she was alone, she read over again last night' s letter. It was the longest she had yet had. There were many pages, closely covered, darkly blotted, scattered with strange little abrupt hieroglyphics. So much Flush could see, from his station at her feet. But he could make no sense of the words that Miss Barrett was murmuring to herself. Only he could trace her agitation when she came to the end of the page and read aloud (though unintelligibly) , ‘Do you think I shall see you in two months, three months?'

Then she took up her pen and passed it rapidly and ner-vously over sheet after sheet. But what did they mean - the little words that Miss Barrett wrote? ‘April is coming. There will be both a May and a June if we live to see such things, and perhaps, after all, we may …… I will indeed see you when the warm weather has revived me a little …… But I shall be afraid of you at first - though I am not, in writing thus. You are Paracelsus and I am a recluse, with nerves that have been broken on the rack, and now hang loosely, quivering at a step and breath.'

Flush could not read what she was writing an inch or two above his head. But he knew just as well as if he could read every word, how strangely his mistress was agitated as she wrote; what contrary desires shook her - that April might come; that April might not come; that she might see this unknown man at once, that she might never see him at all. Flush, too, quivered as she did at a step, at a breath. And remorselessly the days went on. The wind blew out the blind. The sun whitened the busts. A bird sang in the mews. Men went crying fresh flowers to sell down Wimpole Street. All these sounds meant, he knew, that April was coming and May and June - nothing could stop the approach of that dreadful spring. For what was coming with the spring? Some terror - some horror - something that Miss Barrett dreaded, and that Flush dreaded too. He started now at the sound of a step. But it was only Henrietta. Then there was a knock. It was only Mr Kenyon. So April passed; and the first twenty days of May. And then, on the 21st of May, Flush knew that the day itself had come. For on Tuesday, the 21st of May, Miss Barrett looked searchingly in the glass; arrayed herself exquisitely in her Indian shawls; bade Wilson draw the armchair close, but not too close; touched this, that and the other; and then sat upright among her pillows. Flush couched himself taut at her feet. They waited, alone together. At last, Marylebone Church clock struck two; they waited. Then Marylebone Church clock struck a single stroke - It was half-past two; and as the single stroke died away, a rap sounded boldly on the front door. Miss Barrett turned pale; she lay very still. Flush lay still too. Upstairs came the dreaded, the inexorable footfall; upstairs, Flush knew, came the cowled and sinister figure of midnight - the hooded man. Now his hand was on the door. The handle spun. There he stood.

‘Mr Browning', said Wilson.

Flush, watching Miss Barrett, saw the colour rush into her face; saw her eyes brighten and her lips open.

‘Mr Browning!' she exclaimed.

Twisting his yellow gloves in his hands, blinking his eyes, well groomed, masterly, abrupt, Mr Browning strode across the room. He seized Miss Barrett's hand, and sank into the chair by the sofa at her side. Instantly they began to talk.

What was horrible to Flush, as they talked, was his loneli-ness. Once he had felt that he and Miss Barrett were together, in a firelit cave. Now the cave was no longer firelit; it was dark and damp; Miss Barrett was outside. He looked round him. Everything had changed. The bookcase, the five busts - they were no longer friendly deities presiding approvingly-they were hostile, severe. He shifted his position at Miss Barrett' s feet. She took no notice. He whined. They did not hear him. At last he lay still in tense and silent agony. The talk went on; but it did not flow and ripple as talk usually flowed and rippled. It leapt and jerked. It stopped and leapt again. Flush had never heard that sound in Miss Barrett' s voice before - that vigour, that excitement. Her cheeks were bright as he had never seen them bright; her great eyes blazed as he had never seen them blaze. The clock struck four; and still they talked. Then it struck half-past four. At that Mr Browning jumped up. A horrid decision, a dreadful boldness marked every move-ment. In another moment he had wrung Miss Barrett' s hand in his; he had taken his hat and gloves; he had said good-bye. They heard him running down the stairs. Smartly the door banged behind him. He was gone.

But Miss Barrett did not sink back in her pillows as she sank back when Mr Kenyon or Miss Mitford left her. Now she still sat upright; her eyes still burnt; her cheeks still glowed; she seemed still to feel that Mr Browning was with her. Flush touched her. She recalled him with a start. She patted him lightly, joyfully, on the head. And smiling, she gave him the oddest look - as if she wished that he could talk - as if she expected him too to feel what she felt. And then she laughed, pityingly; as if it were absurd - Flush, poor Flush could feel nothing of what she felt. He could know nothing of what she knew. Never had such wastes of dismal distance separated them. He lay there ignored; he might not have been there, he felt. Miss Barrett no longer remembered his existence.

And that night she ate her chicken to the bone. Not a scrap of potato or of skin was thrown to Flush. When Mr Barrett came as usual, Flush marvelled at his obtuseness. He sat himself down in the very chair that the man had sat in. His head pressed the same cushions that the man' s had pressed, and yet he noticed nothing. ‘Don' t you know', Flush marvelled, ‘who' s been sitting in that chair? Can' t you smell him?' For to Flush the whole room still reeked of Mr Brown-ing' s presence. The air dashed past the bookcase, and eddied and curled round the heads of the five pale busts. But the heavy man sat by his daughter in entire self-absorption. He noticed nothing. He suspected nothing. Aghast at his obtuseness, Flush slipped past him out of the room.

But in spite of their astonishing blindness, even Miss Bar-rett's family began to notice, as the weeks passed, a change in Miss Barrett. She left her room and went down to sit in the drawing-room. Then she did what she had not done for many a long day - she actually walked on her own feet as far as the gate at Devonshire Place with her sister. Her friends, her family, were amazed at her improvement. But only Flush knew where her strength came from - it came from the dark man in the armchair. He came again and again and again. First it was once a week; then it was twice a week. He came always in the afternoon and left in the afternoon. Miss Barrett always saw him alone. And on the days when he did not come, his letters came. And when he himself was gone, his flowers were there. And in the mornings when she was alone, Miss Barrett wrote to him. That dark, taut, abrupt, vigorous man, with his black hair, his red cheeks and his yellow gloves, was everywhere. Natu-rally, Miss Barrett was better; of course she could walk. Flush himself felt that it was impossible to lie still. Old long-ings revived; a new restlessness possessed him. Even his sleep was full of dreams. He dreamt as he had not dreamt since the old days at Three Mile Cross - of hares starting from the long grass; of pheasants rocketing up with long tails streaming, of partridges rising with a whirr from the stubble. He dreamt that he was hunting, that he was chasing some spotted spaniel, who fled, who escaped him. He was in Spain; he was in Wales; he was in Berkshire; he was flying before park-keepers' truncheons in Regent' s Park. Then he opened his eyes. There were no hares, and no partridges; no whips cracking and no black men crying ‘Span! Span!' There was only Mr Browning in the armchair talking to Miss Barrett on the sofa.

Sleep became impossible while that man was there. Flush lay with his eyes wide open, listening. Though he could make no sense of the little words that hurtled over his head from two-thirty to four-thirty sometimes three times a week, he could detect with terrible accuracy that the tone of the words was changing. Miss Barrett' s voice had been forced and unnaturally lively at first. Now it had gained a warmth and an ease that he had never heard in it before. And every time the man came, some new sound came into their voices - now they made a grotesque chattering; now they skimmed over him like birds flying widely; now they cooed and clucked, as if they were two birds settled in a nest; and then Miss Barrett' s voice, rising again, went soar-ing and circling in the air; and then Mr Browning' s voice barked out its sharp, harsh clapper of laughter; and then there was only a murmur, a quiet humming sound as the two voices joined together. But as the summer turned to autumn Flush noted, with horrid apprehension, another note. There was a new urgency, a new pressure and energy in the man' s voice, at which Miss Barrett, Flush felt, took fright. Her voice fluttered; hesitated; seemed to falter and fade and plead and gasp, as if she were begging for a rest, for a pause, as if she were afraid. Then the man was silent.

Of him they took but little notice. He might have been a log of wood lying there at Miss Barrett's feet for all the attention Mr Browning paid him. Sometimes he scrubbed his head in a brisk, spasmodic way, energetically, without sentiment, as he passed him. Whatever that scrub might mean, Flush felt nothing but an intense dislike for Mr Browning. The very sight of him, so well tailored, so tight, so muscular, screwing his yellow gloves in his hand, set his teeth on edge. Oh! to let them meet sharply, completely in the stuff of his trousers! And yet he dared not. Taking it all in all, that winter - 1845-6 - was the most distressing that Flush had ever known.

The winter passed; and spring came round again. Flush could see no end to the affair; and yet just as a river, though it reflects still trees and grazing cows and rooks returning to the tree-tops, moves inevitably to a waterfall, so those days, Flush knew, were moving to catastrophe. Rumours of change hovered in the air. Sometimes he thought that some vast exodus impended. There was that indefinable stir in the house which precedes - could it be possible? - a journey. Boxes were actually dusted, were, incredible as it might seem, opened. Then they were shut again. No, it was not the family that was going to move. The brothers and sisters still went in and out as usual. Mr Barrett paid his nightly visit, after the man had gone, at his accustomed hour. What was it, then, that was going to happen? for as the summer of 1846 wore on, Flush was positive that a change was coming. He could hear it again in the altered sound of the eternal voices. Miss Barrett' s voice, that had been pleading and afraid, lost its faltering note. It rang out with a determin-ation and a boldness that Flush had never heard in it before. If only Mr Barrett could hear the tone in which she wel-comed this usurper, the laugh with which she greeted him, the exclamation with which he took her hand in his! But nobody was in the room with them except Flush. To him the change was of the most galling nature. It was not merely that Miss Barrett was changing towards Mr Browning - she was changing in every relation - in her feeling towards Flush himself. She treated his advances more brusquely; she cut short his endearments laughingly; she made him feel that there was something petty, silly, affected, in his old affectionate ways. His vanity was exacerbated. His jealousy was inflamed. At last, when July came, he determined to make one violent attempt to regain her favour, and perhaps to oust the newcomer. How to accomplish this double pur-pose he did not know, and could not plan. But suddenly on the 8th of July his feelings overcame him. He flung himself on Mr Browning and bit him savagely. At last his teeth met in the immaculate cloth of Mr Browning' s trousers! But the limb inside was hard as iron - Mr Kenyon' s leg had been butter in comparison. Mr Browning brushed him off with a flick of his hand and went on talking. Neither he nor Miss Barrett seemed to think the attack worthy of attention. Completely foiled, worsted, without a shaft left in his sheath, Flush sank back on his cushions panting with rage and disappointment. But he had misjudged Miss Barrett' s insight. When Mr Browning was gone, she called him to her and in flicted upon him the worst punishment he had ever known. First she slapped his ears - that was nothing; oddly enough the slap was rather to his liking; he would have welcomed another. But then she said in her sober, certain tones that she would never love him again. That shaft went to his heart. All these years they had lived together, shared everything together, and now, for one moment' s failure, she would never love him again. Then, as if to make her dis-missal complete, she took the flowers that Mr Browning had brought her and began to put them in water in a vase. It was an act, Flush thought, of calculated and deliberate mal-ice; an act designed to make him feel his own insignificance completely. ‘This rose is from him', she seemed to say, ‘and this carnation. Let the red shine by the yellow; and the yel-low by the red. And let the green leaf lie there -' And, setting one flower with another, she stood back to gaze at them as if he were before her - the man in the yellow gloves - a mass of brilliant flowers. But even so, even as she pressed the leaves and flowers together, she could not altogether ignore the fixity with which Flush gazed at her. She could not deny that ‘expression of quite despair on his face'. She could not but relent. ‘At last I said, "If you are good, Flush, you may come and say that you are sorry" ,on which he dashed across the room and, trembling all over, kissed first one of my hands and then another, and put up his paws to be shaken, and looked into my face with such beseeching eyes that you would certainly have forgiven him just as I did.' That was her account of the matter to Mr Browning; and he of course replied: ‘Oh, poor Flush, do you think I do not love and respect him for his jealous supervision - his slowness to know another, having once known you?' It was easy enough for Mr Browning to be magnanimous, but that easy magnanimity was perhaps the sharpest thorn that pressed into Flush' s side.

Another incident a few days later showed how widely they were separated, who had been so close, how little Flush could now count on Miss Barrett for sympathy. After Mr Browning had gone one afternoon Miss Barrett decided to drive to Regent's Park with her sister. As they got out at the Park gate the door of the four-wheeler shut on Flush's paw. He ‘cried piteously'and held it up to Miss Bar-rett for sympathy. In other days sympathy in abundance would have been lavished upon him for less. But now a detached, a mocking, a critical expression came into her eyes. She laughed at him. She thought he was sham-ming: ‘ …… no sooner had he touched the grass than he began to run without a thought of it', she wrote. And she com-mented sarcastically, ‘Flush always makes the most of his misfortunes - he is of the Byronic school - il se pose en vic-time'. But here Miss Barrett, absorbed in her own emotions, misjudged him completely. If his paw had been broken, still he would have bounded. That dash was his answer to her mockery; I have done with you - that was the meaning he flashed at her as he ran. The flowers smelt bitter to him; the grass burnt his paws; the dust filled his nostrils with disillusion. But he raced - he scampered. ‘Dogs must be led on chains' - there was the usual placard; there were the park-keepers with their top-hats and their truncheons to enforce it. But ‘must' no longer had any meaning for him. The chain of love was broken. He would run where he liked; chase partridges; chase spaniels; splash into the middle of dahlia beds; break brilliant, blowing red and yellow roses. Let the park-keepers throw their truncheons if they chose. Let them dash his brains out. Let him fall dead, disembow-elled, at Miss Barrett' s feet. He cared nothing. But naturally nothing of the kind happened. Nobody pursued him; nobody noticed him. The solitary park-keeper was talking to a nursemaid. At last he returned to Miss Barrett and she absent-mindedly slipped the chain over his neck, and led him home.

After two such humiliations the spirit of an ordinary dog, the spirit even of an ordinary human being, might well have been broken. But Flush, for all his softness and silkiness, had eyes that blazed; had passions that leapt not merely in bright flame but sunk and smouldered. He resolved to meet his enemy face to face and alone. No third person should interrupt this final conflict. It should be fought out by the principals themselves. On the afternoon of Tuesday, the 21st of July, therefore, he slipped downstairs and waited in the hall. He had not long to wait. Soon he heard the tramp of the familiar footstep in the street; he heard the familiar rap on the door. Mr Browning was admitted. Vaguely aware of the impending attack and determined to meet it in the most conciliatory of spirits, Mr Browning had come provided with a parcel of cakes. There was Flush waiting in the hall. Mr Browning made, evidently, some well-meant attempt to caress him; perhaps he even went so far as to offer him a cake. The gesture was enough. Flush sprang upon his enemy with unparalleled violence. His teeth once more met in Mr Browning' s trousers. But unfortunately in the excitement of the moment he forgot what was most essential - silence. He barked; he flung himself on Mr Browning, barking loudly. The sound was sufficient to alarm the household. Wilson rushed downstairs. Wilson beat him soundly. Wilson over-powered him completely. Wilson led him in ignominy away. Ignominy it was - to have attacked Mr Browning, to have been beaten by Wilson. Mr Browning had not lifted a finger. Taking his cakes with him, Mr Browning proceeded unhurt, unmoved, in perfect composure, upstairs, alone to the bed-room. Flush was led away.

After two and a half hours of miserable confinement with parrots and beetles, ferns and saucepans, in the kitchen, Flush was summoned to Miss Barrett' s presence. She was lying on the sofa with her sister Arabella beside her. Con-scious of the rightness of his cause, Flush went straight to her. But she refused to look at him. He turned to Arabella. She merely said, ‘Naughty Flush, go away'. Wilson was there - the formidable, the implacable Wilson. It was to her that Miss Barrett turned for information. She had beaten him, Wilson said, ‘because it was right'. And, she added, she had only beaten him with her hand. It was upon her evidence that Flush was convicted. The attack, Miss Barrett assumed, had been unprovoked; she credited Mr Browning with all virtue, with all generosity; Flush had been beaten off by a servant, without a whip, because ‘it was right'. There was no more to be said. Miss Barrett decided against him. ‘So he lay down on the floor at my feet,' she wrote, ‘looking from under his eyebrows at me.' But though Flush might look, Miss Barrett refused even to meet his eyes. There she lay on the sofa; there Flush lay on the floor.

And as he lay there, exiled, on the carpet, he went through one of those whirlpools of tumultuous emotion in which the soul is either dashed upon the rocks and splintered or,find-ing some tuft of foothold, slowly and painfully pulls itself up, regains dry land, and at last emerges on top of a ruined universe to survey a world created afresh on a different plan. Which was it to be - destruction or reconstruction? That was the question. The outlines only of his dilemma can be traced here; for his debate was silent. Twice Flush had done his utmost to kill his enemy; twice he had failed. And why had he failed, he asked himself? Because he loved Miss Barrett. Looking up at her from under his eyebrows as she lay, severe and silent on the sofa, he knew that he must love her for ever. Things are not simple but complex. If he bit Mr Browning he bit her too. Hatred is not hatred; hatred is also love. Here Flush shook his ears in an agony of perplex-ity. He turned uneasily on the floor. Mr Browning was Miss Barrett - Miss Barrett was Mr Browning; love is hatred and hatred is love. He stretched himself, whined and raised his head from the floor. The clock struck eight. For three hours and more he had been lying there, tossed from the horn of one dilemma to another.

Even Miss Barrett, severe, cold, implacable as she was, laid down her pen. ‘Wicked Flush!' she had been writing to Mr Browning, ‘ …… if people like Flush, choose to behave like dogs savagely, they must take the consequences indeed, as dogs usually do! And you, so good and gentle to him! Anyone but you would have said "hasty words" at least.' Really it would be a good plan, she thought, to buy a muz-zle. And then she looked up and saw Flush. Something unusual in his look must have struck her. She paused. She laid down her pen. Once he had roused her with a kiss, and she had thought that he was Pan. He had eaten chicken and rice pudding soaked in cream. He had given up the sunshine for her sake. She called him to her and said she forgave him.

But to be forgiven, as if for a passing whim, to be taken back again on to the sofa as if he had learnt nothing in his anguish on the floor, as if he were the same dog when in fact he differed totally, was impossible. For the moment, exhausted as he was, Flush submitted. A few days later, however, a remarkable scene took place between him and Miss Barrett which showed the depths of his emotions. Mr Browning had been and gone; Flush was alone with Miss Barrett. Normally he would have leapt on to the sofa at her feet. But now, instead of jumping up as usual and claiming her caress, Flush went to what was now called ‘Mr Brown-ing' s armchair'. Usually the chair was abhorrent to him; it still held the shape of his enemy. But now, such was the battle he had won, such was the charity that suffused him, that he not only looked at the chair but, as he looked, ‘suddenly fell into a rapture'. Miss Barrett, watching him intently, observed this extraordinary portent. Next she saw him turn his eyes towards a table. On that table still lay the packet of Mr Browning' s cakes. He ‘reminded me that the cakes you left were on the table'. They were now old cakes, stale cakes, cakes bereft of any carnal seduction. Flush' s meaning was plain. He had refused to eat the cakes when they were fresh, because they were offered by an enemy. He would eat them now that they were stale, because they were offered by an enemy turned to friend, because they were symbols of hatred turned to love. Yes, he signified, he would eat them now. So Miss Barrett rose and took the cakes in her hand. And as she gave them to him she admonished him, ‘So I explained to him that you had brought them for him, and that he ought to be properly ashamed therefore for his past wickedness, and make up his mind to love you and not bite you for the future - and he was allowed to profit from your goodness to him'. As he swallowed down the faded flakes of that distasteful pastry - it was mouldy, it was fly-blown, it was sour - Flush solemnly repeated, in his own language, the words she had used - he swore to love Mr Browning and not bite him for the future.

He was instantly rewarded - not by stale cakes, not by chicken's wings, not by the caresses that were now his, nor by the permission to lie once more on the sofa at Miss Bar-rett's feet. He was rewarded, spiritually; yet the effects were curiously physical. Like an iron bar corroding and festering and killing all natural life beneath it, hatred had lain all these months across his soul. Now, by the cutting of sharp knives and painful surgery, the iron had been excised. Now the blood ran once more; the nerves shot and tingled; flesh formed; Nature rejoiced, as in spring. Flush heard the birds sing again; he felt the leaves growing on the trees; as he lay on the sofa at Miss Barrett' s feet, glory and delight coursed through his veins. He was with them, not against them, now; their hopes, their wishes, their desires were his. Flush could have barked in sympathy with Mr Browning now. The short, sharp words raised the hackles on his neck. ‘I need a week of Tuesdays,' Mr Browning cried, ‘then a month - a year - a life!' I, Flush echoed him, need a month-a year-a life! I need all the things that you both need. We are all three conspirators in the most glorious of causes. We are joined in sympathy. We are joined in hatred. We are joined in defiance of black and beetling tyranny. We are joined in love. - In short, all Flush' s hopes now were set upon some dimly apprehended but none the less certainly emerging triumph, upon some glorious victory that was to be theirs in common, when suddenly, without a word of warning, in the midst of civilisation, security and friendship - he was in a shop in Vere Street with Miss Barrett and her sister: it was the morning of Tuesday the 1st of September - Flush was tumbled head over heels into darkness. The doors of a dungeon shut upon him. He was stolen.

Chapter 4　WHITECHAPEL

‘This morning Arabel and I, and he with us,' Miss Barrett wrote, ‘went in a cab to Vere Street where we had a little business, and he followed us as usual into a shop and out of it again, and was at my heels when I stepped up into the carriage. Having turned, I said "Flush" ,and Arabel looked round for Flush - there was no Flush! He had been caught up in that moment, from under the wheels, do you under-stand?' Mr Browning understood perfectly well. Miss Barrett had forgotten the chain; therefore Flush was stolen. Such, in the year 1846,was the law of Wimpole Street and its neighbourhood.

Nothing, it is true, could exceed the apparent solidity and security of Wimpole Street itself. As far as an invalid could walk or a bath-chair could trundle nothing met the eye but an agreeable prospect of four-storeyed houses, plate-glass windows and mahogany doors. Even a carriage and pair, in the course of an afternoon's airing, need not, if the coach-man were discreet, leave the limits of decorum and respectability. But if you were not an invalid, if you did not possess a carriage and pair, if you were - and many people were - active and able-bodied and fond of walking, then you might see sights and hear language and smell smells, not a stone's-throw from Wimpole Street, that threw doubts upon the solidity even of Wimpole Street itself. So Mr Thomas Beames found when about this time he took it into his head to go walking about London. He was surprised; indeed he was shocked. Splendid buildings raised them-selves in Westminster, yet just behind them were ruined sheds in which human beings lived herded together above herds of cows - ‘two in each seven feet of space'. He felt that he ought to tell people what he had seen. Yet how could one describe politely a bedroom in which two or three families lived above a cow-shed, when the cow-shed had no ventila-tion, when the cows were milked and killed and eaten under the bedroom? That was a task, as Mr Beames found when he came to attempt it, that taxed all the resources of the English language. And yet he felt that he ought to describe what he had seen in the course of an afternoon' s walk through some of the most aristocratic parishes in London. The risk of typhus was so great. The rich could not know what dangers they were running. He could not altogether hold his tongue when he found what he did find in West-minster and Paddington and Marylebone. For instance, here was an old mansion formerly belonging to some great noble-man. Relics of marble mantelpieces remained. The rooms were panelled and the banisters were carved, and yet the floors were rotten, the walls dripped with filth; hordes of half-naked men and women had taken up their lodging in the old banqueting-halls. Then he walked on. Here an enter-prising builder had pulled down the old family mansion. He had run up a jerry-built tenement house in its place. The rain dripped through the roof and the wind blew through the walls. He saw a child dipping a can into a bright-green stream and asked if they drank that water. Yes, and washed in it too, for the landlord only allowed water to be turned on twice a week. Such sights were the more surprising, because one might come upon them in the most sedate and civilised quarters of London - ‘the most aristocratic par-ishes have their share'. Behind Miss Barrett' s bedroom, for instance, was one of the worst slums in London. Mixed up with that respectability was this squalor. But there were certain quarters, of course, which had long been given over to the poor and were left undisturbed. In Whitechapel, or in a triangular space of ground at the bot-tom of the Tottenham Court Road, poverty and vice and misery had bred and seethed and propagated their kind for centuries without interference. A dense mass of aged build-ings in St Giles' s was ‘wellnigh a penal settlement, a pauper metropolis in itself'. Aptly enough, where the poor conglom-erated thus, the settlement was called a Rookery. For there human beings swarmed on top of each other as rooks swarm and blacken tree-tops. Only the buildings here were not trees; they were hardly any longer buildings. They were cells of brick intersected by lanes which ran with filth. All day the lanes buzzed with half-dressed human beings; at night there poured back again into the stream the thieves, beggars and prostitutes who had been plying their trade all day in the West End. The police could do nothing. No single way-farer could do anything except hurry through as fast as he could and perhaps drop a hint, as Mr Beames did, with many quotations, evasions and euphemisms, that all was not quite as it should be. Cholera would come, and perhaps the hint that cholera would give would not be quite so evasive.

But in the summer of 1846 that hint had not yet been given; and the only safe course for those who lived in Wim-pole Street and its neighbourhood was to keep strictly within the respectable area and to lead your dog on a chain. If one forgot, as Miss Barrett forgot, one paid the penalty, as Miss Barrett was now to pay it. The terms upon which Wimpole Street lived cheek by jowl with St Giles' s were well known. St Giles' s stole what St Giles' s could; Wimpole Street paid what Wimpole Street must. Thus Arabel at once ‘began to comfort me by showing how certain it was that I should recover him for ten pounds at most'. Ten pounds, it was reckoned, was about the price that Mr Taylor would ask for a cocker spaniel. Mr Taylor was the head of the gang. As soon as a lady in Wimpole Street lost her dog she went to Mr Taylor; he named his price, and it was paid; or if not, a brown paper parcel was delivered in Wimpole Street a few days later containing the head and paws of the dog. Such, at least, had been the experience of a lady in the neighbour-hood who had tried to make terms with Mr Taylor. But Miss Barrett of course intended to pay. Therefore when she got home she told her brother Henry, and Henry went to see Mr Taylor that afternoon. He found him ‘smoking a cigar in a room with pictures' - Mr Taylor was said to make an income of two or three thousand a year out of the dogs of Wimpole Street - and Mr Taylor promised that he would confer with his ‘Society' and that the dog would be returned next day. Vexatious as it was, and especially annoying at a moment when Miss Barrett needed all her money, such were the inevitable consequences of forgetting in 1846 to keep one' s dog on a chain.

But for Flush things were very different. Flush, Miss Bar-rett reflected, ‘doesn' t know that we can recover him'; Flush had never mastered the principles of human society. ‘All this night he will howl and lament, I know perfectly', Miss Bar-rett wrote to Mr Browning on the afternoon of Tuesday, the 1st September. But while Miss Barrett wrote to Mr Brown-ing, Flush was going through the most terrible experience of his life. He was bewildered in the extreme. One moment he was in Vere Street, among ribbons and laces; the next he was tumbled head over heels into a bag; jolted rapidly across streets, and at length was tumbled out - here. He found himself in complete darkness. He found himself in chillness and dampness. As his giddiness left him he made out a few shapes in a low dark room - broken chairs, a tumbled mat-tress. Then he was seized and tied tightly by the leg to some obstacle. Something sprawled on the floor - whether beast or human being, he could not tell. Great boots and draggled skirts kept stumbling in and out. Flies buzzed on scraps of old meat that were decaying on the floor. Children crawled out from dark corners and pinched his ears. He whined, and a heavy hand beat him over the head. He cowered down on the few inches of damp brick against the wall. Now he could see that the floor was crowded with animals of different kinds. Dogs tore and worried a festering bone that they had got between them. Their ribs stood out from their coats - they were half famished, dirty, diseased, uncombed, unbrushed; yet all of them, Flush could see, were dogs of the highest breeding, chained dogs, footmen' s dogs, like himself.

He lay, not daring even to whimper, hour after hour. Thirst was his worst suffering; but one sip of the thick green-ish water that stood in a pail near him disgusted him; he would rather die than drink another. Yet a majestic grey-hound was drinking greedily. Whenever the door was kicked open he looked up. Miss Barrett - was it Miss Bar-rett? Had she come at last? But it was only a hairy ruffian, who kicked them all aside and stumbled to a broken chair upon which he flung himself. Then gradually the darkness thickened. He could scarcely make out what shapes those were, on the floor, on the mattress, on the broken chairs. A stump of candle was stuck on the ledge over the fireplace. A flare burnt in the gutter outside. By its flickering, coarse light Flush could see terrible faces passing outside, leering at the window. Then in they came, until the small crowded room became so crowded that he had to shrink back and lie even closer against the wall. These horrible monsters - some were ragged, others were flaring with paint and feathers - squatted on the floor; hunched themselves over the table. They began to drink; they cursed and struck each other. Out tumbled, from the bags that were dropped on the floor, more dogs - lapdogs, setters, pointers, with their collars still on them; and a giant cockatoo that flustered and fluttered its way from corner to corner, shrieking ‘Pretty Poll', ‘Pretty Poll', with an accent that would have terrified its mistress, a widow in Maida Vale. Then the women' s bags were opened, and out were tossed on to the table bracelets and rings and brooches such as Flush had seen Miss Barrett wear and Miss Henrietta. The demons pawed and clawed them; cursed and quarrelled over them. The dogs barked. The children shrieked, and the splendid cockatoo - such a bird as Flush had often seen pendant in a Wimpole Street window - shrieked ‘Pretty Poll! Pretty Poll!' faster and faster until a slipper was thrown at it and it flapped its great yellow-stained dove-grey wings in frenzy. Then the candle toppled over and fell. The room was dark. It grew steadily hotter and hotter; the smell, the heat, were unbearable, Flush' s nose burnt; his coat twitched. And still Miss Barrett did not come.

Miss Barrett lay on her sofa in Wimpole Street. She was vexed; she was worried, but she was not seriously alarmed. Of course Flush would suffer; he would whine and bark all night; but it was only a question of a few hours. Mr Taylor would name his sum; she would pay it; Flush would be returned.

The morning of Wednesday the 2nd September dawned in the rookeries of Whitechapel. The broken windows grad-ually became smeared with grey. Light fell upon the hairy faces of ruffians lying sprawled upon the floor. Flush woke from a trance that had veiled his eyes and once more real-ised the truth. This was now the truth - this room, these ruffians, these whining, snapping, tightly tethered dogs, this murk, this dampness. Could it be true that he had been in a shop, with ladies, among ribbons, only yesterday? Was there such a place as Wimpole Street? Was there a room where fresh water sparkled in a purple jar; had he lain on cushions; had he been given a chicken' s wing nicely roasted; and had he been torn with rage and jealousy and bitten a man with yellow gloves? The whole of that life and its emo-tions floated away, dissolved, became unreal.

Here, as the dusty light filtered in, a woman heaved her-self off a sack and staggered out to fetch beer. The drinking and the cursing began again. A fat woman held him up by his ears and pinched his ribs, and some odious joke was made about him - there was a roar of laughter as she threw him on the floor again. The door was kicked open and banged to. Whenever that happened he looked up. Was it Wilson? Could it possibly be Mr Browning? Or Miss Bar-rett? But no - it was only another thief, another murderer; he cowered back at the mere sight of those draggled skirts, of those hard, horny boots. Once he tried to gnaw a bone that was hurled his way. But his teeth could not meet in stony flesh and the rank smell disgusted him. His thirst increased and he was forced to lap a little of the green water that had been spilt from the pail. But as Wednesday wore on and he became hotter and more parched and still more sore, lying on the broken boards, one thing merged in another. He scarcely noticed what was happening. It was only when the door opened that he raised his head and looked. No, it was not Miss Barrett.

Miss Barrett, lying on the sofa in Wimpole Street, was becoming anxious. There was some hitch in the proceed-ings. Taylor had promised that he would go down to Whitechapel on Wednesday afternoon and confer with ‘the Society'. Yet Wednesday afternoon, Wednesday evening passed and still Taylor did not come. This could only mean, she supposed, that the price was going to be raised - which was inconvenient enough at the moment. Still, of course, she would have to pay it. ‘I must have my Flush, you know', she wrote to Mr Browning. ‘I can' t run any risk and bargain and haggle.' So she lay on the sofa writing to Mr Browning and listening for a knock at the door. But Wilson came up with the letters; Wilson came up with the hot water. It was time for bed and Flush had not come.

Thursday the 3rd of September dawned in Whitechapel. The door opened and shut. The red setter who had been whining all night beside Flush on the floor was hauled off by a ruffian in a moleskin vest - to what fate? Was it better to be killed or to stay here? Which was worse - this life or that death? The racket, the hunger and the thirst, the reek-ing smells of the place - and once, Flush remembered, he had detested the scent of eau-de-Cologne - were fast oblit-erating any clear image, any single desire. Fragments of old memories began turning in his head. Was that the voice of old Dr Mitford shouting in the field? Was that Kerenhap-poch gossiping with the baker at the door? There was a rattling in the room and he thought he heard Miss Mitford tying up a bunch of geraniums. But it was only the wind - for it was stormy to-day - battering at the brown paper in the broken window pane. It was only some drunken voice raving in the gutter. It was only the old hag in the corner mumbling on and on and on as she fried a herring in a pan over a fire. He had been forgotten and deserted. No help was coming. No voice spoke to him - the parrots cried ‘Pretty Poll, Pretty Poll', and the canaries kept up their senseless cheeping and chirping.

Then again evening darkened the room; the candle was stuck in its saucer; the coarse light flared outside; hordes of sinister men with bags on their backs, of garish women with painted faces, began to shuffle in at the door and to fling themselves down on the broken beds and tables. Another night had folded its blackness over Whitechapel. And the rain dripped steadily through a hole in the roof and drummed into a pail that had been stood to catch it. Miss Barrett had not come.

Thursday dawned in Wimpole Street. There was no sign of Flush - no message from Taylor. Miss Barrett was very much alarmed. She made enquiries. She summoned her brother Henry, and cross-examined him. She found out that he had tricked her. ‘The arch fiend' Taylor had come accord-ing to his promise the night before. He had stated his terms - six guineas for the Society and half a guinea for himself. But Henry, instead of telling her, had told Mr Bar-rett, with the result, of course, that Mr Barrett had ordered him not to pay, and to conceal the visit from his sister. Miss Barrett was ‘very vexed and angry'. She bade her brother to go at once to Mr Taylor and pay the money. Henry refused and ‘talked of Papa'. But it was no use talking of Papa, she protested. While they talked of Papa, Flush would be killed. She made up her mind. If Henry would not go, she would go herself: ‘ …… if people won' t do as I choose, I shall go down to-morrow morning, and bring Flush back with me', she wrote to Mr Browning.

But Miss Barrett now found that it was easier to say this than to do it. It was almost as difficult for her to go to Flush as for Flush to come to her. All Wimpole Street was against her. The news that Flush was stolen and that Taylor demanded a ransom was now public property. Wimpole Street was determined to make a stand against Whitechapel. Blind Mr Boyd sent word that in his opinion it would be ‘an awful sin' to pay the ransom. Her father and her brother were in league against her and were capable of any treachery in the interests of their class. But worst of all - far worse - Mr Browning himself threw all his weight, all his eloquence, all his learning, all his logic, on the side of Wimpole Street and against Flush. If Miss Barrett gave way to Taylor, he wrote, she was giving way to tyranny; she was giving way to blackmailers; she was increasing the power of evil over right, of wickedness over innocence. If she gave Taylor his demand, ‘ …… how will the poor owners fare who have not money enough for their dogs' redemption' ?His imagination took fire; he imagined what he would say if Taylor asked him even for five shillings; he would say, ‘You are responsible for the proceedings of your gang, and you I mark - don' t talk nonsense to me about cutting off heads or paws. Be as sure as that I stand here and tell you, I will spend my whole life in putting you down, the nuisance you declare yourself - and by every imaginable means I will be the death of you and as many of your accomplices as I can discover - but you I have discovered and will never lose sight of …… ' So Mr Browning would have replied to Taylor if he had had the good fortune to meet that gentleman. For indeed, he went on, catching a later post with a second letter that same Thursday afternoon, ‘ …… it is horrible to fancy how all the oppressors in their several ranks may, if they choose, twitch back to them by the heartstrings after various modes the weak and silent whose secret they have found out'. He did not blame Miss Barrett - nothing she did could be anything but perfectly right, perfectly acceptable to him. Still, he continued on Friday morning, ‘I think it lamentable weakness …… ' If she encouraged Taylor who stole dogs, she encouraged Mr Barnard Gregory who stole characters. Indirectly, she was responsible for all the wretches who cut their throats or fly the country because some blackmailer like Barnard Gregory took down a directory and blasted their characters. ‘But why write all this string of truisms about the plainest thing in the world?' So Mr Browning stormed and vociferated from New Cross twice daily. Lying on her sofa, Miss Barrett read the letters. How easy it would have been to yield - how easy it would have been to say, ‘Your good opinion is worth more to me than a hun-dred cocker spaniels'. How easy it would have been to sink back on her pillows and sigh, ‘I am a weak woman; I know nothing of law and justice; decide for me'. She had only to refuse to pay the ransom; she had only to defy Taylor and his Society. And if Flush were killed, if the dreadful parcel came and she opened it and out dropped his head and paws, there was Robert Browning by her side to assure her that she had done right and earned his respect. But Miss Barrett was not to be intimidated. Miss Barrett took up her pen and refuted Robert Browning. It was all very well, she said, to quote Donne; to cite the case of Gregory; to invent spirited replies to Mr Taylor - she would have done the same had Taylor struck her; had Gregory defamed her; - would that they had! But what would Mr Browning have done if the banditti had stolen her; had her in their power; threatened to cut off her ears and send them by post to New Cross? Whatever he would have done, her mind was made up. Flush was helpless. Her duty was to him. ‘But Flush, poor Flush, who has loved me so faithfully; have I a right to sacrifice him in his innocence, for the sake of any Mr Taylor' s guilt in the world?' Whatever Mr Browning might say, she was going to rescue Flush, even if she went down into the jaws of Whitechapel to fetch him, even if Robert Browning despised her for doing so.

On Saturday, therefore, with Mr Browning's letter lying open on the table before her, she began to dress. She read his ‘one word more - in all this, I labour against the exe-crable policy of the world's husbands, fathers, brothers and domineerers in general'.So, if she went to Whitechapel she was siding against Robert Browning, and in favour of fathers, brothers and domineerers in general. Still, she went on dressing. A dog howled in the mews. It was tied up, help-less in the power of cruel men. It seemed to her to cry as it howled: ‘Think of Flush'. She put on her shoes, her cloak, her hat. She glanced at Mr Browning' s letter once more. ‘I am about to marry you', she read. Still the dog howled. She left her room and went downstairs.

Henry Barrett met her and told her that in his opinion she might well be robbed and murdered if she did what she threatened. She told Wilson to call a cab. All trembling but submissive, Wilson obeyed. The cab came. Miss Barrett told Wilson to get in. Wilson, though convinced that death awaited her, got in. Miss Barrett told the cab-man to drive to Manning Street, Shoreditch. Miss Barrett got in herself and off they drove. Soon they were beyond plate-glass win-dows, the mahogany doors and the area railings. They were in a world that Miss Barrett had never seen, had never guessed at. They were in a world where cows are herded under bedroom floors, where whole families sleep in rooms with broken windows; in a world where water is turned on only twice a week, in a world where vice and poverty breed vice and poverty. They had come to a region unknown to respectable cab-drivers. The cab stopped; the driver asked his way at a public-house. ‘Out came two or three men. "Oh, you want to find Mr Taylor, I daresay!" ' In this mysterious world a cab with two ladies could only come upon one errand, and that errand was already known. It was sinister in the extreme. One of the men ran into a house, and came out saying that Mr Taylor ‘ "wasn' t at home! but wouldn' t I get out?" Wilson, in an aside of terror, entreated me not to think of such a thing.' A gang of men and boys pressed round the cab. ‘Then wouldn' t I see Mrs Taylor?' the man asked. Miss Barrett had no wish whatever to see Mrs Taylor; but now an immense fat woman came out of the house, ‘fat enough to have had an easy conscience all her life', and informed Miss Barrett that her husband was out: ‘might be in in a few minutes, or in so many hours - wouldn' t I like to get out and wait?' Wilson tugged at her gown. Imagine waiting in the house of that woman! It was bad enough to sit in the cab with the gang of men and boys pressing round them. So Miss Barrett parleyed with the ‘immense feminine bandit' from the cab. Mr Taylor had her dog, she said; Mr Taylor had promised to restore her dog; would Mr Taylor bring back her dog to Wimpole Street for certain that very day? ‘Oh yes, certainly,' said the fat woman with the most gracious of smiles. She did believe that Taylor had left home precisely on that business. And she ‘poised her head to right and left with the most easy grace'.

So the cab turned round and left Manning Street, Shoreditch. Wilson was of opinion that ‘we had escaped with our lives barely'.Miss Barrett herself had been alarmed. ‘Plain enough it was that the gang was strong there. The Society, the "Fancy" …… had their roots in the ground', she wrote. Her mind teemed with thoughts, her eyes were full of pictures. This, then, was what lay on the other side of Wimpole Street - these faces, these houses. She had seen more while she sat in the cab at the public-house than she had seen during the five years that she had lain in the back bedroom at Wimpole Street. ‘The faces of those men!' she exclaimed. They were branded on her eyeballs. They stimu-lated her imagination as ‘the divine marble presences', the busts on the bookcase, had never stimulated it. Here lived women like herself; while she lay on her sofa, reading, writ-ing, they lived thus. But the cab was now trundling along between four-storeyed houses again. Here was the familiar avenue of doors and windows: the pointed brick, the brass knockers, the regular curtains. Here was Wimpole Street and No.50.Wilson sprang out - with what relief to find herself in safety can be imagined. But Miss Barrett perhaps hesitated a moment. She still saw ‘the faces of those men'. They were to come before her again years later when she sat writing on a sunny balcony in Italy. They were to inspire the most vivid passages in Aurora Leigh. But now the butler had opened the door, and she went upstairs to her room again.

Saturday was the fifth day of Flush' s imprisonment. Almost exhausted, almost hopeless, he lay panting in his dark corner of the teeming floor. Doors slammed and banged. Rough voices cried. Women screamed. Parrots chattered as they had never chattered to widows in Maida Vale, but now evil old women merely cursed at them. Insects crawled in his fur, but he was too weak, too indifferent to shake his coat. All Flush' s past life and its many scenes - Reading, the greenhouse, Miss Mitford, Mr Kenyon, the bookcases, the busts, the peasants on the blind - had faded like snow flakes dissolved in a cauldron. If he still held to hope, it was to something nameless and formless; the fea-tureless face of someone he still called ‘Miss Barrett'. She still existed; all the rest of the world was gone; but she still existed, though such gulfs lay between them that it was impossible, almost, that she should reach him still. Darkness began to fall again, such darkness as seemed almost able to crush out his last hope - Miss Barrett.

In truth, the forces of Wimpole Street were still, even at this last moment, battling to keep Flush and Miss Barrett apart. On Saturday afternoon she lay and waited for Taylor to come, as the immensely fat woman had promised. At last he came, but he had not brought the dog. He sent up a message - Let Miss Barrett pay him six guineas on the spot, and he would go straight toWhitechapel and fetch the dog ‘on his word of honour'. What ‘the archfiend' Taylor' s word of honour might be worth, Miss Barrett could not say; but ‘there seemed no other way for it'; Flush' s life was at stake; she counted out the guineas and sent them down to Tay-lor in the passage. But as ill luck would have it, as Taylor waited in the passage among the umbrellas, the engravings, the pile carpet and other valuable objects, Alfred Barrett came in. The sight of the arch fiend actually in the house made him lose his temper. He burst into a rage. He called him ‘a swindler, and a liar and a thief'. Thereupon Mr Taylor cursed him back. What was far worse, he swore that ‘as he hoped to be saved, we should never see our dog again', and rushed out of the house. Next morning, then, the blood-stained parcel would arrive.

Miss Barrett flung on her clothes again and rushed down-stairs. Where was Wilson? Let her call a cab. She was going back to Shoreditch instantly. Her family came running to prevent her. It was getting dark. She was exhausted already. The adventure was risky enough for a man in health. For her it was madness. So they told her. Her brothers, her sisters, all came round her threatening her, dissuading her, ‘crying out against me for being "quite mad" and obstinate and wilful - I was called as many names as Mr Taylor'. But she stood her ground. At last they realised the extent of her folly. Whatever the risk might be they must give way to her. Septimus promised if Ba would return to her room ‘and be in good humour' he would go to Taylor' s himself and pay the money and bring back the dog.

So the dusk of the 5th of September faded into the black-ness of night in Whitechapel. The door of the room was once more kicked open. A hairy man hauled Flush by the scruff of his neck out of his corner. Looking up into the hideous face of his old enemy, Flush did not know whether he was being taken to be killed or to be freed. Save for one phan-tom memory, he did not care. The man stooped. What were those great fingers fumbling at his throat for? Was it a knife or a chain? Stumbling, half blinded, on legs that staggered, Flush was led out into the open air.

In Wimpole Street Miss Barrett could not eat her dinner. Was Flush dead, or was Flush alive? She did not know. At eight o'clock there was a rap on the door; it was the usual letter from Mr Browning. But as the door opened to admit the letter, something rushed in also; - Flush. He made straight for his purple jar. It was filled three times over; and still he drank. Miss Barrett watched the dazed, bewildered dirty dog, drinking. ‘He was not so enthusiastic about see-ing me as I expected', she remarked. No, there was only one thing in the world he wanted - clean water.

After all, Miss Barrett had but glanced at the faces of those men and she remembered them all her life. Flush had been at their mercy in their midst for five whole days. Now as he lay on cushions once more, cold water was the only thing that seemed to have any substance, any reality. He drank continually. The old gods of the bedroom - the book-case, the wardrobe, the busts - seemed to have lost their substance. This room was no longer the whole world; it was only a shelter. It was only a dell arched over by one trem-bling dock-leaf in a forest where wild beasts prowled and venomous snakes coiled; where behind every tree lurked a murderer ready to pounce. As he lay dazed and exhausted on the sofa at Miss Barrett' s feet the howls of tethered dogs, the screams of birds in terror still sounded in his ears. When the door opened he started, expecting a hairy man with a knife - it was only Mr Kenyon with a book; it was only Mr Browning with his yellow gloves. But he shrank away from Mr Kenyon and Mr Browning now. He trusted them no longer. Behind those smiling, friendly faces was treach-ery and cruelty and deceit. Their caresses were hollow. He dreaded even walking with Wilson to the pillar-box. He would not stir without his chain. When they said, ‘Poor Flush, did the naughty men take you away?' he put up his head and moaned and yelled. A whip cracking sent him bolting down the area-steps into safety. Indoors he crept closer to Miss Barrett on the sofa. She alone had not des-erted him. He still kept some faith in her. Gradually some substance returned to her. Exhausted, trembling, dirty and very thin, he lay on the sofa at her feet.

As the days passed and the memory ofWhitechapel grew fainter, Flush, lying close to Miss Barrett on the sofa, read her feelings more clearly than ever before. They had been parted; now they were together. Indeed they had never been so much akin. Every start she gave, every movement she made, passed through him too. And she seemed now to be perpetually starting and moving. The delivery of a parcel even made her jump. She opened the parcel; with trembling fingers she took out a pair of thick boots. She hid them instantly in the corner of the cupboard. Then she lay down as if nothing had happened; yet something had happened. When they were alone she rose and took a diamond necklace from a drawer. She took out the box that held Mr Brown-ing' s letters. She laid the boots, the necklace and the letters all in a carpet-box together and then - as if she heard a step on the stair - she pushed the box under the bed and lay down hastily, covering herself with her shawl again. Such signs of secrecy and stealth must herald, Flush felt, some approaching crisis. Were they about to fly together? Were they about to escape together from this awful world of dog-stealers and tyrants? Oh that it were possible! He trem-bled and whined with excitement; but in her low voice Miss Barrett bade him be quiet, and instantly he was quiet. She was very quiet too. She lay perfectly still on the sofa directly any of her brothers or sisters came in; she lay and talked to Mr Barrett as she always lay and talked to Mr Barrett.

But on Saturday, the 12th of September, Miss Barrett did what Flush had never known her do before. She dressed herself as if to go out directly after breakfast. Moreover, as he watched her dress, Flush knew perfectly well from the expression on her face that he was not to go with her. She was bound on secret business of her own. At ten Wilson came into the room. She also was dressed as if for a walk. They went out together; and Flush lay on the sofa and waited for their return. An hour or so later Miss Barrett came back alone. She did not look at him - she seemed to look at nothing. She drew off her gloves and for a moment he saw a gold band shine on one of the fingers of her left hand. Then he saw her slip the ring from her hand and hide it in the darkness of a drawer. Then she laid herself down as usual on the sofa. He lay by her side scarcely daring to breathe, for whatever had happened, it was something that must at all costs be concealed.

At all costs the life of the bedroom must go on as usual. Yet everything was different. The very movement of the blind as it drew in and out seemed to Flush like a signal. And as the lights and shadows passed over the busts they too seemed to be hinting and beckoning. Everything in the room seemed to be aware of change; to be prepared for some event. And yet all was silent; all was concealed. The brothers and sisters came in and out as usual; Mr Barrett came as usual in the evening. He looked as usual to see that the chop was finished, the wine drunk. Miss Barrett talked and laughed and gave no sign when anyone was in the room that she was hiding anything. Yet when they were alone she pulled out the box from under the bed and filled it hastily, stealthily, listening as she did so. And the signs of strain were unmistakable. On Sunday the church bells were ring-ing. ‘What bells are those?' somebody asked. ‘Marylebone Church bells', said Miss Henrietta. Miss Barrett, Flush saw, went deadly white. But nobody else seemed to notice anything.

So Monday passed, and Tuesday and Wednesday and Thursday. Over them all lay a blanket of silence, of eating and talking and lying still on the sofa as usual. Flush, toss-ing in uneasy sleep, dreamt that they were couched together under ferns and leaves in the darkness, in a vast forest; then the leaves were parted and he woke. It was dark; but he saw Wilson come stealthily into the room, and take the box from beneath the bed and quietly carry it outside. This was on Friday night, the 18th of September. All Saturday morning he lay as one lies who knows that at any moment now a handkerchief may drop, a low whistle may sound and the signal will be given for death or for life. He watched Miss Barrett dress herself. At a quarter to four the door opened and Wilson came in. Then the signal was given - Miss Bar-rett lifted him in her arms. She rose and walked to the door. For a moment they stood looking round the room. There was the sofa and by it Mr Browning' s armchair. There were the busts and the tables. The sunfiltered through the ivy leaves and the blind with peasants walking blew gently out. All was as usual. All seemed to expect a million more such movements to come to them; but to Miss Barrett and Flush this was the last. Very quietly Miss Barrett shut the door.

Very quietly they slipped downstairs, past the drawing-room, the library, the dining-room. All looked as they usually looked; smelt as they usually smelt; all were quiet as if sleeping in the hot September afternoon. On the mat in the hall Catiline lay sleeping too. They gained the front door and very quietly turned the handle. A cab was waiting outside.

‘To Hodgson's', said Miss Barrett. She spoke almost in a whisper. Flush sat on her knee very still. Not for anything in the whole world would he have broken that tremendous silence.

Chapter 5　ITALY

Hours, days, weeks, it seemed of darkness and rattling; of sudden lights; and then long tunnels of gloom; of being flung this way and that; of being hastily lifted into the light and seeing Miss Barrett' s face close, and thin trees and lines and rails and high light-specked houses - for it was the bar-barous custom of railways in those days to make dogs travel in boxes - followed. Yet Flush was not afraid; they were escaping; they were leaving tyrants and dog-stealers behind them. Rattle, grind; grind, rattle as much as you like, he murmured, as the train flung him this way and that; only let us leave Wimpole Street and Whitechapel behind us. At last the light broadened; the rattling stopped. He heard birds singing and the sigh of trees in the wind. Or was it the rush of water? Opening his eyes at last, shaking his coat at last, he saw - the most astonishing sight conceivable. There was Miss Barrett on a rock in the midst of rushing waters. Trees bent over her; the river raced round her. She must be in peril. With one bound Flush splashed through the stream and reached her. ‘ …… he is baptized in Petrarch' s name', said Miss Barrett as he clambered up on to the rock by her side. For they were at Vaucluse; she had perched her-self upon a stone in the middle of Petrarch' s fountain.

Then there was more rattling and more grinding; and then again he was stood down on a stable floor; the darkness opened; light poured over him; he found himself alive, awake, bewildered, standing on reddish tiles in a vast bare room flooded with sunshine. He ran hither and thither smelling and touching. There was no carpet and no fire-place. There were no sofas, no armchairs, no bookcases, no busts. Pungent and unfamiliar smells tickled his nostrils and made him sneeze. The light, in finitely sharp and clear, dazzled his eyes. He had never been in a room - if this were indeed a room - that was so hard, so bright, so big, so empty. Miss Barrett looked smaller than ever sitting on a chair by a table in the midst. Then Wilson took him out of doors. He found himself almost blinded,first by the sun, then by the shadow. One half of the street was burning hot; the other bitterly cold. Women went by wrapped in furs, yet they carried parasols to shade their heads. And the street was dry as bone. Though it was now the middle of Novem-ber there was neither mud nor puddle to wet his paws or clot their feathers. There were no areas and no railings. There was none of that heady confusion of smells that made a walk down Wimpole Street or Oxford Street so distract-ing. On the other hand, the strange new smells that came from sharp stone corners, from dry yellow walls, were extraordinarily pungent and queer. Then from behind a black swinging curtain came an astonishing sweet smell, wafted in clouds; he stopped, his paws raised, to savour it; he made to follow it inside; he pushed in beneath the cur-tain. He had one glimpse of a booming light-sprinkled hall, very high and hollow; and then Wilson with a cry of horror, jerked him smartly back. They went on down the street again. The noise of the street was deafening. Everybody seemed to be shouting shrilly at the same moment. Instead of the solid and soporific hum of London there was a rat-tling and a crying, a jingling and a shouting, a cracking of whips and a jangling of bells. Flush leapt and jumped this way and that, and so did Wilson. They were forced on and off the pavement twenty times, to avoid a cart, a bullock, a troop of soldiers, a drove of goats. He felt younger, spryer than he had done these many years. Dazzled, yet exhil-arated, he sank on the reddish tiles and slept more soundly than he had ever slept in the back bedroom at Wimpole Street upon pillows.

But soon Flush became aware of the more profound dif-ferences that distinguish Pisa - for it was in Pisa that they were now settled - from London. The dogs were different. In London he could scarcely trot round to the pillar-box without meeting some pug dog, retriever, bulldog, mastiff,collie, Newfoundland, St Bernard, fox terrier or one of the seven famous families of the Spaniel tribe. To each he gave a different name, and to each a different rank. But here in Pisa, though dogs abounded, there were no ranks; all - could it be possible? - were mongrels. As far as he could see, they were dogs merely-grey dogs, yellow dogs, brin-dled dogs, spotted dogs; but it was impossible to detect a single spaniel, collie, retriever or mastiff among them. Had the Kennel Club, then, no jurisdiction in Italy? Was the Spaniel Club unknown? Was there no law which decreed death to the topknot, which cherished the curled ear, pro-tected the feathered foot, and insisted absolutely that the brow must be domed but not pointed? Apparently not. Flush felt himself like a prince in exile. He was the sole aristocrat among a crowd of canaille. He was the only pure-bred cocker spaniel in the whole of Pisa.

For many years now Flush had been taught to consider himself an aristocrat. The law of the purple jar and of the chain had sunk deep into his soul. It is scarcely surprising that he was thrown off his balance. A Howard or a Caven-dish set down among a swarm of natives in mud huts can hardly be blamed if now and again he remembers Chats-worth and muses regretfully over red carpets and galleries daubed with coronets as the sunset blazes down through painted windows. There was an element, it must be admit-ted, of the snob in Flush; Miss Mitford had detected it years ago; and the sentiment, subdued in London among equals and superiors, returned to him now that he felt himself unique. He became overbearing and impudent. ‘Flush has grown an absolute monarch and barks one distracted when he wants a door opened', Mrs Browning wrote. ‘Robert', she continued, ‘declares that the said Flush considers him, my husband, to be created for the especial purpose of doing him service, and really it looks rather like it.'

‘Robert', ‘my husband' - if Flush had changed, so had Miss Barrett. It was not merely that she called herself Mrs Browning now; that she flashed the gold ring on her hand in the sun; she was changed, as much as Flush was changed. Flush heard her say ‘Robert', ‘my husband', fifty times a day, and always with a ring of pride that made his hackles rise and his heart jump. But it was not her language only that had changed. She was a different person altogether. Now, for instance, instead of sipping a thimbleful of port and complaining of the headache, she tossed off a tumbler of Chianti and slept the sounder. There was a flowering branch of oranges on the dinner-table instead of one denuded, sour, yellow fruit. Then instead of driving in a barouche landau to Regent' s Park she pulled on her thick boots and scram-bled over rocks. Instead of sitting in a carriage and rumbling along Oxford Street, they rattled off in a ramshackle fly to the borders of a lake and looked at mountains; and when she was tired she did not hail another cab; she sat on a stone and watched the lizards. She delighted in the sun; she delighted in the cold. She threw pine logs from the Duke' s forest on to the fire if it froze. They sat together in the crack-ling blaze and snuffed up the sharp, aromatic scent. She was never tired of praising Italy at the expense of England. ‘ …… our poor English', she exclaimed, ‘want educating into glad-ness. They want refining not in the fire but in the sunshine.' Here in Italy was freedom and life and the joy that the sun breeds. One never saw menfighting, or heard them swear-ing; one never saw the Italians drunk; - ‘the faces of those men' in Shoreditch came again before her eyes. She was always comparing Pisa with London and saying how much she preferred Pisa. In the streets of Pisa pretty women could walk alone; great ladies first emptied their own slops and then went to Court ‘in a blaze of undeniable glory'. Pisa with all its bells, its mongrels, its camels, its pine woods, was infinitely preferable to Wimpole Street and its mahog-any doors and its shoulders of mutton. So Mrs Browning every day, as she tossed off her Chianti and broke another orange from the branch, praised Italy and lamented poor, dull, damp, sunless, joyless, expensive, conventional England.

Wilson, it is true, for a time maintained her British bal-ance. The memory of butlers and basements, of front doors and curtains, was not obliterated from her mind without an effort. She still had the conscience to walk out of a picture gallery ‘struck back by the indecency of the Venus'. And later, when she was allowed, by the kindness of a friend, to peep through a door at the glories of the Grand Ducal Court, she still loyally upheld the superior glory of St James' s. ‘It …… was all very shabby', she reported, ‘in com-parison with our English Court.' But even as she gazed, the superb figure of one of the Grand Duke' s bodyguard caught her eye. Her fancy was fired; her judgement reeled; her standards toppled. Lily Wilson fell passionately in love with Signor Righi, the guardsman.

And just as Mrs Browning was exploring her new free-dom and delighting in the discoveries she made, so Flush too was making his discoveries and exploring his freedom. Before they left Pisa - in the spring of 1847 they moved on to Florence - Flush had faced the curious and at first upset-ting truth that the laws of the Kennel Club are not universal. He had brought himself to face the fact that light topknots are not necessarily fatal. He had revised his code accord-ingly. He had acted, at first with some hesitation, upon his new conception of canine society. He was becoming daily more and more democratic. Even in Pisa, Mrs Browning noticed, ‘ …… he goes out every day and speaks Italian to the little dogs'. Now in Florence the last threads of his old fetters fell from him. The moment of liberation came one day in the Cascine. As he raced over the grass ‘like emeralds' with ‘the pheasants all alive and flying', Flush suddenly bethought him of Regent' s Park and its proclamation: Dogs must be led on chains. Where was ‘must' now? Where were chains now? Where were park-keepers and truncheons? Gone, with the dog-stealers and Kennel Clubs and Spaniel Clubs of a corrupt aristocracy! Gone with four-wheelers and hansom cabs! with Whitechapel and Shoreditch! He ran, he raced; his coat flashed; his eyes blazed. He was the friend of all the world now. All dogs were his brothers. He had no need of a chain in this new world; he had no need of protection. If Mr Browning was late in going for his walk - he and Flush were the best of friends now - Flush boldly summoned him. He ‘stands up before him and barks in the most imperi-ous manner possible', Mrs Browning observed with some irritation - for her relations with Flush were far less emo-tional now than in the old days; she no longer needed his red fur and his bright eyes to give her what her own experi-ence lacked; she had found Pan for herself among the vineyards and the olive trees; he was there too beside the pinefire of an evening. So if Mr Browning loitered, Flush stood up and barked; but if Mr Browning preferred to stay at home and write, it did not matter. Flush was independent now. The wistarias and the laburnum were flowering over walls; the judas trees were burning bright in the gardens; the wild tulips were sprinkled in the fields. Why should he wait? Off he ran by himself. He was his own master now. ‘ …… he goes out by himself, and stays hours together', Mrs Browning wrote; ‘ …… knows every street in Florence - will have his own way in everything. I am never frightened at his absence', she added, remembering with a smile those hours of agony in Wimpole Street and the gang waiting to snatch him up under the horses' feet if she forgot his chain in Vere Street. Fear was unknown in Florence; there were no dog-stealers here and, she may have sighed, there were no fathers.

But, to speak candidly, it was not to stare at pictures, to penetrate into dark churches and look up at dim frescoes, that Flush scampered off when the door of Casa Guidi was left open. It was to enjoy something, it was in search of something denied him all these years. Once the hunting horn of Venus had blown its wild music over the Berkshire fields; he had loved Mr Partridge' s dog; she had borne him a child. Now he heard the same voice pealing down the narrow streets of Florence, but more imperiously, more impetuously, after all these years of silence. Now Flush knew what men can never know - love pure, love simple, love entire; love that brings no train of care in its wake; that has no shame; no remorse; that is here, that is gone, as the bee on the flower is here and is gone. To-day the flower is a rose, to-morrow a lily; now it is the wild thistle on the moor, now the pouched and portentous orchid of the conservatory. So variously, so carelessly Flush embraced the spotted spaniel down the alley, and the brindled dog and the yellow dog - it did not matter which. To Flush it was all the same. He fol-lowed the horn wherever the horn blew and the wind wafted it. Love was all; love was enough. No one blamed him for his escapades. Mr Browning merely laughed - ‘Quite dis-graceful for a respectable dog like him' - when Flush returned very late at night or early the next morning. And 9780

Mrs Browning laughed too, as Flush flung himself down on the bedroom floor and slept soundly upon the arms of the Guidi family inlaid in scagliola.

For at Casa Guidi the rooms were bare. All those draped objects of his cloistered and secluded days had vanished. The bed was a bed; the wash-stand was a wash-stand. Every-thing was itself and not another thing. The drawing-room was large and sprinkled with a few old carved chairs of ebony. Over the fire hung a mirror with two cupids to hold the lights. Mrs Browning herself had discarded her Indian shawls. She wore a cap made of some thin bright silk that her husband liked. Her hair was brushed in a new way. And when the sun had gone down and the shutters had been raised she paced the balcony dressed in thin white muslin. She loved to sit there looking, listening, watching the people in the street.

They had not been long in Florence before one night there was such a shouting and trampling in the street that they ran to the balcony to see what was happening. A vast crowd was surging underneath. They were carrying banners and shouting and singing. All the windows were full of faces; all the balconies were full of figures. The people in the win-dows were tossing flowers and laurel leaves on to the people in the street; and the people in the street - grave men, gay young women - were kissing each other and raising their babies to the people in the balconies. Mr and Mrs Browning leant over the balustrade and clapped and clapped. Banner after banner passed. The torches flashed their light on them. ‘Liberty' was written on one; ‘The Union of Italy' on another; and ‘The Memory of the Martyrs' and ‘Viva Pio Nono' and ‘Viva Leopoldo Secondo' - for three and a half hours the banners went by and the people cheered and Mr and Mrs Browning stood with six candles burning on the balcony, waving and waving. For some time Flush too, stretched between them with his paws over the sill, did his best to rejoice. But at last - he could not conceal it - he yawned. ‘He confessed at last that he thought they were rather long about it', Mrs Browning observed. A weariness, a doubt, a ribaldry possessed him. What was it all for? he asked himself. Who was this Grand Duke and what had he promised? Why were they all so absurdly excited? - for the ardour of Mrs Browning, waving and waving, as the ban-ners passed, somehow annoyed him. Such enthusiasm for a Grand Duke was somehow exaggerated, he felt. And then, as the Grand Duke passed, he became aware that a little dog had stopped at the door. Seizing his chance when Mrs Browning was more than usually enthusiastic, he slipped down from the balcony and made off. Through the banners and the crowds he followed her. She fled further and further into the heart of Florence. Far away sounded the shouting; the cheers of the people died down into silence. The lights of the torches were extinguished. Only a star or two shone in the ripples of the Arno where Flush lay with the spotted spaniel by his side, couched in the shell of an old basket on the mud. There tranced in love they lay till the sun rose in the sky. Flush did not return until nine next morning, and Mrs Browning greeted him rather ironically - he might at least, she thought, have remembered that it was the first anniversary of her wedding day. But she supposed ‘he had been very much amused'. It was true. While she had found an inexplicable satisfaction in the trampling of forty thou-sand people, in the promises of Grand Dukes and the windy aspirations of banners, Flush in finitely preferred the little dog at the door.

It cannot be doubted that Mrs Browning and Flush were reaching different conclusions in their voyages of discovery - she a Grand Duke, he a spotted spaniel; - and yet the tie which bound them together was undeniably still binding. No sooner had Flush abolished ‘must' and raced free through the emerald grass of the Cascine gardens where the pheasants fluttered red and gold, than he felt a check. Once more he was thrown back on his haunches. At first it was nothing - a hint merely - only that Mrs Browning in the spring of 1849 became busy with her needle. And yet there was something in the sight that gave Flush pause. She was not used to sew. He noted that Wilson moved a bed and that she opened a drawer to put white clothes inside it. Rais-ing his head from the tiled floor, he looked, he listened attentively. Was something once more about to happen? He looked anxiously for signs of trunks and packing. Was there to be another flight, another escape? But an escape to what, from what? There is nothing to be afraid of here, he assured Mrs Browning. They need neither of them worry themselves in Florence about Mr Taylor and dogs' heads wrapped up in brown paper parcels. Yet he was puzzled. The signs of change, as he read them, did not signify escape. They sig-nified, much more mysteriously, expectance. Something, he felt, as he watched Mrs Browning so composedly, yet silently and steadfastly, stitching in her low chair, was coming that was inevitable; yet to be dreaded. As the weeks went on, Mrs Browning scarcely left the house. She seemed, as she sat there, to anticipate some tremendous event. Was she about to encounter somebody, like the ruffian Taylor, and let him rain blows on her alone and unaided? Flush quivered with apprehension at the thought. Certainly she had no intention of running away. No boxes were packed. There was no sign that anybody was about to leave the house - rather there were signs that somebody was coming. In his jealous anxiety Flush scrutinised each new-comer. There were many now - Miss Blagden, Mr Landor, Hattie Hosmer, Mr Lytton - ever so many ladies and gentlemen now came to Casa Guidi. Day after day Mrs Browning sat there in her armchair quietly stitching.

Then one day early in March Mrs Browning did not appear in the sitting-room at all. Other people came in and out; Mr Browning and Wilson came in and out; and they came in and out so distractedly that Flush hid himself under the sofa. People were trampling up and down stairs, run-ning and calling in low whispers and muted unfamiliar voices. They were moving upstairs in the bedroom. He crept further and further under the shadow of the sofa. He knew in every fibre of his body that some change was taking place - some awful event was happening. So he had waited, years ago, for the step of the hooded man on the staircase. And at last the door had opened and Miss Barrett had cried ‘Mr Browning!' Who was coming now? What hooded man? As the day wore on, he was left completely alone; nobody came into the drawing-room. He lay in the drawing-room without food or drink; a thousand spotted spaniels might have sniffed at the door and he would have shrunk away from them. For as the hours passed he had an overwhelming sense that something was thrusting its way into the house from outside. He peeped out from beneath the flounces. The cupids holding the lights, the ebony chests, the French chairs, all looked thrust asunder; he himself felt as if he were being pushed up against the wall to make room for some-thing that he could not see. Once he saw Mr Browning, but he was not the same Mr Browning; once Wilson, but she was changed too - as if they were both seeing the invisible presence that he felt. Their eyes were oddly glazed.

At last Wilson, looking very flushed and untidy but tri-umphant, took him in her arms and carried him upstairs. They entered the bedroom. There was a faint bleating in the shadowed room - something waved on the pillow. It was a live animal. Independently of them all, without the street door being opened, out of herself in the room, alone, Mrs Browning had become two people. The horrid thing waved and mewed by her side. Torn with rage and jealousy and some deep disgust that he could not hide, Flush struggled himself free and rushed downstairs. Wilson and Mrs Brown-ing called him back; they tempted him with caresses; they offered him titbits; but it was useless. He cowered away from the disgusting sight, the repulsive presence, wherever there was a shadowy sofa or a dark corner. ‘ …… for a whole fort-night he fell into deep melancholy and was proof against all attentions lavished on him' - so Mrs Browning, in the midst of all her other distractions, was forced to notice. And when we take, as we must, human minutes and hours and drop them into a dog' s mind and see how the minutes swell into hours and the hours into days, we shall not exaggerate if we conclude that Flush' s ‘deep melancholy' lasted six full months by the human clock. Many men and women have forgotten their hates and their loves in less.

But Flush was no longer the unschooled, untrained dog of Wimpole Street days. He had learnt his lesson. Wilson had struck him. He had been forced to swallow cakes that were stale when he might have eaten them fresh; he had sworn to love and not to bite. All this churned in his mind as he lay under the sofa; and at last he issued out. Again he was rewarded. At first, it must be admitted, the reward was insubstantial if not positively disagreeable. The baby was set on his back and Flush had to trot about with the baby pulling his ears. But he submitted with such grace, only turning round, when his ears were pulled, ‘to kiss the little bare, dimpled feet', that, before three months had passed, this helpless, weak, puling, muling lump had somehow come to prefer him, ‘on the whole' - so Mrs Browning said - to other people. And then, strangely enough, Flush found that he returned the baby' s affection. Did they not share some-thing in common - did not the baby somehow resemble Flush in many ways? Did they not hold the same views, the same tastes? For instance, in the matter of scenery. To Flush all scenery was insipid. He had never, all these years, learnt to focus his eyes upon mountains. When they took him to Vallombrosa all the splendours of its woods had merely bored him. Now again, when the baby was a few months old, they went on another of those long expeditions in a travelling carriage. The baby lay on his nurse' s lap; Flush sat on Mrs Browning' s knee. The carriage went on and on and on, painfully climbing the heights of the Apennines. Mrs Browning was almost beside herself with delight. She could scarcely tear herself from the window. She could not find words enough in the whole of the English language to express what she felt. ‘ …… the exquisite, almost visionary scenery of the Apennines, the wonderful variety of shape and colour, the sudden transitions and vital individuality of those mountains, the chestnut forests dropping by their own weight into the deep ravines, the rocks cloven and clawed by the living torrents, and the hills, hill above hill, piling up their grand existences as if they did it themselves, chang-ing colour in the effort' - the beauty of the Apennines brought words to birth in such numbers that they positively crushed each other out of existence. But the baby and Flush felt none of this stimulus, none of this inadequacy. Both were silent. Flush drew ‘in his head from the window and didn' t consider it worth looking at …… He has a supreme contempt for trees and hills or anything of that kind', Mrs Browning concluded. The carriage rumbled on. Flush slept and the baby slept. Then at last there were lights and houses and men and women passing the windows. They had entered a village. Instantly Flush was all attention. ‘ …… his eyes were starting out of his head with eagerness; he looked east, he looked west, you would conclude that he was taking notes or preparing them.' It was the human scene that stirred him. Beauty, so it seems at least, had to be crystallised into a green or violet powder and puffed by some celestial syringe down the fringed channels that lay behind his nostrils before it touched Flush' s senses; and then it issued not in words, but in a silent rapture. Where Mrs Browning saw, he smelt; where she wrote, he snuffed.

Here, then, the biographer must perforce come to a pause Where two or three thousand words are insufficient for wha we see - and Mrs Browning had to admit herself beaten by the Apennines: ‘Of these things I cannot give you any idea' she admitted - there are no more than two words and one-half for what we smell. The human nose is practically non-existent. The greatest poets in the world have smel nothing but roses on the one hand, and dung on the other. The in finite gradations that lie between are unrecorded. Ye it was in the world of smell that Flush mostly lived. Love was chiefly smell; form and colour were smell; music and architecture, law, politics and science were smell. To him religion itself was smell. To describe his simplest experienc with the daily chop or biscuit is beyond our power. Not even Mr Swinburne could have said what the smell of Wimpol Street meant to Flush on a hot afternoon in June. As fo describing the smell of a spaniel mixed with the smell o torches, laurels, incense, banners, wax candles and a gar land of rose leaves crushed by a satin heel that has been laid up in camphor, perhaps Shakespeare, had he paused in th middle of writing Antony and Cleopatra - But Shakespeare did not pause. Confessing our inadequacy, then, we can but note that to Flush Italy, in these the fullest, the freest, the happiest years of his life, meant mainly a succession of smells. Love, it must be supposed, was gradually losing its appeal. Smell remained. Now that they were established in Casa Guidi again, all had their avocations. Mr Browning wrote regularly in one room; Mrs Browning wrote regularly in another. The baby played in the nursery. But Flush wan-dered off into the streets of Florence to enjoy the rapture of smell. He threaded his path through main streets and back streets, through squares and alleys, by smell. He nosed his way from smell to smell; the rough, the smooth, the dark, the golden. He went in and out, up and down, where they beat brass, where they bake bread, where the women sit combing their hair, where the bird-cages are piled high on the causeway, where the wine spills itself in dark red stains on the pavement, where leather smells and harness and gar-lic, where cloth is beaten, where vine leaves tremble, where men sit and drink and spit and dice - he ran in and out, always with his nose to the ground, drinking in the essence; or with his nose in the air vibrating with the aroma. He slept in this hot patch of sun-how sun made the stone reek! he sought that tunnel of shade - how acid shade made the stone smell! He devoured whole bunches of ripe grapes largely because of their purple smell; he chewed and spat out what-ever tough relic of goat or macaroni the Italian housewife had thrown from the balcony - goat and macaroni were raucous smells, crimson smells. He followed the swoon-ing sweetness of incense into the violet intricacies of dark cathedrals; and, sniffing, tried to lap the gold on the window-stained tomb. Nor was his sense of touch much less acute. He knew Florence in its marmoreal smoothness and in its gritty and cobbled roughness. Hoary folds of drapery, smooth fingers and feet of stone received the lick of his tongue, the quiver of his shivering snout. Upon the infinitely sensitive pads of his feet he took the clear stamp of proud Latin inscriptions. In short, he knew Florence as no human being has ever known it; as Ruskin never knew it or George Eliot either. He knew it as only the dumb know. Not a singleone of his myriad sensations ever submitted itself to the deformity of words.

But though it would be pleasant for the biographer to infer that Flush's life in late middle age was an orgy of pleas-ure transcending all description; to maintain that while the baby day by day picked up a new word and thus removed sensation a little further beyond reach, Flush was fated to remain for ever in a Paradise where essences exist in their utmost purity, and the naked soul of things presses on the naked nerve - it would not be true. Flush lived in no such Paradise. The spirit, ranging from star to star, the bird whose furthest flight over polar snows or tropical forests never brings it within sight of human houses and their curl-ing wood-smoke, may, for anything we know, enjoy such immunity, such integrity of bliss. But Flush had lain upon human knees and heard men' s voices. His flesh was veined with human passions; he knew all grades of jealousy, anger and despair. Now in summer he was scourged by fleas. With a cruel irony the sun that ripened the grapes brought also the fleas. ‘ …… Savonarola' s martyrdom here in Florence', wrote Mrs Browning, ‘is scarcely worse than Flush' s in the summer.' Fleas leapt to life in every corner of the Florentine houses; they skipped and hopped out of every cranny of the old stone; out of every fold of old tapestry; out of every cloak, hat and blanket. They nested in Flush' s fur. They bit their way into the thickest of his coat. He scratched and tore. His health suffered; he became morose, thin and feverish. Miss Mitford was appealed to. What remedy was there, Mrs Browning wrote anxiously, for fleas? Miss Mit-ford, still sitting in her greenhouse at Three Mile Cross, still writing tragedies, put down her pen and looked up her old prescriptions - what May flower had taken, what Rosebud. But the fleas of Reading die at a pinch. The fleas of Florence are red and virile. To them Miss Mitford' s powders might well have been snuff. In despair Mr and Mrs Browning went down on their knees beside a pail of water and did their best to exorcise the pest with soap and scrubbing-brush. It was in vain. At last one day Mr Browning, taking Flush for a walk, noticed that people pointed; he heard a man lay a finger to his nose and whisper ‘La rogna' (mange) .As by this time ‘Robert is as fond of Flush as I am', to take his walk of an afternoon with a friend and to hear him thus stigmatised was intolerable. Robert, his wife wrote, ‘wouldn' t bear it any longer'. Only one remedy remained, but it was a remedy that was almost as drastic as the dis-ease itself. However democratic Flush had become and careless of the signs of rank, he still remained what Philip Sidney had called him, a gentleman by birth. He carried his pedigree on his back. His coat meant to him what a gold watch inscribed with the family arms means to an impover-ished squire whose broad acres have shrunk to that single circle. It was the coat that Mr Browning now proposed to sacrifice. He called Flush to him and, ‘taking a pair of scis-sors, clipped him all over into the likeness of a lion'.

As Robert Browning snipped, as the insignia of a cocker spaniel fell to the floor, as the travesty of quite a different animal rose round his neck, Flush felt himself emasculated, diminished, ashamed. What am I now? he thought, gazing into the glass. And the glass replied with the brutal sincerity of glasses, ‘You are nothing'. He was nobody. Certainly he was no longer a cocker spaniel. But as he gazed, his ears bald now, and uncurled, seemed to twitch. It was as if the potent spirits of truth and laughter were whispering in them. To be nothing - is that not, after all, the most satis-factory state in the whole world? He looked again. There was his ruff. To caricature the pomposity of those who claim that they are something - was that not in its way a career? Anyhow, settle the matter as he might, there could be no doubt that he was free from fleas. He shook his ruff. He danced on his nude, attenuated legs. His spirits rose. So might a great beauty, rising from a bed of sickness and find-ing her face eternally disfigured, make a bonfire of clothes and cosmetics, and laugh with joy to think that she need never look in the glass again or dread a lover' s coolness or a rival' s beauty. So might a clergyman, cased for twenty years in starch and broadcloth, cast his collar into the dust-bin and snatch the works of Voltaire from the cupboard. So Flush scampered off clipped all over into the likeness of a lion, but free from fleas. ‘Flush', Mrs Browning wrote to her sister, ‘is wise.' She was thinking perhaps of the Greeks saying that happiness is only to be reached through suffer-ing. The true philosopher is he who has lost his coat but is free from fleas.

But Flush had not long to wait before his newly won phil-osophy was put to the test. Again in the summer of 1852 there were signs at Casa Guidi of one of those crises which, gath-ering soundlessly as a drawer opens or as a piece of string is left dangling from a box, are to a dog as menacing as the clouds which foretell lightning to a shepherd or as the rumours which foretell war to a statesman. Another change was indicated, another journey. Well, what of that? Trunks were hauled down and corded. The baby was carried out in his nurse' s arms. Mr and Mrs Browning appeared, dressed for travelling. There was a cab at the door. Flush waited philosophically in the hall. When they were ready he was ready. Now that they were all seated in the carriage, with one bound Flush sprang lightly in after them. To Venice, to Rome, to Paris - where were they going? All countries were equal to him now; all men were his brothers. He had learnt that lesson for himself. But when finally he emerged from obscurity he had need of all his philosophy - he was in London.

Houses spread to right and left in sharp avenues of regu-lar brick. The pavement was cold and hard beneath his feet. And there, issuing from a mahogany door with a brass knocker, was a lady bountifully apparelled in flowing robes of purple plush. A light wreath starred with flowers rested on her hair. Gathering her draperies about her, she glanced disdainfully up and down the street while a footman, stoop-ing, let down the step of the barouche landau. All Welbeck Street - for Welbeck Street it was - was wrapped in a splen-dour of red light - a light not clear and fierce like the Italian light, but tawny and troubled with the dust of a million wheels, with the trampling of a million hooves. The London season was at its height. A pall of sound, a cloud of inter-woven humming, fell over the city in one confluent growl. By came a majestic deer-hound led on a chain by a page. A policeman, swinging past with rhythmical stride, cast his bull' s-eye from side to side. Odours of stew, odours of beef, odours of basting, odours of beef and cabbage rose from a thousand basements. A flunkey in livery dropped a letter into a box.

Overcome by the magnificence of the metropolis, Flush paused for a moment with his foot on the door-step. Wilson paused too. How paltry it seemed now, the civilisation of Italy, its Courts and its revolutions, its Grand Dukes and their bodyguards! She thanked God, as the policeman passed, that she had not married Signor Righi after all. And then a sinisterfigure issued from the public-house at the corner. A man leered. With one spring Flush bolted indoors.

For some weeks now he was closely confined to a lodging-house sitting-room in Welbeck Street. For confine-ment was still necessary. The cholera had come, and it is true that the cholera had done something to improve the condition of the Rookeries; but not enough, for still dogs were stolen and the dogs of Wimpole Street had still to be led on chains. Flush went into society, of course. He met dogs at the pillar-box and outside the public-house; they welcomed him back with the inherent good breeding of their kind. Just as an English peer who has lived a lifetime in the East and contracted some of the habits of the natives - rumour hints indeed that he has turned Moslem and had a son by a Chinese washerwoman - finds, when he takes his place at Court, that old friends are ready enough to overlook these aberrations and he is asked to Chatsworth, though no mention is made of his wife and it is taken for granted that he will join the family at prayers - so the pointers and setters of Wimpole Street welcomed Flush among them and over-looked the condition of his coat. But there was a certain morbidity, it seemed to Flush now, among the dogs of London. It was common knowledge that Mrs Carlyle' s dog Nero had leapt from a top storey window with the intention of committing suicide. He had found the strain of life in Cheyne Row intolerable, it was said. Indeed Flush could well believe it now that he was back again in Welbeck Street. The confinement, the crowd of little objects, the blackbeetles by night, the bluebottles by day, the lingering odours of mutton, the perpetual presence on the sideboard of bananas - all this, together with the proximity of several men and women, heavily dressed and not often or indeed completely washed, wrought on his temper and strained his nerves. He lay for hours under the lodging-house chiffonier. It was impossible to run out of doors. The front door was always locked. He had to wait for somebody to lead him on a chain.

Two incidents alone broke the monotony of the weeks he spent in London. One day late that summer the Brownings went to visit the Rev. Charles Kingsley at Farnham. In Italy the earth would have been bare and hard as brick. Fleas would have been rampant. Languidly one would have dragged oneself from shadow to shadow, grateful even for the bar of shade cast by the raised arm of one of Donatello's statues. But here at Farnham there were fields of green grass; there were pools of blue water; there were woods that murmured, and turf so fine that the paws bounced as they touched it. The Brownings and the Kingsleys spent the day together. And once more, as Flush trotted behind them, the old trumpets blew; the old ecstasy returned - was it hare or was it fox? Flush tore over the heaths of Surrey as he had not run since the old days at Three Mile Cross. A pheasant went rocketing up in a spurt of purple and gold. He had almost shut his teeth on the tail feathers when a voice rang out. A whip cracked. Was it the Rev. Charles Kingsley who called him sharply to heel? At any rate he ran no more. The woods of Farnham were strictly preserved.

A few days later he was lying in the sitting-room at Welbeck Street, when Mrs Browning came in dressed for walking and called him from under the chiffonier. She slipped the chain on to his collar and, for the first time since September 1846,they walked up Wimpole Street together. When they came to the door of No.50 they stopped as of old. Just as of old they waited. The butler just as of old was very slow in coming. At length the door opened. Could that be Catiline lying couched on the mat? The old toothless dog yawned and stretched himself and took no notice. Upstairs they crept as stealthily, as silently as once before they had come down. Very quietly, opening the doors as if she were afraid of what she might see there, Mrs Browning went from room to room. A gloom descended upon her as she looked. ‘ …… they seemed to me', she wrote, ‘smaller and darker, somehow, and the furniture wanted fitness and conveni-ence.' The ivy was still tapping on the back bedroom window-pane. The painted blind still obscured the houses. Nothing had been changed. Nothing had happened all these years. So she went from room to room, sadly remem-bering. But long before she had finished her inspection, Flush was in a fever of anxiety. Suppose Mr Barrett were to come in and find them? Suppose that with one frown he turned the key and locked them in the back bedroom for ever? At last Mrs Browning shut the doors and went downstairs again very quietly. Yes, she said, it seemed to her that the house wanted cleaning.

After that, Flush had only one wish left in him - to leave London, to leave England for ever. He was not happy until he found himself on the deck of the Channel steamer cross-ing to France. It was a rough passage. The crossing took eight hours. As the steamer tossed and wallowed, Flush turned over in his mind a tumult of mixed memories - of ladies in purple plush, of ragged men with bags; of Regent' s Park, and Queen Victoria sweeping past with outriders; of the greenness of English grass and the rankness of English pavements - all this passed through his mind as he lay on deck; and, looking up, he caught sight of a stern, tall man leaning over the rail.

‘Mr Carlyle!' he heard Mrs Browning exclaim; whereupon - the crossing, it must be remembered, was a bad one - Flush was violently sick. Sailors came running with pails and mops. ‘ …… he was ordered off the deck on purpose, poor dog', said Mrs Browning. For the deck was still English; dogs must not be sick on decks. Such was his last salute to the shores of his native land.

Chapter 6　THE END

Flush was growing an old dog now. The journey to England and all the memories it revived had undoubtedly tired him. It was noticed that he sought the shade rather than the sun on his return, though the shade of Florence was hotter than the sun of Wimpole Street. Stretched beneath a statue, couched under the lip of a fountain for the sake of the few drops that spurted now and again on to his coat, he would lie dozing by the hour. The young dogs would come about him. To them he would tell his stories of Whitechapel and Wimpole Street; he would describe the smell of clover and the smell of Oxford Street; he would rehearse his memories of one revolution and another - how Grand Dukes had come and Grand Dukes had gone; but the spotted spaniel down the alley on the left - she goes on for ever, he would say. Then violent Mr Landor would hurry by and shake his fist at him in mock fury; kind Miss Isa Blagden would pause and take a sugared biscuit from her reticule. The peasant women in the market-place made him a bed of leaves in the shadow of their baskets and tossed him a bunch of grapes now and then. He was known, he was liked by all Florence - gentle and simple, dogs and men.

But he was growing an old dog now, and he tended more and more to lie not even under the fountain - for the cobbles were too hard for his old bones - but in Mrs Browning's bedroom where the arms of the Guidi family made a smooth patch of scagliola on the floor, or in the drawing-room under the shadow of the drawing-room table. One day shortly after his return from London he was stretched there fast asleep. The deep and dreamless sleep of old age was heavy on him. Indeed to-day his sleep was deeper even than usual, for as he slept the darkness seemed to thicken round him. If he dreamt at all, he dreamt that he was sleeping in the heart of a primeval forest, shut from the light of the sun, shut from the voices of mankind, though now and again as he slept he dreamt that he heard the sleepy chirp of a dreaming bird, or, as the wind tossed the branches, the mellow chuckle of a brooding monkey.

Then suddenly the branches parted; the light broke in - here, there, in dazzling shafts. Monkeys chattered; birds rose crying and calling in alarm. He started to his feet wide awake. An astonishing commotion was all round him. He had fallen asleep between the bare legs of an ordin-ary drawing-room table. Now he was hemmed in by the billowing of skirts and the heaving of trousers. The table itself, moreover, was swaying violently from side to side. He did not know which way to run. What on earth was happening? What in Heaven' s name possessed the drawing-room table? He lifted up his voice in a prolonged howl of interrogation.

To Flush's question no satisfactory answer can here be given. A few facts, and those of the baldest, are all that can be supplied. Briefly, then, it would appear that early in the nineteenth century the Countess of Blessington had bought a crystal ball from a magician. Her Ladyship ‘never could understand the use of it'; indeed she had never been able to see anything in the ball except crystal. After her death, how-ever, there was a sale of her effects and the ball came into the possession of others who ‘looked deeper, or with purer eyes', and saw other things in the ball besides crystal. Whether Lord Stanhope was the purchaser, whether it was he who looked ‘with purer eyes', is not stated. But certainly by the year 1852 Lord Stanhope was in possession of a crys-tal ball and Lord Stanhope had only to look into it to see among other things ‘the spirits of the sun'. Obviously this was not a sight that a hospitable nobleman could keep to himself, and Lord Stanhope was in the habit of displaying his ball at luncheon parties and of inviting his friends to see the spirits of the sun also. There was something strangely delightful - except indeed to Mr Chorley - in the spec - tacle; balls became the rage; and luckily a London optician soon discovered that he could make them, without being either an Egyptian or a magician, though naturally the price of English crystal was high. Thus many people in the early' fifties became possessed of balls, though ‘many persons', Lord Stanhope said, ‘use the balls, without the moral courage to confess it'. The prevalence of spirits in London indeed became so marked that some alarm was felt; and Lord Stanley suggested to Sir Edward Lytton ‘that the Government should appoint a committee of investiga-tion so as to get as far as possible at the facts'. Whether the rumour of an approaching Government committee alarmed the spirits, or whether spirits, like bodies, tend to multiply in close confinement, there can be no doubt that the spirits began to show signs of restlessness, and, escaping in vast numbers, took up their residence in the legs of tables. What-ever the motive, the policy was successful. Crystal balls were expensive; almost everybody owns a table. Thus when Mrs Browning returned to Italy in the winter of 1852 she found that the spirits had preceded her; the tables of Florence were almost universally infected. ‘From the Legation to the Eng-lish chemists', she wrote, ‘people are "serving tables" …… everywhere. When people gather round a table it isn' t to play whist.' No, it was to decipher messages conveyed by the legs of tables. Thus if asked the age of a child, the table ‘expresses itself intelligently by knocking with its legs, responses according to the alphabet'. And if a table could tell you that your own child was four years old, what limit was there to its capacity? Spinning tables were advertised in shops. The walls were placarded with advertisements of wonders ‘scoperte a Livorno'. By the year 1854,so rapidly did the movement spread, ‘four hundred thousand families in America had given their names …… as actually in enjoyment of spiritual intercourse'. And from England the news came that Sir Edward Bulwer Lytton had imported ‘several of the American rapping spirits' to Knebworth, with the happy result - so little Arthur Russell was informed when he beheld a ‘strange-looking old gentleman in a shabby dressing-gown' staring at him at breakfast - that Sir Edward Bulwer Lytton believed himself invisible.

When Mrs Browning first looked into Lord Stanhope' s crystal ball at a luncheon party she saw nothing - except indeed that it was a remarkable sign of the times. The spirit of the sun indeed told her that she was about to go to Rome; but as she was not about to go to Rome, she contradicted the spirits of the sun. ‘But', she added, with truth, ‘I love the marvellous.' She was nothing if not adventurous. She had gone to Manning Street at the risk of her life. She had discovered a world that she had never dreamt of within half an hour' s drive from Wimpole Street. Why should there not be another world only half a moment' s flight from Florence - a better world, a more beautiful world, where the dead live, trying in vain to reach us? At any rate she would take the risk. And so she sat herself down at the table too. And Mr Lytton, the brilliant son of an invis-ible father, came; and Mr Frederick Tennyson, and Mr Powers and M. Villari - they all sat at the table, and then when the table had done kicking, they sat on drinking tea and eating strawberries and cream, with ‘Florence dissolv-ing in the purple of the hills and the stars looking on', talking and talking: ‘ …… what stories we told, and what miracles we swore to! Oh, we are believers here, Isa, except Robert …… ' Then in burst deaf Mr Kirkup with his bleak white beard. He had come round simply to exclaim, ‘There is a spiritual world - there is a future state. I confess it. I am convinced at last.' And when Mr Kirkup, whose creed had always been ‘the next thing to atheism', was converted merely because, in spite of his deafness, he had heard ‘three taps so loud that they made him leap', how could Mrs Browning keep her hands off the table? ‘You know I am rather a visionary and inclined to knock round at all the doors of the present world to try to get out', she wrote. So she summoned the faithful to Casa Guidi; and there they sat with their hands on the drawing-room table, trying to get out.

Flush started up in the wildest apprehension. The skirts and the trousers were billowing round him; the table was standing on one leg. But whatever the ladies and gentlemen round the table could hear and see, Flush could hear and see nothing. True, the table was standing on one leg, but so tables will if you lean hard on one side. He had upset tables himself and been well scolded for it. But now there was Mrs Browning with her great eyes wide open staring as if she saw something marvellous outside. Flush rushed to the bal-cony and looked over. Was there another Grand Duke riding by with banners and torches? Flush could see nothing but an old beggar woman crouched at the corner of the street over her basket of melons. Yet clearly Mrs Browning saw something; clearly she saw something that was very wonderful. So in the old Wimpole Street days she had wept once without any reason that he could see; and again she had laughed, holding up a blotted scrawl. But this was different. There was something in her look now that fright-ened him. There was something in the room, or in the table, or in the petticoats and trousers, that he disliked exceedingly.

As the weeks passed, this preoccupation of Mrs Brown-ing's with the invisible grew upon her. It might be a fine hot day, but instead of watching the lizards slide in and out of the stones, she would sit at the table; it might be a dark starry night, but instead of reading in her book, or passing her hand over paper, she would call, if Mr Browning were out, for Wilson, and Wilson would come yawning. Then they would sit at the table together until that article of furniture, whose chief function it was to provide shade, kicked on the floor, and Mrs Browning exclaimed that it was telling Wil-son that she would soon be ill. Wilson replied that she was only sleepy. But soon Wilson herself, the implacable, the upright, the British, screamed and went into a faint, and Mrs Browning was rushing hither and thither to find ‘the hygienic vinegar'. That, to Flush, was a highly unpleasant way of spending a quiet evening. Better far to sit and read one' s book.

Undoubtedly the suspense, the intangible but disagree-able odour, the kicks and the screams and the vinegar, told upon Flush's nerves. It was all very well for the baby, Penini, to pray ‘that Flush's hair may grow';that was an aspiration that Flush could understand. But this form of prayer which required the presence of evil-smelling, seedy-looking men and the antics of a piece of apparently solid mahogany, angered him much as they angered that robust, sensible, well-dressed man, his master. But far worse than any smell to Flush, far worse than any antics, was the look on Mrs Browning's face when she gazed out of the window as if she were seeing something that was wonderful when there was nothing. Flush stood himself in front of her. She looked through him as if he were not there. That was the cruellest look she had ever given him. It was worse than her cold anger when he bit Mr Browning in the leg; worse than her sardonic laughter when the door shut upon his paw in Regent' s Park. There were moments indeed when he regret-ted Wimpole Street and its tables. The tables at No.50 had never tilted upon one leg. The little table with the ring round it that held her precious ornaments had always stood perfectly still. In those far-off days he had only to leap on her sofa and Miss Barrett started wide-awake and looked at him. Now, once more, he leapt on to her sofa. But she did not notice him. She was writing. She paid no atten-tion to him. She went on writing - ‘also, at the request of the medium, the spiritual hands took from the table a garland which lay there, and placed it upon my head. The particular hand which did this was of the largest human size, as white as snow, and very beautiful. It was as near to me as this hand I write with, and I saw it as distinctly.' Flush pawed her sharply. She looked through him as if he were invisible. He leapt off the sofa and ran downstairs into the street.

It was a blazing hot afternoon. The old beggar woman at the corner had fallen asleep over her melons. The sun seemed droning in the sky. Keeping to the shady side of the street, Flush trotted along the well-known ways to the market-place. The whole square was brilliant with awnings and stalls and bright umbrellas. The market women were sitting beside baskets of fruit; pigeons were fluttering, bells were pealing, whips were cracking. The many-coloured mon-grels of Florence were running in and out sniffing and pawing. All was as brisk as a bee-hive and as hot as an oven. Flush sought the shade. He flung himself down beside his friend Catterina, under the shadow of her great basket. A brown jar of red and yellow flowers cast a shadow beside it. Above them a statue, holding his right arm outstretched, deepened the shade to violet. Flush lay there in the cool, watching the young dogs busy with their own affairs. They were snarling and biting, stretching and tumbling, in all the abandonment of youthful joy. They were chasing each other in and out, round and round, as he had once chased the spotted spaniel in the alley. His thoughts turned to Read-ing for a moment - to Mr Partridge' s spaniel, to his first love, to the ecstasies, the innocences of youth. Well, he had had his day. He did not grudge them theirs. He had found the world a pleasant place to live in. He had no quarrel with it now. The market woman scratched him behind the ear. She had often cuffed him for stealing a grape, or for some other misdemeanour; but he was old now; and she was old. He guarded her melons and she scratched his ear. So she knitted and he dozed. The flies buzzed on the great pink melon that had been sliced open to show its flesh.

The sun burnt deliciously through the lily leaves, and through the green and white umbrella. The marble statue tempered its heat to a champagne freshness. Flush lay and let it burn through his fur to the naked skin. And when he was roasted on one side he turned over and let the sun roast the other. All the time the market people were chattering and bargaining; market women were passing; they were stopping and fingering the vegetables and the fruit. There was a perpetual buzz and hum of human voices such as Flush loved to listen to. After a time he drowsed off under the shadow of the lilies. He slept as dogs sleep when they are dreaming. Now his legs twitched - was he dreaming that he hunted rabbits in Spain? Was he coursing up a hot hill-side with dark men shouting ‘Span! Span!' as the rabbits darted from the brushwood? Then he lay still again. And now he yelped, quickly, softly, many times in succession. Perhaps he heard Dr Mitford egging his greyhounds on to the hunt at Reading. Then his tail wagged sheepishly. Did he hear old Miss Mitford cry ‘Bad dog! Bad dog!' as he slunk back to her, where she stood among the turnips wav-ing her umbrella? And then he lay for a time snoring, wrapt in the deep sleep of happy old age. Suddenly every muscle in his body twitched. He woke with a violent start. Where did he think he was? In Whitechapel among the ruffians? Was the knife at his throat again?

Whatever it was, he woke from his dream in a state of

terror. He made off as if he were flying to safety, as if he were seeking refuge. The market women laughed and pelted him with rotten grapes and called him back. He took no notice. Cart-wheels almost crushed him as he darted through the streets - the men standing up to drive cursed him and flicked him with their whips. Half-naked children threw pebbles at him and shouted ‘Matta! Matta!' as he fled past. Their mothers ran to the door and caught them back in alarm. Had he then gone mad? Had the sun turned his brain? Or had he once more heard the hunting horn of Venus? Or had one of the American rapping spirits, one of the spirits that live in table legs, got possession of him at last? Whatever it was, he went in a bee-line up one street and down another until he reached the door of Casa Guidi. He made his way straight upstairs and went straight into the drawing-room.

Mrs Browning was lying, reading, on the sofa. She looked up, startled, as he came in. No, it was not a spirit - it was only Flush. She laughed. Then, as he leapt on to the sofa and thrust his face into hers, the words of her own poem came into her mind:

You see this dog. It was but yesterday

I mused forgetful of his presence here

Till thought on thought drew downward tear on tear,

When from the pillow, where wet-cheeked I lay,

A head as hairy as Faunus, thrust its way

Right sudden against my face, - two golden-clear

Great eyes astonished mine, - a drooping ear

Did flap me on either cheek to dry the spray!

I started first, as some Arcadian,

Amazed by goatly god in twilight grove;

But, as the bearded vision closelier ran

My tears off,I knew Flush, and rose above

Surprise and sadness,-thanking the true Pan,

Who, by low creatures, leads to heights of love.

She had written that poem one day years ago in Wimpole Street when she was very unhappy. Now she was happy. She was growing old now and so was Flush. She bent down over him for a moment. Her face with its wide mouth and its great eyes and its heavy curls was still oddly like his. Broken asunder, yet made in the same mould, each, perhaps, com-pleted what was dormant in the other. But she was woman; he was dog. Mrs Browning went on reading. Then she looked at Flush again. But he did not look at her. An extra-ordinary change had come over him. ‘Flush!' she cried. But he was silent. He had been alive; he was now dead. That was all. The drawing-room table, strangely enough, stood perfectly still.

Notes

P. 13. ‘painted fabric'.Miss Barrett says, ‘I had a transparent blind put up in my open window'.She adds, ‘papa insults me with the analogy of a back window in a confectioner's shop, but is obviously moved when the sunshine lights up the castle, notwithstanding'.Some hold that the castle, etc.,was painted on a thin metallic sub-stance; others that it was a muslin blind richly embroidered. There seems no certain way of settling the matter.

P. 26. ‘Mr Kenyon mumbled slightly because he had lost two front teeth.'There are elements of exaggeration and conjecture here. Miss Mitford is the authority. She is reported to have said in conversation with Mr Horne, ‘Our dear friend, you are aware, never sees anybody but the members of her own family, and one or two others. She has a high opinion of the skill in reading as well as the fine taste, of Mr -, and she gets him to read her new poems aloud to her …… So Mr - stands upon the hearth-rug, and uplifts the MS, and his voice, while our dear friend lies folded up in Indian shawls upon her sofa, with her long black tresses streaming over her bent-down head, all attention. Now, dear Mr - has lost a front tooth - not quite a front one, but a side front one-and this, you see, causes a defective utterance …… an amiable indistinctness, a vague softening of syllables into each other, so that silence and ilence would really sound very like one another …… ' There can be little doubt that Mr - was Mr Kenyon; the blank was necessitated by the peculiar delicacy of the Victorians with regard to teeth. But more important questions affecting English literature are involved. Miss Barrett has long been accused of a defective ear. Miss Mitford maintains that Mr Kenyon should rather be accused of defective teeth. On the other hand, Miss Barrett herself maintained that her rhymes had nothing to do with his lack of teeth or with her lack of ear. ‘A great deal of attention', she wrote, ‘- far more than it would have taken to rhyme with complete accuracy - have I given to the subject of rhymes and have determined in cold blood to hazard some experiments.' Hence she rhymed ‘angels' with ‘candles', ‘heaven' with ‘unbelieving', and ‘islands' with ‘silence' -in cold blood. It is of course for the professors to decide; but anybody who has studied Mrs Browning' s character and her actions will be inclined to take the view that she was a wilful breaker of rules whether of art or of love, and so to convict her of some complicity in the development of modern poetry.

P. 35. ‘yellow gloves'.It is recorded in Mrs Orr's Life of Brown-ing that he wore lemon-coloured gloves. Mrs Bridell-Fox, meeting him in 1835-6, says, ‘he was then slim and dark, and very hand-some, and-may I hint it - just a trifle of a dandy, addicted to lemon-coloured kid gloves and such things'.

P. 48. ‘He was stolen.'As a matter of fact, Flush was stolen three times; but the unities seem to require that the three stealings shall be compressed into one. The total sum paid by Miss Barrett to the dog-stealers was£20.

P. 63. ‘The faces of those men were to come back to her on a sunny balcony in Italy.' Readers of Aurora Leigh - but since such persons are non-existent it must be explained that Mrs Browning wrote a poem of this name, one of the most vivid passages in which (though it suffers from distortion natural to an artist who sees the object once only from a four-wheeler, with Wilson tugging at her skirts) is the description of a London slum. Clearly Mrs Browning possessed a fund of curiosity as to human life which was by no means satisfied by the busts of Homer and Chaucer on the washing-stand in the bedroom.

P. 76. ‘Lily Wilson fell in love with Signor Righi, the guards-man.'The life of Lily Wilson is extremely obscure and thus criesaloud for the services of a biographer. No human figure in the Browning letters, save the principals, more excites our curiosity and baffles it. Her Christian name was Lily, her surname Wilson. That is all we know of her birth and upbringing. Whether she was the daughter of a farmer in the neighbourhood of Hope End, and became favourably known to the Barrett cook by the decency of her demeanour and the cleanliness of her apron, so much so that when she came up to the great house on some errand, Mrs Barrett made an excuse to come into the room just then and thought so well of her that she appointed her to be Miss Elizabeth' s maid; or whether she was a Cockney; or whether she was from Scotland - it is impossible to say. At any rate she was in service with Miss Barrett in the year 1846.She was ‘an expensive servant' - her wages were£16 a year. Since she spoke almost as seldom as Flush, the outlines of her character are little known; and since Miss Barrett never wrote a poem about her, her appearance is far less familiar than his. Yet it is clear from indications in the letters that she was in the beginning one of those demure, almost inhumanly correct British maids who were at that time the glory of the British basement. It is obvious that Wilson was a stickler for rights and ceremonies. Wilson undoubtedly revered ‘the room'; Wilson would have been the first to insist that under servants must eat their pudding in one place, upper servants in another. All this is implicit in the remark she made when she beat Flush with her hand ‘because it is right'. Such respect for convention, it need hardly be said, breeds extreme horror of any breach of it; so that when Wilson was confronted with the lower orders in Manning Street she was far more alarmed, and far more certain that the dog-stealers were murderers, than Miss Barrett was. At the same time the heroic way in which she overcame her terror and went with Miss Barrett in the cab shows how deeply the other convention of loyalty to her mistress was ingrained in her. Where Miss Barrett went, Wilson must go too. This principle was triumphantly demonstrated by her conduct at the time of the elopement. Miss Barrett had been doubtful of Wil-son' s courage; but her doubts were unfounded. ‘Wilson', she wrote - and these were the last words she ever wrote to Mr Brown-ing as Miss Barrett - ‘has been perfect to me. And I …… calling her "timid" and afraid of her timidity! I begin to think that none are so bold as the timid, when they are fairly roused.' It is worth, par-enthetically, dwelling for a second on the extreme precariousness of a servant' s life. If Wilson had not gone with Miss Barrett, she would have been, as Miss Barrett knew, ‘turned into the street before sunset', with only a few shillings, presumably, saved from her sixteen pounds a year. And what then would have been her fate? Since English fiction in the' forties scarcely deals with the lives of ladies' maids, and biography had not then cast its search-light so low, the question must remain a question. But Wilson took the plunge. She declared that she would ‘go anywhere in the world with me'. She left the basement, the room, the whole of that world of Wimpole Street, which to Wilson meant all civilisation, all right thinking and decent living, for the wild debauchery and irreligion of a foreign land. Nothing is more curious than to observe the conflict that took place in Italy between Wilson' s English gentility and her natural passions. She derided the Italian Court; she was shocked by Italian pictures. But, though ‘she was struck back by the indecency of the Venus', Wilson, greatly to her credit, seems to have bethought her that women are naked when they take their clothes off. Even I myself, she may have thought, am naked for two or three seconds daily. And so ‘She thinks she shall try again, and the troublesome modesty may subside, who knows?' That it did subside rapidly is plain. Soon she not merely approved of Italy; she had fallen in love with Signor Righi of the Grand Ducal body-guard- ‘all highly respectable and moral men, and some six feet high' -was wearing an engagement ring; was dismissing a London suitor; and was learning to speak Italian. Then the clouds descend again; when they lift they show us Wilson deserted - ‘the faithless Righi had backed out of his engagement to Wilson'. Suspicion attaches to his brother, a wholesale haberdasher at Prato. When Righi resigned from the Ducal bodyguard, he became, on his brother' s advice, a retail haberdasher at Prato. Whether his position required a knowledge of haberdashery in his wife, whether one of the girls of Prato could supply it, it is certain that he did not write to Wilson as often as he should have done. But what conduct it was on the part of this highly respectable and moral man that led Mrs Browning to exclaim in 1850, ‘[Wilson]is over it completely, which does the greatest credit to her good sense and rectitude of charac-ter. How could she continue to love such a man?' - why Righi had shrunk to ‘such a man' in so short a time, it is impossible to say. Deserted by Righi, Wilson became more and more attached to the Browning family. She discharged not only the duties of a lady' s maid, but cooked knead cakes, made dresses, and became a devoted nurse to Penini, the baby; so that in time the baby himself exalted her to the rank of the family, where she justly belonged, and refused to call her anything but Lily. In 1855 Wilson married Romagnoli, the Brownings' manservant, ‘a good tender-hearted man'; and for some time the two kept house for the Brownings. But in 1859 Robert Browning ‘accepted office as Landor' s guardian', an office of great delicacy and responsibility, for Landor' s habits were difficult; ‘of restraint he has not a grain', Mrs Browning wrote, ‘and of suspiciousness many grains'. In these circumstances Wilson was appointed ‘his duenna' with a salary of twenty-two pounds a year ‘besides what is left of his rations'. Later her wages were increased to thirty pounds, for to act as duenna to ‘an old lion' who has ‘the impulses of a tiger', throws his plate out of the window or dashes it on the ground if he dislikes his dinner, and suspects servants of opening desks, entailed, as Mrs Browning observed, ‘certain risks, and I for one would rather not meet them'. But to Wilson, who had known Mr Barrett and the spirits, a few plates more or less flying out of the window or dashed upon the floor was a matter of little consequence - such risks were all in the day' s work.

That day, so far as it is still visible to us, was certainly a strange one. Whether it began or not in some remote English village, it ended in Venice in the Palazzo Rezzonico. There at least she was still living in the year 1897,a widow, in the house of the little boy whom she had nursed and loved - Mr Barrett Browning. A very strange day it had been, she may have thought, as she sat in the red Venetian sunset, an old woman, dreaming. Her friends, married to farm hands, still stumbled up the English lanes to fetch a pint of beer. And she had eloped with Miss Barrett to Italy; she had seen all kinds of queer things - revolutions, guardsmen, spirits; Mr Landor throwing his plate out of the window. Then Mrs Brown-ing had died - there can have been no lack of thoughts in Wilson' s old head as she sat at the window of the Palazzo Rezzonico in the evening. But nothing can be more vain than to pretend that we can guess what they were, for she was typical of the great army of her kind - the inscrutable, the all-but-silent, the all-but-invisible ser-vant maids of history. ‘A more honest, true and affectionate heart than Wilson' s cannot be found' - her mistress' s words may serve her for epitaph.

P. 88 ‘he was scourged by fleas'. It appears that Italy was famous for its fleas in the middle of the nineteenth century. Indeed, they served to break down conventions that were otherwise insurmount-able. For example, when Nathaniel Hawthorne went to tea with Miss Bremer in Rome (1858) , ‘we spoke of fleas-insects that, in Rome, come home to everybody' s business and bosom, and are so common and inevitable, that no delicacy is felt about alluding to the sufferings they inflict. Poor little Miss Bremer was tormented with one while turning out our tea …… '

P. 93. ‘Nero had leapt from a top storey window.'Nero (c.1849-60) was, according to Carlyle, ‘A little Cuban (Maltese? and otherwise mongrel) shock, mostly white - a most affectionate, lively little dog, otherwise of small merit, and little or no training'. Material for a life of him abounds, but this is not the occasion to make use of it. It is enough to say that he was stolen; that he brought Carlyle a cheque to buy a horse with tied round his neck; that ‘twice or thrice I flung him into the sea[at Aberdour],which he didn' t at all like'; that in 1850 he sprang from the library window, and, clearing the area spikes, fell ‘plash' on to the pavement. ‘It was after breakfast,' Mrs Carlyle says, ‘and he had been standing at the open window, watching the birds …… Lying in my bed, I heard thro' the deal partition Elizabeth scream: Oh God! oh Nero! and rush downstairs like a strong wind out at the street door …… then I sprang to meet her in my night-shift …… Mr C. came down from his bedroom with his chin all over soap and asked, "Has anything happened to Nero?" - "Oh, sir, he must have broken all his legs, he leapt out at your window!" - "God bless me!" said Mr C. and returned to finish his shaving.' No bones were broken, however, and he survived, to be run over by a butcher' s cart, and to die at last from the effects of the accident on 1st February 1860.He is buried at the top of the garden at Cheyne Row under a small stone tablet.

Whether he wished to kill himself, or whether, as Mrs Carlyle insinuates, he was merely jumping after birds, might be the occa-sion for an extremely interesting treatise on canine psychology. Some hold that Byron' s dog went mad in sympathy with Byron; others that Nero was driven to desperate melancholy by associating with Mr Carlyle. The whole question of dogs' relation to the spirit of the age, whether it is possible to call one dog Elizabethan, another Augustan, another Victorian, together with the influence upon dogs of the poetry and philosophy of their masters, deserves a fuller discussion than can here be given it. For the present, Nero' s motives must remain obscure.

P. 99. ‘Sir Edward Bulwer Lytton believed himself invisible.'Mrs Huth Jackson in A Victorian Childhood says: ‘Lord Arthur Russell told me, many years later, that when a small boy he was taken to Knebworth by his mother. Next morning he was in the big hall having breakfast when a strange-looking old gentleman in a shabby dressing-gown came in and walked slowly round the table staring at each of the guests in turn. He heard his mother' s neighbour whisper to her, "Do not take any notice, he thinks he is invisible" .It was Lord Lytton himself' (pp.17-18) .

P. 106. ‘he was now dead'.It is certain that Flush died; but the date and manner of his death are unknown. The only reference consists in the statement that ‘Flush lived to a good old age and is buried in the vaults of Casa Guidi'. Mrs Browning was buried in the English Cemetery at Florence, Robert Browning in Westmin-ster Abbey. Flush still lies, therefore, beneath the house in which, once upon a time, the Brownings lived.

THE END

序章　德国医生马丁·赫斯利乌斯

/

虽然受过医学和外科学的严格训练，但我却从未有过实践经验。尽管如此，我对这两门学科的研究却一直没有中断，对其一直抱有浓厚的兴趣。刚刚进入医生这一光荣的职业却旋即退出，究其原因，既非我懒惰，也不是一时心血来潮。罪魁祸首是一把解剖刀，它造成的轻微划伤却让我付出了两根手指的代价。截肢是立即进行的，更令人痛苦的是，我的健康也毁了。因为从那以后，我总是感觉不舒服，从未在同一个地方待过十二个月以上。

四处闲逛的时候，我认识了马丁·赫斯利乌斯医生。他是一个和我一样的漂泊客。和我一样，他也是一名医生。和我一样，他也热衷于自己的职业。和我不一样的是，他闲逛是出于自愿。按照我们英格兰人对富有的判断，他那个人，如果不能称之为富有的话，那么至少也达到了我们先辈常说的“宽展得很”了。我初次见到他的时候，他年纪已经挺大，差不多比我年长三十有五。

邂逅马丁·赫斯利乌斯医生，让我有一种得遇良主的感觉。他知识渊博，对病情的掌握具有一种直觉。他恰恰是一个能让我这样的年轻发烧友充满敬畏和喜悦的人。我的钦佩之情经受住了时间的考验，甚至生死离别也无法令其动摇。我确信其理由十分充分。

我担任他的医学秘书将近二十年，精心保管着他留下的大量文件，做着整理、索引和装订的工作。其间，我发现他对一些病例的治疗颇为奇怪。他以两种截然不同的文字风格写作。首先，以一个聪明的外行人的口吻，描述自己的所见所闻，按照这种叙事风格，描写那些病人，直至他们要么穿过厅门，重见天日，要么跨过黑暗之门，走向死亡；然后笔锋一转，以高超的技艺，使出浑身解数，运用天才的独创性，开始进行分析、诊断和说明的工作。

时不时会有某个病例引发我的兴趣，那种兴趣与专家的特有兴趣大不相同，是一名外行的读者觉得有趣或者恐怖的地方。我稍许做了一些修改，主要是文字上的，当然也改了名字，于是就有了下面的故事。讲述人是马丁·赫斯利乌斯医生。我是在大量的病情记录中找到这个故事的，那是大约六十四年前，他在一次英格兰之旅中记录下的。

故事与他的一位朋友——莱顿[1]的范·洛教授的一系列通信有关。这位教授并不是医生，而是一名化学家，也是一个喜欢历史、玄学和医学的人，并且还在他年轻的时候写过一出戏剧。

因此，如果这番叙述的价值不如医疗记录那么高的话，那么就必须以一种能让不懂医学的读者感兴趣的方式来写。

附在备忘录里的这些信件，似乎是在范·洛教授去世后的一八一九年寄回给赫斯利乌斯医生的。一些信件是用英语写的，一些是用法语写的，但是大多数用的都是德语。虽然我意识到，自己的翻译远远谈不上优美，但我却是一名忠实的译者。尽管我时不时会省略掉一些段落，缩短一些句子，掩饰掉某些名字，但我绝没有添油加醋。

[1]莱顿，荷兰西部城市。——译者注

第一章　赫斯利乌斯医生讲述他是如何遇见牧师詹宁斯先生的

/

牧师詹宁斯先生又高又瘦。他正值中年，整洁的衣着完全是那种高教会派[2]的老旧风格。他生来就带有一丝威严，但是一点儿也不拘谨。他的相貌虽然称不上英俊，长相却很匀称；面色极其和善，也带有几分腼腆。

一天晚上，我在玛丽·海杜克小姐的家里遇见了他。他脸上流露出的谦虚和慈爱的表情非常令人着迷。

我们的聚会是小范围的，他十分惬意地同大家聊着天。相比起发表高见，他似乎更乐于倾听；但是，只要他一开口，总是一语中的，恰如其分。他是玛丽小姐的最爱。玛丽小姐似乎在很多问题上都要向他请教，认为他是世界上最幸福美满的人。但是，她对他其实几乎一无所知。

牧师詹宁斯先生是个单身男人，手头据说有六万英镑的积蓄。他为人仁慈，非常渴望献身于神圣的宗教事业。虽然他在别的地方都还过得去，但是，一回到沃里克郡他自己的教区，真正开始投身那份神圣的职业，从事实际的工作，他的健康状况就让他无以为继，并且情况还十分奇怪。玛丽小姐如是说着。

毫无疑问的是，詹宁斯先生的健康问题，大体上说，是一种突如其来、神秘莫测的行为。有时候，他正在肯利斯那座古老、优美的教堂里主持宗教仪式时，就会突然发病。也许是因为他的心脏，也许是大脑。但是，那样反复发作了三四次，甚至更多回，每次都是当仪式举行了一段时间后，他突然间停了下来，沉默片刻后，显然无法再度开始。他独自陷入了无声的祷告，双手高举，双眼朝天，然后变得面如死灰。在一种奇怪的、夹杂着羞愧和恐惧的不安中，他颤抖着走下讲坛，步入法衣室，没有做出任何解释，就把会众留在了原地。这一切发生的时候，他的助理牧师并不在场。现在，他每次只要去肯利斯，总是会留心安排一位牧师同自己一同工作。这样万一他突然无法履职，有人就可以迅速顶替他。

詹宁斯先生的身体彻底垮了之后，便从教区逃了出来，回到伦敦，待在皮卡迪利大街后一条黑暗的街道里，住进了一间窄屋。玛丽小姐说，他的身体一直以来都很棒。对此我有着自己的看法。有关好坏的程度当然见仁见智。我们可以拭目以待。

詹宁斯先生是一个十足的绅士。不过人们总是能从他身上察觉到一些奇怪的地方，或是多少对这奇怪的感觉有点儿模棱两可的印象。有一件事儿肯定是对此的有力佐证。我觉得人们要么就彻底忘了那件事儿，要么就肯定清晰地记着。反正我是记着的，仿如昨日一般。詹宁斯先生会斜着眼看地毯，紧盯着不放，似乎那边有某样东西在移动一样。当然，他也并不总是如此，而是时不时发作一番。不过，正如我所说的那样，这总是令他的举止显得颇有一些怪异。他那在地板上漂移的目光中，既带着一丝胆怯，又流露出几分焦虑。

一名医学哲学家，正如你们恭维我的那样，会借助自己挖掘出的病例来阐述各种理论，并花更多的时间，亲自观察，精心审视。因此，相比一般的医生，这样得出的判断无疑要缜密许多。我还会不自觉地养成注意观察的习惯。这种习惯时刻伴随着我，我也随时都会找机会操练一番。有些人会说，甚至连一些毫不相关、毫无价值的事情我也不肯放过。

这场令人愉快的晚间聚会上，我初次相识的这位牧师，瘦削、胆小、和善，但却是一位矜持的绅士。他的身上，可能就具有吸引我的那种特质。当然，我观察到的，要比我在这里写的多得多。但是，有关技术的环节，都被放到一篇严谨的科学论文中去了。

我想说的是，我在此谈到医学，目的是希望有一天，人们能对这门学科有一种更为广义的理解。相比通常的物理治疗所起的作用，那种感受会全面得多。我相信，整个自然世界只是精神世界的最终表现形式，只有在精神世界中，自然世界才拥有生命力。我认为，人在本质上是一种精神，而精神也是一种条理分明的物质，但是在材质特点方面，与我们熟知的物质截然不同，就像光或者电那样。从纯粹字面的意思上来说，肉体只不过是一具躯壳。因此，死亡并不意味着生命的终结，而只是让人脱离了肉体的羁绊——这一过程，始于我们所称的死亡。最迟在几天以后，在复活“奇迹”展现的一刻，终成大道。

持这些立场的人可能会看到这种观点在医学上的实例。然而，这些事实的存在普遍未得到承认。这里也绝不是展示证据、讨论结果的适当场合。

出于习惯，我开始小心翼翼地偷偷观察詹宁斯先生——我想，他也觉察到了这一点——我明显发现，他也同样小心谨慎地观察着我。玛丽小姐在介绍我的时候，碰巧称我为赫斯利乌斯医生。我发现，他扫视我的目光变得更加明显，然后陷入了几分钟的沉思。

之后，我一边在房间的另一头与一位绅士攀谈，一边发现他更沉着地注视着我，而我当时也确信我很了解他对我的兴趣所在。再之后，我发现他找机会和玛丽小姐聊起天来。一如既往，人们在这种时刻，总是能清晰地觉察到，自己成了远处一问一答的话题。

稍后，这位高个儿牧师朝我走来。没过一会儿，我们就聊了起来。当两个人都喜欢读书，对于书籍和各地的风土人情都略知一二，又有过跋山涉水的经历，同时还乐意交谈一番的时候，要是还找不到话题，简直就是一桩咄咄怪事了。他向我走来，还与我相谈甚欢，原因并不是偶然的。他懂德语，并且读过我写的有关玄医学的论文。相比起字面上所写的，那些论文深层次的含义更值得玩味。

这人彬彬有礼，性格温顺，略带几分羞涩，显然是一个博览群书、颇有想法的人。他在我们中间走来走去，谈天说地，但并不是完全地敞开心扉。我已经开始怀疑，他是那种把所有大事小事都深深藏在心底的人，不仅对全世界都有所保留，甚至对他最亲爱的朋友也是如此。但是，他的内心深处却在小心地权衡，是否要对我网开一面。

他还没有意识到我看透了他的想法。我也尽量只字不提，以免触动他那敏感的神经，怀疑我洞悉了他的观点，或者猜到了他对我的打算。

我们聊了一阵无关紧要的话题，但是最终他说：

“赫斯利乌斯医生，我对您的一些论文很感兴趣，那些您称为玄医学的论文——十到十二年前，我读过德文版的——现在翻译过来了吗？”

“没有，我敢肯定没有——不然我会有所耳闻的。我想，应该是要事先征得我的同意的。”

“几个月前，我拜托了本地的出版商，帮我找找德文原版的，可他们告诉我已经绝版了。”

“确实是，已经绝版好些年了。但是，身为作者，听到您还没有忘记拙作，还是深感荣幸的。”我笑着继续说道，“您在这十到十二年的时间里，没有那本书都过得好好的，但是我猜您一定是在脑子里又想起了那个话题，或者近来发生了什么事，让您对它又产生了兴趣。”

詹宁斯先生听了这番话，旋即露出疑问的眼神，突然感到一阵尴尬，就好像一位年轻的小姐那样脸红起来，看上去傻傻的。他垂下双眼，两手不安地交叉在一起，看起来怪怪的。有那么一刻，甚至可以说有点儿愧疚。

为了尽量让他摆脱这份局促，我表现出若无其事的样子，然后继续说道：“我也总是碰到这种重拾兴趣的事，一本书接着另一本，经常会徒劳无功地把我带回到二十年前。但是，如果你依旧还有兴趣的话，我会很乐意奉送上一本。我身边还有两三本存货——如果您愿意接受，我将不胜荣幸。”

“您真是太好了，”他说，一时之间又轻松自在起来，“我几乎已经绝望了——真不知道该如何感谢您。”

“千万别那么说。实在是太微不足道了，我简直有点儿羞于启齿。您要是再表示感谢，羞愧之下，我唯有将书付之一炬了。”

詹宁斯先生大笑起来。他问我住在伦敦的什么地方，又海阔天空地聊了一阵后，便起身告辞了。

[2]高教会派，英国国教的一个派别。——译者注

第二章　医生和玛丽小姐的问与答

/

“玛丽小姐，我非常喜欢那位牧师。”他刚一走，我就说道，“他饱读诗书，游历甚广，有自己的想法，还遭遇过磨难，应该是个多才多艺的好伙伴。”

“他当然是，而且更重要的是，他还是一个真正的好人，”她说，“无论是对于我的学校还是我在道尔布里奇的小事业，他的建议都价值连城。要知道，只要他认为自己能帮上忙，总会劳心竭力，克服重重困难施以援手。他脾气真好，还那么地通情达理。”

“听到你说他有乐于助人的美德，真是令人欣慰。我只能证明他是一个和蔼可亲的伙伴。除了你刚刚告诉我的以外，我想，我还能同你说说他的两三件事。”我说。

“真的吗？”

“当然。首先，他未婚。”

“没错，请继续。”

“他一直在写东西。嗯，他过去在写，但是他也许搁笔有两三年了吧。那本书是关于某些比较深奥的话题的——也许是神学。”

“确实如你所说，他之前一直在写一本书。我不太确定是关于什么内容的，但是肯定是些我不太关心的东西，很有可能你是对的。而现在，他确实停了下来。”

“还有，虽然今晚在这里，他只喝了一点点咖啡，但他是喜欢喝茶的，至少在过去极为喜欢。”

“噢，简直太对了。”

“他过去喝的是绿茶，喝很多，对吧？”我继续问道。

“嗯，确实很奇怪。过去，为了绿茶的事情，我们总会差点吵起来。”

“但是，现在他已经完全戒掉了。”我说。

“的确如此。”

“那么，还有一件事。你认识他的父亲或是母亲吗？”

“他的双亲我都认识。他的父亲去世才十年，他们就葬在道尔布里奇附近。我们对他们都很了解。”她回答道。

“那么，要么是他的母亲，要么是他的父亲——我想父亲更有可能，见到过幽灵。”我说。

“噢，赫斯利乌斯，你真的是魔法师吧？”

“魔法师不魔法师的先放一边，我说的对吗？”我开心地问道。

“当然对啦。见到幽灵的是他父亲。他是一个沉默寡语、异想天开的人，常常缠着我父亲讲他做的那些梦。他最后讲过一个关于幽灵的故事。那是一个奇怪的故事，他说那个幽灵是他亲眼所见的，还能和他对答如流。我对这个故事记忆犹新，因为我特别害怕他。他是在去世前很多年说的这个故事，我还很小的时候。他总是默不作声，神情忧郁，常常喜欢在黄昏时分来我们家串门。他来的时候，我常常一个人待在客厅里。过去，我总是幻想，他的周围全是幽灵。”

我笑着点点头。

“好吧，既然你已经认定我是个魔法师，我想该是说晚安的时候了。”我说。

“但是，你究竟是怎么发现的？”

“当然是占星术，就像吉卜赛人那样。”我回答道。于是，我们愉快地互道了晚安。

第二天一早，我给詹宁斯先生寄去了他一直想要的那本小书，还附上了一张便条。晚上回来的时候，我发现他拜访过我的住所，留下了一张卡片。他问我是否在家，还问什么时候最有可能找到我。

他是打算敞开心扉，如同人们说的，咨询我的“专业意见”了吗？我希望如此。我已经构想出了一种关于他的理论。我在告辞前与玛丽小姐的问答，也证实了这一点。而我却更想从他自己的嘴里得到确认。但是，我该做些什么，才能秉持一贯的优雅风度，邀请他吐露心声呢？什么也不做。我倒是认为，他自己会深思熟虑一番的。无论如何，尊敬的范·洛，我是不会令自己难以接近的。我打算明天就回访他。去求见他，完全是一种礼节，是对他的彬彬有礼的一种回应。也许我会有所收获。无论有还是没有，收获或大或小，尊敬的范·洛，我都会告诉你的。

第三章　赫斯利乌斯医生在拉丁文书中找到了一些东西

/

好吧，我去布兰克大街拜访过了。

仆人在门口稍一打听，便告诉我，詹宁斯先生和一位绅士正有事忙着呢，那是从他的教区肯利斯来的一位牧师。为了保留自己的一点儿特权，也为了能再次拜访，我只是暗示自己改日还会再来。我转身刚要走，那位仆人就向我表示歉意，问我是不是赫斯利乌斯医生。他十分专注地看着我。作为教养还不错的仆人，通常是不会这么看人的。知道了我的身份后，他说：“那么，先生，请允许我向詹宁斯先生通报一声。我敢肯定他想要见您。”

过了一会儿，仆人回来了，带来了詹宁斯先生的口信。他请我去他的书房，那实际上是他后部的客厅。他答应几分钟后就来见我。

这真的是一间书房——几乎称得上是图书馆了。房间很高，有两扇细长的窗户，配有深黑色的窗帘。房间比我预想的要大得多，书堆得到处都是，从地板一直堆到了天花板。上层的地毯——凭我踩上去的感觉，有两三层——是土耳其地毯。脚步落下去，悄然无声。书架突出在外，使得窗户都显得非常幽深，尤其是那几扇窄窗。房间虽然非常舒适，甚至能用奢华来形容，但是显然有些阴暗，再加上那份寂静，简直可以称得上是令人压抑了。然而，也许是因为我产生了一些联想。在我的头脑中，已经把一些奇怪的想法和詹宁斯先生联系起来了。我带着一种特别的不祥的预感，走进这幢非常安静的屋子，步入这间极其寂静的房间。那份黑暗，以及各类书籍庄重的封皮，更是加深了这份忧郁的感觉。除了墙上两扇窄窄的玻璃以外，书堆得到处都是。

我在等着詹宁斯先生的到来。为了打发时间，我瞄了瞄他书橱里堆放的书。我的目光落到了书橱下面的一堆书上。那些书放在地板上，背面朝上，是斯维登堡的一整套拉丁文原版《属天的奥秘》。那是一套非常精致的对开本，装帧极为考究，深受神学风格的影响，纯羊皮封面上烫印着金色的字母，书边也是胭脂红色的。这套书里插着一些纸质书签。我拾起那些书，一本接一本地放到桌上，把书翻到插有书签的地方。我读起了肃穆的拉丁术语，文中用铅笔画出了许多句子。在此我摘录一些，并翻译成了英语。

“当人的内在视觉，即他的灵魂的视觉打开的那一刻，生命的另一种形式就出现了，那是肉眼无从可见的。”

“拥有了内在视觉，我就得以看见另一种形式的生命，要比我看见的这个世界的东西清晰许多。从这个角度考虑，显然外部视觉脱胎于内在视觉，而内在视觉则来源于更加内在的视觉，如此等等。”

“每个人至少都有两种邪灵在侧。”

“恶鬼在旁的人同样也能流利地讲话，但是声音刺耳，听来让人不快。他们有时候也会出现说话不畅的情况，因为那时正有某样东西悄悄潜伏在内，令想法产生了分歧。”

“附身于人的邪灵确实来自地狱，但是附上人身之后，他们就脱离了地狱。这时他们所在的地方，位于天堂和地狱之间，称为灵界——邪灵附在人身上的时候，就处在灵界之中。此时他们免受地狱的一切折磨，而是分享宿主的全部所思所想。因此，该人的一颦一笑，邪灵都能一一体会。但是，他们返回地狱之后，又回归到了以前的状态。”

“邪灵觉察到自己附身于人时，此时他们还只是与人分离的灵。而如果他们可以飘入那人的肉体，他们就会千方百计地摧毁他，因为他们对人抱有无穷的敌意。”

“因此，当他们认识到我是肉身的主人后，就会不断地试图除灭我，不仅要除灭我的肉身，更要除灭掉我的灵魂。因为，对于地狱里的一切生命，消灭人类或灵魂都是他们的乐趣所在。但是，我主一直保护着我。因此，与灵共生的人是何等危险啊，除非他的信仰无比坚定。”

“精心防护，不让附体的灵知道他们已经与人合体实在是太重要了，因为如果他们知道了这一点，就会和他对话，其意图就是为了摧毁他。”

“地狱的乐趣就是对人作恶，让他快速而永远地灭亡。”

页面底部的一长串注释吸引了我的目光，那是詹宁斯先生干净的手笔，是用十分尖细的铅笔写就的。我期望看到他的评价，便读了一两句，但是随即停了下来，因为写的内容完全不是那些，而是以这样的文字开头的，“Deus misereatui mei [3]”。我意识到了这段文字的私密性，于是挪开双眼，合上书，把全套书都放到原先的地方，除了一本之外。那本书吸引了我的注意。我就像一个勤奋好学、惯于独处的人那样，完全沉浸在了书中，浑然不知外物，也不记得自己究竟身处何处。

我读到的那部分，用斯维登堡的术语来说，是有关“代表物”和“对应物”的内容。正在读的这一段，主要说的是，当邪灵为其地狱伙伴之外的人所见时，他们就以“对应物”的形式出现，呈现出野兽的模样。那是他们可怕、残暴的一面，代表了他们的特殊欲望和生命。这一段很长，特别列举了一些野兽的形式。

[3]Deus misereatui mei, 拉丁文，愿上帝怜悯我。——译者注

第四章　四目同读

/

我一边读，一边用铅笔盒的一端沿着文字移动，突然某样东西迫使我抬起了目光。

我的正前方是刚才提到过的一面镜子，我在镜子里看到了我那位朋友高大的身影。詹宁斯先生弓着背，俯身在我的肩膀上，读着我正在埋头苦读的那一页，脸色阴沉而激动，我几乎都认不出他了。

我转身站了起来。他也站直了身子，努力挤出一丝笑容，说道：

“我走进来，向您问好，但是没能把您从书中唤醒。所以我禁不住好奇，就从您肩膀上偷看了，恐怕是有些失礼。您应该不是第一次看那些文章了。毫无疑问，您在很久以前研究过斯维登堡？”

“噢，太对了！我欠斯维登堡的实在是太多了。您一定会记得，《玄医学》那本小书里也能找到他的影子。”

虽然我的朋友装出一副高兴的样子，但是他的脸上闪过一丝红晕，我能觉察到他内心里极大的不安。

“我简直不够资格，我对斯维登堡知之甚少。两周前，我才拿到那些书。”他回答道，“我认为，它们会让一个孤独的人感到神经紧张——嗯，从我读过的一点点来判断——我不是说它们把我也弄得紧张了。”他笑道，“我非常感激这本书。您拿到我的便条了？”

我尽量表示赞同，但也少许保留了一点意见。

“读您的书，我是彻彻底底读进去了，”他接着说道，“我一眼就看出来，那本书的内涵要比写出来的丰富得多。您认识哈利医生吗？”他问道，显得有些突然。

顺便说一下，笔者认为，此处提到的这位医生是英格兰有史以来最杰出的医生之一。

我认识他，和他通过信，并且在我访问英格兰期间，受到他的热情款待，得到了他极大的帮助。

“我觉得，他是我此生遇见过的最大的傻瓜。”詹宁斯先生说道。

这是我第一次听到他说别人的坏话，如此高贵的名字竟会配上这样的字眼，着实让我大吃一惊。

“真的吗？在什么方面？”我问道。

“他的专业上。”他回答道。

我笑了起来。

“我的意思是，”他说，“在我看来，他的决定，有半数都是盲目做出的——我指的是，他看待万物，有一半都是暗淡悲观的——而另一半则无比光明、充满活力。最糟的是，他似乎是故意的。我简直无法理解——我是说，他不应该这样——他行医的时候，我和他打过交道，但是我觉得，在这层意义上，他只不过是个思想上的瘫子，智力上的活死人。也许在某个时候，我会和您详细说说。”他带着一点儿激动说道，“您在英格兰多待几个月吧。如果在您逗留期间我不在城里，能允许我给您写信吗？”

“荣幸之至。”我向他保证道。

“您真是太好了。我对哈利实在是太不满意了。”

“他有点儿倾向于唯物主义学派。”我说。

“一个彻头彻尾的唯物主义者。”他纠正我道，“您无法想象，那种事情会让更了解底细的人多么担心啊。请您不要告诉任何人——任何您认识的我的朋友——我所郁闷的事情。比方说，现在没有人知道——甚至玛丽小姐也不知道——我去找哈利医生，或是任何其他的医生看过病。所以请不要提起此事。如果我有任何发作的征兆，请允许我给您写信。如果我在城里的话，还能跟您谈一谈。”

我满脑子都是猜测。不知不觉中，我发现自己正凝重地盯着他，因为他的目光垂下了片刻，然后他说：

“我觉得您大概在想，我还是现在就告诉您吧，不然您会乱猜的，但是您还是放弃吧。就算用尽整个余生，您也永远猜不到。”

他微笑着摇着头。冬日的阳光下，突然飘过一片乌云。他像是忍受着痛苦一样，咬着牙齿吸了一口气。

“很抱歉，您曾经找机会咨询过我的同行的意见。但是，只要您愿意，我随时随地都听候您的吩咐。不用我提醒您，信心无比重要。”

然后，他又聊了很多其他的事情，氛围要轻松愉快很多。过了一会儿，我就起身告辞了。

第五章　赫斯利乌斯被召唤到了里士满

/

我们欢快地告别，但是他高兴不起来，我也是。人脸——这一强大的心灵的器官——一定具有某种表达形式。虽然我经常见到各种各样的脸，并且拥有医生的坚强神经，但是这张脸却深深搅乱了我的心神。看一眼詹宁斯先生就让我焦躁不安。它具有一种凄凉的力量，令我浮想联翩。我不得不改变了晚间的计划，去了歌剧院。我觉得，自己需要换换脑子。

有两三天的时间，我没有听到他的消息，也没有收到他的信息，直到他给我送来了一张便条，读来满心欢喜，充满希望。他说，一段时间以来，他已经好多了——实际上，是很不错——他要做一个小试验，到他的教区去上一个多月，试试看一点点工作是否会让他不舒服。对于他的康复，现在他几乎打算这么称呼了，洋溢着一股强烈的宗教感激之情。

一两天后，我见到了玛丽小姐，她又说了一遍他在便条里告知的事情，告诉我他实际上是在沃里克郡，继续履行他在肯利斯的牧师职责。她还补充说道：“我禁不住认为，他真的是完全健康的，除了神经过敏和胡思乱想，其实什么事也没有。我们都会神经紧张，但是我觉得，对付那种缺点，一点点的辛勤工作就是最好的灵丹妙药，他下定决心去试试看。他要是过了一年多也不回来，我一点儿也不会奇怪的。”

尽管她信心十足，但是仅仅两天之后，我就收到了这张便条，那是从他皮卡迪利大街附近的房子里发出的，还有落款日期：

尊敬的先生，我无比失望地回来了。如果我觉得能够见您，我会写信请您来拜访的。此刻，我的心情太低落了。实际上，甚至连想说的话都说不出来。请不要和朋友们提到我的名字。我无法见任何人。上帝保佑，不久之后，您会听到我的消息的。我打算去什罗浦郡跑一趟，那里有一些我的亲戚。上帝保佑您！愿我回来以后，相比起现在，我们能更加愉快地相见。

此后大约一周，我在玛丽小姐自家的宅邸碰到了她。她说，最后一个留在城里的人，也要动身前往布莱顿了，因为伦敦的好季节马上就要过去了。她告诉我她从詹宁斯先生的侄女玛莎那里听说了他在什罗浦郡。他侄女的信里没有多说什么，只是提到他情绪低落、神经紧张。那些字眼，健康的人们觉得只不过是轻描淡写，而暗中却隐藏着怎样的痛苦啊！

将近五周过去，我都没有接到詹宁斯先生的任何消息。最终，我收到了他的一张便条。他写道：

我到了乡下，呼吸着不同的空气，看着不同的风景，感受着不同的人，所有的东西都不一样了——所有东西都有了改变——除了我以外。作为地球上最犹豫不决的生物，我已经下定决心，要完全向您坦露我的病情。如果您时间允许，请今天、明天或是后天就来找我。但是请一定要越快越好。您不知道我有多么需要帮助。我在里士满有一幢安静的房子，现在我就在这里。也许您可以赶过来吃晚餐，或是午餐，甚至是喝茶也可以。您会毫不费力地找到我的。只要您方便，带信来的布兰克大街的仆人随时都会把马车停到您的大门口。我也随时恭候您的大驾。您也许会说我不应该一个人独处。我什么都试过了。来看我吧。

我叫来了仆人，决定今晚就去。于是我就真的去了。

我想，他要是待在寄宿处，或者旅馆里，应该会觉得好很多。此时，我乘坐的马车正穿过两排低矮阴郁的榆树林，前往一幢相当老式的砖式房屋。那些树木的叶子遮住了屋子，超过了房顶的高度，几乎把屋子包围了。这是一种不合常理的选择，因为没有什么比这更沉闷和寂静的了。他在城里待了一两天，因为某种无法忍受的原因，搬来了这里。也许是因为这里家具齐全，还是他自己的房子，来这里便能摆脱思绪上的困扰，也不会有选择上的困难。

太阳已经落山了，西边的天空反射出的红光照亮了四周的景色。我们都很熟悉这种景致。大厅显得非常黑暗，但是，走到后面的客厅之后，因为有窗户是朝着西面的，于是我又沐浴在了同样的微光之下。

我坐了下来，望着窗外枝繁叶茂的风景。在壮丽而凄凉的光线中，万物都闪烁着柔和的光芒，而那一丝光芒，也正在一点点地褪去。房间的几个角落已经全黑了，所有的东西都变得昏暗起来。不知不觉中，我的心绪也随着那份阴暗而变动着，做好了面对真正邪恶的准备。我独自等待着他的到来，很快就如愿了。与前厅相通的那扇门打开了，在红彤彤的暮色中，詹宁斯先生高大的身影隐约可见。他迈着隐秘的步子，不声不响地走进了房间。

我们握了握手，靠窗坐在椅子上。那里还足够亮，能让我们看见彼此的脸庞。他坐在我旁边，把手放在我的手臂上，没有半点儿开场白，直接讲起了自己的故事。

第六章　詹宁斯先生是如何遇到自己的同伴的

/

我们身前，是西方的落日余晖，是荒凉的里士满森林壮丽的一面。我们身后，我们身旁，是一点点暗淡下去的房间。那道昏暗、古怪的光辉落在患者石头一样冰冷的脸上——他的脸庞依旧和蔼温柔，但是有点儿不一样了——似乎陷了进去。光辉触碰到的地方，突然间仿佛变幻出了某种光线，尽管十分暗淡。那缕光线还来不及发生一丝变化，就融化在了那片黑暗之中。四周同样无声无息：没有远方马车的车轮滚滚，没有一声狗吠，也没有来历不明的口哨声。有的只是一个生病的单身汉的屋中那份压抑的寂静。

受害人僵硬的脸庞涨得通红，在黑色背景的映衬下，仿佛沙尔肯的肖像画一般。虽然对于细节内幕尚一无所知，但是我从他的那张脸上，很轻易猜到了问题的实质。

“事情开始于，”他说道，“十月十五日，三年十一个星期零两天以前——我对日期记得清清楚楚，因为此后每一天都是煎熬。如果我的讲述中有所遗漏，请您告诉我。”

“大约四年前，我开始着手从事一项工作，耗费了我大量的思绪，也让我阅读了很多东西。那是关于古人的宗教玄学的问题。”

“明白，”我说，“基于一定事实，有着成套思想体系的异教是一种宗教现实，与象征性的崇拜是大不相同的。那是一个非常有趣，范围很广的研究领域。”

“没错，但是对于心智是不利的——我指的是，基督徒的心智。异教在本质上自成一体，总体而言是邪恶的。他们的宗教包括了他们的艺术，还有他们的行为举止。痴迷于这项课题的研究是一件丢脸的事，当然也会带来报应。上帝啊，请宽恕我。

“我写了大量的东西，夜里很晚还在写。我一直在思考我的研究，走路也想，无论走到什么地方，都在想。我彻底陷了进去。您要记住，所有与此相关的物质概念，或多或少都有美丽的一面，而这项课题本身就非常有趣。而那时的我，则对此毫不担心。”

他重重地叹了一口气。

“我相信，所有认认真真投入写作的人都会对某样东西——用我朋友的话说——上瘾：茶、咖啡，或是烟草。我猜，从事这种职业的人，每小时都必须要补充物质的消耗，不然就会变得心不在焉。思维也一样，会渐渐脱离肉体，除非经常能得到某种真情实感的提醒。无论如何，我觉得有那种需要，我也开始尝试物质上的补充。陪伴我的是茶——一开始是普通的红茶，通常的喝法，不是很浓：但是我喝了很多，并且越喝越浓。我也从未有过不舒服的感觉。我开始尝试喝一点儿绿茶。我发现效果更好，让我耳清目明，思绪敏捷。于是，我渐渐喝得频繁了，但是还没有超出消遣的程度。我在这个地方写了很多东西，就在这间房间里，这里很安静。那时，我会熬夜到很晚。一边工作，一边时不时抿上一口茶——绿茶——于是便习惯成自然。我在桌上放了一把小水壶，就挂在灯上。从夜里十一点到凌晨两三点间，我都要沏上两三回茶。那之后，我才上床睡觉。我通常每天都会进城。我并非修道士。虽然我要在图书馆里待上一两个小时，搜寻权威的说法，寻找启发我研究的闪光点，但是我知道自己在精神上并没有处于病态。我还是像往常那样时常与朋友相见，喜欢与他们交往。总体而言，我觉得，生活从未如此快乐。

“我认识了一个人，他有一些不同寻常的旧书，是德意志出版的中世纪拉丁文的版本。得知获准一睹书的真容，我高兴万分。这位好心人的书都在城里，而且是非常偏远的地方。我在那儿待得比预定时间要长。一出来后，看到附近没有出租马车，我就想去乘公共马车，因为这间屋子附近常常有公共马车驶过。马车驶过一幢旧房子的时候，天已经比现在还黑了。我注意到，那幢房子的大门口，两旁各有四棵杨树。除了我之外的最后一名乘客也下了车。马车一路跑得更快了。当时已经是黄昏。我倚靠在车门这边的角落里，愉快地细细回味着。

“公共马车内已经近乎全黑了。我看了看正对面的那个角落。紧挨着马匹后部的地方，有两个小圆点，似乎是一道红色光线的反光。它们大约间隔两英寸[4]，大概有开游艇人外套上的小铜纽扣那么大。百无聊赖之下，我不禁琢磨起那到底是什么小玩意儿。那道虽然昏暗，但却颜色深红的光线究竟从何而来？到底是什么东西在反射光芒——玻璃珠？纽扣？还是玩具的装饰物？我们一路摇摇晃晃地行驶着，还剩下大约一英里[5]的路。我还没有解开这个谜团。接下来，那个东西变得更加奇怪了。因为那两个光点突然猛地一动，距离地板越来越近，但还是保持着彼此的相对距离和水平位置。然后，它们忽然升高到与我的座位相同的高度，我一下子看不见它们了。

“我的好奇心现在是真的被点燃了。我还来不及细想，那两个昏暗的光点又出现了，再一次一同出现在靠近地板的地方。然后又消失了，然后又回到我一开始看到它们的角落里。

“于是，我双眼一边紧紧地盯着它们，一边从我这一侧不动声色地慢慢挪过去。到了那一端后，我看见那些小红点还在。

“公共马车内几乎没有一点儿亮光。天近乎全黑了。我身子向前倾了倾，以便能更好地搞清楚那些小圆点到底是什么。随着我的移动，它们的位置也发生了一些变化。现在，我能察觉到那里有一个黑影了。片刻后，我看见了一只黑色小猴的轮廓，还算比较清楚。它正模仿着我的动作，把脸伸向前。那两个小圆点是它的双眼。我现在还能隐约地看见，它正露出牙齿，咧嘴朝我笑着。

“我往后退了退，不知道它会不会跳过来。我猜，一定是哪位乘客把这难看的宠物忘在车上了。我想试试看它脾气如何，但又不愿意用手指去冒险，便把伞轻轻地朝它戳去。它一动不动——伞戳到它身上了——伞穿了过去。穿过它的身体时，来来回回都没有遇到一丝的阻力。

“我的那种恐惧，无法向您形容半分。当我弄明白那东西是一种幻觉之后，我不禁为自己担心害怕起来。这种惊骇让我魂不守舍，我凝视着那畜生的双眼，甚至片刻也无法脱离。我目不转睛地看着，那东西朝后跳了跳，退回到了角落里。而我在慌乱之间，发现自己已经靠在了车门口，于是探出头去，深深呼吸着外边的空气，眼睛盯着驶过的灯光和树木。重新触到现实的感觉让我高兴不已。

“我叫停马车，走了下去。在付钱的时候，我能察觉到车夫看我的眼神怪怪的。我敢说，自己的表情和举止一定有些不同寻常，因为我以前从未有过如此怪异的感觉。”

[4]1英寸=2.54厘米。——编者注

[5]1英里≈1.6千米。——编者注

第七章　历程：第一阶段

/

“公共马车继续向前驶去，把我一个人留在了马路上。我仔细地朝四周打量，想搞清楚那只猴子是不是还跟着我，结果一无所获。我不由得如释重负。我无法形容，刚才遭受的打击有多么大。而我觉得，重拾自我的欣喜让自己多少摆脱了那种情绪。

“马车还没驶到这幢房子前，我就提前下了车，现在还有两三百步的距离。人行小路旁有一堵砖墙，墙内是一道紫杉树篱，或是那一类的深色常绿植物。树篱里面还有一排硕大的乔木，你在来的路上应该注意到了。

“砖墙大约有我肩膀那么高。我抬起双眼，正好看见了那只猴子。它在墙头上，弯着腰，四肢着地，边走边爬，紧紧地跟着我。我停了下来，带着恐惧和憎恨的情绪看着它。我一停，它也停了下来，坐在墙上，长长的双手搁在膝盖上，也看着我。灯光昏暗，只能看见那只猴子的轮廓。可天又黑得不够彻底，无法让它眼中那道怪异的光芒尽情释放。然而，我依旧能清晰地看见那道雾蒙蒙的红光。那只猴子没有露出牙齿，也没有表现出任何愤怒的迹象，它似乎厌烦了，闷闷不乐地一直盯着我看。

“我退到了马路中间，那是一种无意识的后退，我就站在那里，看着它。它一动不动。

“我本能地决定试试看别的招数——什么都行。我转过身，迈着轻快的步伐朝镇上走去，同时一直斜眼观察着那只畜生的动向。它飞快地沿着墙头爬着，与我的速度完全一致。

“马路快转弯的地方，围墙到底了。它跃下墙头，结结实实地蹦上一两下，便来到我的脚边，继续紧跟着我，我加快了脚步也没有用。它在我的左侧，就在我的腿旁，每时每刻我都担心自己会一脚踩到它。

“马路上空旷无人，安静异常。天在一点点地黑下去。我惊慌失措地停住脚步，向着另外一个方向转身——我指的是，朝着这幢房子的方向，和我刚才行走的方向相反。我站定之后，那只猴子朝后退了一段距离，我估计，大约有五六码[6]远，一动不动地看着我。

“我比刚才说的还要激动。和大家一样，我当然也听说过‘幽灵幻觉’的说法。那是你们医生用来形容类似这样的情况的。我思考了一下自己的处境，正视自己面对的不幸。

“我读到过，这种病情有时候是暂时的，有时候则很顽固。据说有的病例中，幽灵的外表起初人畜无害。而渐渐地，它变成了可怕的模样，令人无法忍受，最终把受害人折磨得精疲力竭。我孤孤单单地静静站在原地，陪伴我的只有那只野兽。我试图安慰自己，一遍又一遍地向自己保证，‘那个东西纯粹是一种病，一种有名的身体疾病，和天花或是神经痛无疑是一样的。医生们的看法一致，在原理上也得到了证明。我肯定不是傻瓜。我一直熬夜到太晚，而且消化也不正常。上帝助我，一定会没事的。这只不过是神经消化不良的症状’。我相信这些吗？一个字也不信。不过是和其他可怜人的想法一样罢了。他们也曾经遭遇过这种恶魔般的境遇，深陷其中，欲罢不能。我只能说自己的学识违背了我的信仰，我只不过是在欺骗自己、徒增勇气而已。

“现在，我朝家的方向走去。离家只有几百码了。我强迫自己听天由命，但是还没有从那种令人作呕的震惊中摆脱出来，还处在初逢厄运的慌乱之中。

“我打定主意，当晚就待在家里。那个畜生靠近了我。我不禁想，是不是因为朝着家的方向前进，它就产生了某种急切的情绪。有时，筋疲力尽的马或狗朝家走去时，也会出现这样的情况。

“我害怕到镇上去，我担心被人看到、认出来。我意识到，自己的一举一动中有一种抑制不住的焦虑。此外，我还害怕生活习惯上出现任何剧烈的变化，例如去到某个娱乐场所，或者为了让自己疲劳一些而离家散步。它一直在大厅门口等着我，直到我迈上台阶。大门一开，它就和我一起走了进去。

“那天夜里，我一口茶也没有喝。我抽了雪茄，喝了一点儿白兰地和水。我的想法是，自己应该尽情进行物质享受，过上一阵随心所欲的生活，就像这样，强迫自己养成一种新的习惯。我来到这间客厅，就坐在这个位置上。然后，那只猴子爬上了一张小桌子，当时是放在那里的。它看上去头昏眼花、无精打采。它动来动去，让我有一股抑制不住的不安，迫使自己一直盯着它。它的眼睛半睁半闭，但是还能看得出双眼的光芒。它不停地看着我。随时随地，一直清醒地看着我，片刻也不停息。

“我就不再详细讲述那一晚的遭遇了。我会接着形容第一年的情况，其实基本一样。我会讲讲这只猴子白天的样子。您刚刚已经听到了，在夜里，它有很多怪异之处。这只猴子不大，全身通黑。它只有一个特点——具有某种恶意——无法名状的恶意。第一年里，它看起来郁郁寡欢，总是病恹恹的。但是，在那份具有敌意的慵懒之下，总潜伏着一股强烈的恶意和警戒。在那段时间里，它什么也没有做，也没有给我惹一点儿麻烦，仿佛计划好的一般，只是持续不断地看着我。它的眼睛一刻也不曾离开我。自从它出现之后，除了睡梦中以外，我的视线里始终有它，无论白天黑夜，无论天明天暗，除了它每次会无缘由地离开几周之外。

“在完全黑暗的情况下，它也像白天一样清晰可见。我不仅仅指它的双眼。它笼罩在一层光晕之中，让浑身上下都能看得清清楚楚。那道光晕仿佛是一团红色的余烬，它走到哪里，光晕就跟到哪里。

“它暂时离开我的时候，总是在夜里，在黑暗之中，每次都如出一辙。它一开始变得很不自在，然后狂怒不已。之后它会向我扑来，龇着牙，浑身颤抖，爪子攥得紧紧的。与此同时，壁炉里出现了火光。我从来也不生火。在点火的房间里，我睡不着。它离烟囱越来越近，似乎因为愤怒而发抖。当那份怒火累积到最高点的时候，它跳进壁炉里，爬上烟囱，消失不见了。

“这一幕刚刚发生的时候，我有一种如释重负的感觉。现在，我重获新生了。一个白天过去了，一个晚上过去了，它没有回来。然后是一整周……一周……又一周。赫斯利乌斯医生，我跪倒在地，感谢上帝，跪着祈祷。整一个月就这样无忧无虑地过去了，但是突然之间，它又和我在一起了。”

[6]1码=3英尺，约0.9米。——编者注

第八章　第二阶段

/

“它伴随着我的左右。阴沉的外表下原来那股懒散的恶意，现在却活跃起来。其他方面则一点儿未变。从它的活动和外观上就能明显感觉出这股新生的力量，这股力量很快也表现在了其他的地方。

“你要知道，在一段时间里，这种变化只是表现为它更加活跃，恐吓的氛围更浓，就仿佛它一直在盘算着某种凶残的计划一样。它的眼睛，和以前一样，从未离开过我。”

“现在它在这里吗？”我问道。

“不在，”他回答道，“确切地说，它离开已有两周零一天了——十五天。有的时候，离开的时间会长达近乎两个月，有一次整整三个月。通常都会超过两周的时间，虽然也有可能只过一天它就回来了。我上次见到它，是十五天以前了。现在，它随时都可能回来。”

“它回来的时候，”我问道，“有什么异象吗？”

“没有，一点儿也没有。”他说，“它只是又来到我的身边。眼神离开书本，或是一转头的工夫，我就看见它了。它同往常一样看着我。然后就和从前一样，只要它在，就一直看着我。此前，我从未向任何人讲过这么许多，这么详细。”

我感觉到了他的激动，他看起来面无人色，不停地用手帕擦着前额。我表示，他也许是累了，并告诉他，我会很乐意第二天上午再来拜访，但是他说：

“不，如果您不介意现在听完的话，我已经说了这么多了，我愿意再努一把力。我和哈利医生谈的时候，我不愿像现在这样畅所欲言。您是一位哲学医生。您认可幽灵的存在。如果这样东西是真实的——”

他停了下来，带着疑问的神情激动地看着我。

“将来我们可以详细地讨论讨论，非常详细。我会把我的想法原原本本地告诉你。”我顿了一顿，回答道。

“好的，非常好。如果这东西是真实的，我想说，它正在逐步占据上风，一点一点地，把我的心灵拉进地狱。他谈到了视神经的问题。噢，好吧——还有其他的负责沟通的神经的问题。愿全能的上帝帮助我！您会听到的。

“我告诉过您，它行动的能力增强了。它的恶意，在某种程度上，变得具有攻击性了。大约两年前，我和主教间一直悬而未决的问题终于搞定，我去了自己在沃里克郡的教区，渴望实现自己的职业抱负。对于后来发生的事情，我没有做好准备，尽管自那以后，我一直认为自己可能会理解类似的事。我这么说是因为——”

他的话语开始变得更加吃力，更加勉强，还时常叹气，有时候似乎就要坚持不下去了。但是，此时他的态度并不激动，而更像是一名意志消沉的病人，已经完全自暴自弃了。

“好吧，但是我会首先和您谈谈我的教区，肯利斯。

“我离开此地，前往道尔布里奇的时候，它也在我旁边，是我旅途中无声的同伴。我住进牧师住宅后，它依旧跟着我。当我开始履行职责的时候，另外一个变化发生了。那个东西展现出了可怕的决心，千方百计地想要阻挠我。它和我一起在教堂里，一起在读经台上，一起在布道坛上，一起在领圣餐的围栏之内。最后，它终于发作了。我正在带领会众朗读的时候，它一下跳到书上，蹲坐在那里，令我无法看见书页。这样的事情发生了不止一次。

“我一度离开了道尔布里奇。我把自己交到哈利医生手里，对他言听计从。他很关心我的病情。我想，他很感兴趣。他似乎取得了成功。有将近三个月的时间，那东西都没有回来。我不禁想，自己已经安全了。在完全取得他的同意后，我回到了道尔布里奇。

“我是乘马车去的。一路上精神很好，不只很好，我非常开心，心情也很愉快。我觉得，自己已经从可怕的幻觉中解脱出来，要回归到渴望从事的工作中去了。那是一个阳光明媚的美丽傍晚，万物都显得欢乐、安详，我高兴极了。我记得，自己朝窗外看去，想在树影之间找到肯利斯教堂的尖顶，据说人们最早能在这个地方看见它。区分教区边界的一条小溪，恰好在那个地方从涵洞下穿过马路。它就在路边出现了，路边竖立着一块石头，石头上刻有古老的碑文。经过这个地点之后，我把脑袋缩回来，坐了下来。马车的角落里，坐着那只猴子。

“一时之间，我感到头晕目眩，然后又因为绝望和恐惧而感到愤怒。我叫停马车夫，下了车，坐在路边，默默地向上帝祈祷，请求宽恕。随之而来的是绝望的顺从。我的同伴跟着我再度走进牧师的住宅。它对我的迫害再度发生了。在一段短时间的抗争后，我屈服了，不久就离开了那个地方。

“我和您说过，”他说，“在此之前，那只畜生就已经表现得有些攻击性了。我再详细解释一下。每当我祈祷，甚至是冥想祈祷的时候，似乎有一股强烈的怒火驱使着它。那股怒火越积越强，直到最终，会以一种可怕的方式打断我。您也许会问，一个无声的非物质幻影是如何做到这点的？就像这样，每当我开始冥想祈祷的时候，它就一直待在我的面前，越来越近，越来越近。

“它常常在桌子上、椅背上、壁炉架上蹦蹦跳跳，一边盯着我不放，一边慢慢地左右摇摆。它的动作具有一种说不清的力量，可以驱散思想，让人把注意力集中在那单调的动作上，直到渐渐忘了刚才的打算，直到所有想法最终都烟消云散——除非我已经开始祈祷，摆脱了那种强迫，而此时我的脑子仿佛已经迷失了一般。它还有其他的方法，”他重重地叹了一口气，“比如像这样，我双眼闭着祈祷的时候，它会越靠越近，越靠越近，于是我便看见它了。我知道这根本无法解释，但是我确实看见它了，虽然我两眼紧闭。它就这样让我的思想出现动摇，可以说，它压倒了我，迫使我放弃跪拜，站起身来。如果曾经亲身经历过，你就会了解绝望是怎么一回事了。”

第九章　第三阶段

/

“赫斯利乌斯医生，我发觉，我说的每一个字您都听进去了。我不用请您再特别留意我接下来要说的话。他们谈到了视神经的问题，还有幽灵幻觉的现象，仿佛视觉器官是本人唯一受到影响的地方——我知道远不止如此。我那悲惨的病情，在两年的时间里不断发展。但是，就像食物在唇间温柔地下咽，终究还是会面对牙齿的咀嚼。就像卷进研磨机曲柄里的，一开始只是小拇指的指尖，然后会带进去一只手掌，一条胳膊，最后是整个身体。因此，哪怕可怜的凡人最初被抓住的只是最纤细的神经，也会被地狱的庞大势力一点点吞噬，直到他变得和我一模一样。一点儿没错，医生，和我一模一样。我和您交谈片刻，是为了祈求获得解脱。我觉得，我是在为不可能的事而祈祷，而我的祈求也终将一无所获。”

他显然越来越激动，我试图让他平静下来，告诉他不应该失去希望。

我们交谈的时候，夜幕已经降临了。朦胧的月色洒满了窗外，我说道：

“也许你更愿意点起蜡烛？你看，这种光线，有点儿奇怪。我希望，我在做诊断的时候，你能尽可能地和平时一样。我能说诊断吗——当然换个别的说法我也没有意见。”

“对我来说，所有的光线都是一样的，”他说，“除了在我读书写字的时候。长夜与否，我也不在乎。我还想告诉您，大约一年前发生的事。那东西开始和我说话了。”

“说话！你是什么意思——像人一样说话，是吗？”

“是的。逐字逐句，发音清楚，条理分明，但是有一点很奇怪。和人类的嗓音不一样，声音不是通过耳朵传来的——而是像在我的脑海中唱歌一样。

“这种能力，和我说话的技能，会是毁灭我的根源所在。它不让我祈祷，用可怕的亵渎神灵的话语打断我。我不敢再继续，没法儿再继续。噢！医生，人类的技能、思想和祈祷对我毫无用处！”

“你必须向我保证，尊敬的先生，不要再胡思乱想，而仅仅向我描述事实。最重要的是，你要记住，就算那个东西让你不堪其扰，似乎觉得它是真实存在的独立生命，具有独立意志，然而它还是没有能力伤害到你，除非上天赋予了它那样的能力：它能否进入你的感官主要取决于你的身体状况——上帝在上，这是你值得信赖和宽慰的地方：我们都是同样的肉体凡躯。在你的病情中，只不过是你的‘外壳’，肉体的屏障，那道屏风，有点儿失修了，光线和声音都能透过来。我们必须开始新的征程，先生——鼓起勇气。今晚，我会详细思考一下你的整个病情。”

“您真是太好了，先生。您觉得我还值得治疗，并没有完全放弃我。但是，先生，您不知道，它对我的影响越来越大：向我发号施令，简直就是一个暴君。我变得越来越无助。愿上帝解救我！”

“它向你发号施令？当然你是指通过语言？”

“是的，是的。它总是怂恿我去犯罪，去伤害别人，或者伤害我自己。要知道，医生，情况非常危急，这是真的。几周以前，我在什罗浦郡的时候，”现在，詹宁斯先生的语速越来越快，声音还有一些颤抖，一只手抓住我的手臂，看着我的脸，“一天，我和一群朋友出去散步——我的迫害者，您知道，当时也在我的身边。我落在了其他人的后面，要知道，迪河附近的乡间风景非常美丽。我们走的小路恰好位于一座煤矿附近，树林边缘有一口垂直的竖井，据说有一百五十英尺[7]深。我的侄女还在身后跟着我——当然，对于我痛苦的根源，她一无所知。然而，她知道我病了，行动不快。她就留了下来，以免我落单。我们俩一起慢慢地走走停停，陪伴我的那只畜生不断地怂恿我跳进那口竖井里。现在我可以告诉您——噢，先生，想想有多么可怕吧！——把我从可怕的死亡中拯救出来的唯一原因，是我担心如果那个可怜的女孩亲眼看见这一幕，会对她打击过大。我让她继续朝前走，到她的朋友们那里去。我说我没法儿再向前走了。她找了些借口。我越是催她，她越不肯走。她看上去又惊又怕。我猜想，一定是我的模样或是我的行为让她感到担忧。她坚持不肯离开，这实际上救了我一命。先生，您一定无法理解，一个活人怎么会沦落为撒旦的奴隶呢？”他说着，伴随着可怕的呻吟和颤抖。

他讲到这里停顿了下来，于是我说：“不过你还是得救了。这是上帝的意志。我主庇佑着你没有受到任何其他异端的支配：因此，对未来要有信心。”

[7]1英尺≈0.3米。——编者注

第十章　家

/

离开之前，我帮他点亮了蜡烛，让整个房间变得欢快一些，看起来像是有人居住的样子。我告诉他，他必须把自己的病情纯粹当成是与身体有关的原因，尽管是难以察觉的身体原因。我告诉他，他刚才描述的被解救的经过，就是得到上帝关爱的最好证明。而我痛苦地发现，他似乎把那特殊的一幕理解为自己已经走到了为神灵摈弃的地步。我坚持认为，这样的说法是毫无根据的。不仅如此，他在什罗浦郡远足时，神秘地摆脱了自杀的念头，这一事实更是与他的理解大相径庭。首先，尽管他并不打算让侄女一直在自己身旁，但是她却一直陪伴在他的左右。其次，在她面前实施那个可怕的建议，让他在心灵深处产生了无法抗拒的厌恶情绪。

随着我对詹宁斯先生一点一滴地娓娓道来，他不禁流下了眼泪，似乎感到备受安慰。我要求他答应我一件事，任何时候，只要那只猴子一回来，就立即通知我前来。我再三保证，在我彻底搞清楚他的病情前，不会在别的问题上浪费一点儿时间和精力，明天他就会知道结果的。然后，我才告辞。

走进马车车厢之前，我告诉仆人，他主人的状况很不好。他应该特别注意经常去他的房间查看查看。为了完全不受打扰，我自己也做了一番安排。

我只是去了一下住处，就带着一张旅行用的写字台和一个旅行袋，乘坐一辆出租马车，去了一个叫作“号角”的小旅馆，离镇上大约有两英里远。这是一所非常安静舒适的屋子，墙壁十分厚实。我下定决心，要在那舒适的客厅里，不受打扰，专心致志，把晚上几小时的时间都用来处理詹宁斯先生的病情，也许还需要加上第二天上午的不少时光。

（此处赫斯利乌斯医生详细记录了他对本病例的看法，以及他开出的生活习惯、膳食结构和药物方面的系列处方。这十分奇特——有些人也许会说太过神秘。但是，总体而言，我能遇到的那类读者，多半对此是不感兴趣的。因此也就没有必要在此一五一十地如数照抄了。这一整封信都是在他临时藏身的小旅馆里写的。而后一封信的落款地址，是他在镇上的住所。）

我是在前一天晚上九点半离开小镇，前往小旅馆的，直到第二天下午一点钟，才回到镇上的房间。我在桌上发现了一封詹宁斯先生的亲笔信，并不是通过邮局寄来的。询问之后，我得知那是詹宁斯先生的仆人送来的。当他知道我直到今天才会回来，并且没有人知道我的地址之后，似乎很不自在。他说，自己主人的命令是，没有得到答复前不得回去。

我打开信，读了起来：

尊敬的赫斯利乌斯医生，它来了。您离开还不到一小时，它就回来了。它说话了。对于发生的事情，它了如指掌。它全都知道，也知道您。它发狂了，穷凶极恶地大肆辱骂。我给您寄的这封信，它对每一个字都心知肚明———每一个字。因为我承诺过，所以才写了这封信，但是我担心写得语无伦次、不清不楚。我不停地被打断，心情烦躁不安。

您的永远诚挚的，

罗伯特·林德·詹宁斯

“信是什么时候送来的？”我问道。

“大约昨天夜里十一点。那个人又来了，今天已经来了三次了。上一次大约是一小时以前。”

听到这样的回答后，我几分钟内就跳上了前往里士满的马车去见詹宁斯先生，口袋里装着我写的关于他病情的笔记。

如你所知，对于詹宁斯先生的病情，我丝毫没有丧失希望。我在《玄医学》一书中写下的原则，是适用于所有病例的。他自己记住了那些原则，并采取了一些实践，虽然方法上错误甚多。我打算认认真真地实践一场。我对此很有兴趣，并渴望在“敌人”真正出现的时候，亲自对他检查一番。

我驱车来到那幢阴暗的房子，跑上台阶，叩响了大门。没过多久，门就开了。开门的是一位身着黑色丝绸的高个儿女子。她看上去一脸病容，似乎一直在哭。她行了个屈膝礼，听到我的问题后，却没有回答。她转过脸去，向两名正在下楼的男子伸出了手。她就这样默默地把我交给了他们，然后她匆忙穿过一扇侧门，并把门关上了。

我立刻和离大厅最近的那名男子搭话，但是走近之后，我震惊地发现，他的两只手上全是鲜血。

我退后了几步。那名正在下楼的男子，只是用低沉的嗓音说道：“仆人来了，先生。”

那名仆人在楼梯上停了下来，一看到我就不知所措、哑口无言。他用一块手绢搓着自己的双手，手绢上浸满了鲜血。

“琼斯，那是什么？发生了什么事？”我问道，疑虑之情涌上心头，不禁毛骨悚然。

那人叫我前去大厅。我立刻走到他的身边。他皱着眉，眯着眼，脸色苍白地和我讲述着我已经猜到一半的可怕遭遇。

他的主人自杀了。

我和他一起走进楼上的房间——那里的一幕令我无法启齿。他用剃刀割开了自己的喉咙。伤口令人不寒而栗。两人已经把他放到床上，整理好了他的四肢。地板上的一大摊血迹表明，悲剧是在床和窗户之间的地方发生的。床铺的四周铺着地毯，梳妆台下面也铺着，但地板上的其他地方却没有，因为他说过他不喜欢在卧室里铺地毯。这间房间本就阴暗，现在又平添了几分可怕的成分。这幢房子原本就被一棵棵大榆树遮住了阳光。现在，一根粗枝的阴影正缓慢地在那可怖的地板上移动着。

我向仆人示意，我们一起下了楼。我关上大厅的门，进入一间老式的镶板房间。站在那里，我听完了仆人讲述的故事。可讲的并不多。

“先生，从您昨晚离开时的言谈和神色来看，我断定您认为我的主人病得很重。我想，也许您是担心他突然发作，或是别的什么事情。所以我完全遵从了您的指示。他熬夜到很晚，一直到三点过后。他并不是在写东西，也没有看书。他一直在自言自语，但那也不是什么稀奇事了。大约在那个时候，我帮他脱了衣服，给他换上了拖鞋和睡袍。大约半小时后，我轻手轻脚地走了回去。他赤身裸体地躺在床上，床边的桌子上点着一对蜡烛。我进去的时候，他正倚着胳膊肘，看着床的另一边。我问他想要些什么，他回答说不用。

“先生，我不知道那是否就是您对我说的，还是他有些不同寻常的地方。但是昨晚，我对他感到不安，非同寻常的不安。

“又过了半小时，也许还要久一点儿，我又一次起身。我没有听见他像刚才那样讲话。我把门打开了一点儿。两支蜡烛都熄灭了，这不同往常。我有一支放在卧室的蜡烛，我让光线稍稍照进去，轻轻地环顾四周。我看见他坐在梳妆台旁边的椅子上，衣服又都穿好了。他转过身来看着我。我觉得奇怪的是，他竟然穿衣服起床，然后灭掉蜡烛，那样坐在黑暗里。但是我只是又问了一遍，有什么我可以做的。他说，不用。听起来相当刺耳。我问他，是否需要点蜡烛，他说，‘随你的便，琼斯’。于是我点亮了蜡烛，在房间里踱来踱去。他说：‘和我说实话，琼斯。你为什么又来了，是听见有人在咒骂吗？’‘没有，先生。’我说，搞不清楚他是什么意思。

“‘没有，’他跟着我说道，‘当然没有。’我对他说，‘您到床上去不好吗，先生？现在才五点钟’。他什么也没有回答，只是说，‘很可能会的。晚安，琼斯’。于是我就走了，先生。但是还不到一小时，我又去了。门关得紧紧的。他听见了我的声音，问我想要做什么。我想那声音是从床上传来的。他希望我不要再去打扰他。我躺下睡了一会儿。我再次起来的时候，大约是六点多钟不到七点的样子。门还是关得紧紧的，他没有作声。我想他大概是睡着了，就不想再去打扰他了。九点钟的时候，我才又去看了看。他的习惯是希望叫我来的时候，会打铃。我并没有叫醒他的专门时间。我轻轻地拍了拍门，没有回音。我离开了好一会儿，以为他一定是在休息。直到十一点，我才真的担心起他来——因为在我的印象里，他最迟也没有睡到过十点半以后。没有一点儿回音。我又是敲门，又是叫嚷，但还是没有回音。因为推不开门，我便从马厩叫来了汤姆斯。我们合力打开了门，于是发现了他那副令人震惊的样子。”

琼斯没有什么可说的了。可怜的詹宁斯先生非常和蔼可亲。所有人都很喜欢他。我看得出，那名仆人被深深触动了。

于是，我垂头丧气、焦虑不安地走出那座可怕的房子，也走出了那片黑暗的榆树林树荫。我希望自己今生再也不要看见这里了。我给你写信的时候，仿佛觉得自己还处在一个可怕而单调的梦境中，半梦半醒。因为怀疑和恐惧，我的记忆里容不下那幅画面。然而，我知道那些都是真的。这是一个有关毒药如何发挥作用的故事。那种毒药激发了心灵和神经的相互作用，并使得区分外部和内部感官功能的组织麻痹。就这样，我们发现了奇怪的“同床伴侣”，凡人和不朽者过早地相识了。

结论　致蒙受痛苦者

/

尊敬的范·洛，你曾经承受过那种病情的折磨，与我刚刚描述的相仿。你两次抱怨说，那个东西又回来了。

是谁，在上帝的指引下，治好了你？你卑微的仆人，马丁·赫斯利乌斯。请让我引用一位杰出的法国外科老医生在三百年前所说的无比虔诚的话：“治疗的是我，而治愈你的是上帝。”

来吧，朋友，打起精神。我来告诉你一个事实。

正如我在书里揭示的那样，我遇见、治疗过五十七个这类的视觉病例。我毫无差别地称呼它们为“理想化”“早熟性”与“精神性”的问题。

还有另外一类的病情，虽然通常会和我描述的那些相混淆，实际上被称为“幽灵幻觉”。在我看来，后者的治愈方法，并不比鼻炎或者轻微消化不良要复杂。

正是那些位居第一类的疑难杂症考验着我们的思维敏捷程度。我碰到过五十七个这类的病例，不多也不少。而我治疗失败的情况有多少呢？一个也没有。

只要稍有耐心，并对医生抱有合理的信任，任何患者都无须承受死亡的折磨。这简直就是小菜一碟，并且是完全可以做到的。只要具备这些简单的条件，我认为治愈是理所当然的事情。

你要记住，我甚至还没有开始着手治疗詹宁斯先生的病情。我拥有充分的把握，可以在十八个月的时间里，完全治愈他，当然或许会延长到两年。有些病例迅速得以痊愈，而另一些则要费时费力许多。任何一位聪明的医生，只要他用心思考、勤勉努力，就一定能实现完美的治愈。

你知道我写过一篇短文《大脑的基本功能》。在文中，我通过无数的事实证明了，如我所想的那样，动脉和静脉的循环在构造上通过神经的可能性是极高的。如此考虑的话，在这个系统中，大脑就是心脏。因此，液体通过一种类型的神经传播，改变成其他形态通过另一种神经返回。这种液体在本质上是精神性的，虽然并不是无形的，但是如同我之前所说的，最多就像光或电的情况那样。

由于各种滥服滥用，例如习惯性服用绿茶这种药剂，这种液体在质量上可能会受到影响，在平衡方面更是频繁遭到破坏。这种液体的存在，令我们与灵魂有了共处之处。它是在大部分大脑或神经上发现的一种充血，与内部感官相连，毫无必要地形成一个暴露的表面，脱离肉体的灵魂可以在其上运行：于是就或多或少地建立起一种有效的沟通渠道。在这种大脑循环和心脏循环之间存在一种密切的相互作用。外部视觉的核心，或者说重要因素，是眼睛。内部视觉的核心是神经组织和大脑，就位于眉毛的周围和上部。我只是用冰镇古龙水外敷，就驱散了你的幻影。效果有多棒，你还记得吗？然而，病例的治疗可以依样画葫芦的情况是极少的，也不是都能够快速见效的。神经液体对于寒冷具有强烈的排斥作用。持续的时间足够长，它甚至能导致永久性失去知觉的情况，我们称为麻痹。时间再久一点儿，会发生肌肉和感官的瘫痪。

我再说一遍，我毫不怀疑，自己应该首先让詹宁斯先生无意间开启的内在的眼睛变得暗淡，并最终把它完全封闭。因震颤性谵妄打开的相同感官，当大脑以及心脏出现过度活跃症状，并伴随着惊人的神经充血现象时，就会再度完全关闭，并且因为身体状况的明显改变而彻底停止。只要持续在身体上采用一个简单的方法，就能产生这样的结果——必然会出现这样的结果——我从未失败过。

可怜的詹宁斯先生自杀了。但是，这一灾难是另一种完全不同的疾病造成的，可以说，那种疾病将自身投射于另一种已经确认的病痛之上。他的病情明显表现为并发症，真正压垮他的疾病，是遗传性自杀癖。我不能称呼可怜的詹宁斯先生为我的病人，因为我甚至还没有开始对他的治疗。并且我确信，他也没有给予我充分的、毫无保留的信任。只要病人不站在疾病那一边，治愈就是一桩水到渠成的事情。

Prologue MARTIN HESSElIUS, THE GERMAN PHYSICIAN

Though carefully educated in medicine and surgery, I have never practised either. The study of each continues, never-theless, to interest me profoundly. Neither idleness nor caprice caused my secession from the honourable calling which I had just entered. The cause was a very trifling scratch inflicted by a dissecting knife. This trifle cost me the loss of two fingers, amputated promptly, and the more painful loss of my health, for I have never been quite well since, and have seldom been twelve months together in the same place.

In my wanderings I became acquainted with Dr Martin Hesselius, a wanderer like myself, like me a physician, and like me an enthusiast in his profession. Unlike me in this, that his wanderings were voluntary, and he a man, if not of fortune, as we estimate fortune in England, at least in what our forefathers used to term ‘easy circumstances. 'He was an old man when I first saw him; nearly five-and-thirty years my senior.

In Dr Martin Hesselius, I found my master. His know-ledge was immense, his grasp of a case was an intuition. He was the very man to inspire a young enthusiast, like me, with awe and delight. My admiration has stood the test of time and survived the separation of death. I am sure it was well-founded.

For nearly twenty years I acted as his medical secretary. His immense collection of papers he has left in my care, to be arranged, indexed and bound. His treatment of some of these cases is curious. He writes in two distinct characters. He describes what he saw and heard as an intelligent layman might, and when in this style of narrative he had seen the patient either through his own hall-door, to the light of day, or through the gates of darkness to the caverns of the dead, he returns upon the narrative, and in the terms of his art, and with all the force and originality of genius, proceeds to the work of analysis, diagnosis and illustration.

Here and there a case strikes me as of a kind to amuse or horrify a lay reader with an interest quite diferent from the peculiar one which it may possess for an expert. With slight modifcations, chiefy of language, and of course a change of names, I copy the following. The narrator is Dr Martin Hesselius. I fnd it among the voluminous notes of cases which he made during a tour in England about sixty-four years ago.

It is related in a series of letters to his friend Professor Van Loo of Leyden. The professor was not a physician, but a chemist, and a man who read history and metaphysics and medicine, and had, in his day, written a play.

The narrative is therefore, if somewhat less valuable as a medical record, necessarily written in a manner more likely to interest an unlearned reader.

Tese letters, from a memorandum attached, appear to have been returned on the death of the professor, in 1819,to Dr Hesselius. Tey are written, some in English, some in French, but the greater part in German. I am a faithful, though I am conscious, by no means a graceful translator, and although here and there, I omit some passages, and shorten others and disguise names, I have interpolated nothing.

Chapter I DR HESSElIUS RElATES HOW HE MET THE REv.MR JENNINGS

The Rev. Mr Jennings is tall and thin. He is middle-aged, and dresses with a natty, old-fashioned, high-church preci-sion. He is naturally a little stately, but not at all stiff. His features, without being handsome, are well formed, and their expression extremely kind, but also shy.

I met him one evening at Lady Mary Heyduke's. The mod-esty and benevolence of his countenance are extremely prepossessing.

We were but a small party, and he joined agreeably enough in the conversation. He seems to enjoy listening very much more than contributing to the talk; but what he says is always to the purpose and well said. He is a great favour-ite of Lady Mary's, who it seems, consults him upon many things, and thinks him the most happy and blessed person on earth. Little knows she about him.

The Rev. Mr Jennings is a bachelor, and has, they say, sixty thousand pounds in the funds. He is a charitable man. He is most anxious to be actively employed in his sacred profession, and yet though always tolerably well elsewhere, when he goes down to his vicarage in Warwickshire, to engage in the actual duties of his sacred calling his health soon fails him, and in a very strange way. So says Lady Mary.

There is no doubt that Mr Jennings'health does break down in, generally a sudden and mysterious way, sometimes in the very act of officiating in his old and pretty church at Kenlis. It may be his heart, it may be his brain. But so it has happened three or four times, or oftener, that after proceed-ing a certain way in the service, he has on a sudden stopped short, and after a silence, apparently quite unable to resume, he has fallen into solitary, inaudible prayer, his hands and eyes uplifted, and then pale as death, and in the agitation of a strange shame and horror, descended trembling, and got into the vestry-room, leaving his congregation, without explanation, to themselves. This occurred when his curate was absent. When he goes down to Kenlis, now, he always takes care to provide a clergyman to share his duty, and to supply his place on the instant should he become thus sud-denly incapacitated.

When Mr Jennings breaks down quite, and beats a retreat from the vicarage, and returns to London, where, in a dark street off Piccadilly, he inhabits a very narrow house, Lady Mary says that he is always perfectly well. I have my own opinion about that. There are degrees of course. We shall see.

Mr Jennings is a perfectly gentleman-like man. People, however, remark something odd. There is an impression a little ambiguous. One thing which certainly contributes to it, people I think don't remember; or, perhaps, distinctly remark. But I did, almost immediately. Mr Jennings has a way of looking sidelong upon the carpet, as if his eye followed the movements of something there. Tis, of course, is not always. It occurs only now and then. But often enough to give a certain oddity, as I have said to his manner, and in this glance travelling along the foor there is something both shy and anxious.

A medical philosopher, as you are good enough to call me, elaborating theories by the aid of cases sought out by himself, and by him watched and scrutinized with more time at command, and consequently infnitely more minute-ness than the ordinary practitioner can aford, falls insensibly into habits of observation, which accompany him everywhere, and are exercised, as some people would say, impertinently, upon every subject that presents itself with the least likelihood of rewarding inquiry.

Tere was a promise of this kind in the slight, timid, kindly, but reserved gentleman, whom I met for the frst time at this agreeable little evening gathering. I observed, of course, more than I here set down; but I reserve all that borders on the technical for a strictly scientifc paper.

I may remark, that when I here speak of medical science, I do so, as I hope some day to see it more generally under-stood, in a much more comprehensive sense than its generally material treatment would warrant. I believe the entire natural world is but the ultimate expression of that spiritual world from which, and in which alone, it has its life. I believe that the essential man is a spirit, that the spirit is an organized substance, but as diferent in point of mater-ial from what we ordinarily understand by matter, as light or electricity is; that the material body is, in the most literal sense, a vesture, and death consequently no interruption of the living man's existence, but simply his extrication from the natural body - a process which commences at the moment of what we term death, and the completion of which, at furthest a few days later, is the resurrection ‘in power.'

The person who weighs the consequences of these pos-itions will probably see their practical bearing upon medical science. This is, however, by no means the proper place for displaying the proofs and discussing the consequences of this too generally unrecognized state of facts.

In pursuance of my habit, I was covertly observing Mr Jennings, with all my caution - I think he perceived it - and I saw plainly that he was as cautiously observing me. Lady Mary happening to address me by my name, as Dr Hesse-lius, I saw that he glanced at me more sharply, and then became thoughtful for a few minutes.

After this, as I conversed with a gentleman at the other end of the room, I saw him look at me more steadily, and with an interest which I thought I understood. I then saw him take an opportunity of chatting with Lady Mary, and was, as one always is, perfectly aware of being the subject of a distant inquiry and answer.

This tall clergyman approached me by-and-by: and in a little time we had got into conversation. When two people, who like reading, and know books and places, having trav-elled, wish to converse, it is very strange if they can't find topics. It was not accident that brought him near me, and led him into conversation. He knew German, and had read my Essays on Metaphysical Medicine which suggest more than they actually say.

This courteous man, gentle, shy, plainly a man of thought and reading, who moving and talking among us, was not altogether of us, and whom I already suspected of leading a life whose transactions and alarms were carefully con-cealed, with an impenetrable reserve from, not only the world, but his best beloved friends - was cautiously weigh-ing in his own mind the idea of taking a certain step with regard to me.

I penetrated his thoughts without his being aware of it, and was careful to say nothing which could betray to his sensitive vigilance my suspicions respecting his position, or my surmises about his plans respecting myself.

We chatted upon indifferent subjects for a time; but at last he said:

‘I was very much interested by some papers of yours, Dr Hesselius, upon what you term Metaphysical Medicine - I read them in German, ten or twelve years ago-have they been translated?'

‘No, I'm sure they have not - I should have heard. They would have asked my leave, I think.'

‘I asked the publishers here, a few months ago, to get the book for me in the original German; but they tell me it is out of print.'

‘So it is, and has been for some years; but it flatters me as an author to find that you have not forgotten my little book, although,' I added, laughing, ‘ten or twelve years is a con-siderable time to have managed without it; but I suppose you have been turning the subject over again in your mind, or something has happened lately to revive your inter-est in it.'

At this remark, accompanied by a glance of inquiry, a sudden embarrassment disturbed Mr Jennings, analogous to that which makes a young lady blush and look foolish. He dropped his eyes, and folded his hands together uneas-ily, and looked oddly, and you would have said, guiltily for a moment.

I helped him out of his awkwardness in the best way, by appearing not to observe it, and going straight on, I said: ‘Those revivals of interest in a subject happen to me often; one book suggests another, and often sends me back on a wild-goose chase over an interval of twenty years. But if you still care to possess a copy, I shall be only too happy to pro-vide you; I have still got two or three by me - and if you allow me to present one I shall be very much honoured.'

‘You are very good indeed,' he said, quite at his ease again, in a moment: ‘I almost despaired - I don't know how to thank you.'

‘Pray don't say a word; the thing is really so little worth that I am only ashamed of having offered it, and if you thank me any more I shall throw it into the fire in a fit of modesty.'

Mr Jennings laughed. He inquired where I was staying in London, and after a little more conversation on a variety of subjects, he took his departure.

Chapter II THE DOCTOR QUESTIONS lADY MARY, AND SHE ANSWERS

‘I like your vicar so much, Lady Mary,' said I, so soon as he was gone. ‘He has read, travelled, and thought, and having also suffered, he ought to be an accomplished companion.'

‘So he is, and, better still, he is a really good man,' said she. ‘His advice is invaluable about my schools, and all my little undertakings at Dawlbridge, and he's so painstaking, he takes so much trouble - you have no idea - wherever he thinks he can be of use: he's so good-natured and so sensible.'

‘It is pleasant to hear so good an account of his neigh-bourly virtues. I can only testify to his being an agreeable and gentle companion, and in addition to what you have told me, I think I can tell you two or three things about him,' said I.

‘Really!'

‘Yes, to begin with, he's unmarried.'

‘Yes, that's right, - go on.'

‘He has been writing, that is he was, but for two or three years perhaps, he has not gone on with his work, and the book was upon some rather abstract subject - perhaps theology.'

‘Well, he was writing a book, as you say; I'm not quite sure what it was about, but only that it was nothing that I cared for, very likely you are right, and he certainly did stop - yes.'

‘And although he only drank a little coffee here to-night, he likes tea, at least, did like it, extravagantly.'

‘Yes, that'squitetrue.'

‘He drank green tea, a good deal, didn't he?' I pursued.

‘Well, that's very odd! Green tea was a subject on which we used almost to quarrel.'

‘But he has quite given that up,' said I.

‘So he has.'

‘And, now, one more fact. His mother or his father, did you know them?'

‘Yes, both; his father is only ten years dead, and their place is near Dawlbridge. We knew them very well,' she answered.

‘Well, either his mother or his father - I should rather think his father, saw a ghost,' said I.

‘Well, you really are a conjurer, Dr Hesselius.'

‘Conjurer or no, haven't I said right?' I answered merrily.

‘You certainly have, and it was his father: he was a silent, whimsical man, and he used to bore my father about his dreams, and at last he told him a story about a ghost he had seen and talked with, and a very odd story it was. I remem-ber it particularly, because I was so afraid of him. This story was long before he died - when I was quite a child - and his ways were so silent and moping, and he used to drop in, sometimes, in the dusk, when I was alone in the drawing-room, and I used to fancy there were ghosts about him.'

I smiled and nodded.

‘And now having established my character as a conjurer I think I must say good-night,' said I.

‘But howdidyou find it out?'

‘By the planets of course, as the gipsies do,' I answered, and so, gaily, we said good-night.

Next morning I sent the little book he had been inquiring after, and a note to Mr Jennings, and on returning late that evening, I found that he had called, at my lodgings, and left his card. He asked whether I was at home, and asked at what hour he would be most likely to find me.

Does he intend opening his case, and consulting me ‘pro-fessionally,' as they say? I hope so. I have already conceived a theory about him. It is supported by Lady Mary's answers to my parting questions. I should like much to ascertain from his own lips. But what can I do consistently with good breeding to invite a confession?Nothing. I rather think he meditates one. At all events, my dear Van L. , I shan't make myself difficult of access; I mean to return his visit to-morrow. It will be only civil in return for his politeness, to ask to see him. Perhaps something may come of it. Whether much, little, or nothing, my dear Van L. ,you shall hear.

Chapter III DR HESSElIUS PICkS UP SOMETHING IN lATIN BOOkS

Well, I have called at Blank-street.

On inquiring at the door, the servant told me that Mr Jennings was engaged very particularly with a gentleman, a clergyman from Kenlis, his parish in the country. Intend-ing to reserve my privilege and to call again, I merely intimated that I should try another time, and had turned to go, when the servant begged my pardon, and asked me, looking at me a little more attentively than well-bred persons of his order usually do, whether I was Dr Hesselius; and, on learning that I was, he said, ‘Perhaps then, sir, you would allow me to mention it to Mr Jennings, for I am sure he wishes to see you.'

The servant returned in a moment, with a message from Mr Jennings, asking me to go into his study, which was in effect his back drawing-room, promising to be with me in a very few minutes.

This was really a study - almost a library. The room was lofty, with two tall slender windows, and rich dark curtains. It was much larger than I had expected, and stored with books on every side, from the floor to the ceiling. The upper carpet - for to my tread it felt that there were two or three - was a Turkey carpet. My steps fell noiselessly. The book-cases standing out, placed the windows, particularly narrow ones, in deep recesses. The effect of the room was, although extremely comfortable, and even luxurious, decidedly gloomy, and aided by the silence, almost oppres-sive. Perhaps, however, I ought to have allowed something for association. My mind had connected peculiar ideas with Mr Jennings. I stepped into this perfectly silent room, of a very silent house, with a peculiar foreboding; and its dark-ness, and solemn clothing of books, for except where two narrow looking-glasses were set in the wall, they were every-where, helped this sombre feeling.

While awaiting Mr Jennings'arrival, I amused myself by looking into some of the books with which his shelves were laden. Not among these, but immediately under them, with their backs upward, on the floor, I lighted upon a complete set of Swedenborg's Arcana Cælestia, in the original Latin, a very fine folio set, bound in the natty livery which the-ology affects, pure vellum, namely, gold letters, and carmine edges. There were paper markers in several of these volumes, I raised and placed them, one after the other, upon the table, and opening where these papers were placed, I read in the solemn Latin phraseology, a series of sentences indicated by a pencilled line at the margin. Of these I copy here a few, translating them into English.

‘When man's interior sight is opened, which is that of his spirit, then there appear the things of another life, which cannot possibly be made visible to the bodily sight. '……

‘By the internal sight it has been granted me to see the things that are in the other life, more clearly than I see thosethat are in the world. From these considerations, it is evident that external vision exists from interior vision, and this from a vision still more interior, and so on. '……

‘There are with every man at least two evil spirits. '……

‘With wicked genii there is also a fluent speech, but harsh and grating. There is also among them a speech which is not fluent, wherein the dissent of the thoughts is perceived as something secretly creeping along within it. '……

‘The evil spirits associated with man are, indeed, from the hells, but when with man they are not then in hell, but are taken out thence. The place where they then are is in the midst between heaven and hell, and is called the world of spirits - when the evil spirits who are with man, are in that world, they are not in any infernal torment, but in every thought and affection of the man, and so, in all that the man himself enjoys. But when they are remitted into their hell, they return to their former state. '……

‘If evil spirits could perceive that they were associated with man, and yet that they were spirits separate from him, and if they could flow in into the things of his body, they would attempt by a thousand means to destroy him; for they hate man with a deadly hatred. '……

‘Knowing, therefore, that I was a man in the body, they were continually striving to destroy me, not as to the body only, but especially as to the soul; for to destroy any man or spirit is the very delight of the life of all who are in hell; but I have been continually protected by the Lord. Hence it appears how dangerous it is for man to be in a living consort with spirits, unless he be in the good of faith. '……

‘Nothing is more carefully guarded from the knowledge of associate spirits than their being thus conjoint with a man, for if they knew it they would speak to him, with the intention to destroy him. '……

‘The delight of hell is to do evil to man, and to hasten his eternal ruin.'

A long note, written with a very sharp and fine pencil, in Mr Jennings' neat hand, at the foot of the page, caught my eye. Expecting his criticism upon the text, I read a word or two, and stopped, for it was something quite different, and began with these words, Deus misereatur mei - 'May God compassionate me. 'Thus warned of its private nature, I averted my eyes, and shut the book, replacing all the vol-umes as I had found them, except one which interested me, and in which, as men studious and solitary in their habits will do, I grew so absorbed as to take no cognizance of the outer world, nor to remember where I was.

I was reading some pages which refer to ‘representatives' and ‘correspondents,' in the technical language of Sweden-borg, and had arrived at a passage, the substance of which is, that evil spirits, when seen by other eyes than those of their infernal associates, present themselves, by‘correspond-ence,' in the shape of the beast (fera) which represents their particular lust and life, in aspect direful and atrocious. This is a long passage, and particularizes a number of those bes-tial forms.

Chapter IV FOUR EYES WERE READING THE PASSAGE

I was running the head of my pencil-case along the line as I read it, and something caused me to raise my eyes.

Directly before me was one of the mirrors I have men-tioned, in which I saw reflected the tall shape of my friend Mr Jennings leaning over my shoulder, and reading the page at which I was busy, and with a face so dark and wild that I should hardly have known him.

I turned and rose. He stood erect also, and with an effort laughed a little, saying:

‘I came in and asked you how you did, but without suc-ceeding in awaking you from your book; so I could not restrain my curiosity, and very impertinently, I'm afraid, peeped over your shoulder. This is not your first time of looking into those pages. You have looked into Swedenborg, no doubt, long ago?'

‘Oh dear, yes! I owe Swedenborg a great deal; you will discover traces of him in the little book on Metaphysical Medicine, which you were so good as to remember.'

Although my friend affected a gaiety of manner, there was a slight flush in his face, and I could perceive that he was inwardly much perturbed.

‘I'm scarcely yet qualified, I know so little of Swedenborg. I've only had them a fortnight,' he answered, ‘and I think they are rather likely to make a solitary man nervous - that is, judging from the very little I have read - I don't say that they have made me so,' he laughed; ‘and I'm so very much obliged for the book. I hope you got my note?'

I made all proper acknowledgments and modest disclaimers.

‘I never read a book that I go with, so entirely, as that of yours,' he continued. ‘I saw at once there is more in it than is quite unfolded. Do you know Dr Harley?' he asked, rather abruptly.

In passing, the editor remarks that the physician here named was one of the most eminent who had ever practised in England.

I did, having had letters to him, and had experienced from him great courtesy and considerable assistance during my visit to England.

‘I think that man one of the very greatest fools I ever met in my life,' said Mr Jennings.

This was the first time I had ever heard him say a sharp thing of anybody, and such a term applied to so high a name a little startled me.

‘Really! and in what way?' I asked.

‘In his profession,' he answered.

I smiled.

‘I mean this,' he said: ‘he seems to me, one half, blind - I mean one half of all he looks at is dark - preternaturally bright and vivid all the rest; and the worst of it is, it seems wilful. I can't get him - I mean he won't - I've had some experience of him as a physician, but I look on him as, in that sense, no better than a paralytic mind, an intellect half dead, I'll tell you - I know I shall some time - all about it,' he said, with a little agitation. ‘You stay some months longer in England. If I should be out of town during your stay for a little time, would you allow me to trouble you with a letter?'

‘I should be only too happy,' I assured him.

‘Very good of you. I am so utterly dissatisfied with Harley.'

‘A little leaning to the materialistic school,' I said.

‘Amerematerialist,' he corrected me; ‘you can't think how that sort of thing worries one who knows better. You won't tell any one - any of my friends you know - that I am hip-pish; now, for instance, no one knows - not even Lady Mary - that I have seen Dr Harley, or any other doctor. So pray don't mention it; and, if I should have any threatening of an attack, you'll kindly let me write, or, should I be in town, have a little talk with you.'

I was full of conjecture, and unconsciously I found I had fixed my eyes gravely on him, for he lowered his for a moment, and he said:

‘I see you think I might as well tell you now, or else you are forming a conjecture; but you may as well give it up. If you were guessing all the rest of your life, you will never hit on it.'

He shook his head smiling, and over that wintry sunshine a black cloud suddenly came down, and he drew his breath in, through his teeth as men do in pain.

‘Sorry, of course, to learn that you apprehend occasion to consult any of us; but, command me when and how you like, and I need not assure you that your confdence is sacred.'

He then talked of quite other things, and in a compara-tively cheerful way and after a little time, I took my leave.

Chapter V DOCTOR HESSElIUS IS SUMMONED TO RICHMOND

We parted cheerfully, but he was not cheerful, nor was I. There are certain expressions of that powerful organ of spirit - the human face - which, although I have seen them often, and possess a doctor's nerve, yet disturb me pro-foundly. One look of Mr Jennings haunted me. It had seized my imagination with so dismal a power that I changed my plans for the evening, and went to the opera, feeling that I wanted a change of ideas.

I heard nothing of or from him for two or three days, when a note in his hand reached me. It was cheerful, and full of hope. He said that he had been for some little time so much better - quite well, in fact - that he was going to make a little experiment, and run down for a month or so to his parish, to try whether a little work might not quite set him up. There was in it a fervent religious expression of gratitude for his restoration, as he now almost hoped he might call it.

A day or two later I saw Lady Mary, who repeated what his note had announced, and told me that he was actually in Warwickshire, having resumed his clerical duties at Ken-lis; and she added, ‘I begin to think that he is really perfectly well, and that there never was anything the matter, more than nerves and fancy; we are all nervous, but I fancy there is nothing like a little hard work for that kind of weakness, and he has made up his mind to try it. I should not be sur-prised if he did not come back for a year.'

Notwithstanding all this confidence, only two days later I had this note, dated from his house off Piccadilly:

Dear Sir.- I have returned disappointed. If I should feel at all able to see you, I shall write to ask you kindly to call. At present I am too low, and, in fact, simply unable to say all I wish to say. Pray don't mention my name to my friends. I can see no one. By-and-by, please God, you shall hear from me. I mean to take a run into Shropshire, where some of my people are. God bless you! May we, on my return, meet more happily than I can now write.

About a week after this I saw Lady Mary at her own house, the last person, she said, left in town, and just on the wing for Brighton, for the London season was quite over. She told me that she had heard from Mr Jennings'niece, Martha, in Shropshire. There was nothing to be gathered from her let-ter, more than that he was low and nervous. In those words, of which healthy people think so lightly, what a world of suffering is sometimes hidden!

Nearly five weeks passed without any further news of Mr Jennings. At the end of that time I received a note from him. He wrote:

I have been in the country, and have had change of air, change of scene, change of faces, change of everything and in everything - but myself. I have made up my mind, so far as

the most irresolute creature on earth can do it, to tell my case fully to you. If your engagements will permit, pray come to me to-day, to-morrow, or the next day; but, pray defer as little as possible. You know not how much I need help. I have a quiet house at Richmond, where I now am. Perhaps you can manage to come to dinner, or to luncheon, or even to tea. You shall have no trouble in fnding me out. The servant at Blank street, who takes this note, will have a carriage at your door at any hour you please; and I am always to be found. You will say that I ought not to be alone. I have tried everything. Come and see.

I called up the servant, and decided on going out the same evening, which accordingly I did.

He would have been much better in a lodging-house, or hotel, I thought, as I drove up through a short double row of sombre elms to a very old-fashioned brick house, dark-ened by the foliage of these trees, which over-topped, and nearly surrounded it. It was a perverse choice, for nothing could be imagined more triste and silent. The house, I found, belonged to him. He had stayed for a day or two in town, and, fnding it for some cause insupportable, had come out here, probably because being furnished and his own, he was relieved of the thought and delay of selection, by coming here.

The sun had already set, and the red refected light of the western sky illuminated the scene with the peculiar efect with which we are all familiar. The hall seemed very dark, but, getting to the back drawing-room, whose windows com-mand the west, I was again in the same dusky light.

I sat down, looking out upon the richly-wooded landscape that glowed in the grand and melancholy light which was every moment fading. The corners of the room were already dark; all was growing dim, and the gloom was insensibly toning my mind, already prepared for what was sinister. I was waiting alone for his arrival, which soon took place. The door communicating with the front room opened, and the tall fgure of Mr Jennings, faintly seen in the ruddy twi-light, came, with quiet stealthy steps, into the room.

We shook hands, and, taking a chair to the window, where there was still light enough to enable us to see each other's faces, he sat down beside me, and, placing his hand upon my arm, with scarcely a word of preface began his narrative.

Chapter VI HOW MR JENNINGS MET HIS COMPANION

The faint glow of the west, the pomp of the then lonely woods of Richmond, were before us, behind and about us the darkening room, and on the stony face of the sufferer - for the character of his face, though still gentle and sweet, was changed - rested that dim, odd glow which seems to descend and produce, where it touches, lights, sudden though faint, which are lost, almost without gradation, in darkness. The silence, too, was utter; not a distant wheel, or bark, or whistle from without; and within the depressing stillness of an invalid bachelor's house.

I guessed well the nature, though not even vaguely the particulars of the revelations I was about to receive, from that fixed face of suffering that so oddly flushed stood out, like a portrait of Schalken's, before its background of darkness.

‘It began,' he said, ‘on the 15th of October, three years and eleven weeks ago, and two days - I keep very accurate count, for every day is torment. If I leave anywhere a chasm in my narrative tell me.

‘About four years ago I began a work, which had cost me very much thought and reading. It was upon the religious metaphysics of the ancients.'

‘I know,' said I; ‘the actual religion of educated and think-ing paganism, quite apart from symbolic worship?A wide and very interesting field.'

‘Yes; but not good for the mind - the Christian mind, I mean. Paganism is all bound together in essential unity, and, with evil sympathy, their religion involves their art, and both their manners, and the subject is a degrading fas-cination and the nemesis sure. God forgive me!

‘I wrote a great deal; I wrote late at night. I was always thinking on the subject, walking about, wherever I was, everywhere. It thoroughly infected me. You are to remember that all the material ideas connected with it were more or less of the beautiful, the subject itself delightfully interest-ing, and I, then, without a care.'

He sighed heavily.

‘I believe that every one who sets about writing in earnest does his work, as a friend of mine phrased it, on something - tea, or coffee, or tobacco. I suppose there is a material waste that must be hourly supplied in such occupations, or that we should grow too abstracted, and the mind, as it were, pass out of the body, unless it were reminded often of the connection by actual sensation. At all events, I felt the want, and I supplied it. Tea was my companion - at first the ordin-ary black tea, made in the usual way, not too strong: but I drank a good deal, and increased its strength as I went on. I never experienced an uncomfortable symptom from it. I began to take a little green tea. I found the effect pleasanter, it cleared and intensified the power of thought so. I had come to take it frequently, but not stronger than one might take it for pleasure. I wrote a great deal out here, it was so quiet, and in this room. I used to sit up very late, and it became a habit with me to sip my tea - green tea - every now and then as my work proceeded. I had a little kettle on my table, that swung over a lamp, and made tea two or three times between eleven o'clock and two or three in the morn-ing, my hours of going to bed. I used to go into town every day. I was not a monk, and, although I spent an hour or two in a library, hunting up authorities and looking out lights upon my theme, I was in no morbid state as far as I can judge. I met my friends pretty much as usual, and enjoyed their society, and, on the whole, existence had never been, I think, so pleasant before.

‘I had met with a man who had some odd old books, Ger-man editions in mediæval Latin, and I was only too happy to be permitted access to them. This obliging person's books were in the City, a very out-of-the-way part of it. I had rather out-stayed my intended hour, and, on coming out, seeing no cab near, I was tempted to get into the omnibus which used to drive past this house. It was darker than this by the time the bus had reached an old house, you may have remarked, with four poplars at each side of the door, and there the last passenger but myself got out. We drove along rather faster. It was twilight now. I leaned back in my corner next the door ruminating pleasantly.

‘The interior of the omnibus was nearly dark. I had observed in the corner opposite to me at the other side, and at the end next the horses, two small circular reflections, as it seemed to me of a reddish light. They were about two inches apart, and about the size of those small brass buttons that yachting men used to put upon their jackets. I began to speculate, as listless men will, upon this trifle, as it seemed. From what centre did that faint but deep red light come, and from what - glass beads, buttons, toy decorations - was it reflected?We were lumbering along gently, having nearly a mile still to go. I had not solved the puzzle, and it became in another minute more odd, for these two luminous points, with a sudden jerk, descended nearer the floor, keeping still their relative distance and horizontal position, and then, as suddenly, they rose to the level of the seat on which I was sitting, and I saw them no more.

‘My curiosity was now really excited, and, before I had time to think, I saw again these two dull lamps, again together near the floor; again they disappeared, and again in their old corner I saw them.

‘So, keeping my eyes upon them, I edged quietly up my own side, towards the end at which I still saw these tiny discs of red.

‘There was very little light in the'bus. It was nearly dark. I leaned forward to aid my endeavour to discover what these little circles really were. They shifted their position a little as I did so. I began now to perceive an outline of something black, and I soon saw with tolerable distinctness the outline of a small black monkey, pushing its face forward in mim-icry to meet mine; those were its eyes, and I now dimly saw its teeth grinning at me.

‘I drew back, not knowing whether it might not meditate a spring. I fancied that one of the passengers had forgot this ugly pet, and wishing to ascertain something of its temper, though not caring to trust my fingers to it, I poked my umbrella softly towards it. It remained immovable - up to it - throughit! For through it, and back and forward, it passed, without the slightest resistance.

‘I can't, in the least, convey to you the kind of horror that I felt. When I had ascertained that the thing was an illusion, as I then supposed, there came a misgiving about myself and a terror that fascinated me in impotence to remove my gaze from the eyes of the brute for some moments. As I looked, it made a little skip back, quite into the corner, and I, in a panic, found myself at the door, having put my head out, drawing deep breaths of the outer air, and staring at the lights and trees we were passing, too glad to reassure myself of reality.

‘I stopped the ’bus and got out. I perceived the man look oddly at me as I paid him. I daresay there was something unusual in my looks and manner, for I had never felt so strangely before.'

Chapter VII THE JOURNEY: FIRST STAGE

‘When the omnibus drove on, and I was alone upon the road, I looked carefully round to ascertain whether the monkey had followed me. To my indescribable relief I saw it nowhere. I can't describe easily what a shock I had received, and my sense of genuine gratitude on finding myself, as I supposed, quite rid of it.

‘I had got out a little before we reached this house, two or three hundred steps. A brick wall runs along the foot-path, and inside the wall is a hedge of yew or some dark evergreen of that kind, and within that again the row of fine trees which you may have remarked as you came.

‘This brick wall is about as high as my shoulder, and hap-pening to raise my eyes I saw the monkey, with that stooping gait, on all fours, walking or creeping, close beside me on top of the wall. I stopped, looking at it with a feeling of loathing and horror. As I stopped so did it. It sat up on the wall with its long hands on its knees looking at me. There was not light enough to see it much more than in outline, nor was it dark enough to bring the peculiar light of its eyes into strong relief. I still saw, however, that red foggy light plainly enough. It did not show its teeth, nor exhibit any sign of irritation, but seemed jaded and sulky, and was observing me steadily.

‘I drew back into the middle of the road. It was an uncon-scious recoil, and there I stood, still looking at it, it did not move.

‘With an instinctive determination to try something - anything, I turned about and walked briskly towards town with a skance look, all the time, watching the movements of the beast. It crept swiftly along the wall, at exactly my pace.

‘Where the wall ends, near the turn of the road, it came down and with a wiry spring or two brought itself close to my feet, and continued to keep up with me, as I quickened my pace. It was at my left side, so close to my leg that I felt every moment as if I should tread upon it.

‘The road was quite deserted and silent, and it was darker every moment. I stopped dismayed and bewildered, turning as I did so, the other way - I mean, towards this house, away from which I had been walking. When I stood still, the monkey drew back to a distance of, I suppose, about five or six yards, and remained stationary, watching me.

‘I had been more agitated than I have said. I had read, of course, as every one has, something about "spectral illu-sions, " as you physicians term the phenomena of such cases. I considered my situation, and looked my misfortune in the face.

‘These affections, I had read, are sometimes transitory and sometimes obstinate. I had read of cases in which the appearance, at first harmless, had, step by step, degenerated into something direful and insupportable, and ended by wearing its victim out. Still as I stood there, but for my bes-tial companion, quite alone, I tried to comfort myself by repeating again and again the assurance, "the thing is purely disease, a well-known physical afection, as distinctly as small-pox or neuralgia. Doctors are all agreed on that, philosophy demonstrates it. I must not be a fool. I've been sitting up too late, and I daresay my digestion is quite wrong, and with God's help, I shall be all right, and this is but a symptom of nervous dyspepsia." Did I believe all this?Not one word of it, no more than any other miserable being ever did who is once seized and riveted in this satanic cap-tivity. Against my convictions, I might say my knowledge, I was simply bullying myself into a false courage.

‘I now walked homeward. I had only a few hundred yards to go. I had forced myself into a sort of resignation, but I had not got over the sickening shock and the furry of the frst certainty of my misfortune.

‘I made up my mind to pass the night at home. The brute moved close beside me, and I fancied there was the sort of anxious drawing toward the house, which one sees in tired horses or dogs, sometimes as they come toward home.

‘I was afraid to go into town, I was afraid of any one's seeing and recognizing me. I was conscious of an irrepress-ible agitation in my manner. Also, I was afraid of any violent change in my habits, such as going to a place of amusement, or walking from home in order to fatigue myself. At the hall door it waited till I mounted the steps, and when the door was opened entered with me.

‘I drank no tea that night. I got cigars and some brandy-and-water. My idea was that I should act upon my material system, and by living for a while in sensation apart from thought, send myself forcibly, as it it were, into a new groove. I came up here to this drawing-room. I sat just here. The monkey then got upon a small table that then stood there. It looked dazed and languid. An irrepressible uneasi-ness as to its movements kept my eyes always upon it. Its eyes were half closed, but I could see them glow. It was looking steadily at me. In all situations, at all hours, it is awake and looking at me. That never changes.

‘I shall not continue in detail my narrative of this particu-lar night. I shall describe, rather, the phenomena of the first year, which never varied, essentially. I shall describe the monkey as it appeared in daylight. In the dark, as you shall presently hear, there are peculiarities. It is a small monkey, perfectly black. It had only one peculiarity - a character of malignity - unfathomable malignity. During the first year it looked sullen and sick. But this character of intense malice and vigilance was always underlying that surly languor. During all that time it acted as if on a plan of giving me as little trouble as was consistent with watching me. Its eyes were never off me. I have never lost sight of it, except in my sleep, light or dark, day or night, since it came here, excepting when it withdraws for some weeks at a time, unaccountably.

‘In total dark it is visible as in daylight. I do not mean merely its eyes. It isallvisible distinctly in a halo that resem-bles a glow of red embers, and which accompanies it in all its movements.

‘When it leaves me for a time, it is always at night, in the dark, and in the same way. It grows at first uneasy, and then furious, and then advances towards me, grinning and shak-ing its paws clenched, and, at the same time, there comes the appearance of fire in the grate. I never have any fire. I can't sleep in the room where there is any, and it draws nearer and nearer to the chimney, quivering, it seems, with rage, and when its fury rises to the highest pitch, it springs into the grate, and up the chimney, and I see it no more.

‘When first this happened I thought I was released. I was a new man. A day passed - a night - and no return, and a blessed week - a week - another week. I was always on my knees, Dr Hesselius, always, thanking God and praying. A whole month passed of liberty, but on a sudden, it was with me again.'

Chapter VIII THE SECOND STAGE

‘It was with me, and the malice which before was torpid under a sullen exterior, was now active. It was perfectly unchanged in every other respect. This new energy was apparent in its activity and its looks, and soon in other ways.

‘For a time, you will understand, the change was shown only in an increased vivacity, and an air of menace, as if it was always brooding over some atrocious plan. Its eyes, as before, were never off me.'

‘Is it here now?' I asked.

‘No,' he replied, ‘it has been absent exactly a fortnight and a day - fifteen days. It has sometimes been away so long as nearly two months, once for three. Its absence always exceeds a fortnight, although it may be but by a single day. Fifteen days having past since I saw it last, it may return now at any moment.'

‘Is its return,' I asked, ‘accompanied by any peculiar manifestation?'

‘Nothing - no,' he said. ‘It is simply with me again. On lifting my eyes from a book, or turning my head, I see it, as usual, looking at me, and then it remains, as before, for its appointed time. I have never told so much and so minutely before to any one.'

I perceived that he was agitated, and looking like death, and he repeatedly applied his handkerchief to his forehead; I suggested that he might be tired, and told him that I would call, with pleasure, in the morning, but he said:

‘No, if you don't mind hearing it all now. I have got so far, and I should prefer making one effort of it. When I spoke to Dr Harley, I had nothing like so much to tell. You are a philosophic physician. You give spirit its proper rank. If this thing is real -'

He paused, looking at me with agitated inquiry.

‘We can discuss it by-and-by, and very fully. I will give you all I think,' I answered, after an interval.

‘Well - very well. If it is anything real, I say, it is prevail-ing, little by little, and drawing me more interiorly into hell. Optic nerves, he talked of. Ah! well - there are other nerves of communication. May God Almighty help me! You shall hear.

‘Its power of action, I tell you, had increased. Its malice became, in a way aggressive. About two years ago, some questions that were pending between me and the bishop having been settled, I went down to my parish in Warwick-shire, anxious to find occupation in my profession. I was not prepared for what happened, although I have since thought I might have apprehended something like it. The reason of my saying so, is this -'

He was beginning to speak with a great deal more effort and reluctance, and sighed often, and seemed at times nearly overcome. But at this time his manner was not agitated. It was more like that of a sinking patient, who has given him-self up.

‘Yes, but I will first tell you about Kenlis, my parish.

‘It was with me when I left this place for Dawlbridge. It was my silent travelling companion, and it remained with me at the vicarage. When I entered on the discharge of my duties, another change took place. The thing exhibited an atrocious determination to thwart me. It was with me in the church - in the reading-desk - in the pulpit - within the communion rails. At last, it reached this extremity, that while I was reading to the congregation, it would spring upon the open book and squat there, so that I was unable to see the page. This happened more than once.

‘I left Dawlbridge for a time. I placed myself in Dr Har-ley's hands. I did everything he told me. He gave my case a great deal of thought. It interested him, I think. He seemed successful. For nearly three months I was perfectly free from a return. I began to think I was safe. With his full assent I returned to Dawlbridge.

‘I travelled in a chaise. I was in good spirits. I was more - I was happy and grateful. I was returning, as I thought delivered from a dreadful hallucination, to the scene of duties which I longed to enter upon. It was a beautiful sunny evening, everything looked serene and cheerful, and I was delighted. I remember looking out of the window to see the spire of my church at Kenlis among the trees, at the point where one has the earliest view of it. It is exactly where the little stream that bounds the parish passes under the road by a culvert, and where it emerges at the road-side, a stone with an old inscription is placed. As we passed this point, I drew my head in and sat down, and in the corner of the chaise was the monkey.

‘For a moment I felt faint, and then quite wild with des-pair and horror. I called to the driver, and got out, and sat down at the road-side, and prayed to God silently for mercy. A despairing resignation supervened. My companion was with me as I re-entered the vicarage. The same persecution followed. After a short struggle I submitted, and soon I left the place.

‘I told you,' he said, ‘that the beast has before this become in certain ways aggressive. I will explain a little. It seemed to be actuated by intense and increasing fury, whenever I said my prayers, or even meditated prayer. It amounted at last to a dreadful interruption. You will ask, how could a silent immaterial phantom effect that?It was thus, whenever I meditated praying; it was always before me, and nearer and nearer.

‘It used to spring on a table, on the back of a chair, on the chimney-piece, and slowly to swing itself from side to side, looking at me all the time. There is in its motion an indefin-able power to dissipate thought, and to contract one's attention to that monotony, till the ideas shrink, as it were, to a point, and at last to nothing - and unless I had started up, and shook off the catalepsy I have felt as if my mind were on the point of losing itself. There are other ways,' he sighed heavily; ‘thus, for instance, while I pray with my eyes closed, it comes closer and closer, and I see it. I know it is not to be accounted for physically, but I do actually see it, though my lids are closed, and so it rocks my mind, as it were, and overpowers me, and I am obliged to rise from my knees. If you had ever yourself known this, you would be acquainted with desperation.'

Chapter IX THE THIRD STAGE

‘I see, Dr Hesselius, that you don't lose one word of my statement. I need not ask you to listen specially to what I am now going to tell you. They talk of the optic nerves, and of spectral illusions, as if the organ of sight was the only point assailable by the influences that have fastened upon me - I know better. For two years in my direful case that limitation prevailed. But as food is taken in softly at the lips, and then brought under the teeth, as the tip of the little finger caught in a mill crank will draw in the hand, and the arm, and the whole body, so the miserable mortal who has been once caught firmly by the end of the finest fibre of his nerve, is drawn in and in, by the enormous machinery of hell, until he is as I am. Yes, Doctor, as I am, for while I talk to you, and implore relief, I feel that my prayer is for the impossible, and my pleading with the inexorable.'

I endeavoured to calm his visibly increasing agitation, and told him that he must not despair.

While we talked the night had overtaken us. The filmy moonlight was wide over the scene which the window com-manded, and I said:

‘Perhaps you would prefer having candles. This light, you know, is odd. I should wish you, as much as possible, under your usual conditions while I make my diagnosis, shall I call it - otherwise I don't care.'

‘All lights are the same to me,' he said: ‘except when I read or write, I care not if night were perpetual. I am going to tell you what happened about a year ago. The thing began to speak to me.'

‘Speak! How do you mean - speak as a man does, do you mean?'

‘Yes; speak in words and consecutive sentences, with per-fect coherence and articulation; but there is a peculiarity. It is not like the tone of a human voice. It is not by my ears it reaches me - it comes like a singing through my head.

‘This faculty, the power of speaking to me, will be my undoing. It won't let me pray, it interrupts me with dreadful blasphemies. I dare not go on, I could not. Oh! Doctor, can the skill, and thought, and prayers of man avail me nothing!'

‘You must promise me, my dear sir, not to trouble yourself with unnecessarily exciting thoughts; confine yourself strictly to the narrative of facts; and recollect, above all, that even if the thing that infests you be all you seem to suppose, a reality with an actual independent life and will, yet it can have no power to hurt you, unless it be given from above: its access to your senses depends mainly upon your physical condition - this is, under God, your comfort and reliance: we are all alike environed. It is only that in your case, the "paries," the veil of the flesh, the screen, is a little out of repair, and sights and sounds are transmitted. We must enter on a new course, sir - be encouraged. I'll give to-night to the careful consideration of the whole case.'

‘You are very good, sir; you think it worth trying, you don't give me quite up; but, sir, you don't know, it is gaining such an influence over me: it orders me about, it is such a tyrant, and I'm growing so helpless. May God deliver me!'

‘It orders you about - of course you mean by speech?'

‘Yes, yes; it is always urging me to crimes, to injure others, or myself. You see, Doctor, the situation is urgent, it is indeed. When I was in Shropshire, a few weeks ago' (Mr Jennings was speaking rapidly and trembling now, holding my arm with one hand, and looking in my face), ‘I went out one day with a party of friends for a walk: my persecutor, I tell you, was with me at the time. I lagged behind the rest: the country near the Dee, you know, is beautiful. Our path happened to lie near a coal mine, and at the verge of the wood is a perpendicular shaft, they say, a hundred and fifty feet deep. My niece had remained behind with me - she knows, of course, nothing of the nature of my sufferings. She knew, however, that I had been ill, and was low, and she remained to prevent my being quite alone. As we loi-tered slowly on together the brute that accompanied me was urging me to throw myself down the shaft. I tell you now - oh, sir, think of it! - the one consideration that saved me from that hideous death was the fear lest the shock of wit-nessing the occurrence should be too much for the poor girl. I asked her to go on and take her walk with her friends, saying that I could go no further. She made excuses, and the more I urged her the firmer she became. She looked doubtful and frightened. I suppose there was something in my looks or manner that alarmed her; but she would not go, and that literally saved me. You had no idea, sir, that a living man could be made so abject a slave of Satan,' he said, with a ghastly groan and a shudder.

Tere was a pause here, and I said, ‘You werepreserved nevertheless. It was the act of God. You are in his hands and in the power of no other being: be therefore confdent for the future.'

Chapter X HOME

I made him have candles lighted, and saw the room looking cheery and inhabited before I left him. I told him that he must regard his illness strictly as one dependent on physical, thoughsubtlephysical, causes. I told him that he had evidence of God's care and love in the deliverance which he had just described, and that I had perceived with pain that he seemed to regard its peculiar features as indicating that he had been delivered over to spiritual reprobation. Than such a conclu-sion nothing could be, I insisted, less warranted; and not only so, but more contrary to facts, as disclosed in his mysterious deliverance from that murderous influence during his Shrop-shire excursion. First, his niece had been retained by his side without his intending to keep her near him; and, secondly, there had been infused into his mind an irresistible repug-nance to execute the dreadful suggestion in her presence.

As I reasoned this point with him, Mr Jennings wept. He seemed comforted. One promise I exacted, which was that should the monkey at any time return, I should be sent for immediately; and, repeating my assurance that I would give neither time nor thought to any other subject until I had thoroughly investigated his case, and that to-morrow he should hear the result, I took my leave.

Before getting into the carriage I told the servant that his master was far from well, and that he should make a point of frequently looking into his room.

My own arrangements I made with a view to being quite secure from interruption.

I merely called at my lodgings, and with a travelling-desk and carpet-bag, set off in a hackney-carriage for an inn about two miles out of town, calledThe Horns, a very quiet and comfortable house, with good thick walls. And there I resolved, without the possibility of intrusion or distraction, to devote some hours of the night, in my comfortable sitting-room, to Mr Jennings'case, and so much of the morning as it might require.

(There occurs here a careful note of Dr Hesselius'opinion upon the case and of the habits, dietary, and medicines which he prescribed. It is curious - some persons would say mystical. But on the whole I doubt whether it would sufficiently interest a reader of the kind I am likely to meet with, to warrant its being here reprinted. The whole letter was plainly written at the inn where he had hid himself for the occasion. The next letter is dated from his town lodgings.)

I left town for the inn where I slept last night at half-past nine, and did not arrive at my room in town until one o'clock this afternoon. I found a letter in Mr Jennings'hand upon my table. It had not come by post, and, on inquiry, I learned that Mr Jennings'servant had brought it, and on learning that I was not to return until to-day, and that no one could tell him my address, he seemed very uncomfort-able, and said that his orders from his master were that he was not to return without an answer.

I opened the letter, and read:

‘Dear Dr Hesselius. It is here. You had not been an hour gone when it returned. It is speaking. It knows all that has hap-pened. It knows everything - it knows you, and is frantic and atrocious. It reviles. I send you this. It knows every word I have written - I write. This I promised, and I therefore write, but I fear very confused, very incoherently. I am so inter-rupted, disturbed.

‘Ever yours, sincerely yours,

‘ROBERT LYNDER JENNINGS.'

‘When did this come?' I asked.

‘About eleven last night: the man was here again, and has been here three times to-day. The last time is about an hour since.'

Thus answered, and with the notes I had made upon his case in my pocket, I was in a few minutes driving towards Richmond, to see Mr Jennings.

I by no means, as you perceive, despaired of Mr Jennings'case. He had himself remembered and applied, though quite in a mistaken way, the principle which I lay down in my Metaphysical Medicine, and which governs all such cases. I was about to apply it in earnest. I was profoundly inter-ested, and very anxious to see and examine him while the ‘enemy' was actually present.

I drove up to the sombre house, and ran up the steps, and knocked. The door, in a little time, was opened by a tall woman in black silk. She looked ill, and as if she had been crying. She curtseyed, and heard my question, but she did not answer. She turned her face away, extending her hand towards two men who were coming down-stairs; and thus having, as it were, tacitly made me over to them, she passed through a side-door hastily and shut it.

The man who was nearest the hall, I at once accosted, but being now close to him, I was shocked to see that both his hands were covered with blood.

I drew back a little, and the man passing down-stairs merely said in a low tone, ‘Here's the servant, sir.'

The servant had stopped on the stairs, confounded and dumb at seeing me. He was rubbing his hands in a hand-kerchief, and it was steeped in blood.

‘Jones, what is it, what has happened?' I asked, while a sickening suspicion overpowered me.

The man asked me to come up to the lobby. I was beside him in a moment, and frowning and pallid, with contracted eyes, he told me the horror which I already half guessed.

His master had made away with himself.

I went upstairs with him to the room - what I saw there I won't tell you. He had cut his throat with his razor. It was a frightful gash. The two men had laid him on the bed and composed his limbs. It had happened, as the immense pool of blood on the floor declared, at some distance between the bed and the window. There was carpet round his bed, and a carpet under his dressing-table, but none on the rest of the floor, for the man said he did not like a carpet on his bedroom. In this sombre, and now terrible room, one of the great elms that darkened the house was slowly moving the shadow of one of its great boughs upon this dreadful floor.

I beckoned to the servant and we went down-stairs together. I turned off the hall into an old-fashioned panelled room, and there standing, I heard all the servant had to tell. It was not a great deal.

‘I concluded, sir, from your words, and looks, sir, as you left last night, that you thought my master seriously ill. I thought it might be that you were afraid of a ft, or some-thing. So I attended very close to your directions. He sat up late, till past three o'clock. He was not writing or reading. He was talking a great deal to himself, but that was nothing unusual. At about that hour I assisted him to undress, and left him in his slippers and dressing-gown. I went back softly in about half an hour. He was in his bed, quite undressed, and a pair of candles lighted on the table beside his bed. He was leaning on his elbow and looking out at the other side of the bed when I came in. I asked him if he wanted any-thing, and he said no.

‘I don't know whether it was what you said to me, sir, or something a little unusual about him, but I was uneasy, uncommon uneasy about him last night.

‘In another half hour, or it might be a little more, I went up again. I did not hear him talking as before. I opened the door a little. The candles were both out, which was not usual. I had a bedroom candle, and I let the light in, a little bit, looking softly round. I saw him sitting in that chair beside the dressing-table with his clothes on again. He turned round and looked at me. I thought it strange he should get up and dress, and put out the candles to sit in the dark, that way. But I only asked him again if I could do anything for him. He said, no, rather sharp, I thought. I asked if I might light the candles, and he said, "Do as you like, Jones." So I lighted them, and I lingered about the room, and he said, "Tell me truth, Jones, why did you come again - you did not hear any one cursing?" "No, sir," I said, wondering what he could mean.

‘"No," said he, after me, "of course, no;" and I said to him, "Wouldn't it be well, sir, you went to bed? It's just five o'clock," and he said nothing but, "Very likely; good-night, Jones." So I went, sir, but in less than an hour I came again. The door was fast, and he heard me, and called as I thought from the bed to know what I wanted, and he desired me not to disturb him again. I lay down and slept for a little. It must have been between six and seven when I went up again. The door was still fast, and he made no answer, so I did not like to disturb him, and thinking he was asleep, I left him till nine. It was his custom to ring when he wished me to come, and I had no particular hour for calling him. I tapped very gently, and getting no answer, I stayed away a good while, supposing he was getting some rest then. It was not till eleven o'clock I grew really uncomfortable about him - for at the latest he was never, that I could remember, later than half-past ten. I got no answer. I knocked and called, and still no answer. So not being able to force the door, I calledThomas from the stables, and together we forced it, and found him in the shocking way you saw.'

Jones had no more to tell. Poor Mr Jennings was very gentle, and very kind. All his people were fond of him. I could see that the servant was very much moved.

So, dejected and agitated, I passed from that terrible house, and its dark canopy of elms, and I hope I shall never see it more. While I write to you I feel like a man who has but half waked from a frightful and monotonous dream. My memory rejects the picture with incredulity and horror. Yet I know it is true. It is the story of the process of a poison, a poison which excites the reciprocal action of spirit and nerve, and paralyses the tissue that separates those cognate functions of the senses, the external and the interior. Tus we fnd strange bed-fellows, and the mortal and immortal prematurely make acquaintance.

Conclusion A WORD FOR THOSE WHO SUFFER

My dear Van L-,you have suffered from an affection similar to that which I have just described. You twice complained of a return of it.

Who, under God, cured you?Your humble servant, Mar-tin Hesselius. Let me rather adopt the more emphasized piety of a certain good old French surgeon of three hundred years ago:‘ I treated, and God cured you.'

Come, my friend, you are not to be hippish. Let me tell you a fact.

I have met with, and treated, as my book shows, fifty-seven cases of this kind of vision, which I term indifferently‘ sublim-ated,' ‘precocious,' and ‘interior.'

There is another class of affections which are truly termed - though commonly confounded with those which I describe - spectral illusions. These latter I look upon as being no less simply curable than a cold in the head or a trifling dyspepsia.

It is those which rank in the first category that test our promptitude of thought. Fifty-seven such cases have I encountered, neither more nor less. And in how many of these have I failed?In no one single instance.

There is no one affliction of mortality more easily and certainly reducible, with a little patience, and a rational conf-dence in the physician. With these simple conditions, I look upon the cure as absolutely certain.

You are to remember that I had not even commenced to treat Mr Jennings'case. I have not any doubt that I should have cured him perfectly in eighteen months, or possibly it might have extended to two years. Some cases are very rapidly curable, others extremely tedious. Every intelligent physician who will give thought and diligence to the task, will efect a cure.

You know my tract on The Cardinal Functions of the Brain. I there, by the evidence of innumerable facts, prove, as I think, the high probability of a circulation arterial and venous in its mechanism, through the nerves. Of this sys-tem, thus considered, the brain is the heart. The fuid, which is propagated hence through one class of nerves, returns in an altered state through another, and the nature of that fuid is spiritual, though not immaterial, any more than, as I before remarked, light or electricity are so.

By various abuses, among which the habitual use of such agents as green tea is one, this fuid may be afected as to its quality, but it is more frequently disturbed as to equilib-rium. Tis fuid being that which we have in common with spirits, a congestion found upon the masses of brain or nerve, connected with the interior sense, forms a surface unduly exposed, on which disembodied spirits may operate: communication is thus more or less efectually established. Between this brain circulation and the heart circulation there is an intimate sympathy. The seat, or rather the instru-ment of exterior vision, is the eye. The seat of interior vision is the nervous tissue and brain, immediately about and above the eyebrow. You remember how effectually I dissi-pated your pictures by the simple application of iced eau-de-cologne. Few cases, however, can be treated exactly alike with anything like rapid success. Cold acts powerfully as a repellant of the nervous fluid. Long enough continued it will even produce that permanent insensibility which we call numbness, and a little longer, muscular as well as sen-sational paralysis.

I have not, I repeat, the slightest doubt that I should have first dimmed and ultimately sealed that inner eye which Mr Jennings had inadvertently opened. The same senses are opened in delirium tremens, and entirely shut up again when the over-action of the cerebral heart, and the prodigious ner-vous congestions that attend it, are terminated by a decided change in the state of the body. It is by acting steadily upon the body, by a simple process, that this result is produced - and inevitably produced - I have never yet failed.

Poor Mr Jennings made away with himself. But that catas-trophe was the result of a totally different malady, which, as it were, projected itself upon that disease which was estab-lished. His case was in the distinctive manner a complication, and the complaint under which he really succumbed, was hereditary suicidal mania. Poor Mr Jennings I cannot call a patient of mine, for I had not even begun to treat his case, and he had not yet given me, I am convinced, his full and unreserved confidence. If the patient do not array himself on the side of the disease, his cure is certain.

瑞普·凡·温克尔

/

迪德里克·尼克博克曾经是纽约的一位老绅士，对该州的荷兰殖民历史及其原住民后裔的风俗掌故很有研究兴趣。但是他做研究不靠书本，书本上也没有多少他感兴趣的东西，倒是发现坊间百姓，特别是那些老太太，知道很多民间逸事，这对真实的历史无疑是无价之宝，所以他就走街串巷，民间采风。每当他在亭亭如盖的梧桐下碰上一家地道的荷兰人，住着矮顶农舍，过着怡然自得、与世隔绝的日子，就喜出望外，仿佛得到一部印着哥特文字的珍稀卷帙，如饥似渴地研究起来。

他研究的是荷兰总督执政该州的那段历史，几年以后，书出版了。对于书中的文学特色，仁者见仁，智者见智，时至今日，依然不敢恭维。它的主要亮点在于严谨和精确，虽然刚开始面世时，受到些质疑，但是现在完全立住脚了，被所有历史馆藏收录，成为公认的史学经典。

这本书出版不久，老绅士就死了。斯人已逝，说句他的一生应该干点更大的事，不至于有失恭敬。然而，人各有志，他还是太由着自己的性子了。即使现在他的书在邻居看来不时会惹是生非，不时令朋友不快（对这些朋友，他很尊重，很热爱），但大家想起他的错误与愚蠢，感到更多的是“悲伤而不是愤怒”，以至于人们开始怀疑他的初衷根本就不是有意伤害或冒犯。现在不管批评家如何评论他，老百姓对他还是好评如潮，特别是一些面点师，为了永远纪念他，一度把他的肖像印在新年蛋糕上，这几乎算得上是与把他的肖像印在滑铁卢奖牌或安妮女王的硬币上一样的荣幸了。

下面的故事就是在迪德里克·尼克博克的遗稿里发现的。

迪德里克·尼克博克的遗作《瑞普·凡·温克尔》

沃登，撒克逊人的上帝，

星期三，以你命名。

永远，我将保持那份至诚

直到沃登之日

悄悄爬进坟墓——

——卡特赖特[1]

凡是在哈德孙河上航行过的人，一定记得卡茨基尔山脉，那是阿巴拉契亚山系的一支断脉。远远望去，溯河向西，巍峨峻拔，傲视周围的乡村。季节轮转，天气无常，甚至一天中的每一个时辰，山色与山形都会变幻。于是，整个山脉在远近乡村的主妇看来，是完美的晴雨表。天气晴朗，披上紫蓝衣裳的崇山峻岭倒映在璀璨的夜空；有时，万里无云，唯有山顶氤氲弥漫，在残阳余晖中，犹如荣耀的冠冕，光芒四射。

在仙山脚下，可以望见一座村子，炊烟袅袅，掩映在树丛中的木瓦屋顶泛着微光；高地的浅蓝和近处的葱翠交相辉映。这是一个非常古老的小村庄，由该省早期一些荷兰殖民者创建，也就是大约在虔诚的彼得・斯特伊弗桑特（愿他安息！）执政之初。几年前，这里还可以看到一些早期原住民的屋子。这些屋子都是用荷兰运来的小黄砖建的，都装着格子窗，正面是三角墙，顶部有风信鸡。

就在这个村子里，就在其中的一间屋子里（说老实话，这种房子都经年饱受风侵雨蚀，全是破败不堪的样子），许多年来（当时整个乡村还是大不列颠的一个省），一直住着一个单纯而善良的人，名叫瑞普・凡・温克尔。瑞普・凡・温克尔是凡・温克尔斯的后裔。在彼得・斯特伊弗桑特统治下的骑士时代，凡・温克尔斯威武勇猛，还同彼得・斯特伊弗桑特一道参加了围攻克里斯蒂娜堡的战斗。然而，瑞普・凡・温克尔一点儿也没有遗传祖先骁勇善战的性格。我注意到他是一个单纯善良的男人，一个心肠很好的邻居，一个在妻子面前言听计从的丈夫。后一种情况造就他脾气温顺，人缘很好，因为大凡在家里被悍妇管束的丈夫，出门在外，往往都会体贴入微、讨人欢喜，他们的性格，在家庭烈火的熔炉里被打磨得温文尔雅。看来，培养人们忍耐和坚毅的品格，枕边风抵得上世间所有的布道。所以，从某种意义上讲，摊上一个凶悍的妻子还是不幸中的万幸。以此类推，瑞普・凡・温克尔应该算得上是三生有幸了。

事实正是如此，村子里所有贤妻良母都特别喜欢他，通常女人都喜欢好脾气的男人。凡是出现家庭争吵，她们都一边倒站在瑞普・凡・温克尔的一边。晚上扎堆儿闲聊家长里短时，也都一股脑儿地把所有罪过全部推到凡・温克尔夫人身上。就连村里的孩子们在他走过时，都欢呼雀跃。瑞普跟孩子们一起玩耍，帮他们做玩具，教他们放风筝、打弹珠，给他们讲很长很长的幽灵、女巫和印第安人的故事。一见他为了躲避悍妻而在村子里晃荡，孩子们就蜂拥而至，有的扯住他衣服的下摆，有的爬到他背上，跟他玩着千奇百怪的恶作剧，他却从不生气，就连附近的狗都没有朝他叫的。

可是，瑞普这人有一个大毛病，那就是，他对各种有利可图的劳动都无可救药地厌恶透顶。这完全不是他这个人不勤奋或者没有恒心。因为他可以带上一根同鞑靼人的长矛一样又长又重的钓鱼竿，坐在一块潮湿的石头上，一钓就是一整天，而不会有丝毫的怨言，即使没有一条鱼儿咬钩，他也不会觉得扫兴。他经常是一连几小时扛着猎枪，步履艰难地穿过森林，穿过沼泽地，爬上山冈，越过山谷，就是为了打几只松鼠或几只野鸽。邻居需要帮忙时，他从来都是二话不说，即使需要付出最艰苦的劳动，诸如给印第安玉米剥皮，或者建石头围墙之类的乡下趣事儿，他总是冲锋在前的。村里的妇女们也总喜欢找他跑跑腿，让他做一些连她们自己不体贴的丈夫都不干的各种小零活儿。也就是说，瑞普对外人的事情百般殷勤，对自家的事情从不过问。对于如何尽家里的义务，把自家地里的活儿干得利利落落，他觉得比登天还难。

事实上，他跟别人说过，在自家地里干活儿，是白费工夫。他家的那块地，小得可怜，整个村子，就没有哪块地比这还小。那块地怎么种也种不好，他再怎么努力都没用。他家的栅栏一而再再而三地倒塌；他家的牛不是跑得没影儿，就是钻进了卷心菜的菜地里；田里的杂草一定是他家的长得最快；只要他一想外出做点活儿，还没等出门，天就下起雨来。就这样，他的祖传家产在他手上日复一日地缩水。他的田地，今天少一亩，明天少一亩，最后就只剩下一小块土地用来种植印度玉米和土豆了。可是，这块地算得上是附近一带种得最为糟糕的一块地呀。

瑞普的几个孩子同他本人一样，穿得破破烂烂，整天到处撒野，像是没有爹妈的孩子。他儿子小瑞普，跟他就像是一个模子刻出来的捣蛋鬼，穿着他父亲的旧衣服，各种脾气秉性相较他父亲有过之而无不及。经常看到他就像一匹小马驹，屁颠儿地跟在母亲身后，穿着一条他父亲不穿了的灯笼裤，费力地用一只手提拎着，就像一位贵妇在雨天提着裙裾走路一样。

可是，瑞普・凡・温克尔整天乐呵呵的，看上去傻傻的，很讨人喜欢。他把日子过得轻轻松松，管它是白面包还是黑面包，怎么省事怎么吃，宁可只有一便士挨饿，也不为了一英镑干活儿。按他的性格，就是开开心心吹着口哨过日子。可他妻子就是没完没了、絮絮不休地在他耳边唠叨着，说他游手好闲；说他缺心少肺；说一家人都要毁在他的身上了。从清晨，到中午，再到夜晚，她的舌头就嚼个不停，无论瑞普说什么或者做什么，都会招来一顿机关枪般的训斥。对付这类训斥，瑞普都准备好了统一的回复，而且因为使用得过于频繁，已逐渐成了习惯——耸耸肩，摇摇头，抬眼望天，一声不吭。可是，这又会招来妻子新一轮的连珠炮，最后，他只好偃旗息鼓，走到外边去——这是给怕老婆的男人们唯一的退路。

在家里，跟瑞普形影不离的就只有他的那条狼狗——沃尔夫。沃尔夫跟他的主人一样，对凡・温克尔夫人怕得要命，因为凡・温克尔夫人认为她丈夫和狗简直是懒到一块儿了。她甚至双眼充满邪恶地看着它，认为沃尔夫就是把主人引入歧途的祸根。的确是那么回事儿，从符合爱犬要求的精神层面来说，沃尔夫勇敢无比，就像曾经在野外森林中生活过一样——可是，有什么勇气能够经受得住一个爱嚼舌头的妇女所带来的喋喋不休、令人困扰的恐惧呢？只要沃尔夫一进到家，它的毛发就耷拉了下去，它的尾巴就垂到地面上或者夹在两腿之间。它在屋子里窜来窜去，活像是要上绞刑架的样子，时不时斜着眼睛，瞅瞅凡・温克尔夫人。只要看到她拿起扫帚柄或者长柄勺做出哪怕是一丁点儿挥舞的动作，沃尔夫就狂叫不止，夺门而逃。

瑞普・凡・温克尔的婚姻车轮滚滚向前，可生活却度日如年。尖酸刻薄的性子，绝不会因为天增岁月而柔软温和。而那尖刻的舌头，是唯一锐利的工具，经过不断使用，不钝反利。有好一阵子，只要被赶出家门，瑞普就到一个由村里的贤达、智者及闲人常年聚集的俱乐部里寻求慰藉。俱乐部在一个小客栈前面的条凳上召开会议，小客栈上挂着乔治三世陛下的那幅脸色红润的画像。大家就坐在树荫底下，度过漫漫、懒散的夏日。他们无精打采，闲扯村子里的事情，要么就讲着无聊乏味的故事，没完没了，让人昏昏欲睡。但是，碰巧有旧报纸从途经此地的旅行者那里落入他们手中时，他们便会围绕报纸内容展开深刻讨论，即便是政治家花钱来听，也很值得。当衣冠楚楚、满腹经纶的小个子德里克・凡・布默尔，这位连词典里最难的词语都难不倒的小学教师，不紧不慢读报的时候，大家便开始侧耳倾听，那是多么庄严的场景哪！他们在对发生在几个月内的公共事件发表真知灼见时，又是多么的贤明呀！

这个小团体的意见完全受尼古拉斯・维德的控制。尼古拉斯既是村长，也是店主。他从早到晚都坐在小客栈门口，只有在为了躲避太阳，且还要保证自己能始终待在那棵大树的树荫底下时，才会稍微移动一下。这样，邻居们完全可以根据他移动的位置来确定每天的具体时间，那准确度可与日晷相媲美。的确，很难听到他开口说什么，他只是一个劲儿地抽烟斗。可是，拥护他的人（因为凡是大人物都有拥护者）都很懂他，也知道怎样去揣摩他的心思。当读给他听或者讲给他听的东西让他不快时，你就会注意到他抱着烟斗吸个不停，并且短促地、频繁地、愤怒地吐着烟雾。但在他感到满意的时候，便会慢条斯理、心平气和地把烟吸进去，再吐出一缕缕轻盈、平和的烟雾。有时，他会从嘴里抽出烟斗，让香气在鼻子周围缭绕升腾。与此同时，他还会严肃地点点头，表示完全同意。

可即便是如此固若金汤的堡垒，不幸的瑞普最终还是被他那凶悍的妻子寻到了踪迹。她会突然闯进来把整个聚会搅得不得安宁，还把在场的所有人一个个骂得一文不值。就连那个令人敬畏的大人物尼古拉斯・维德，碰到这位使人不寒而栗的悍妇口无遮拦的舌根时，也一样在劫难逃。她公然指控就是他让自己的男人染上了游手好闲的恶习。

可怜的瑞普，最后几乎到了绝望的境地。要逃避农活儿，还有妻子的谩骂，唯一的选择就是手持猎枪，进入森林游荡。在森林里，他有时会坐在树下，与沃尔夫一起分享行囊中的食物。他很同情沃尔夫，把沃尔夫看成同病相怜的伙伴。“可怜的沃尔夫，”他经常会说，“汝之女主人，让汝之生活牛马莫如了。请勿把心伤，伙伴。只要老朽一息尚存，汝将永远有一友人相伴相依。”沃尔夫总会摇摇尾巴，满怀期望地看着主人的脸庞。假如狗能够感受到他人对自己的同情，我深信它会用整个身心来回报这种情感的。

在一个秋高气爽的日子里，在一段长时间的闲逛后，瑞普不知不觉地爬到了卡茨基尔山脉其中一处最高的地方。他到这里是做他最喜欢的事情——打松鼠。在这里，周围一片静谧，猎枪响起时，枪声在孤寂的山谷里回荡来回荡去。傍晚时分，他气喘吁吁，精疲力竭，一屁股坐到一个绿色的小山包上，山包上覆盖着草本植被，这是悬崖边缘的顶端。从树与树之间的空隙处，他可以俯瞰到延绵数英里[2]满是葱茏树木的乡村。他还能看到远处高贵的哈德孙河，在他的身下，远远地，远远地，流淌着，平静却庄严。一块紫色的云印在了河面上，间或有零零星星缓缓行驶的小帆船，静静地卧在犹如明镜的河面上，最后隐没于蓝色的高地之间。

在小山的另一边，他俯视着幽深的山谷，那里一片荒凉寂寞，高低不平，谷底到处都是从悬空的悬崖上撒落下来的碎片，夕阳反射的光线是几乎照不到这里的。有一阵子，瑞普趴在地上，看着这里的景色，陷入了沉思。夜幕渐渐降临，卡茨基尔山脉开始把长长的蓝色的阴影投进山谷。他意识到，天就要黑下来了，回到村子还需要走很长很长的路。可是，一想到回家要面对凡・温克尔夫人所带来的恐惧，瑞普长长地叹了一口气。

正要下山的时候，他听到从远处传来的一个声音大喊着：“瑞普・凡・温克尔！瑞普・凡・温克尔！”他环顾四周，但什么也没能看到，只有一只乌鸦形只影单地飞到山的那边去了。他想，一定是他的想象给他带来幻觉了。他转过身去，又开始准备下山。这时，他听到同样的叫声在寂静的夜空里回响：“瑞普・凡・温克尔！瑞普・凡・温克尔！”——与此同时，沃尔夫弓起了脊背，发出低沉的吼叫，偷偷地躲到主人身边，胆怯地朝山谷望去。瑞普这时感到，一种无可名状的恐惧向他整个身子袭来。他急切地朝着相同的方向望去，察觉到有一个奇怪的人影正在缓慢而吃力地往岩石上爬，他背着的什么东西太重，把他的背都压弯了。他非常吃惊，居然在这个偏僻且人迹罕至的地方看到有人出现。但他猜想，那很可能是附近的某个人需要他的帮助，于是他加快了脚步，准备下去伸出援手。

在离那个人更近了一些时，这个陌生人奇特的外表让瑞普倍感吃惊。他身材矮小，体形宽阔，年岁老迈，头发浓密，胡子灰白；一身古荷兰式装束，棉布短上衣紧紧勒在腰上，下身套了好几层马裤，最外面的那件马裤有着足够大的容量，马裤上镶着两排扣子，扣子往下一直到两侧和膝盖的隆起处。他肩上扛着装酒的小木桶，里面似乎装满了烈酒。他示意瑞普走过去给他帮帮忙。尽管面对这个刚刚认识的人他还有点儿胆怯，半信半疑，可瑞普还是像平常那样，很乐意地照办了。他们稍事休息了一下，就接着攀上一条狭窄的沟壑，这里显然是山溪干涸后留下的河床。再往上爬时，瑞普不时听见连绵不断的、轰隆隆的声音，就像远处的雷鸣。那声音似乎是从深谷中，或者是从高大的岩石的裂缝里传来。崎岖的山路朝着深谷延伸开去。他停留了片刻，继而猜想，那一定是那些转瞬即逝的雷阵雨发出的轰隆声，在山间这样的海拔高度上，这样的雷阵雨非常常见。他们继续前行，穿过峡谷，二人来到了一个像圆形剧场的山坳里。山坳周围，都是垂直的悬崖。悬崖边缘高悬着枝繁叶茂的树木，只能偶尔从缝隙间看到蔚蓝的天空和闪着光芒的夜云。在整个过程中，瑞普同他的伙伴只是默默地、艰辛前行着。尽管瑞普对于要把一小木桶烈酒扛到这荒山上的做法感到惊奇不已，但在这未知的事物中有一种奇怪和不可理解的东西被激发出来，让人心生敬畏，也倍感陌生。

一走进圆形剧场，让人感到好奇的新事情便出现了。就在中间的一块平地上，一帮看上去模样古怪的人正在玩着九柱地滚球。他们个个穿着稀奇古怪的服装——一些人穿着短短的紧身上衣，另一些人穿着皮带上别着长刀的坎肩，大多数人的马裤都宽大无比，跟那个领路长者穿的式样相似。他们的面容也非同寻常。有一个人脑袋很大，脸很宽，眼睛小小的，像猪一样。另一个人的脸看上去好像就只长了鼻子，他头上戴着白色的锥形帽，上面还插了个公鸡的红尾巴。他们都留着胡须，形状各异，颜色也各异。其中一个人似乎是指挥官，他矮胖胖的，年纪很大，有绅士风度，看上去饱经风霜。他身着花边紧身上衣，皮带和挂剑的饰带都很宽大，帽子上面装饰着羽毛，脚穿红色的长筒袜和饰有玫瑰花的高跟鞋。这一大群人，让瑞普想起了村子牧师多米尼・凡・沙伊克家客厅里挂着的那幅佛拉芒古画中的人物。那幅画是在殖民时期从荷兰带回来的。

让瑞普感觉最为奇怪的是，尽管这些人看起来是在自娱自乐，可他们始终表情严肃，极尽神秘不语之能事，而且这也是他曾见过的最扫兴的娱乐的人群了。没有什么声音可以打破这里的宁静，有的只是一次次击球的声音。每次滚球的声音都会顺着山脉回响，就像轰隆隆的雷鸣。

当瑞普和他的同伴走近时，所有人突然停止了游戏，并带着雕塑般呆呆的眼神凝视着他，他们面容古怪、粗野，神情呆滞，看得他的心怦怦直跳，双膝像筛糠一样战栗不已。就在这时，他的伙伴把酒桶里的酒倒进了大酒壶里，并示意他招待这些人。他战战兢兢地照办。他们不声不响地把酒一饮而尽，接着又玩起球来。

渐渐地，瑞普的敬畏之情和忧虑之感都消失了。他甚至在没有人盯住自己的时候，大胆地尝了尝那酒。他觉得那酒尝起来有荷兰制杜松子酒的味道。他天生是个好酒之徒，很快就经不住诱惑又过去喝了一口。一种味道激发出另一种新的味道，他一次又一次地走过去，以至于到最后迷失了所有的感官。他的双眼恍惚起来——脑袋慢慢地不听使唤耷拉下来，人也陷入了深度睡眠。

等他一觉醒来时，发现自己躺在一个绿色的小山包上。当初他正是在这里看到那个来自峡谷里的老人。他揉了揉眼睛——这是一个阳光灿烂的早晨。鸟儿在树丛中欢跳啁啾，老鹰在空中盘旋，并迎着纯净的山风翱翔。“毫无疑问，”瑞普想了想说，“我并没有整夜都睡在这里。”他回忆了一下自己睡前发生的事情：那个背着一小木桶酒的怪人，还有山谷——岩石中那个荒凉隐蔽之地，那群愁眉苦脸的玩九柱地滚球的人们，那只酒壶……“啊哈！那只酒壶！那只邪恶的酒壶！”瑞普心里说道，“我该找个什么借口向凡・温克尔夫人道歉呢？”

他环顾四周，想要寻找自己的那支枪，可是，在先前放置那支油光闪亮、光洁猎枪的地方，放着一把旧火枪：枪管锈迹斑斑，枪机已经脱落，枪托已被虫蛀。他此刻满腹狐疑，认为山里的那帮表情冷峻的戏子把他捉弄了一番，并在他喝醉酒之后，把他的枪给劫走了。沃尔夫也不见了踪影，它或许是在追松鼠或鹧鸪时迷路了吧。瑞普一路边吹哨子，边喊着沃尔夫的名字——但一切都枉然。山里的回声重复着他的口哨和喊声，却依旧不见狗的影子。

他决定再次回到昨晚那伙人玩耍的地方，只要碰到其中的任何一个，就向他索要自己的狗和枪。当他起身准备走时，发现身上的关节变得非常僵硬，而且要做一些平常的活动也变得力不从心。“这些山路不适合我走了，”瑞普思忖道，“如果这场闹剧让我落下一身的风湿病，继而使我卧床不起，那凡・温克尔夫人可是得跟我度过一段‘美好时光’了。”他有些吃力地向山下走去，找到了前一天晚上与同伴一起往上爬的那条冲沟，但让他吃惊的是，一条山溪此刻正泛着泡沫沿着冲沟流淌，冲过一块又一块岩石，让整个山谷回荡着潺潺流水声。他想办法尽量爬到冲沟的侧边，不无艰辛地穿过由白桦树、黄樟树和金缕梅树组成的灌木丛，不时还被那些树间盘绕纠缠的野葡萄藤绊倒或缠住，卷曲的藤条在他前进的路上布下了天罗地网。

终于，他来到了山谷穿过悬崖的地方，到达了圆形剧场——先前的空旷地带已经没有了踪影。无数的岩石形成了一堵高高的、坚不可摧的墙。溪水的急流从墙面上翻腾而下，泛着一片片羽毛状的泡沫，落入又阔又深的水潭，水潭在周围森林阴影的掩映下黯然无光。就是在这儿，可怜的瑞普被迫停了下来。他又唤了一次狗的名字，吹了声口哨——只有一群闲散的乌鸦用呱呱的叫声回应着。它们在悬崖边上向阳的那棵枯树周围盘旋，高高在上，似乎在鄙视和嘲笑这位可怜男子的困惑与烦恼。

这可怎么办呢？上午慢慢地过去了。瑞普对早餐的渴望让他更加饥肠辘辘。他舍不得自己的狗和枪，惧怕见到妻子。可在这群山里头挨饿，也不是个事儿呀！他摇了摇头，扛起了锈迹斑斑的火枪，带着满腹的忧愁和焦虑，踏上了回家的路。

走回村庄的路上，他遇到很多人，可一个也不认识。这让他有点儿吃惊，他原以为自己认识周围乡村里的每一个人。他们的衣着也同他以往所看到的不一样。村里的人也是个个都用同样吃惊的目光盯着他瞧。而所有人在与他对视的时候，都会无一例外地摸一下下巴。看到他们一而再再而三地重复这个动作，瑞普也情不自禁地做了起来。让他万分惊讶的是自己的胡须，竟然有一英尺[3]长了！

这时，他已经来到村边。一群陌生的孩子跟在他后面跑个不停，一边大声叫嚣，一边指着他那灰白的胡须。还有那些狗，也没有哪一只是他所认得的老相识。当他经过时，所有的狗都朝他叫了起来。就连村子本身都变了——比以往更大，人也更多。一排又一排从未见过的房屋，那些他一直很熟悉并经常光顾的房子已经不知去向了。门牌上面贴着的都是陌生的名字，窗边出现的都是陌生的面孔——一切都是陌生的。他心里感到非常不安。他开始怀疑自己周围的世界是不是都着魔了。这确实是他前一天才离开的土生土长的村子呀！卡茨基尔山脉就矗立在那里，远处流淌着银色的哈德孙河，每一座小山和每一个山谷都在原处没有动，瑞普充满了困惑，痛苦不堪。“昨晚那个酒壶，”他心里想，“把我可怜的脑袋瓜弄糊涂了！”

费了不少气力，他才找到回家的路。他不敢吭声，非常畏惧地走近自己的家，每一刻都希望听到凡・温克尔夫人那刺耳的叫声。可是他发现，自家的房子已经年久失修了——屋顶已经坍塌，窗户均已破碎，门板也已脱落。一只看上去就像沃尔夫一样，并且饿得半死的狗在房子周围躲躲闪闪。瑞普直呼其名，但那只恶狗却咆哮了起来，龇着牙走开了。这可真是杀人不见血的一招。“我的爱犬呀，”可怜的瑞普长吁短叹地说，“把我都忘得一干二净了！”

他走进自己的屋子。说实话，以往那屋子总是由凡・温克尔夫人打理得利利落落的，现在空空如也，没有人住，显然是遭人遗弃了。这份苍凉让他所有的惧内情绪荡然无存。他大声呼喊妻子和几个孩子的名字，有那么一会儿，这孤寂的房间回荡着他的声音，但紧接着，一切又归于沉寂。

他疾跑出去，来到以往常去的地方——那个村子里的小客栈，但它也不见了。取而代之的是一座摇摇欲坠的大木屋，开着几扇大窗户，有些已经破裂，用一些旧帽子和旧衬裙修补着，门的上方印着“乔纳森・杜立特尔联合旅店”的字样。昔日的那棵给这个荷兰小客栈带来一片荫蔽的大树已经没有了，现在矗立着一根高大裸露的柱子，顶部挂着个好似红色睡帽的玩意儿。那东西下面飘着一面旗子，旗子上面是奇怪的星星和条纹的组合。这一切都很怪异，也很让人费解。不过，瑞普认出了指示牌上肤色红润的乔治三世的面容，他曾在这张脸的下面平静地抽了那么多的烟斗，但即使是这个，也大大地改变了模样。原本的大衣颜色从红色变成了蓝色和黄色，手上握着的是剑，而不是权杖，头上戴着一顶三角帽，三角帽下面印着大字：GENERAL WASHINGTON（华盛顿将军）。

就像往常一样，门口依旧围着一群人，但这些人瑞普一个也想不起。就连他们的性子似乎也都发生了变化。瞧他们说话的语气，一个个都很急于争个是非曲直，争先恐后地喧闹不已，没有了昔日的那份平和与安宁。他找了找贤明之士尼古拉斯・维德，但没有找到。尼古拉斯・维德有一张大脸和双下巴，他总是叼着长长的烟斗，喷出团团的烟雾，并不跟人闲聊。他也找了找小学老师凡・布默尔，但同样没有找到。凡・布默尔喜欢拿着旧报纸，慢慢品读其中的内容。取代他们的，是一个精瘦的，看上去很有脾气的家伙，他口袋里装满了传单，正在激情满怀地神侃什么公民的权利，选举，议会议员，自由，邦克山战役，七六年的英雄们[4]，以及那些完全令人摸不着头脑的行话术语，弄得凡・温克尔一头雾水。

蓄着灰白的长须、扛着生锈的猎枪、穿着破烂衣服、身后还跟着一群妇孺的瑞普，很快引起了旅店政治家们的注意。他们满是好奇地将他团团围住，从头到脚打量了一番。演讲者急急忙忙地走到瑞普跟前，把他稍稍拉到一边问他到底投哪一边的票。瑞普傻乎乎的，茫然瞪着双眼。另一位忙来忙去的小矮个子拉着他的胳膊，踮起脚，凑近他的耳朵，问他是支持联邦政府还是民主党人。对这个问题瑞普同样听不懂。这时，一位头上戴着尖尖的三角帽，非常世故，也自以为了不起的年长绅士，从人群那边走了过来。他在经过人群时，用胳膊肘把他们拨到左右两边。直挺挺地站到了凡・温克尔跟前。他一只手叉着腰，另一只手拄着拐杖。那双锐利的眼睛和尖尖的帽子似乎刺进了瑞普的灵魂。他语气严峻，逼问瑞普为什么扛着枪，身后还带着一群人来选举，是不是要在村子里搞暴动。“呜呼，各位先生，”瑞普带着沮丧，大声说道，“我是个安分守己的穷苦人，土生土长的本地人，是国王的忠实臣民——愿上帝护佑他！”

这时，从围观的人群中爆发出一片呼喊：“是个托利党！是个托利党！是个间谍！是个难民！去他的！让他滚！”那个戴着三角帽，自以为了不得的男人费了好大的劲儿才让一切恢复了秩序。他慎重地紧锁起眉头，再次质问这位不明身份的“罪犯”到这里来是干什么的，来找谁的。可怜的瑞普，他谦卑地向他保证，自己毫无恶意，只是来此寻找曾经的邻居，他们以前常在这客栈附近相聚。

“那好，他们是哪些人？叫什么名字？”

瑞普思考了片刻，然后问：“尼古拉斯・维德在哪里？”

有好一阵子，大家都沉默不语。这时，一位长者用细声细气的声音回答说，“尼古拉斯・维德呀？唉，他过世了呀，过世十八年啦！教堂的墓地上，有一块木制的墓碑，上面写有他的身世，可那块墓碑也腐烂了，不知去向了。”

“布罗姆・达彻在哪儿呢？”

“哦，他在战争一开始就参军啦。有人说，他在进攻哈德孙河西岸的斯托尼波因特时阵亡了，又有人说他在安东尼碧山的山脚下，在一次暴风中溺亡了——我不知道哪个是真，哪个是假——反正他再也没有回来。”

“那小学老师凡・布默尔在哪里呢？”

“他也去参军了——还当上了国民军的大将，现在在议会当议员呢。”

听到自己的家，自己的朋友们，都发生了这样令他难过的变化，发现自己在这个世界上变得孤孤单单的，瑞普的心都碎了——他得到的每一个答复都让他感到莫名其妙，时间怎么会有那么大的跨度，他们所谈及的一切词汇竟然是那么难以理解——战争呀，国会呀，斯东尼角呀，等等，他都无法理解了。他再也没有勇气打听别的朋友的情况，唯有绝望地大声叫了起来：“难道这儿就没有人认识瑞普・凡・温克尔的吗？”

“噢，你是说瑞普・凡・温克尔吗？”两三个人大声说道，“当然认识啦！那就是瑞普・凡・温克尔——在那边——正靠在那棵树上呢。”

瑞普向那边瞧了瞧，注意到自己上山时，有个人跟他长得一模一样：不用说跟他一样懒散，穿得也跟他一样破破烂烂！这可怜的人儿现在已经完全糊涂。他都怀疑起自己到底是个什么了，怀疑起自己到底是本人呢，还是别的什么人。他正犯迷糊，那个戴着三角帽的人过来询问起他到底是谁——姓甚名谁？

“鬼知道呢，”他不知所措地叫道，“我不是我自己了，我是别的什么人了，那边的那个人是我了吧。不不不，那是别的什么人附着我的身体吧。可昨晚我还是我自己呀，我只不过是在山上睡了一觉而已，他们就把我的枪给换掉了，结果什么都变了，我自己也变了，这下好，我连自己姓甚名谁也说不出，我是谁呀！”

这个时候，旁边看热闹的人开始你看看我，我看看你，点点头，意味深长地使着眼色，用手指头轻轻地敲敲自己的前额。接着他们还相互耳语着要把枪夺下来，免得这老家伙会闹出什么乱子来——听到这话，那个戴三角帽、自认为了不起的家伙便匆匆溜之大吉。就在这千钧一发之际，一位年轻貌美的女子从人群中挤了过来，也想看看这个白胡子老头儿。她怀里抱着一个胖乎乎的孩子，那孩子看到瑞普的那般模样，惊恐万分，开始哭了起来。“嘘，别说话，瑞普，”她叫道，“嘘，别哭，小傻瓜，这老头儿不会把你怎么样的。”这小孩儿的名字，母亲的那副神态和她说话的语气，都在他脑子里唤起了一连串的回忆。“你到底姓甚名谁呀，漂亮的姑娘？”他问道。

“我是裘迪斯・嘉尔顿尼尔呀。”

“令尊姓甚名谁呢？”

“甭提了，那可是可怜的人啦，他叫瑞普・凡・温克尔，可是，自他带着枪离家出走已经二十年了，那之后他就杳无音讯了——他的狗自个儿回家了——可是，他到底是开枪自杀了，还是被印第安人给抓走了，谁也不知道。我那时只是个小姑娘。”

瑞普还想问最后一个问题，但他问的时候已经结结巴巴了——

“那令堂在哪里呢？”

“哦，她也过世了，不过这还是不久以前的事儿——在跟一个新英格兰小贩发火的时候，血管爆裂了。”

听到这个消息，至少让他得到一丝安慰。这个老实人再也无法抑制住自己的心情了，他一把搂住女儿和女儿怀里的孩子。“我就是你的父亲呀！”他大叫道，“那时风华正茂的瑞普・凡・温克尔变成了现在年老体衰的瑞普・凡・温克尔。难道就没有人认识我这个可怜的瑞普・凡・温克尔了吗？”

所有的人都站住了，一个个带着惊愕的表情。这时候，一位年迈的妇女摇摇晃晃地走出人群。她一手遮住额头，瞅了瞅他的脸，大声叫道，“果真是他！他就是瑞普・凡・温克尔！就是他本人！老邻居你又回来啦！欢迎啊！——哎呀，那么长的二十年，你都到哪儿去了呀？”

瑞普很快又讲了一遍自己的经历，因为那整整二十年，对他来说只是一个晚上的事儿。听到他的经历，邻居们个个都瞪大了眼睛。有几个人相互使眼色，显出挖苦的表情。那个戴着三角帽、自以为了不起的男子在惊恐过后回过身来，嘴唇紧闭，摇了摇头——看到他的这个举动，在场的所有人也都摇了摇头。

这个时候，大家看到老彼得・范德尔敦克从大路上慢慢走了过来。因此，大家决定去征求他的意见。他是与他同名的那位历史学家的后裔。那位历史学家曾经记述过本省早期的历史。彼得是村子里年事最高的居民，对附近一带所有的神奇事件和各种传奇都了如指掌。他立刻记起了瑞普，断定他讲的事情完全可信。这下，大家才满意了。彼得确切地告诉大家，那是从他的那位历史学家先辈传下来的事实——也就是说，卡茨基尔山脉总是有各种稀奇古怪的人光顾。他确切地告诉大家，伟大的英国航海家兼探险家亨德里克・哈德孙第一个发现了这条河流和附近这一带地区。于是，每隔二十年，他都要率领他的“半月号”船的全体船员，来这一带守夜一次。这样，他就可以重访他曾冒险过的每个地方，严密守护以他的名字命名的河流和大城市。他确切地告诉大家说，他父亲曾经看到过他们身着旧时的荷兰人服饰，在山中的一个山坳里玩九柱地滚球，还说他自己在一个夏日的午后，也曾听到过他们滚球的声音，就像远处轰隆隆的雷鸣。

长话短说吧——那群人后来散开了，都去忙乎他们更加关心的选举的事情了。瑞普的女儿把他带回去一起生活。她屋子里的家具齐全，居住舒适。她丈夫是个农民，身躯魁梧，整天乐呵呵的。瑞普记起来了，他就是过去曾经爬到他背上的那些调皮捣蛋鬼中的一个。至于瑞普的儿子兼继承人——也就是大家看到的，跟他父亲是一个模子倒出来、正靠着那棵树站着的那一位——在田里给人做农活。但他显现出了从父亲那里继承过来的性情：对别人的事情百般殷勤，对自己的事情从不上心。

现在，瑞普又开始像以前那样过日子了。不久，他又找到了很多以前的老朋友，不过这些人都已经饱经沧桑。瑞普更喜欢同年轻的一代交朋友，很快便得到了年轻人的爱戴。因为在家无事可做，而且也到了可以不受惩罚而到处闲逛逍遥的年纪，他再一次坐在了摆在小客栈门口的那张条凳上。人们把他奉为村子里德高望重的长者之一，把他奉为“大战之前”的那个旧时代的编年史。过了好一阵子，瑞普才能在同大家闲聊时跟得上趟儿，也才弄清楚了在他一觉睡去的二十年间所发生的奇奇怪怪的事件：如何发生了革命战争，美国如何摆脱了古老的英格兰的奴役，他如何从一个乔治三世陛下的臣民摇身变成了美国自由的公民，等等。事实上，瑞普对政治毫无兴趣。美利坚合众国同大英帝国之间的变迁没有给他留下什么印象。不过，有一种专制统治的重压曾让他长期呻吟，那就是“妇人的专政”。让他开心的是，那样的专政结束了——他已经脱离婚姻的桎梏，开始扬眉吐气了，他可以随着自己的意愿而自由进出，可以不再为凡・温克尔夫人的暴政感到恐惧。不过，只要有人提到凡・温克尔夫人的名字，他还是会摇摇头，耸耸肩，抬抬眼。这样的神态既可以看作是他对自己命运的屈服，也可以表示他对获得解放的欢欣。

后来，瑞普经常把自己的经历讲给每一位到“杜立特尔先生旅店”住宿的新客人。起初，人们注意到，每次在他讲起自己的经历时，总有些细节会有所变化，大抵是因为他才从沉睡中醒来没多久的缘故。最后，他讲的故事才跟我所讲的一模一样，附近一带的男男女女，大人小孩，没有谁对这个故事不是了然于心的。有些人却总假装怀疑这个故事的真实性。他们还坚持认为，瑞普的脑子以前就有毛病，坚信这就是他脑海中众多奇思怪想中的一个。然而，旧时的荷兰居民，几乎全都相信这个故事是真实的。即使到今天，每当他们在夏天午后听到从卡茨基尔山脉传来的雷声时，还是会说，那是亨德里克・哈德孙和他的船员们正在玩九柱地滚球的声音。对于附近一带所有惧内的丈夫们来说，每当日子实在过不下去的时候，都巴望着能从瑞普・凡・温克尔的酒壶里，喝上一口让人一醉不醒的美酒。

附言

读者会怀疑上面这个故事是尼克博克先生从有关腓特烈皇帝和基普霍塞尔山的，一个不起眼的德国迷信故事中得到启发而写成的。可是，这里附在故事后面的注释表明，那是绝对的事实。尼克博克先生一向以忠实著称，下面是他的叙述：

“瑞普·凡·温克尔的故事在许多人看来，似乎难以置信，可我完全相信它的真实性。因为我知道，在我们古老的荷兰殖民地附近，经常发生一些不可思议的事件，出现一些不可思议的现象。的确，我也听说过在沿哈德孙河的各个村子里所发生的比这还要稀奇古怪的故事。

所有这些故事都得到充分证实，因而是毋庸置疑的。我甚至亲自同瑞普·凡·温克尔谈过话。我最后一次见到他时，他已是一位德高望重的老人了。在其他每一个问题上，他都极尽理性，并且始终如一。在我看来，凡是本着良心行事的人，没有谁会对这件事情有相左的意见了——还有，我还看到就这件事情还在一位法官面前颁发过一个证书，上面还有法官亲笔签的‘十’字。因此，这个故事是不容怀疑的。”

D.K.

又及

下面是基于尼克博克先生的备忘录而写的游记：

卡茨基尔山脉一向是个充满神奇传说的区域。印第安人把卡茨基尔山脉看成是精灵的住处。这些精灵影响着天气，让阳光普照或阴云笼罩在这个景观的上空，为人们带来或好或坏的狩猎季节。他们由一个年长的女精灵统管。据说她就是这些精灵的母亲，就住在卡茨基尔山脉的最高峰，把守着白天和黑夜之门，并在恰当的时刻开启和关闭。她把新的月亮挂上天空，把旧的月亮碎成一颗颗星星。干旱时，如果把她关照好，她就会从蜘蛛网和晨露中编织出轻盈的夏日云彩，并从山巅将这云彩送走，一片接着一片，就像一片片弹过的棉花一样，让它们飘浮在空中。直到后来，它们被太阳的热融化，形成柔和细腻的雨水，让草儿生长，让水果成熟，让玉米一小时就长出一英寸。可是，如果她不高兴，她就孕育出墨水一样黑的乌云，坐在乌云中间，就像一只大腹便便的蜘蛛坐在蜘蛛网中间。当这样的乌云发作时——灾难就降临到山谷上了！

旧时，根据印第安人的传说，曾经有一种神灵一直在卡茨基尔山最为荒凉的幽深之处到处游荡。这种神灵喜欢恶作剧，以给红种的印第安人制造各种灾祸和烦恼为乐事。有时，他装扮成一头熊，有时又装扮成一只豹，有时会装扮成一只鹿，弄得那个眼花缭乱的猎人在盘根错节的森林里、在崎岖不平的岩石间疲于奔命地追踪他。然后，他又忽然一跃而起，大喊两声“嗬！嗬！”，让站在悬崖边或汹涌澎湃的河流边的猎人大惊失色。

这位神灵最喜欢的住处今天仍然可见，就是卡茨基尔山脉中最偏僻处的一块大石或一处悬崖。这里被攀附着开了花的葡萄藤挡住，附近遍地都是野花。因此，这里也叫“花园石”。它脚下的不远处是一个小湖。那是孤独的麻鸦经常出没的地方，一条条水蛇爬到睡莲的叶子上晒着太阳。这是最让印第安人充满敬畏的地方，即便是最勇敢的狩猎者也不会在此区域内追杀猎物。然而，从前有一个猎人迷了路，走进花园石，发现树杈上挂着很多葫芦，他抓了其中一个葫芦就走，但在离开时，他匆匆忙忙，竟把葫芦掉进了岩石中。这时候，一股巨大的水流喷涌向前，将他卷走，并冲下悬崖，顷刻间他粉身碎骨。那溪水再次流入哈德孙河，永不停息地流到今天。这条河同人们所知道的卡特斯基尔河是同一条河流。

（杨枫　译）

[1]威廉・卡特赖特（1611-1643），英国诗人，剧作家，教士。（说明：书中脚注均为编者注。）

[2]1英里约等于1.6千米。

[3]1英尺约等于30厘米。

[4]指领导美国独立战争的人。

妻子

/

汪洋大海的珍宝

同锁在女人爱情里的男人

那隐藏的慰藉相比，

完全无法匹敌。

每次走近家门，

我便嗅到祝福的气息。

婚姻散发的芬芳

多么沁人心脾！

即使是紫罗兰的芳香

哪能与它相比！

——米德尔顿[5]

我常有机会谈论坚忍力。正是运用这种坚忍力，让妇女们完胜了势不可当的命运逆转。那些让一个男人精神崩溃并从此一蹶不振的灾难，似乎最能激发起温柔女性身上所聚集的全部能量，并让她们展现出品格上的无畏和崇高，这种品格有时会到达高尚的境地。当踏在人生的康庄大道上时，一直是孱弱、事事依赖他人、一丁点儿不顺就发脾气的她，突然精神力量猛增，给遭遇不幸的丈夫以安慰和支持，并以永不退缩的坚毅，承受着逆境所带来的最为猛烈的打击。看到这样一位温存而娇柔的女子，还有什么比这更令人感动的呢！

正如长时间把橡树周围那优美的叶子盘绕，并被橡树高高地托起面向阳光的蔓藤，当橡树这种耐寒的植物被雷电劈裂时，它仍然会用爱抚的卷须盘绕着它，并将它那碎裂的大树枝紧紧地连在一起。同样，经由上帝的绝妙安排，在丈夫快乐时仅仅是附属物、仅仅是装饰品的女人，在丈夫遭受突然的灾难打击时，就应成为他的支柱，成为他的安慰，机智地帮他绕过他天性中的崎岖不平，温柔地托起他那低垂的头，用整个身心紧紧地贴近那颗破碎的心。

我曾给一位朋友道贺，他的家庭兴旺发达，家庭成员间被最强有力的爱编织在了一起。“我希望你交上好运，”他说，带着满腔热情，“最好的运气莫过于拥有妻子和孩子了。假如你成功了，他们会在那儿，与你一同分享；假如你失败了，他们还在那儿，给你带来安慰。”的的确确，我观察到，一个遭到不幸的已婚男子，比起一个单身男子，更容易重新恢复常人的生活。一部分原因是由于那些无助的人，他至爱的人，生活之必需都依靠他，因他才得以生存，他因此而更受刺激，必须加以努力。但主要原因是，他的精神在家人的关爱下得以舒缓、得以缓解，他的自尊就得以维持——因为他发现，尽管外面是无边的黑暗，是无尽的羞辱，可在家里，有一个充满着爱的小天地，而自己就是这小天地里的君主。单身男子则是另一番景象，他们自暴自弃，轻视自己，自觉孤立无助、遭人摒弃，他们的内心世界已成为废墟，犹如无人居住而遭人遗弃的宅邸，期待着住客的到来。

这些感悟让我想起了一则家庭小故事，是我曾亲眼目睹的一件事。我的挚交莱斯利娶了一位中产阶级家庭的才貌双全的女子。这个女孩没有什么财产，但我朋友却很富有。他很高兴，期盼着让女孩尽情追求优雅的生活，期盼着她能培养那些高雅的情趣和爱好，以传递出女性特有的魅力。“她的生活，”他说，“将会过得像童话一般。”

正是他们性格上的差异，使他们的结合非常和谐。他是那种追求浪漫又不失庄重的人，而她则充满活力，是十足的乐天派。我常注意到，有她做伴时，他凝视她的眼神中带着无声的狂喜，她身上那股明快的精气神儿也使她成为大家的开心果。我还发现，当掌声响起时，她的视线会转向他，好像只有在那里，她才寻求到了赞同和认可。倚靠在他的手臂上时，她那苗条的身材同他那伟岸魁梧的体形形成鲜明的对比。她仰望他时，那种亲切而信任的神情，似乎唤起一股强烈的自豪感，还有时刻被珍视的柔情。而他也非常愿意担起这份甜蜜的责任，成为她永久的依靠。没有一对夫妇能像他们这样，从婚姻之初仿佛就踏上了铺满鲜花的大道，无比般配，且幸福的婚姻之路前景乐观。

可是，我的那位朋友非常不幸，他把自己大把的财产都拿去做了投机生意。结婚不到几个月，突如其来的灾难就接踵而至，他的财产被席卷一空，他发现自己几乎沦为穷光蛋了。有一阵子，他对自己的境遇守口如瓶，带着憔悴的面容和一颗破碎的心四处游荡。他的生活不过是无尽的痛苦，让他更难以忍受的是，他还得在妻子面前强装笑脸，因为，他是万万不能够把这个消息告诉妻子，让她崩溃的。然而，那双温存而敏锐的眼睛，是不会看不出他的境遇不佳。她注意到了他表情的变化，注意到了他克制着的叹息。尽管他强装着开心快乐，可这背后的闷闷不乐和郁郁寡欢，都逃不过她的双眼。她调动起自己所有的精力和温柔的甜言蜜语，一定要让他再次幸福地生活起来。可她这样做，只会像把利剑更深地刺进了他的灵魂——他越发觉有理由更爱她，便越会为自己即将给她带来的不幸而更受煎熬。他思忖道，要不了多久，笑容就会从那张脸上消失，歌声就会从那唇间慢慢减弱，那双眼睛的光泽会被忧伤浇灭，而此刻在那个胸膛里轻松跳动着的快乐的心，也会如同他自己的心一般，因人世间的种种忧虑和苦难而不堪重负。

终于有一天，他找到了我，以一种最深的绝望的语气，把他境遇的来龙去脉告诉了我。听完他的话，我问，“你妻子知道这一切吗？”听到这个问题，他突然痛哭流涕。“看在上帝的份儿上！”他哭丧着脸说，“要是你对我还有一丁点儿怜悯之心，就甭提我妻子了——就是想到她，我才快要发疯的呀！”

“为什么不告诉她呢？”我说，“她迟早会知道的。你是不可能长时间瞒着她的。要是从别人口里得到这个消息，她会更震惊，更受不了的，不如你亲自告诉她。因为，从所爱之人的口中说出来的话，是可以软化最严酷的消息的。另外，你不仅剥夺自己从她的关心中所得到的安慰，你还危及了能够把两颗心联系在一起的唯一纽带，那可是一种对思想和情感都不做任何隐瞒的小团体。她会很快察觉到，有什么东西在暗地里让你魂不守舍，真正的爱情里是容不下有任何隐瞒的；要是知道爱人对自己隐瞒了伤心之事，她会觉得自己受到了轻视和伤害，然后更加生气的。”

“唉，可是老朋友！想想看，我跟她说她丈夫已成乞丐了，那会给她的前途带来多大的打击，会给她的心灵带来怎样的重创！那样的话，她就要放弃优雅的生活、快乐的社交活动；就要同我一道，陷入贫困的境地，变得默默无闻！如果我告诉她，我已把她从原来的那种有可能一直光鲜亮丽（众目聚焦的对象，众人仰慕的对象）的生活圈子中拉下马，她怎么忍受得了那份贫寒！她在富足优雅的生活环境中长大，她怎么受得了被人忽视的滋味！她一直是人们的偶像。唉，这会让她心碎的！这会让她心碎的呀！”

看到他口若悬河地诉说着自己的痛苦，我只是在一旁默不作声地听着，因为痛苦是可以通过言语的释放得以缓解的。当他激动的情绪慢慢平息，重新陷于忧郁的沉默中时，我温和地重提原来的话题，催促他当即把自己的现状告诉妻子。他痛不欲生，但却很肯定地，摇了摇头。

“可是，那你是怎样隐瞒着不告诉她的呢？她有必要知道这件事。只有这样，你才能够逐渐采取适当的措施，改变你的境况。你得改变自己的生活方式——而且，”看到他脸上掠过一阵痛苦的神情，“别让这种事儿折磨你了。我相信你不是那种四处炫耀幸福的人。况且，你还有那么多朋友，他们那么热情，不会因为你住得不如以前富丽堂皇就小瞧了你呀。不过当然，跟玛丽一起寻求幸福的生活，也不见得非得有宫殿才可以。”

“我是可以跟她过幸福日子的，”他一个劲儿地抽搐着，“哪怕是住在一间茅屋里！我可以和她一起堕入贫困，甚至一起走向坟墓！我可以的！我可以的！上帝保佑她吧！上帝保佑她吧！”他哭号着，一阵悲伤与柔情涌上心头。

“你就信了我吧，朋友，”我说着，走到他身边，热情地握住他的手，“信了我吧，她会对你一如既往的。哎，还有——对她来说，这将是让她永远感到自豪，永远感到欣慰的事儿呢。那会唤起她天性中潜在的活力与炽热的同情心，因为她会很高兴地证明，她爱的就是你这个人。在每一个真诚女人的内心深处，都有一束天堂之火。这一束火，在有着旺盛生命力的光天化日之下是处在休眠状态的。但在出现逆境的黑夜里，它会燃烧起来，放射出万丈光芒。没有男人知道自己心目中的妻子到底是什么样子——没有男人知道服侍自己的天使到底是什么样子——直到这个男人同他的妻子一道，历经了人世间各种烈火的试炼。”

在说这些时，我的态度非常诚挚，而言语中那些比喻的话引发了莱斯利激动的畅想，他很快陷入遐思之中。我了解身边这位听众。趁我说的话还有效果，我劝他回家，把自己心中的伤心事向妻子一吐为快。

我必须承认，尽管我说了这么多，但对结果还是有些担心的。谁能指望一个一辈子都在享乐的人会坚忍不拔呢？他妻子一直很快乐，当如果突然发现眼前是一条低微、卑贱、黑暗的下坡路时，她很可能会奋起反抗，或许会一直待在让他们如痴如醉的阳光灿烂的地带不愿离去。另外，时尚的生活被摧毁了不说，接下来又是没完没了的，令人烦心的种种屈辱。这对于其他阶层的人来说，是难以理解的。次日早上我见到莱斯利不免担忧。他告诉了我最终的结果。

“她怎么承受这一切的？”

“就像天使那样！一切对她来说，似乎更像是一种宽慰，因为她张开双臂搂住了我的脖子，还问我是不是这一切让我最近郁郁寡欢的。可是，我可怜的人儿，”他接着说，“她并没认识到我们必须经受的变化呀。她对贫穷只有抽象的概念——她只是在诗歌里读到过什么是贫穷，而那里的贫穷都是同爱情联系在一起的。她至今都没尝过穷困的滋味——她还不知道，如果没有惯常的各种便利，没有惯常的高雅生活，那到底是什么滋味。当我们实实在在地去经受可悲的忧虑，为满足低微的需求，蒙受琐碎的羞辱时，迎来的才是真正的考验。”

“不过，”我说，“既然你已闯过最难的一关，也就是向她摊牌了，那你越早让世人知道这个秘密越好。让他人知道你的秘密，或许会令你难为情，但这只是一次性的痛苦，而且不久就会过去的。如果不这样做的话，你想着想着，白天里的每个时辰都会很痛苦。束缚一个一文不名之人手脚的，与其说是贫穷，不如说是虚伪。这是一场心高气傲同一文不名之间的斗争——维持虚假外表的做法，必须尽快终止。如果你有勇气展露贫穷，你就可以消除贫穷带给你的无以复加的剧痛。”关于这一点，我发现莱斯利已有充分的思想准备。他本人并没有虚荣心，至于他妻子，她只是很急于去顺应他们命运改变之后的生活。

几天后，傍晚时分，他来看我。他卖掉了自己的住宅，在离城几英里的乡下买了一间小屋。在这之前，他整天忙着处理家具。新住处需要的家当不多，而且都是最简单的那种。原先住宅里所有的豪华家具全都卖掉了，只留下了他妻子的竖琴。他说，那架竖琴，与他对妻子的念想紧密联系在一起——那是他们爱情的小插曲——因为他们求爱时最甜蜜的时刻就包括他俯在琴上，聆听她美妙声音的时刻。一个宠溺妻子的丈夫所表现出的浪漫殷勤，让我都忍不住为之一笑。

他现在要回乡下的小屋了，他妻子一整天都在那儿指挥如何布置和安排家当。我对这个家庭故事如何进展有着强烈的兴趣，加之那天晚上天气很好，于是就提出与他一同前往。

劳累了一天，他已十分疲乏。当我们走出城时，他陷入一阵阴郁的沉思。

“我可怜的玛丽！”终于，他脱口而出，深深叹了口气。

“她怎么啦？”我问道，“出了什么事儿吗？”

“怎么了，”他说，飞快地瞥了我一眼，很不耐烦，“落入如此卑微的境地，被囚在简陋的小屋里，被迫几乎像仆人一样为那可怜的住所劳心费力，难道能什么事儿也没有吗？”

“那她埋怨过你们生活的变化吗？”

“埋怨？！她一直就是除了高兴还是高兴，除了快乐就是快乐。说实在的，我认识她那么久了，她的情绪似乎从来没有这样好过——她对我是一往情深，温柔体贴！”

“多让人钦佩的女子呀！”我大声叫道，“老朋友，你还说自己穷呢。你以前有这么富吗？你以前压根儿就没认识到自己所拥有的这个女人的优秀品质，那可是无尽的珍宝。”

“哎呀，老朋友呀，如果我现在已经结束了与她在小屋子里的第一次会面，我想我确实会感到舒服的。但这是她亲身体验穷苦的第一天，是别人把她送到我们简陋的住处的。一整天，她就一直在忙于安排和布置屋内那些可怜的家当。她第一次体会到了家务事会让人身心疲惫，她第一次环顾了没有高档家用品，几乎没有任何便利用品的家到底是个什么样子。或许她现在坐下来，精疲力竭、无精打采，正沉思着未来等着她的穷苦生活呢。”

这样的画面，一定程度上确是有可能出现的，对此我无可否认。所以，我们默默地继续前行。

我们从大路转到一条向上去的狭窄小巷，巷子掩映在茂密的林木当中，这里完全是隐秘的。这时，我们看见了他们的小屋。对于多数田园诗人来说，这小屋真是足够简陋的，可是，它有着令人愉快的乡村面貌。一棵野葡萄藤叶子繁茂，把小屋的一端覆盖住了，有好几棵树在小屋上方优雅地伸展着树枝。我注意到门的附近和前面的草地上有几盆花，它们都被打理得很有品位。一扇小边门通往人行道。人行道蜿蜒曲折，穿过灌木丛，一直通到小屋的门。快要走近时，我们听到音乐的声音。莱斯利抓住我的手臂，我们驻足倾听。是玛丽唱歌的声音，那声音纯朴但极为动人，那是她丈夫特别喜欢的一支小曲。

我感觉到，莱斯利的手在我手臂上颤抖。他移步向前，想听得更加清楚，他的脚步在铺着砾石的路上发出了声响。一张光鲜而美丽的脸庞在窗前向外张望，接着便消失了，轻盈的脚步声传来了，玛丽轻快地走上前来迎接我们。她穿着乡下人的那种白色连衣裙，十分漂亮。几朵野花盘在她的秀发上；她面目清新、活力四射，面带灿烂的微笑——我还没有看到过她那么可爱的容颜。

“亲爱的乔治，”她大声说，“很高兴你来了。我一直在期盼着你，期盼着你；我一直在沿着小巷跑来跑去，我一直想得到你的消息。我在小屋后面的一棵漂亮的树下摆了一张桌子，我还一直在采摘最好吃的草莓，因为我知道你很喜欢草莓，我们还有那么好的奶油。这儿的一切都那么甜蜜，一切都那么宁静，啊！”她说着，一下扑进他的怀里，高兴地仰望着他的脸，“噢，我们就是那么幸福！”

可怜的莱斯利再也无法控制住自己——他把妻子拥抱在怀里，他用双臂抱住她，一遍又一遍地吻她，他说不出话来，泪水充满了他的双眼。他经常肯定地告诉我，尽管他从一开始就非常富足，而且他的确也一直生活得很幸福。然而，他却从来没有体验过如那一刻的精彩与幸福。

[5]米德尔顿（1570-1627），英国剧作家，代表作有《米迦勒节期》《一个疯狂的世界，我的老爷》等。

伦敦古迹

/

我在漫步

千真万确，

心同圭多·沃克斯，提着黑暗的灯笼，

偷偷给这座城市放火；

跑到乡下，我被认为神出鬼没，

或者是罗宾·古德菲洛[6]。

——弗莱彻

我有那么点儿热衷于搜寻古物，喜欢跑遍整个伦敦，探寻古时的遗迹。这些遗迹多深藏于伦敦的某个角落，掩埋于乃至消失在由砖块和泥浆构成的一片荒芜之中。不过，从环绕它们的那个司空见惯、平淡无奇的世界里，却可以领略其诗情画意和浪漫情趣。近来夏日，在漫游伦敦的过程中，我对这种情形感触至深，因为只有在夏季去探寻伦敦才最便利。此时的伦敦，没有烟，没有雾，没有冬日的雨水和泥浆。有好一阵子，我一直是在逆行于舰队街的人流中，艰难地行进。暖和的天气早已让我神经紧张，让我对每一次的震动、每一次的推撞、每一种刺耳的声音，都异常敏感。我的身体疲惫不堪，精神萎靡不振，挣扎着挤过那熙熙攘攘、忙忙碌碌的人群，让我失去了好心情。我感到一阵绝望，便从人群中挤了过去，冲进一条小巷子，穿过几个不起眼的拐角，来到一个古雅而宁静的院子里。院子中央有一片草地，榆树低垂，喷泉喷着水，闪闪发光，让草地始终保持着青翠。一个手上捧着书的学生坐在一张石凳上，一边看书，一边若有所思地望着两三个负责照看婴孩、身材苗条的保姆们的一举一动。

我就像一个在贫瘠得令人窒息的沙漠中突然找到绿洲的阿拉伯人。渐渐地，这个地方的宁静和凉爽让我心绪安宁，精神焕发。我继续前行，来到了附近一座非常古老的教堂。低矮的撒克逊式门额宏伟而富丽。教堂的内部呈圆形，顶部高耸，灯光从高处照下来。教堂四周，是古时的纪念墓碑，上面是一个个身穿盔甲大理石武士雕像。有的武士虔诚地把双手交叉在胸前，另一些则紧握剑柄圆头——即使是在墓中，他们也要气势汹汹，满怀敌意！还有几位交叉着双腿，他们看上去是心怀信仰，曾参加过十字军东征，去往圣地的士兵。

我，实际上是在“骑士圣殿”的教堂里，它竟出乎意料地置身于肮脏喧闹的市中心。于我这个精通世故的人来说，突然离开忙碌、追求金钱生活的人生道路，端坐于唯有暮色、尘埃和被人遗忘的阴暗的坟墓之间时，让我坚信，我定能获得更为深刻的教益。

在接下来的考察之旅中，我又遇到另一个被锁于伦敦市中心的，一个“往昔世界”的遗迹。当时，我已在那些单调乏味的街道上闲逛了好一阵子，没有任何东西吸引我的眼球，也没有任何东西激发我的想象。这时，我突然看到前方有一个已成为残壁遗物的哥特式入口。它通向一个宽敞的四合院，与之形成了一座庄严的哥特式建筑的庭院，哥特式建筑的大门矗立在那里，“令人向往地开着”。

这显然是一座公共大厦。因为我就是来探访古迹的，所以尽管迈着迟疑的步子，我还是贸然走了进去。如此闯入，既没人阻止，也没人非难。我继续前行，直至来到一个大厅。大厅那高耸的顶部呈拱形，走廊是橡木制成的，都是清一色的哥特式风格。大厅的一端是一个巨大的壁炉，壁炉的两边都放着高背长椅。大厅的另一端是一个高台，或许是讲坛，那是至尊的席位。高台的上方是一个男子的画像，男子身着古代服饰：一袭长袍，白色的拉夫领，令人肃然起敬的灰白胡须。

整个建筑有一种修道院式的宁静和隐秘感。而令这个建筑有着神秘魅力的另一个地方在于：自我跨过门槛后，还没碰到过一个人。

受到眼前这种寂寥的刺激，我在一个大弓形窗的凹处坐了下来。一大片金色的阳光透过彩色玻璃窗户射进来，被分割成了小方格，投射在地上。柔和的夏日微风从一扇开着的窗户轻拂入内。此时，我把头倚靠在手上，把胳膊撑在一张旧橡木桌上，然后就这个问题陷入了沉思：这座大厦在古代最有可能做何种用途呢？很显然，它起初一直是用来做修道院的。也许是从前建起来为了推广学术的一种学院机构。这里的僧侣都很有耐心，在修道院那无垠的孤寂中，他们一页页地，一卷卷地，不断增添内容，精心打造自己的作品，尽量使它有着与自己所居的建筑群相匹敌的魅力。

当我坐着冥思苦想时，大厅上端的拱门内，一个有饰板的小门打开了。一帮头发灰白、身着长长的黑色斗篷的老人逐一走了出来。他们一言不发，穿过大厅，往前行进。在经过时，一个个面色苍白地看了看我，然后穿过大厅下端的另一扇门，消失了。

我对他们的外表感到异常惊奇。他们那黑色的斗篷，他们那古风十足的神态，与这栋庄严而神秘建筑的风格非常相称。他们就像是那些我一直在冥思苦想的古代幽灵，像放电影一样，从我眼前飘过。我本着浪漫主义的精神，用这些幻象来取悦自己，着手去探寻那个我为自己所描绘的，存于黑暗中的国度。这个国度恰巧存在于现实世界的正中心。

我漫步着，穿过了迷宫般的内部庭院、走廊和破旧的修道院。许多大型建筑物都会有各种建于不同时期、风格各异的扩建部分和附属建筑物。在一个开阔地带，有很多显然就住在这座建筑物中的男孩子在玩着游戏。无论我去哪里，都能注意到那些身穿黑色斗篷、头发灰白、异常神秘的老人。他们时而独自漫步，时而凑在一起说说话，看上去俨然成了停留于此，随处可见的鬼魂。这时，我突然回想起自己读过的古时候某些大学的情况。这些大学，给学生教授的是司法占星术、泥土占卜、招魂术和其他被禁止的神奇科学。难道这就是那样的一种机构？难道那些身穿黑色斗篷的老人，真正的身份其实是传授这些黑暗艺术的教授们吗？

当这些猜测正掠过我的脑海时，我的目光刚好瞥过一个房间的内部。房间里挂满了各种奇怪、做工粗糙的物品，有野蛮人的作战工具；奇怪的玩偶和填充的鳄鱼标本；瓶装的蛇和怪物装饰着的壁炉架；还有，在一张老式床的高台上，一个咧嘴笑着的人的头骨，两侧各有一只风干的猫。

我向前走去，更仔细地看了看这个神秘的房间。房间似乎非常适合做巫师的实验室。这时，我看到一双眼睛正从一个阴暗的角落盯着我看，不免大吃一惊。原来是一个个头很小、全身干瘪的老头儿，他的脸颊瘦削，双眼明亮，突出的眉毛灰白、坚硬。我起初还以为是一只神奇的保存良好的木乃伊。结果它开始到处走动，我才注意到“它”是活的。这是另一位身着黑色斗篷的老头儿。在我端详那古怪的面相、过时的装束，还有环绕在他周围的那些可怕而又凶险的各种物品时，我开始说服自己：我这是碰到大法师了——正是他管辖着这个有魔力的男信徒组织。

看到我在门前停了下来，他起身请我进去。我以从未有过的胆量，应邀而入，因为，我怎么能确保，他不会挥一挥法杖，把我变成某种怪物呢？或者把我收进他壁炉台上的某只瓶子里？可是，他的一切都证明了他绝不是个巫师。他很单纯，话很多，这很快消除了我先前认为的，一直笼罩在这栋古老的建筑及同样古老的居民周围的所有魔法和神秘气息。

看上去我是进入了一个古老的，庇护老迈商人和衰落房主的中心，同该中心相连的是一所男孩子数量有限的学校。它建在一座古修道院上，两个多世纪以来多少还保留了修道院的氛围和特征。先前在大厅里从我面前经过的那些身穿斗篷的，被我视为魔术师的老人其实是靠养老金生活的人。他们刚从礼拜堂做完早礼拜回来。

约翰・哈勒姆，也就是先前那位被我当成大法师的古董收藏家，在这个地方已经生活了六年，还用他一生收集到的圣物和珍品给这个作为他晚年最后归宿的地方做了装饰。根据他自己的说法，他好歹也算得上是个旅游家，曾在法国待过，还差点儿去了荷兰。他很后悔荷兰之旅未曾成行，“要是去成了，他很可能早就聊起去过那儿的事儿了”——可以很明显地看出，他是那种很单纯的游客。

他在观念很有贵族气。据我观察，他跟那些普通的靠养老金生活的人拒不往来。他主要交往的人包括：一位讲拉丁语和希腊语的盲人，而对这两种语言，哈勒姆是一窍不通的；另一位是一个穷困潦倒的绅士，他早就把他父亲遗留的四万英镑挥霍掉了，还把妻子的嫁妆钱一万英镑挥霍光了。个头小小的哈勒姆似乎觉得，能够挥霍掉这么大的两笔巨款，确实是无可辩驳地显示出了崇高的精神和高贵的出身。

附笔：

这个让读者如痴如醉的旧时风景如画的遗迹，就是现在的“查特豪斯慈善机构”，原先叫“加尔都西修道院”。它是于一六六一年由托马斯・萨顿爵士在一个古老的女修道院旧址上建造起来的，是经个人慷慨解囊而着手建造的高贵慈善机构之一。尽管置身于伦敦的现代变革与创新之中，但它一直保持着远古时代的古怪与圣洁。这里八十位身体衰弱的男子，曾过着富裕的日子。如今，他们的晚年却要由他人来提供衣食、燃料，领用年度津贴。他们像昔日的僧侣那样一起在大厅里就餐。大厅曾是早先修道院的食堂。该建筑还有个附属机构，是一所招收了四十四名男生的学校。

斯托——他的著作我在探讨这个问题时参考过——在谈到这些头发灰白、靠养老金生活的人的各种义务时，说：“关涉到医院事务的任何事情，他们是不允许干预的。他们只需专心侍奉上帝，只需对提供给他们的一切心存感激而不要嘀咕，不要私下抱怨，不要嫉恨。任何人都不得携带武器，不得留长发，不得穿彩色的靴子，不得穿骑马时用的靴刺，不得在帽子上装饰羽毛，不得凶神恶煞，不得穿奇装异服，只得穿着像病人一样的衣服。”“说实在话，”斯托补充道，“真正幸福的就是这样一些人，他们从人世间的一切忧愁和烦恼中解脱出来，然后就像这些老人那样，固定地住在一个这么好的地方，毫无后顾之忧，只有宁静的心灵来侍奉上帝，在兄弟般的情谊中生活。”

[6]罗宾・古德菲洛，英国民间传说中的恶作剧专家，又被称为“好人罗宾”，是个好心肠、爱帮忙的小精灵，在莎士比亚的《仲夏夜之梦》里以浦克的名字出场。

破碎的心

/

我从未听说

有什么真正的爱情

可以不为忧虑所吞食，

忧虑，犹如毛虫

蛀蚀着春天最甜蜜的图书——玫瑰的叶子。

——米德尔顿

从早期情感伤痛中活过来的人，或者在享乐至上、冷漠无情的环境中长大的人，通常的做法便是嘲笑所有的爱情故事，把富于浪漫激情的各种故事仅仅看成是小说家们和诗人们虚构的作品。我对人性的种种考察，让我有了不同的见解。这些考察让我相信，就算性格的表象可能会因人世间的烦恼而变得冷漠，因社交中的圆滑塑造而徒留一张笑脸，但在最冰冷的内心深处，仍然潜伏着随时都有可能爆发的烈火。一旦被触发，烈火就会肆虐，有时还会带来凄惨的后果。真的，我笃信盲神，并充分理解他的教义——我要承认吗？——我相信会有破碎的心，相信会有死于失恋的可能！可我并不认为这对于男性来说，是致命的疾病；但我坚信，这会使许多可爱的女子渐渐枯萎，早早地进入坟墓。

男人是追逐利益、野心勃勃的动物。他们的天性使得他们勇猛地闯入人世间的斗争和喧嚣之中。爱，仅仅是他们早年生活的点缀，抑或是在幕间休息时用管乐器演奏的一首歌。男人追名逐利，试图在世人的思想中占有一席之地，试图统领自己的同胞。可是，女人的一生就是一部感情史，心即是她的世界：就是在那里，她雄心勃勃地要得到绝对控制权；就是在那里，她贪婪地寻觅着深藏的珍宝。她对冒险会不遗余力，并在情感交流中寄托自己的整个灵魂，而一旦触礁，她便无可救药，因为那颗心碎了。

对于男人而言，失恋也许会引起某种刻骨铭心的剧痛：它伤害了脉脉的柔情，它毁灭了幸福的前景。但他是一个有活力的个体，他会在各种纷繁事务中把各种念想抛到九霄云外，或者一头扎进快乐的洪流中。再或者，如果失恋之地带给他痛苦的回忆，他会随自己意愿迁往另一个住地，他会乘上清晨的翅膀，“飞往海角天涯，寻求那份安宁”。

但相比而言，女人过的是一种固定的、隐蔽的、冥想的生活。更多时候，她往往离不开自己的思想，离不开自己的感情。如果她的思想和感情被转化成悲伤的代言人，她从何处得到慰藉！她命中注定要被男人追求，要被男人俘虏。如果在爱中得不到幸福，她的心就像被攻破的、被洗劫的、被抛弃的堡垒，惨遭劫掠，最后剩下的就只有凄凉和孤寂。

有多少明亮的眼睛最终黯淡无光，有多少柔软的面颊最终没有血色，有多少优美的身段逐渐消失入墓。可是没有谁能说得清到底是什么摧毁了她们的美丽。就像鸽子要把翅膀搭在身体的一侧，遮住和掩盖射中它命脉的飞箭一样，女人天性也是要向世人隐瞒受伤的情感带来的剧痛。细腻的女子，总是爱得羞涩，爱得无声。即便当幸运降临时，她也几乎是只字不提。但当不幸降临时，她便将痛苦埋藏于内心深处。在那里，她让厄运在自己安宁的废墟间萎缩、消退。对她来说，心中的渴望已经远去，生存的巨大魅力已经结束。她无视一切令人欢愉的运动，尽管这些运动使人精神振奋，加快脉搏跳动，使生命潮汐在血管里健康地涌动着。她的那份宁静已被打破——忧郁的梦魇破坏了清新甜蜜的睡眠——“干涸的悲伤吸干了她的鲜血”，直到她那衰弱的躯干在最轻微的外部伤害下垮掉。假如你过一段时间去找她，你就发现朋友因她过早走进坟墓而哭泣。你大惑不解：一个不久前还容光焕发、光鲜美丽的人儿，怎么那么快就坠落到“黑暗与蠕虫”为伍的阴间。有人会告诉你，那是由于冬日严寒，某种不经意的小病，要了她的小命——但是，谁又知晓先前就耗掉了她体力、使她轻易成为掠夺者猎物的心理疾病？

她就像一棵娇嫩的树，代表着小树林的荣耀和美丽；它姿态婀娜，枝繁叶茂，但心里却遭受着蠕虫的叮咬。在它最应该充满活力、繁茂之时，却突然枯萎了。我们看到它的枝头低垂到了地面；看到它一片树叶接着一片树叶地凋零。直到消耗殆尽、慢慢消亡，在寂静的森林中轰然倒下。而当我们重温这美丽的废墟时，我们再怎么努力也无法追忆起究竟是什么狂风暴雨将它摧毁。

我见过许多女人自我轻视，自我毁灭，并渐渐从这世上消失，就好像她们早早地被蒸发到了天国。我不止一次地想，我可以通过对耗掉她们生命的各种衰微症状（如感冒、衰弱、疲倦、忧郁等）的研究，来追踪她们死亡的痕迹，直至我找到她们失恋的首发症状。可是，最近有人给我讲起同样的事例。这件事在事件发生的国度尽人皆知，我在这里就只讲讲是如何发生的。

大家一定记得爱尔兰爱国人士——年轻的艾某某[7]的悲惨故事。他的故事太感人了，让人难以忘记。在爱尔兰动乱期间，他被指控犯有叛国罪，受到了审判和谴责，继而被处以绞刑。他的命运引起公众深深的同情。他是那么年轻、聪明，那么大方、勇敢，一个年轻人受人青睐的种种美德，均在他身上有所体现。在接受审判时，他的表现是那样高尚、无畏。他用崇高而激愤的方式击退了他人对他叛国罪的指控。那是一场维护名誉的雄辩，也是在受到谴责的无望时刻，对下一代人发出的可悲的呼吁。所有这些，都深深扎进每一个慷慨之人的心胸，就连他的敌人也痛恨那条规定处死他的严苛政策。

但是有一颗心，它的痛苦是无法描述的。在先前快乐、幸运的日子里，他赢得了一位美丽可爱的姑娘的芳心。姑娘是已故著名爱尔兰律师的女儿。她爱着他，像所有年轻女孩初恋之时那样无私，充满热情。当他与世俗的行为准则格格不入时，当他遭受厄运，耻辱和危险黑压压地笼罩着他的名声时，她却正因为他所遭受的苦难而爱得更加热烈。倘若此时，他的命运甚至都能够唤起敌人的同情……那个全部灵魂都被他音容笑貌所占据的她，从头到尾又将忍受何种极度的痛苦！请那些人说说，到底是谁让他们突然阴阳两隔？就像一个人坐在坟墓的门槛上，眼看着另一个被关进了寒冷而寂寞的世界，从此，一切可爱的事物，所有亲爱的人儿，都将永远地诀别。

紧接着，看看这是怎样一个恐怖的坟墓！那么可怕，那么不光彩！没有任何回忆可以用来抚慰这样分离的痛苦；也没有温柔而忧郁的环境，使分别稍显亲切；没有任何东西可以把悲伤融化成犹如天堂露水般幸福的泪珠，使人在痛苦的焦灼时刻，恢复往日的心情。

她不幸的恋情还引得父亲的不快，恼怒的父亲早已将她赶出家门，这一切使现在寡居的她更显凄凉。假若朋友们的同情之心和仁慈之举能触动这个被恐怖经历所震惊、被恐惧所裹挟的灵魂的话，她应该也就不再需要什么安慰了，因为爱尔兰人是一个思维敏捷、慷慨大方的民族。很多富有又显赫的家庭都对她关怀备至，她被介绍进社交圈子，他们让她参加各种娱乐活动，以消除她内心的悲痛，让她同先前那悲剧的爱情故事一刀两断。但一切都是徒然。在遭受如此打击之后，她的灵魂已经被灼烧甚至焦化；而她幸福的温床也随之被毁，再也不会发芽或开花。她从来没有拒绝去光顾娱乐的场所，但她还是像原先那样，形单影孤，置身于深深的孤独中。她会四下里走走，却总处于悲伤的遐想之中，很显然，她对周围的世界失去感觉。她内心深处，满满的都是忧伤。她用内心的忧伤嘲笑着朋友给予的所有甜言蜜语，“不听行法术的声音，虽用极灵的咒语、也是不听”[8]。

向我讲述她故事的人曾在一个化装舞会上碰到过她。没有比在这样的场合遇见她，更能显示出她早先曾有过的痛苦是多么触目惊心、令人心碎。他看到她像幽灵一样，四处游荡，孤独、悲伤，而环绕周围的却是欢乐的景象。他看到她穿着欢乐的服装，脸色是那么苍白，那么愁苦，就好像她曾徒然努力去欺骗那颗可怜的心，让它把伤悲短暂地遗忘。心不在焉地信步穿过一个个富丽堂皇的房间和眼花缭乱的人群后，她就在管弦乐队的台阶上坐了下来。有一阵子，她茫然地四下张望，这说明她对眼前花哨的场面没有了感觉。带着一颗病弱的心，她开始反复无常地哼起了哀伤的小调。她的声音本来很甜美，但在这个场合，它是那么简朴，那么动人。它吐露出了一颗悲戚的灵魂，让周围的人听得鸦雀无声，把周围的每个人软化得眼含热泪。

在一个以热情著称的国度，如此真诚而又温柔的故事，不可能不激起人们浓厚的兴趣。她完全赢得了一位勇敢军官的心。军官向她求爱，并认为一个对死者如此忠贞的人，对生者不可能不一往情深。她谢绝了军官的求婚，她的全部心思不可动摇地专注于昔日情人的记忆里。可是，那位军官却紧追不舍。他所寻求的不是她的柔情，而是她的尊重。她心里清楚，他很富有，也知道自己穷困，且要依赖他人才能生存。现下她要靠好心的朋友接济才能维持生活，这境况帮了他的忙。总之，他同她终于成功牵手，尽管明确地知道：她的心不可改变地属于另一个男人。

那位军官带着她去了意大利的西西里岛，希望换一个环境会让她慢慢忘记昔日的悲痛。她和蔼可亲，是一个模范的妻子，她也在努力成为快乐生活的人。可是，没有什么医治得了那份早已进入她灵魂的，默默地、吞噬着她生命的悲哀。她在缓慢却是无望的消瘦中日渐衰弱，最后走进了坟墓，成了破碎之心的牺牲品。

就是为了她，著名的爱尔兰诗人托马斯・穆尔[9]写下了如下诗行：

她远离了那片土地，那个她年轻英雄的长眠之地，

周围爱恋她的人无不哀叹；

但很冷漠地，她避开他们的注视而独自哭泣，

因为她的心留在了躺着那英雄的地底。

她唱着可爱家乡的平原上那豪放的歌曲，

他热爱的每个音符震撼人心——

哎，喜欢听她歌曲的人们，

很少想到这是被怎样撕碎着的歌者的心！

他为了爱人而活；为了祖国献身而死。

这乃是伴随他生命的一切——

他祖国的眼泪不会很快干涸，

他爱的人儿亦不会在他身后久留！

啊！给她造一座阳光永驻的坟墓吧，

因为阳光预示着灿烂一天的开始；

阳光将照耀她的睡姿，那仿佛是来自西方的微笑，

仿佛是来自她至爱的悲伤之岛的微笑！

[7]此处所指应该是爱尔兰民族主义领袖罗伯特・埃米特（1778-1803）。

[8]《圣咏集》58：5。

[9]托马斯・穆尔（1779-1852），爱尔兰杰出爱国主义诗人，代表作《爱尔兰歌曲集》。

Te Wife

The treasures of the deep are not so precious

As are the conceal' d comforts of a man

Lock' d up in woman's love. I scent the air

Of blessings, when I come but near the house.

What a delicious breath marriage sends forth,

The violet bed's not sweeter!

MIDDLETON.

I have often had occasion to remark the fortitude with which women sustain the most overwhelming reverses of fortune. Those disasters which break down the spirits of a man, and prostrate him in the dust, seem to call forth all the energies of the softer sex, and give such intrepidity and elevation to their character, that at times it approaches to sublimity. Nothing can be more touching than to behold a soft and tender female, who had been all weakness and dependence, and alive to every trivial roughness while treading the pros‑perous paths of life, suddenly rising in mental force, to be the comforter and supporter of her husband under misfor‑tune, and abiding, with unshrinking firmness, the bitterest blasts of adversity.

As the vine which has long twined its graceful foliage about the oak, and been lifted by it into sunshine, will, when the hardy plant is rifted by the thunderbolt, cling round it with its caressing tendrils and bind up its shattered boughs; so is it beautifully ordered by providence, that woman, who is the mere dependent and ornament of man in his happier hours, should be his stay and solace when smitten with sud‑den calamity, winding herself into the rugged recesses of his nature; tenderly supporting the drooping head, and binding up the broken heart.

I was once congratulating a friend, who had around him a blooming family knit together in the strongest afection. ‘I can wish you no better lot,' said he, with enthusiasm, ‘than to have a wife and children. If you are prosperous, there they are to share your prosperity; and if otherwise, there they are to comfort you. - ‘And indeed I have observed that a married man falling into misfortune, is more apt to retrieve his situation in the world than a single one; partly because he is more stimulated to exertion by the necessities of the helpless and beloved beings who depend upon him for sub‑sistence; but chiefy because his spirits are soothed and relieved by domestic endearments, and his self respect kept alive by fnding, that though all abroad is darkness and humiliation, yet there is still a little world of love at home, of which he is the monarch. Wereas a single man is apt to run to waste and self neglect; to fancy himself lonely and abandoned, and his heart to fall to ruin like some deserted mansion for want of an inhabitant.

Tese observations call to mind a little domestic story, of which I was once a witness. My intimate friend Leslie had married a beautiful and accomplished girl, who had been brought up in the midst of fashionable life. She had, it is true, no fortune, but that of my friend was ample and he delighted in the anticipation of indulging her in every ele‑gant pursuit; and administering to those delicate tastes and fancies, that spread a kind of witchery about the sex - ‘her life,' said he, ‘shall be like a fairy tale.'

The very difierence in their characters produced an har‑monious combination. He was of a romantic and somewhat serious cast; she was all life and gladness. I have often noticed the mute rapture with which he would gaze upon her in company, of which her sprightly powers made her the delight; and how in the midst of applause, her eye would still turn to him, as if there alone she sought favour and acceptance. When leaning on his arm her slender form con‑trasted finely with his tall, manly person. The fond confiding air with which she looked up to him, seemed to call forth a flush of triumphant pride and cherishing tenderness; as if he doted on his lovely burthen, for its very helplessness. - Never did a couple set forward on the flowery path of early and well suited marriage, with a fairer prospect of felicity.

It was the misfortune of my friend, however, to have embarked his property in large speculations, and he had not been married many months, when, by a succession of sudden disasters, it was swept from him, and he found him‑self reduced almost to penury. For a time he kept his situation to himself and went about with a haggard coun‑tenance and a breaking heart. His life was but a protracted agony, and what rendered it more insupportable was the necessity of keeping up a smile in the presence of his wife; for he could not bring himself to overwhelm her with the news. She saw, however, with the quick eyes of affection, that all was not well with him. She marked his altered looks and stifled sighs, and was not to be deceived by his sickly and vapid attempts at cheerfulness. She tasked all her sprightly powers and tender blandishments to win him back to happiness; but she only drove the arrow deeper into his soul - the more he saw cause to love her the more torturing was the thought that he was soon to make her wretched. A little while, thought he, and the smile will vanish from that cheek - the song will die away from those lips - the lustre of those eyes will be quenched with sorrow; and the happy heart which now beats lightly in that bosom, will be weighed down like mine by the cares and miseries of the world.

At length he came to me, one day, and related his whole situation in a tone of the deepest despair. When I had heard him through I enquired, ‘Does your wife know all this?' - at the question he burst into an agony of tears - ‘For God's sake!' cried he, ‘if you have any pity on me don't mention my wife - it is the thought of her that drives me almost to madness!'

‘And why not?' said I, ‘she must know it sooner or later: you cannot keep it long from her, and the intelligence may break upon her in a more startling manner than if imparted by yourself; for the accents of those we love soften the harsh‑est tidings. Besides you are depriving yourself of the comforts of her sympathy and not merely that, but also endangering the only bond that can keep hearts together, an unreserved community of thought and feeling. She will soon perceive that something is secretly preying upon your mind, and true love will not brook reserve: it feels under‑valued and outraged when even the sorrows of those it loves are concealed from it.'

‘Oh but my friend! to think what a blow I am to give to all her future prospects - how I am to strike her very soul to the earth, by telling her that her husband is a beggar! - That she is to forego all the elegancies of life - all the pleasures of society - to shrink with me into indigence and obscurity! - To tell her that I have dragged her down from the sphere in which she might have continued to move in constant brightness - the light of every eye - the admiration of every heart!——How can she bear poverty! - she has been brought up in all the refinements of opulence. - How can she bear neglect! - she has been the idol of society - oh, it will break her heart! - it will break her heart! -'

I saw his grief was eloquent and I let it have its flow, for sorrow relieves itself by words. When his paroxysm had sub‑sided and he had relapsed into moody silence, I resumed the subject gently, and urged him to break his situation at once to his wife. He shook his head mournfully, but positively.

‘But how are you to keep it from her?It is necessary she should know it, that you may take the steps proper to the alteration of your circumstances. You must change your style of living - nay,' observing a pang to pass across his countenance- ‘don' t let that afflict you. I am sure you have never placed your happiness in outward shew - you have yet friends, warm friends, who will not think the worse of you for being less splendidly lodged; - and surely it does not require a palace to be happy with Mary -'

‘I could be happy with her,' cried he convulsively, ‘in a hovel! - I could go down with her into poverty and the dust! - I could - I could——God bless her! - God bless her! -' cried he, bursting into a transport of grief and tenderness.

‘And believe me my friend,' said I stepping up and grasp‑ing him warmly by the hand -‘ believe me, she can be the same with you. Aye, more - it will be a source of pride and triumph to her - it will call forth all the latent energies and fervent sympathies of her nature; for she will rejoice to prove that she loves you for yourself. There is in every true woman's heart a spark of heavenly fire which lies dormant in the broad daylight of prosperity; but which kindles up, and beams and blazes in the dark hour of adversity. No man knows what the wife of his bosom is - no man knows what a ministering angel she is - until he has gone with her through the fiery trials of this world.'

There was something in the earnestness of my manner, and the figurative style of my language that caught the excited imagination of Leslie. I knew the auditor I had to deal with; and following up the impression I had made, I finished by persuading him to go home and unburthen his sad heart to his wife.

I must confess, notwithstanding all I had said, I felt some little solicitude for the result. Who can calculate on the for‑titude of one whose whole life has been a round of pleasures? - Her gay spirits might revolt at the dark down‑ward path of low humility suddenly pointed out before her, and might cling to the sunny regions in which they had hitherto revelled. Besides, ruin in fashionable life is accom‑panied by so many galling mortifications to which in other ranks it is a stranger - in short, I could not meet Leslie the next morning without trepidation. He had made the disclosure.

- ‘And how did she bear it?'

‘Like an angel! It seemed rather to be a relief to her mind, for she threw her arms round my neck, and asked if this was all that had lately made me unhappy - but, poor girl,' - added he, ‘she cannot realize the change we must undergo. She has no idea of poverty but in the abstract - she has only read of it in poetry, where it is allied to love. She feels as yet no privation - she suffers no loss of accustomed conveniences nor elegancies. When we come practically to experience its sordid cares, its paltry wants, its petty humiliations - then will be the real trial.'

‘But,' said I, ‘now that you have got over the severest task, that of breaking it to her, the sooner you let the world into the secret the better. The disclosure may be mortifying, but then it is a single misery and soon over, whereas you other‑wise suffer it in anticipation, every hour in the day. It is not poverty so much as pretence, that harrasses a ruined man. The struggle between a proud mind and an empty purse - the keeping up a hollow shew that must soon come to an end. Have the courage to appear poor and you disarm pov‑erty of its sharpest sting.' - On this point I found Leslie perfectly prepared. He had no false pride himself, and as to his wife she was only anxious to conform to their altered fortunes.

Some days afterwards he called upon me in the evening. He had disposed of his dwelling house and taken a small cottage in the country, a few miles from town. He had been busied all day in sending out furniture. The new establish‑ment required few articles, and those of the simplest kind. All the splendid furniture of his late residence had been sold excepting his wife's Harp. That, he said, was too closely associated with the idea of herself - it belonged to the little story of their loves - for some of the sweetest moments of their courtship were those when he had leant over that instrument and listened to the melting tones of her voice. - I could not but smile at this instance of romantic gallantry in a doting husband.

He was now going out to the cottage, where his wife had been all day, superintending its arrangement. My feelings had become strongly interested in the progress of this family story and as it was a fine evening I offered to accom‑pany him.

He was wearied with the fatigues of the day, and as we walked out, fell into a fit of gloomy musing.

‘Poor Mary!' at length broke with a heavy sigh from his lips.

‘And what of her,' asked I, ‘has any thing happened to her?'

‘What,' said he, darting an impatient glance, ‘is it nothing to be reduced to this paltry situation - to be caged in a miserable cottage - to be obliged to toil almost in the menial concerns of her wretched habitation?'

‘Has she then repined at the change?'

‘Repined! - she has been nothing but sweetness and good humour. Indeed she seems in better spirits than I have ever known her - she has been to me all love and tenderness and comfort!'

‘Admirable girl!' exclaimed I. ‘You call yourself poor my friend; you never were so rich - you never knew the bound‑less treasures of excellence you possessed in that woman.'

‘Oh, but my friend - if this first meeting at the cottage were over - I think I could then be comfortable. But this is her first day of real experience. She has been introduced into our humble dwelling. She has been employed all day in arranging its miserable equipments. She has for the first time known the fatigues of domestic employment - She has for the first time looked around her on a home destitute of every thing elegant, - almost of every thing convenient, and may now be sitting down exhausted and spiritless, brooding over a prospect of future poverty.'

There was a degree of probability in this picture that I could not gainsay - so we walked on in silence.

After turning from the main road up a narrow lane so thickly shaded by forest trees as to give it a complete air of seclusion, we came in sight of the cottage. It was humble enough in its appearance for the most pastoral poet; and yet it had a pleasing rural look. A wild vine had over run one end with a profusion of foliage - a few trees threw their branches gracefully over it, and I observed several pots of flowers tastefully disposed about the door and on the grass plot in front. A small wicket gate opened upon a foot path that wound through some shrubbery to the door. Just as we approached we heard the sound of music. - Leslie grasped my arm - we paused and listened. It was Mary's voice sing‑ing, in a style of the most touching simplicity, a little air of which her husband was peculiarly fond.

I felt Leslie's hand tremble on my arm. He stepped for‑ward to hear more distinctly - His step made a noise on the gravel walk - a bright beautiful face glanced out at the window and vanished - a light footstep was heard, and Mary came tripping forth to meet us. She was in a pretty, rural dress of white; a few wild flowers were twisted in her fline hair; a fresh bloom was on her cheek; her whole coun‑tenance beamed with smiles - I had never seen her look so lovely.

‘My dear George,' cried she, ‘I am so glad you are come - I' ve been watching and watching for you; and running down the lane, and looking out for you. I' ve set out a table under a beautiful tree behind the cottage - and I' ve been gathering some of the most delicious strawberries, for I know you are fond of them - and we have such excellent cream - and every thing is so sweet and still here - Oh!' said she, putting her arm within his, and looking up brightly in his face - ‘oh, we shall be so happy!'

Poor Leslie was overcome - He caught her to his bosom - he folded his arms round her - he kissed her again and again - he could not speak, but the tears gushed into his eyes - And he has often assured me that though the world has since gone prosperously with him, and his life has, indeed, been a happy one; yet never has he experienced a moment of more exquisite felicity.

London Antiques

- I do walk

Methinks like Guido Vaux, with my dark lanthorn,

Stealing to set the town o' fire; i'th'country

I should be taken for William o' the Wisp,

Or Robin Goodfellow.

FLETCHER.

I am somewhat of an antiquity hunter and am fond of exploring London in quest of the reliques of old times. These are principally to be found in the depths of the city, swallowed up and almost lost in a wilderness of brick and mortar; but deriving poetical and romantic interest from the commonplace prosaic world around them. I was struck with an instance of the kind in the course of a recent sum‑mer ramble into the city; for the city is only to be explored to advantage in summer time; when free from the smoke and fog, and rain and mud of winter. I had been buffeting for some time against the current of population setting through Fleet Street. The warm weather had unstrung my nerves and made me sensitive to every jar and jostle and discordant sound. The flesh was weary, the spirit faint and I was getting out of humor with the bustling busy throng through which I had to struggle, when in a fit of desperation I tore my way through the crowd, plunged into a bye lane, and after passing through several obscure nooks and angles emerged into a quaint and quiet court with a grass plot in the centre overhung by elms, and kept perpetually fresh and green by a fountain with its sparkling jet of water. A student with book in hand was seated on a stone bench, partly read‑ing, partly meditating on the movements of two or three trim nursery maids with their infant charges.

I was like an Arab who had suddenly come upon an oasis amid the panting sterility of the desert. By degrees the quiet and coolness of the place soothed my nerves and refreshed my spirit. I pursued my walk and came, hard by, to a very ancient chapel with a low browed saxon portal of massive and rich architecture. The interior was circular and lofty, and lighted from above. Around were monumental tombs of ancient date, on which were extended the marble effigies of warriors in armour. Some had the hands devoutly crossed upon the breast; others grasped the pummel of the sword - menacing hostility even in the tomb! - while the crossed legs of several indicated soldiers of the Faith who had been on crusades to the Holy Land.

I was in fact, in the chapel of the Knights Templars, strangely situated in the very centre of sordid traffic; and I do not know a more impressive lesson for the man of the world than thus suddenly to turn aside from the high way of busy money seeking life, and sit down among these shadowy sepulchres, where all is twilight, dust and forget‑fulness.

In a subsequent tour of observation I encountered another of these reliques of a ‘foregone world' locked up in the heart of the city. I had been wandering for some time through dull monotonous streets, destitute of any thing to strike the eye or excite the imagination, when I beheld before me a gothic gate way of mouldering antiquity. It opened into a spacious quadrangle forming the court yard of a stately gothic pile the portal of which stood ‘invitingly open.'

It was apparently a public edifice, and as I was antiquity hunting I ventured in, though with dubious steps. Meeting no one either to oppose or rebuke my intrusion I continued on until I found myself in a great hall with a lofty arched roof and oaken gallery, all of gothic architecture. At one end of the hall was an enormous fireplace with wooden set‑tles on each side; at the other end was a raised platform or dais, the seat of state, above which was the portrait of a man in antique garb, with a long robe, a ruff and a venerable grey beard.

The whole establishment had an air of monastic quiet and seclusion, and what gave it a mysterious charm was, that I had not met with a human being since I had passed the threshold.

Encouraged by this loneliness I seated myself in a recess of a large bow window which admitted a broad flood of yellow sunshine, checquered here and there by tints from panes of colored glass; while an open casement let in the soft summer air. Here leaning my head on my hand and my arm on an old oaken table I indulged in a sort of reverie about what might have been the ancient uses of this edi‑fice. It had evidently been of monastic origin; perhaps one of those collegiate establishments built of yore for the pro‑motion of learning, where the patient monk, in the ample solitude of the cloister, added page to page and volume to volume, emulating in the productions of his brain the mag‑nitude of the pile he inhabited.

As I was seated in this musing mood a small panneled door in an arch at the upper end of the hall was opened and a number of grey headed old men, clad in long black cloaks, came forth one by one; proceeding in that manner through the hall, without uttering a word, each turning a pale face on me as he passed, and disappearing through a door at the lower end.

I was singularly struck with their appearance; their black cloaks and antiquated air comported with the style of this most venerable and mysterious pile. It was as if the ghosts of the departed years about which I had been musing were passing in review before me. Pleasing myself with such fan‑cies, I set out, in the spirit of Romance, to explore what I pictured to myself a realm of shadows, existing in the very centre of substantial realities.

My ramble led me through a labyrinth of interior courts and corridors and delapidated cloisters, for the main edifce had many additions and dependencies, built at various times and in various styles; in one open space a number of boys who evidently belonged to the establishment, were at their sports; but every where I observed those mysterious old grey men in black mantles, sometimes sauntering alone; some‑times conversing in groups: they appeared to be the pervading genii of the place. I now called to mind what I had read of certain colleges in old times where judicial astrology, geomancy, necromancy and other forbidden and magical sciences were taught. Was this an establishment of the kind - and were these black cloaked old men really professors of the black art?

These surmises were passing through my mind as my eye glanced into a chamber, hung round with all kinds of strange and uncouth objects: implements of savage warfare; strange idols and stuffed alligators; bottled serpents and monsters decorated the mantelpiece; while on the high tester of an old fashioned bed stead grinned a human skull, flanked on each side by a dried cat.

I approached to regard more narrowly this mystic cham‑ber, which seemed a fitting laboratory for a necromancer, when I was startled at beholding a human countenance staring at me from a dusky corner. It was that of a small, shrivelled old man, with thin cheeks, bright eyes, and grey wiry projecting eyebrows. I at first doubted whether it were not a mummy curiously preserved, but it moved and I saw that it was alive. It was another of these black cloaked old men, and, as I regarded his quaint physiognomy, his obso‑lete garb, and the hideous and sinister objects by which he was surrounded, I began to persuade myself that I had come upon the Arch Mago, who ruled over this magical fraternity.

Seeing me pausing before the door he rose and invited me to enter. I obeyed, with singular hardihood, for how did I know whether a wave of his wand might not metamorphose me into some strange monster, or conjure me into one of the bottles on his mantelpiece. He proved, however, to be any thing but a conjuror, and his simple garrulity soon dispelled all the magic and mystery with which I had enveloped this antiquated pile and its no less antiquated inhabitants.

It appeared that I had made my way into the centre of an ancient asylum for superannuated tradesmen and decayed householders, with which was connected a school for a limited number of boys. It was founded upwards of two centuries since on an old monastic establishment, and retained somewhat of the conventual air and character. The shadowy line of old men in black mantles who had passed before me in the hall, and whom I had elevated into magi, turned out to be the pensioners returning from morning service in the chapel.

John Hallum the little collector of curiosities whom I had made the arch magician, had been for six years a resident of the place, and had decorated this final nestling place of his old age with reliques and rarities picked up in the course of his life. According to his own account he had been somewhat of a traveller; having been once in France and very near making a visit to Holland. He regretted not having visited the latter country, ‘as then he might have said he had been there.' - He was evidently a traveller of the simple kind.

He was aristocratical too in his notions; keeping aloof, as I found, from the ordinary run of pensioners. His chief associates were a blind man who spoke Latin and Greek, of both which languages Hallum was profoundly ignorant; and a broken down gentleman who had run through a for‑tune of forty thousand pounds left him by his father, and ten thousand pounds, the marriage portion of his wife. Little Hallum seemed to consider it an indubitable sign of gentle blood as well as of lofty spirit to be able to squander such enormous sums.

*

P. S. The picturesque remnant of old times into which I have thus beguiled the reader is what is called the Charter House, originally the Chartreuse. It was founded in 1611 on the remains of an ancient convent by Sir Thomas Sutton, being one of those noble charities set on foot by individual munificence, and kept up with the quaintness and sanctity of ancient times amidst the modern changes and innovations of London. Here eighty broken down men, who have seen better days, are provided, in their old age, with food, cloth‑ing, fuel and a yearly allowance for private expenses. They dine together as did the monks of old, in the hall which had been the refectory of the original convent. Attached to the establishment is a school for forty four boys.

Stow, whose work I have consulted on the subject; speak‑ing of the obligations of the grey headed pensioners, says, ‘They are not to intermeddle with any business touching the affairs of the hospital; but to attend only to the service of God, and take thankfully what is provided for them, with‑out muttering, murmuring or grudging. None to wear weapon, long hair, colored boots, spurs or colored shoes; feathers in their hats, or any ruffian like or unseemly apparel, but such as becomes hospital men to wear.' ‘And in truth,' adds Stow, ‘happy are they that are so taken from the cares and sorrows of the world, and fixed in so good a place as these old men are; having nothing to care for, but the good of their souls, to serve God and to live in brotherly love.'

Te Broken Heart

I never heard

Of any true affection but'twas nipt

With care, that, like the caterpillar, eats

The leaves of the spring's sweetest book, the rose.

MIDDLETON.

It is a common practice with those who have outlived the susceptibility of early feeling, or have been brought up in the gay heartlessness of dissipated life, to laugh at all love stories, and to treat the tales of romantic passion as mere fictions of novelists and poets. My observations on human nature have induced me to think otherwise. They have convinced me, that however the surface of the character may be chilled and frozen by the cares of the world, or cultivated into mere smiles by the arts of society, still there are dormant fires lurking in the depths of the coldest bosom, which, when once enkin‑dled, become impetuous and are sometimes desolating in their effects. Indeed, I am a true believer in the blind deity, and go to the - Shall I confess it?- I believe in broken hearts and the possibility of dying of disappointed love! - I do not, howevefull extent of his doctrinesr, consider it a mal‑ady often fatal to my own sex; but I firmly believe that it withers down many a lovely woman into an early grave.

Man is the creature of interest and ambition. His nature leads him forth into the struggle and bustle of the world. Love is but the embellishment of his early life, or a song piped in the intervals of the acts. He seeks for fame, for fortune, for space in the world's thought, and dominion over his fellow men. But a woman's whole life is a history of the affections. The heart is her world: it is there her ambition strives for empire: it is there her avarice seeks for hidden treasures. She sends forth her sympathies on adventure; she embarks her whole soul in the traffic of affection, and if shipwrecked her case is hopeless, for it is a bankruptcy of the heart.

To a man the disappointment of love may occasion some bitter pangs - it wounds some feelings of tenderness - it blasts some prospects of felicity; but he is an active being - he may dissipate his thoughts in the whirl of varied occupation; or may plunge into the tide of pleasure. Or if the scene of disappointment be too full of painful associ‑ations, he can shift his abode at will, and, taking as it were the wings of the morning, can ‘fly to the uttermost parts of the earth and be at rest.'

But woman's is comparatively a fixed, a secluded, and a meditative life. She is more the companion of her own thoughts and feelings; and if they are turned to ministers of sorrow, where shall she look for consolation! Her lot is to be wooed and won; and if unhappy in her love, her heart is like some fortress that has been captured, and sacked, and abandoned and left desolate.

How many bright eyes grow dim - how many soft cheeks grow pale - how many lovely forms fade away into the tomb, and none can tell the cause that blighted their loveliness. As the dove will clasp its wings to its side, and cover and conceal the arrow that is preying on its vitals; so is it the nature of woman to hide from the world the pangs of wounded afection. Te love of a delicate female is always shy and silent. Even when fortunate, she scarcely breathes it to herself; but when otherwise, she buries it in the recesses of her bosom, and there lets it cower and brood among the ruins of her peace. With her the desire of the heart has failed. Te great charm of existence is at an end. She neglects all the cheerful exercises which gladden the spirits, quicken the pulses and send the tide of life in healthful cur‑rents through the veins. Her rest is broken - the sweet refreshment of sleep is poisoned by melancholy dreams - ‘dry sorrow drinks her blood,' until her enfeebled frame sinks under the slightest external injury. Look for her, after a little while, and you fnd friendship weeping over her untimely grave, and wondering that one, who but lately glowed with all the radiance of health and beauty, should so speedily be brought down to ‘darkness and the worm.' You will be told of some wintry chill, some casual indispos‑ition that laid her low - but no one knows of the mental malady which previously sapped her strength and made her so easy a prey to the spoiler.

She is like some tender tree, the pride and beauty of the grove; graceful in its form; bright in its foliage, but with the worm preying at its heart. We fnd it suddenly withering when it should be most fresh and luxuriant. We see it droop‑ing its branches to the earth and shedding leaf by leaf; until wasted and perished away, it falls even in the stillness of the forest; and as we muse over the beautiful ruin, we strive in vain to recollect the blast or thunderbolt that could have smitten it with decay.

I have seen many instances of women running to waste and self neglect, and disappearing gradually from the earth, almost as if they had been exhaled to heaven; and have repeatedly fancied that I could trace their deaths through the various declensions of consumption, cold, debility, lan‑guor, melancholy, until I reached the first symptom of disappointed love. But an instance of the kind was lately told to me; the circumstances are well known in the country where they happened, and I shall but give them in the man‑ner in which they were related.

Every one must recollect the tragical story of young E——the Irish patriot; it was too touching to be soon forgotten. During the troubles in Ireland he was tried, condemned and executed on a charge of treason. His fate made a deep impression on public sympathy. He was so young - so intelligent - so generous - so brave - so every thing that we are apt to like in a young man. His conduct under trial too was so lofty and intrepid. The noble indignation with which he repelled the charge of treason against his country - the eloquent vindication of his name, his pathetic appeal to posterity in the hopeless hour of condemnation - all these entered deeply into every generous bosom, and even his enemies lamented the stern policy that dictated his execution.

But there was one heart, whose anguish it would be impossible to describe. In happier days and fairer fortunes he had won the affections of a beautiful and interesting girl, the daughter of a late celebrated Irish Barrister. She loved him with the disinterested fervour of a woman's first and early love. When every worldly maxim arrayed itself against him; when blasted in fortune, and disgrace and danger darkened around his name, she loved him the more ardently for his very sufferings. If then his fate could awaken the sympathy even of his foes, what must have been the agony of her whose whole soul was occupied by his image! Let those tell who have had the portals of the tomb suddenly closed between them, and the being they most loved on earth - who have sat at its threshold, as one shut out in a cold and lonely world, from whence all that was most lovely and loving had departed.

But then the horrors of such a grave! so frightful - so dishonoured! - There was nothing for memory to dwell on that could soothe the pang of separation - none of those tender though melancholy circumstances which endear the parting scene - nothing to melt sorrow into those blessed tears, sent like the dews of heaven, to revive the heart in the parching hour of anguish.

To render her widowed situation more desolate, she had incurred her father's displeasure by her unfortunate attach‑ment, and was an exile from the paternal roof. But could the sympathy and kind offices of friends have reached a spirit so shocked and driven in by horror, she would have experi‑enced no want of consolation, for the Irish are a people of quick and generous sensibilities. The most delicate and cher‑ishing attentions were paid her by families of wealth and distinction. She was led into society; and they tried by all kinds of occupations and amusements to dissipate her grief and wean her from the tragical story of her loves. But it was all in vain. There are some strokes of calamity which scathe and scorch the soul; which penetrate to the vital seat of hap‑piness, and blast it, never again to put forth bud or blossom. She never objected to frequent the haunts of pleasure, but was as much alone there, as in the depths of solitude; walk‑ing about in a sad reverie, apparently unconscious of the world around her. She carried with her an inward woe that mocked at all the blandishments of friendship, and ‘heeded not the song of the charmer, charm he never so wisely.'

The person who told me her story had seen her at a mas‑querade. There can be no exhibition of far gone wretchedness more striking and painful than to meet it in such a scene. To find it wandering like a spectre, lonely and joyless, where all around is gay - To see it dressed out in the trappings of mirth, and looking so wan and woe begone, as if it had tried in vain to cheat the poor heart into a momentary forgetful‑ness of sorrow. After strolling through the splendid rooms and giddy crowd with an air of utter abstraction, she sat herself down on the steps of an orchestra, and looking about for some time with a vacant air that shewed her insensibility to the garish scene, she began, with the capriciousness of a sickly heart, to warble a little plaintive air. She had an exquisite voice; but on this occasion it was so simple, so touching, it breathed forth such a soul of wretchedness, that she drew a crowd mute and silent around her, and melted every one into tears.

The story of one so true and tender could not but excite great interest in a country remarkable for enthusiasm. It completely won the heart of a brave officer, who paid his addresses to her, and thought that one so true to the dead, could not but prove affectionate to the living. She declined his attentions, for her thoughts were irrevocably engrossed by the memory of her former lover. He, however, persisted in his suit. He solicited not her tenderness, but her esteem. He was assisted by her conviction of his worth, and her sense of her own destitute and dependent situation, for she was existing on the kindness of friends - In a word he at length succeeded in gaining her hand, though with the solemn assurance that her heart was unalterably another's.

He took her with him to Sicily, hoping that a change of scene might wear out the remembrance of early woes. She was an amiable and exemplary wife, and made an effort to be a happy one; but nothing could cure the silent and devouring melancholy that had entered into her very soul. She wasted away in a slow but hopeless decline, and at length sunk into the grave, the victim of a broken heart.

It was on her that Moore the distinguished Irish poet composed the following lines.

She is far from the land where her young hero sleeps,

And lovers around her are sighing;

But coldly she turns from their gaze and weeps,

For her heart in his grave is lying.

She sings the wild song of her dear native plains,

Every note which he lov'd awaking -

Ah! little they think, who delight in her strains,

How the heart of the minstrel is breaking!

He had liv'd for his love, for his country he died;

Tey were all that to life had entwin'd him -

Nor soon shall the tears of his country be dried,

Nor long will his love stay behind him!

Oh! make her a grave where the sunbeams rest,

Wen they promise a glorious morrow;

Tey'll shine o'er her sleep, like a smile from the west,

From her own lov'd island of sorrow!

黑桃皇后

/

黑桃皇后主大祸临头。

——最新详梦书

一

在阴雨连绵的日子，

他们常常聚集

在一起；

押上宝——上帝饶恕！

他们的赌注

从五十到一百卢布，

有人赌赢了，

有人用粉笔

勾去输掉的数字。

在阴雨连绵的日子，

他们聚集在一起，

干的就是这件事。

一天，有些人聚集在近卫军骑兵纳鲁莫夫家里打牌。漫长的冬夜不知不觉过尽了，大家坐下来吃夜宵的时候已经是早上四点多钟。那些赌赢的人都吃得津津有味，另一些人却失魂落魄地坐在空餐具跟前。但香槟酒送来了，谈话又活跃起来，于是大家又在一起聊天。

“你打得怎么样，舒林？”主人问道。

“输了，跟以前一样。只能承认我运气不好：我没有加过赌注，从来不急躁，谁也不能把我搞糊涂，可我总是输！”

“你一次也没有着魔过吗？你一次也没有押过那张总能赢钱的牌吗？……你的倔强真叫我吃惊。”

“可你瞧瞧赫尔曼！”一个客人指着年轻的工兵军官说，“他从来没有摸过牌，从来没有叫过一次加倍，可总是陪我们坐到五点钟，一直瞧着我们打牌！”

“我对打牌很感兴趣，”赫尔曼说，“可是我不能为了非分之财，把少不了要用的钱拿去做赌注。”

“赫尔曼是德国人：他很节俭，就是这么回事！”托木斯基说，“如果说还有什么人使我摸不透，那就是我的祖母安娜·费多托夫娜伯爵夫人了。”

“怎么？你在说什么？”客人们都提高声音问道。

“我搞不懂，”托木斯基继续说，“为什么我祖母不再赌钱了！”

“一个八十岁的老太太不再赌钱，这有什么好奇怪的？”纳鲁莫夫问。

“这么说，您对她一点儿也不了解？”

“不了解！是的，一点儿也不了解！”

“噢，那么您听我说：

“您知道，我祖母六十年前去过巴黎，在那里她可是个风流人物。好多人都跟在她后面跑，想看看这个莫斯科的维纳斯[1]；黎塞留[2]热烈追求过她，祖母肯定地说，由于她心肠太硬，几乎弄得他开枪自杀。

“那时太太们都流行打法拉翁[3]。有一次，她在宫廷里和奥尔良公爵打赌，输了很多钱。祖母回到家里，从脸上揭下美人斑[4]，脱下箍骨裙，对祖父说了她输钱的事，要他把钱付掉。

“我记得，祖父本来是祖母的管家。他怕她，就像怕火一样；可是一听到她输掉这么一笔惊人的数目，不禁大怒，他拿来账册，向她证明，半年来他们已经花掉五十万，还说在巴黎他们没有像莫斯科乡下或萨拉托夫乡下那样的财产，因此干脆拒绝替她还钱。祖母打了他一记耳光，单独躺下睡觉，表示不喜欢他。

“第二天，祖母吩咐仆人把祖父叫来，指望这种家庭的处罚能对他起作用，结果发现祖父仍毫不动摇。她有生以来第一次不得不和他讲道理；她想让他感到于心有愧，就好言好语地对他说，债务也有各种各样，欠公爵的债和欠马车匠的债是不一样的。有什么用！祖父造反了。不行，没什么可说的！祖母简直走投无路。

“她有一个要好的朋友，是个相当有名的人物。你们都听说过圣热尔曼伯爵[5]，他的奇事是那么多，大家都在纷纷传说。你们都知道，他自称是“终身漂泊的犹太人”[6]、长命水和点金石的发明者，等等。大家都笑他，说他到处招摇撞骗，卡萨诺瓦则在回忆录中说他是奸细；不过，尽管圣热尔曼是个很神秘的人，却仪表堂堂，在社交界中很讨人喜欢。祖母至今还迷恋着他，要是有人说他坏话，她就会生气。祖母知道圣热尔曼有办法搞到大量金钱。她决定去找他帮忙。她给他写了一张便条，请他立即到她这儿来。

“这个老怪人立刻就来了，正看到祖母愁眉不展、十分痛苦。她用最恶毒的语言描绘了一通丈夫的野蛮，最后对他说，她只能在他的友谊和盛情厚意上面寄托她的全部希望了。

“圣热尔曼沉吟了一会儿。

“‘我可以为您筹措这笔钱，’他说，‘不过，我知道，在您还清这笔钱之前，您一定不会安心，而我则不想让您愁上加愁。我有一个办法，可以让您去翻本。’‘可是，亲爱的伯爵，’祖母回答，‘我跟您说，我根本没有钱。’‘这事不需要用钱，’圣热尔曼说，‘请您听我说完。’这时他向她公开了一个秘密，要是能知道这个秘密，我们当中每一个人都肯付出极昂贵的代价……”

年轻的赌徒们更注意听了。托木斯基吸起烟来，他深深地吸了一口，又说下去。

“当天晚上祖母到凡尔赛去，在皇后那里打牌[7]。奥尔良公爵坐庄；祖母稍稍对他表示了一下歉意，说没有把欠款带来。为了替自己辩解，她还编造了一个小小的故事，接着便坐在他对面下注。她挑出三张牌，一张接一张下注：三张牌都替她赢了钱，这一来祖母便完全翻了本。”

“这是偶然的！”一个客人说。

“神话！”赫尔曼说。

“这牌大概玩弄了什么手法？”第三个接着说。

“我不认为这样。”托木斯基一本正经地说。

“真是怪事！”纳鲁莫夫说，“你有一个祖母，她能连续猜中三张牌，可你至今还没有向她学到这个秘诀。”

“是啊，有什么办法！”托木斯基回答，“她有四个儿子，我父亲是其中一个：四个人都是不顾死活的赌徒，可是她没有向任何一个公开过这个秘密；虽然这样做对他们并没有坏处，对我也是这样。我叔父伊凡·伊里奇伯爵曾向我说过一件事，他用人格担保这是真的。已故的恰普利茨基，就是挥霍了万贯家财，死于穷困潦倒的那个，年轻的时候，有一次记得是输给佐里奇近三十万。他完全绝望了。祖母对年轻人的胡闹一向是很严厉的，可这一次她倒有点儿可怜恰普利茨基。她给他三张牌，让他一张一张押，并要他保证以后永远不再赌博。恰普利茨基到赢他钱的人那里去了。他们坐下来赌钱。恰普利茨基在第一张牌上押了五万，一下子就赢了；他押了两次加倍，翻了本，还赢了钱……

“然而该睡觉了，已经六点差一刻。”

其实，天已经大亮。这些年轻人喝完了杯里的酒，便各自回去了。

二

“您好像更喜欢那些使女。”

“有什么办法，太太？她们更鲜艳。”

——社交界的闲谈[8]

某某老伯爵夫人坐在梳妆室的镜子前面。她身边有三个使女。一个拿着胭脂盒，一个端着发针匣，还有一个捧着一顶饰有红带子的高包发帽。伯爵夫人早已人老色衰，她丝毫不想再打扮自己的姿容，但她还保留着年轻时的习惯，严格模仿七十年代的流行式样，像六十年前一样，煞费苦心地打扮，花那么多时间。靠窗口的地方有一位小姐坐在那儿刺绣，那是她的养女。

“您好，祖母[9]，”一个青年军官走进来，对她说，“您好，丽莎小姐。祖母，我有一件事要求您。”

“什么事，保罗[10]？”

“请允许我向您介绍一个朋友，礼拜五我想把他带到舞会上来见您。”

“你把他直接带到舞会上来见我，那时候你就可以向我介绍了。你昨天去过某某人那里吗？”

“那还用说！快活极了，跳舞一直跳到早晨五点钟。叶烈茨卡娅多漂亮啊！”

“咳，我亲爱的！她有什么漂亮啊？她的祖母达丽亚·彼得罗夫娜公爵夫人也像她那样吗？……顺便说一句：我想，达丽亚·彼得罗夫娜公爵夫人，她也很老了吧？”

“什么很老了？”托木斯基心不在焉地回答，“她过世七年了。”

小姐抬起头，对年轻人暗示了一下。他这才想起来，他们是对老伯爵夫人隐瞒了她这位同年女友的死讯的，于是他咬了咬嘴唇。可是伯爵夫人听到这个新闻却一点儿也不在乎。

“过世啦！”她说，“我一点儿也不知道！我们一起被封为宫中女官，我们一起觐见时，女皇……”

伯爵夫人又对她的孙子讲起自己的趣事，这件事她说过有一百遍了。

“好吧，保罗，”后来她说，“现在你扶我起来。丽桑卡[11]，我的鼻烟壶在哪儿？”

接着，伯爵夫人带着几个使女到屏风后面去更衣。托木斯基和小姐留在房间里。

“您要介绍的人是谁？”丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜轻声问道。

“纳鲁莫夫。您认识他吗？”

“不！他是不是军人？”

“是军人。”

“是工兵军官吗？”

“不！是骑兵。您为什么以为他是个工兵军官？”

小姐痴痴地笑起来，一个字也没有回答。

“保罗！”伯爵夫人在屏风后面叫道，“给我送一本新的小说来，不过不要现代的。”

“那要什么样的，祖母？”

“要这样的小说，里面的主人公并不掐死父亲或母亲，里面没有淹死的尸体。我最怕溺死的人了！”

“如今可没有这样的小说。您不想要俄国小说吗？”

“有俄国小说吗？……送来吧，亲爱的，请送来吧！”

“再见，祖母，我有事……再见，丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜！您为什么以为纳鲁莫夫是工兵军官？”

托木斯基走出梳妆室。

房间里只剩下丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜一个人，她放下手工，望着窗外。不一会儿从街对面一个屋角里转出一个年轻军官来。她脸上泛起一片红晕。她又拿起手工，低头伏在绣布上。这时伯爵夫人换好衣服进来了。

“丽桑卡，”她说，“吩咐套上马车，我们出去玩玩。”

丽桑卡从绣架旁站起来，收拾着手工。

“你怎么了，我的孩子！是聋了还是怎么的！”伯爵夫人提高嗓门儿，“吩咐快点套上马车。”

“马上就去！”小姐轻声回答，立即跑到前厅去。

一个仆人走进来，把巴维尔·亚历山大罗维奇公爵送来的几本书交给伯爵夫人。

“很好！很感谢。”伯爵夫人说，“丽桑卡，丽桑卡！你到底跑到哪儿去了？”

“换衣服。”

“你还来得及的，我的孩子。坐在这儿。翻开第一卷，念给我听……”

小姐拿起一本书，读了几行。

“大声点！”伯爵夫人说，“你怎么啦，我的孩子？嗓子哑了还是怎么的？……等一等，把脚凳挪给我，再近点……好！”

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜又读了两页。伯爵夫人打了个呵欠。

“别读了，”她说，“真是一派胡言！把它送还巴维尔公爵，要谢谢他……可马车怎么啦？”

“马车准备好了。”丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜探头看看街上，说。

“你怎么还不换衣服？”伯爵夫人说，“老是叫人等你！我的孩子，这可叫人受不了。”

丽莎赶紧跑到她的房间去。还不到两分钟，伯爵夫人便死命地打起铃来。三个使女一起从一扇门里冲进来，侍仆则从另一扇门跑进来。

“你们怎么都叫不应呀？”伯爵夫人对他们说，“告诉丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜，说我在等她。”

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜穿着晨衣、戴着帽子走进来。

“终于来了，我的孩子！”伯爵夫人说，“怎么穿这身衣服？这是干吗？……向谁卖俏？……今天天气怎么样？看样子有风吧。”

“一点儿风也没有，夫人！天气很好！”侍仆回答。

“你们总是瞎说一气！把通风窗打开。一点儿也不错，有风！还很冷呢！卸掉马车吧！丽桑卡，我们不去了，用不着打扮了。”

“我过的就是这种日子！”丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜想。

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜确实是个极其不幸的人。但丁说过，别人的面包是苦的，别人的台阶是难登的。除了这个显贵老太婆的苦命养女，还有谁了解寄人篱下的生活是多么痛苦呢？某某伯爵夫人的心肠并不坏，这是不消多说的，但她是个养尊处优的女人，因而非常任性，她和那些在自己有生之年既不再谈恋爱又和现时的社会格格不入的老年人一样悭吝，一样养成了冷酷的利己主义的习惯。她参加上流社会的一切娱乐活动，出席舞会。在舞会上，她搽了胭脂，穿着老式服装，坐在角落里，就像舞厅里的一件丑陋而不可缺少的装饰品；来客都走到她跟前，向她深深鞠躬，好像在履行一种明文规定的仪式，此后就没人理她了。她遵守严格的礼节，在家里接待全城的名人，可是认不出任何人的面孔。无数的婢仆在她的前厅和下房里养得肥肥胖胖的，连头发也白了，他们想干什么就干什么，争相盗窃这个行将就木的老太婆的财产。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜是家里最倒霉的人。她给伯爵夫人倒茶，常常因此而受一顿训斥，说她糖放多了；她为伯爵夫人朗读小说，凡是作者的错误，都要怪她读错；她陪伯爵夫人出去散步，遇到天气不好或道路不平，她也要负责。她有规定的薪资，却从来没有拿到那么多；然而对她的装束却很挑剔，要求她穿得和极少数有钱人一样好。在交际场所里，她是个极可怜的角色。大家都认识她，可谁也不把她放在眼里。在舞会上，只有舞伴[12]不够的时候才轮得到她跳；每当太太小姐们需要到梳妆室去理理衣装的时候，都要把她拉去帮忙。她懂得自爱，深深明白自己的处境，总是注意着自己周围的人，迫切希望有人来解救她；但是那些青年人，为了维持浅薄的虚荣心，从不轻举妄动，并不对她表示垂怜，虽然丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜比他们死死缠住不放的那些厚颜无耻而又冷若冰霜的姑娘可爱一百倍。多少次她悄悄离开无聊而豪华的客厅，跑到她那简陋的房间里痛哭一场。她的房间里只有一扇裱着花纸的屏风，一个五斗橱，一面小镜子，和一张油漆过的床。一支脂油蜡烛在铜烛台上幽暗地燃烧着。

有一次——那是在这部小说开头所描写的那个晚上的两天以后，我们刚才谈到的那幕情景之前一个礼拜——丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜坐在窗下刺绣，无意中朝街上看了一眼，看见一个青年工兵军官，一动不动地站在那儿，注视着她的窗口。她低下头，重新做起手中的针线活；过了五分钟，她又朝街上看了看，青年军官仍旧站在那儿。她一向不和过路的军官调情，便不再朝街上看，埋头绣了近两个钟头。吃中饭了，她站起来收拾绣架，无意中瞧了瞧街上，又看见那个军官。她觉得这事很蹊跷。饭后她怀着有些不安的心情走到窗边，但那个军官已经不在，于是她把他忘记了……

大约过了两天，她和伯爵夫人一起出门，刚登上马车，她又看到他了。他就站在大门口，竖起海龙皮领子，遮着脸，一双黑眼睛在帽檐底下闪闪发亮。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜不知为什么感到害怕，坐上马车，心还在莫名其妙地怦怦跳着。

回到家里，她走近窗口——那军官站在原来的地方，一双眼睛直盯着她。她从窗口走开，不知道这究竟是怎么回事，心里老想着这个问题，同时，一种从未有过的感情也使她激动不已。

从这个时候起，那青年人每天都在固定时间出现在她的窗下，从不间断。他们之间无形中产生了一种默契。她一坐下来做针线，就感到他在近旁，就抬起头看看他，停留在他身上的目光也一天比一天长久。为此青年人似乎很感激她：她那少女的敏锐目光看到，当他们的目光相遇时，每一次他那苍白的脸颊都会立即红起来。过了一个礼拜，她对他微笑了一下……

当托木斯基请求伯爵夫人允许他把朋友带来拜访她的时候，这可怜姑娘的心便怦怦跳起来了。可是当她得知纳鲁莫夫不是工兵军官，而是近卫军骑兵的时候，她很后悔，因为她不慎提了这么个问题，把自己心头的秘密泄露给轻浮的托木斯基了。

赫尔曼是个俄国化的德国人的儿子，父亲给他留下了一笔小小的资产。赫尔曼坚信一个人必须保持独立，他连父亲遗产的利息也不敢动用，只靠薪俸过活，丝毫不敢放纵自己。不过他是个性格内向而且自尊心很强的人，伙伴们难得有机会嘲笑他的过分节俭。他怀着强烈的欲望和狂热的幻想，但是坚强的意志使他避免了一般青年人常常陷入的迷误。譬如说，他嗜赌如命，却从来不打牌，因为他考虑到他的财产不允许他（正如他所说的）“为了非分之财，把少不了要用的钱拿去做赌注”——然而，他却整夜整夜地坐在牌桌旁边，狂热地注视着变化无常的牌局。

三张牌的奇闻使他强烈地幻想起来，他整夜都在想着这件事。第二天傍晚，他在彼得堡边散步边想：“要是老伯爵夫人肯向我公开这个秘密，或者告诉我这三张必胜的牌，那该有多好啊！为什么不去碰碰运气呢？……到她那里去，做自我介绍，博得她的宠爱，或者做她的情人，但这需要一段时间，而她已经八十七岁了，也许再过一个礼拜，也许再过两天，她就会死去！……可这个奇闻本身呢？……是不是可信？……不！俭省、节制和勤劳，这才是三张可靠的牌，只有这三张牌才能使我的资产增加两倍，增加六倍，才能给我安宁和独立！”

他这样思忖着，不觉来到彼得堡一条主要大街的一座老式房屋前面。街上车水马龙，马车一辆接一辆向这个灯火辉煌的大门口驶去。从这些马车里时时露出妙龄美女的秀足、铿锵作响的长靴、条纹袜子和外交官的软底鞋。皮大衣和斗篷不时从傲慢的司阍[13]身边闪过。赫尔曼停住脚步。

“这是谁家的公馆？”他问一个站在拐角上的岗警。

“是某某伯爵夫人的公馆。”岗警回答。

赫尔曼浑身战栗起来。他脑海里又浮现出那个令人惊异的奇闻。他在公馆旁边踱来踱去，心里想着这座公馆的女主人和她那奇妙的本事。他很晚才回到自己那简陋的房间，久久不能入眠，等到一睡着，便梦见纸牌、绿色桌子、一沓沓钞票和一堆堆金币。他押下一张张纸牌，一次次毫不犹豫地折着牌角，不断地赢钱，不断地把金币搂到自己面前，把钞票装入衣袋。他醒来的时候已经很迟，因失去这虚幻的财富，他长叹了一声，接着又上街去闲逛，又一次来到某某伯爵夫人的公馆门前。仿佛有一种神秘的力量把他吸引到这个地方。他停住脚步，举目望着这座公馆的窗口。在一个窗口里，他看见一个黑头发的头，低垂着，大概在看书或工作。头稍稍抬起来了。赫尔曼看见了一个艳丽的脸蛋和一对黑眼睛。这一刻决定了他的命运。

三

我的安琪儿，您每次给我写四页信，

比我读起来还快。[14]

——通信

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜刚刚脱下大衣和帽子，伯爵夫人就派人来找她，又吩咐准备马车。她们走出去乘车。就在两个仆人把老太太扶上马车送进车门里边的那一刻，丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜发现那个工兵军官就在车轮旁边；他抓住她的手，她惊呆了，还没有回过神来，年轻人已经走掉了，她手里留下一封信。她把信藏在手套里，一路上昏昏沉沉，什么也没听见，什么也没看见。伯爵夫人有个习惯，坐在马车里不时要问点什么：她们碰到的是什么人？这座桥叫什么桥？那边招牌上写的是什么？这一回丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜总是随口回答，每一次都是牛头不对马嘴，伯爵夫人因此大为生气。

“你怎么啦，我的孩子！你是昏了头还是怎么的？你是没有听见我的话还是没有听懂？……荣耀归于上帝，我话还说得清楚，也没有老糊涂！”

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜没听进她的话。一回到家里，她就奔进自己的房间，从手套里取出信来，信没有封口。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜一口气把它读完。这是一封向她表白爱情的信，写得情意绵绵、彬彬有礼，都是一字不差地从德国小说里抄来的。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜因为不懂德文，所以非常高兴。

然而，这封信却使她坐立不安。她有生以来第一次和一个年轻男子建立秘密而亲近的关系。他这种大胆的行为使她害怕。她责备自己行为太不谨慎，不知道怎么办好：是不是别再坐在窗口？是不是应该不理睬他，冷淡他，让他以后别再追求下去？要不要给他写封信？要不要冷淡而斩钉截铁地回绝他？她没有人好商量，她既没有小姐妹，也没有人能给予指导。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜决定给他写一封回信。

她在写字台前面坐下，拿起笔和纸，沉思起来。她开了几次头，又把信撕了：一会儿觉得语气太宽容，一会儿又觉得太生硬。她终于写出几句话，自己觉得还满意。她写道：“我相信您的心意是真诚的，并不想用轻率的举动来侮辱我；但我们的结识不应当采取这种方式。现将来信退回，并希望今后不至于让我怪您对我不尊重。”

第二天，丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜看见赫尔曼走过来，便从绣架旁边站起来，走到大厅里，打开气窗，把信扔到街上，希望青年军官能迅速捡去。赫尔曼跑过来，捡起信，走进一家食品店。拆开信封，他看到自己的信和丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜的答复。这是他预料中的事，回家之后，他便一心一意地策划起求爱的事来了。

三天后，一个年纪轻轻、眼睛灵活的女裁缝从时装店里给丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜送来一张纸条。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜以为是来付债的，忐忑不安地把纸条打开，但立即就认出是赫尔曼的笔迹。

“亲爱的，您搞错了，”她说，“这张条子不是给我的。”

“不，确实是给您的！”那大胆的姑娘并不掩饰神秘的微笑，回答说，“请您看一看！”

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜把纸条迅速地看了一遍。赫尔曼要求和她约会。

“不可能！”丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜说，赫尔曼竟迫不及待地提出这种要求，并且采用这种办法，这使她大为吃惊。“这张纸条真的不是写给我的！”说着她把信撕成了碎片。

“既然信不是写给您的，那您干吗把它撕掉？”女裁缝说，“我可以把它送还发信的人啊！”

“您请便，亲爱的！”丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜说，由于女裁缝点穿她的秘密，她的脸唰地红了起来。“以后再别给我送纸条来。请您对那个叫您送纸条的人说，他应该感到羞耻……”

可是赫尔曼并不罢休。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜每天都收到他通过各种办法送来的信。信的内容已经不是从德文翻译过来的了。赫尔曼热情洋溢地给她写了这些信，使用的语言都是他自己所特有的：他在信中表达了他的坚定不移的愿望，倾吐了自己理不清的无法遏制的幻想。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜已经不想把信退回去了，这些信使她陶醉。她开始给他写回信，她的信也写得越来越长，越来越情意缠绵。有一天，她终于从窗口扔给他如下的一封信：

今天某国公使将举行舞会。伯爵夫人将到那里去。我们在那里要待到两点钟。现在您有机会和我单独见面了。伯爵夫人一走，她的仆人就会走开，门廊里只剩下一个看门人，但他通常也会回自己的房间去。您可以在十一点半来。直接上楼梯。您要是在前厅里遇到人，就问伯爵夫人在不在家。他们会告诉您不在——那就没有办法，您只好回去。但是您大概不会遇到任何人。使女们都一起待在她们的房间里。您穿过前厅往左拐，一直走到伯爵夫人的卧室。在卧室的屏风后面，您会看见两扇小门：右边通书房，伯爵夫人从来不到那里去；左边通走廊，那里有一座狭小的螺旋梯，上面就是我的房间。

赫尔曼浑身绷紧，抖嗦得像一只等待猎物的老虎，焦急地等待着约定时间的到来。晚上十点钟，他已经来到伯爵夫人的公馆门前。天气坏极了，风呼呼地吼着，潮湿的雪一大片一大片飘落下来，街灯发出昏黄的光线，街上空荡荡的。驾着由一匹瘦马拉的马车的车夫偶尔伸长脖子看看有没有晚归的乘客。赫尔曼只穿着常礼服站在那儿，既没有感觉到狂风，也没有感觉到暴雪。伯爵夫人的马车终于备好了。赫尔曼看见几个仆人扶出一个裹着貂皮大衣的驼背老太婆，接着，她的养女披着一件单薄的斗篷，头戴鲜花闪现了一下。车门啪的一声关上了。马车吃力地从松软的雪地上驶出去。看门人关上门。窗子里的灯光熄灭了。赫尔曼便在这座空公馆周围走来走去，他走近街灯，看看表——表上指着十一点二十分。他就站在街灯下，注视着表上的指针，等待过完这几分钟。到了十一点半，赫尔曼走上伯爵夫人公馆门前的台阶，走进灯火通明的门廊。看门人不在。赫尔曼登上楼梯，打开通前厅的门，看见一个仆人坐在灯下一把肮脏的老式圈椅上睡觉。赫尔曼轻轻地然而毫不犹豫地从他身旁走过去。大厅和客厅都很昏暗。只有前厅里的灯光微弱地照到这两个厅堂。赫尔曼走进卧室。摆满古老神像的神龛前面点着一盏金色的神灯。几件褪色的缎面圈椅和镀金剥落的带羽绒靠垫沙发对称地靠在裱着中国糊墙纸的墙边，显得凄清冷落。墙上挂着勒布朗夫人[15]在巴黎画的两幅肖像。其中一幅画着一个约莫四十岁的男人，他脸色红润、身体肥胖，穿着浅绿色制服，佩戴着勋章；另一幅画着一个年轻美女，她长着高鼻子，两鬓的头发往后梳，扑粉的头发上戴着一朵玫瑰花。所有的角落里都摆满牧女瓷像、著名的勒鲁瓦[16]制造的台钟、小盒子、赌博用的轮盘、扇子和上世纪末与蒙哥利菲哀尔[17]气球及梅斯梅尔[18]催眠术同时发明的妇女的玩具。赫尔曼走到屏风后面。屏风后面有一张小铁床，右边是一扇通往书房的门，左边另一扇门通往走廊。赫尔曼把左边的门打开，看见一座狭小的螺旋梯，从这里可以通向那苦命的养女的房间……但他转过身来走进漆黑的书房。

时间过得真慢。屋子里静悄悄的。客厅里的钟敲了十二下，所有房间里的钟都先后敲了十二下——过后屋子里又沉寂下来。赫尔曼站着，靠在没生火的炉子上。他一点儿都不焦急，心脏平静地跳动着，像所有为了某种需要而决心去冒险的人一样。时钟相继敲过一点和两点，这时他听到远处马车的辚辚声。他不由得激动起来。马车驶到门口，停下来。他听见放下踏板的声音。公馆里奔忙起来。仆人们奔跑着，喊叫着，屋子里点亮了灯。三个老使女跑进卧室，接着伯爵夫人有气无力地走进来，落坐在高背躺椅上。赫尔曼从隙缝里看到丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜从他身边走过。他听见她登上楼梯的急促脚步声。他似乎感到于心有愧，但一会儿便完全平静了。他的心肠变得像石头一样硬。

伯爵夫人开始对着镜子卸妆。使女们从她头上摘下插玫瑰花的帽子；从她那银白头发剪得极短的头上拿下扑粉的假发，别针一根根像下雨似的落在她的身旁；绣着银线的黄色衣裙落到她浮肿的脚上。赫尔曼亲眼看到了她那副打扮所掩盖的令人恶心的秘密。最后伯爵夫人身上只剩下一件睡衣，头上戴着压发帽——这种打扮还比较适合她那耄耋的年龄，因此看起来就不那么可怕和丑陋了。

就像一般老年人那样，伯爵夫人也患有失眠症。她卸好妆，就坐在靠窗口的高背躺椅上，打发掉使女。蜡烛拿走了，房间里又只剩下一盏灯。伯爵夫人坐在那里，脸色蜡黄，耷拉下来的嘴唇微微抖动着，全身不停地左右摆动。她那混浊的眼睛显得十分呆滞，望着她，真可以认为，这个可怕的老太婆的摆动并不是出于她的意志，而是她身上一种潜在的电流在起作用。

突然，这张死气沉沉的面孔大大变了样。嘴唇停止抖动，眼睛紧张地活动起来。伯爵夫人面前站着一个陌生男人。

“请您不要害怕，看在上帝面上，请不要害怕！”他很清楚地轻声说，“我并不想谋害您，我只是来请求您的恩典。”

老太婆默默地瞧着他，好像没有听见他在说什么。赫尔曼以为她耳背，因此弯下腰在她耳边把刚才说的话重说了一遍。老太婆还是不吭声。

“您可以使我获得一生的幸福，”赫尔曼继续说，“这在您是不费吹灰之力的，我知道您能一连猜中三张牌……”

赫尔曼没再说下去。伯爵夫人似乎明白了他的要求，她仿佛在考虑用什么恰当的话来回答他。

“这是个玩笑，”她终于说，“我可以向您发誓！这是个玩笑！”

“这没有什么好开玩笑的，”赫尔曼愤愤地回答道，“您该记得恰普利茨基吧，是您帮助他翻本的。”

伯爵夫人显然很紧张。她的神色反映出内心强烈的激荡，但她很快又陷入先前那种麻木状态。

“您能告诉我这三张必胜的牌吗？”赫尔曼又问。

伯爵夫人沉默不语，赫尔曼又继续说：

“您在替谁保守这个秘密呢？替您的孙子吗？他们就算不掌握这个秘密也够有钱的了。他们根本不知道金钱的价值。您这三张牌帮助不了那些挥金如土的人。那些不会爱惜父辈遗产的人，他们即使像魔鬼那样使尽力气，也不得不死于贫困。我不是一个爱挥霍金钱的人，我懂得金钱的价值。我不会把这三张牌白白糟蹋掉的。告诉我吧！……”

他停住话头，浑身颤抖着等待她的回答。伯爵夫人还是默不作声。赫尔曼跪了下来。

“要是您的心曾经感受过爱的情感，”他说，“要是您还记得爱的欢乐，要是您哪怕只有一次在刚生下的儿子哇哇哭闹的时候微笑了一下，要是您的胸中曾经激荡过人类的感情，那么我就用妻子、情人、母亲，总之，一个人的生命中可能有的一切神圣的感情恳求您，不要拒绝我的请求！——向我公开您的秘密吧！您还要它干什么？……也许，它会造成骇人听闻的罪恶，会使人失去一生的幸福，要和魔鬼订下什么协议……您想想看吧：您已经老了，活不了多久，我愿用我的灵魂承受您的罪孽。您只要向我公开您的秘密。您想想看，一个人的幸福就掌握在您的手心里，不仅是我，还有我的儿子、孙子、曾孙都要感戴您的大恩大德，把您的恩德看成圣物一般……”

老太婆一个字也没有回答。

赫尔曼站起来。

“老妖婆！”他咬咬牙说，“我只好强迫你回答了……”

说着，他从口袋里拔出手枪。

伯爵夫人一看到手枪，情绪又强烈激动起来。她摇摇头，举起一只手，好像要挡住他的射击……接着她便往后倒下去……一动不动了。

“别胡闹，”赫尔曼抓住她的手，说，“我最后问您一次，您想不想把三张牌告诉我？”

伯爵夫人没有回答。赫尔曼发现，她已经死了。

四

一八××年五月七日。

一个没有道德准则和毫无信念的人。[19]

——通信

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜坐在房间里，还穿着参加舞会的衣服，深深地沉思着。她一回到家里，便急忙把那个不情愿服侍她的睡意蒙眬的使女打发走。她对使女说，她可以自己脱衣服，便战战兢兢地走进自己的房间，心里既想在那里遇到赫尔曼，又希望见不到他。她一眼就断定他没有来，因此感谢命运为他们的幽会设置了障碍。她坐下来，衣服也不脱，便想起在这么短的时间内就使她如此迷恋的一切情形。自从她第一次在窗口看见这个年轻人以来，还不到三个礼拜，她已经和他通了信，而他也已经得到她的同意，准备在夜间和她幽会！她只是从几封他签过名的信里了解到他的名字；在这个晚上以前，她从来没有和他谈过话，没有听见过他的声音，从来也没有听说过他的事……真是怪事！就在这个夜晚的舞会上，托木斯基很生年轻的波利娜公爵小姐的气。因为她一反常态，不和他撒娇调情，他便邀请丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜跳那没完没了的玛祖卡舞，对波利娜表示冷淡，想借此对她进行报复。整个晚上，托木斯基老是和丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜开玩笑，取笑她对那个工兵军官的痴情，对她说，他知道的事比她所能设想的要多得多。他开的玩笑中有几次都击中她的要害，因此丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜有好几次都想到，他一定知道她的秘密。

“这些事情您是听谁说的？”她笑着问他。

“听您的一个熟人的朋友说的，”托木斯基回答，“那是一个很出色的人。”

“这个出色的人到底是谁呀？”

“他叫赫尔曼。”

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜什么也没有回答，但她的手脚却冷得像冰一样……

“这个赫尔曼，”托木斯基继续说，“有一张典型的小说中人物的面孔：他的侧面像拿破仑，灵魂像靡非斯特[20]。我认为，至少有三样罪恶他应该于心有愧。您的脸色怎么这样苍白！……”

“我头痛……赫尔曼对您说了些什么？您说他到底是怎样一个人呢？”

“赫尔曼对他那位朋友很不满意。他说，换了他，他一定采取另一种办法……我甚至认为，赫尔曼正在打您的主意，至少他听到朋友心醉神迷的向往时，心里很不平静。”

“他究竟在哪儿看见过我？”

“也许是在教堂里，或者是散步的时候！……天知道！也许是在您的房间里，那时您正在睡觉，他……”

走过来三个淑女，问他“遗忘还是惋惜”[21]，打断了丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜极想继续下去的谈话。

托木斯基选中的小姐就是那位波利娜公爵小姐。她和他多跳了一圈，又在自己座椅前面多转了一转，在这段时间里，她和他又言归于好了。托木斯基回到座位上的时候，已经不再想起赫尔曼和丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜很想恢复刚才那场中断的谈话，但玛祖卡舞已经结束，接着老伯爵夫人也走了。

托木斯基的话不过是跳玛祖卡舞时随便说说的，却深深印入这个好幻想的年轻姑娘心里。托木斯基随便描绘的肖像正和她心中想象的不谋而合；由于听了一段最新的故事，这张已显得很俗气的面孔不由得使她感到惴惴不安，也使她耽于幻想。她坐着，交叉着两条赤裸的手臂，还插着鲜花的头低垂在袒露的胸前……突然，门打开了，赫尔曼走进房间。她浑身战栗起来……

“您刚才到底在哪里？”她惊惧地轻声问道。

“在老伯爵夫人的卧室里，”赫尔曼回答，“我刚刚从她那里来。伯爵夫人死了。”

“我的天！……您在说什么？……”

“看样子，是我把她吓死的。”赫尔曼继续说。

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜瞥了他一眼，心里不由得想起托木斯基说过的话：“至少有三样罪恶他应该于心有愧！”赫尔曼坐在她身边的窗台上，把经过情形一一告诉她。

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜惊恐地听完他的话。原来，这些热情洋溢的信件，这些火焰般炽烈的要求，这种无礼而又纠缠不清的追求，统统都不是出于爱情！金钱——这才是他心中渴望得到的东西！能够满足他的欲望，使他得到幸福的并不是她！这可怜的养女不过是一个杀害她老恩人的凶手和强盗的盲目帮凶！……她后悔莫及，难过得痛哭起来。赫尔曼默默地瞧着她。他也心痛如绞，但无论是这可怜姑娘的眼泪，还是她那痛苦的样子所表现出来的惊人魅力，都不能触动他的铁石心肠。想到老太婆的死，他并没有受到良心的谴责。只有一点使他感到恼恨：那个秘密他再也搞不到手了，本来他是指望靠它发财的。

“您是个魔鬼！”丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜终于对他说。

“我并不想害死她，”赫尔曼回答，“我的手枪没有装子弹。”

他们都默不作声。

早晨来临了。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜吹灭快燃尽的蜡烛，淡淡的曙光已照临她的房间。她擦干满是泪痕的眼睛，举目望着赫尔曼：他坐在窗台上，抄着手，凶狠地皱着眉头。那样子竟和拿破仑的肖像一模一样。这两个人这样相像，连丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜都感到吃惊。

“您怎么走出这座公馆？”丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜终于说，“我本来想带您从秘密楼梯走出去，但要从伯爵夫人的卧室旁边走过，我害怕。”

“请您告诉我怎么找到这座秘密楼梯，我自己走出去。”

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜站起来，从柜子里拿出钥匙，交给赫尔曼，并且详细告诉他出门的路径。赫尔曼握了握她那冰冷的、毫无反应的手，吻了吻她低垂着的头，走出去。

他从螺旋梯走下去，又一次走进伯爵夫人的卧室。死去的老太婆仍旧坐着，已经僵硬了；她的脸显得很安详。赫尔曼站在她面前，久久地望着她，似乎想再看看这件可怕的事情是不是属实。最后，他走进书房，摸到糊墙纸后面的暗门，走下漆黑的楼梯。一种奇怪的感觉使他兴奋起来。他想，也许在六十年前，有那么一个年轻的幸运儿，穿着绣花长袍，梳着仙鹤式[22]头发，把三角帽拿在手里，紧贴在胸口上，也在这个时刻，同样从这座楼梯偷偷溜进这间卧室，这个年轻人早已在坟墓里腐烂，而这个年过古稀的情妇的心今天才停止跳动……

赫尔曼在楼梯下面找到一扇门，他用那把钥匙开了锁，走进过道，从那儿走到大街上。

五

这天晚上，已故的冯·V男爵夫人向我显灵。她全身穿着白色衣服，对我说：“您好，顾问先生！”

——斯维登堡[23]

在那命中注定的夜晚之后的第三天，上午九点钟，赫尔曼动身到某某修道院去，人们将在那里为已故的伯爵夫人举行葬礼。他虽然一点儿不后悔，但也不能完全压下良心的呼声，这声音一再对他说：你是杀害老太太的凶手！他没有多少虔诚的信仰，却有很多迷信。他相信死去的伯爵夫人会给他的一生带来很多危害，因此决定亲自去参加葬礼，以便祈求她的宽恕。

教堂里挤得水泄不通。赫尔曼费了好大力气才从人群中挤过去。灵柩停放在富丽堂皇的灵台上，上面张着天鹅绒的帐幔。死者两手放在胸前，安卧在灵柩里，头上戴着镶花边的帽子，身上穿着白缎衣裙。家属侍立在她的四周。仆人穿着黑袍，肩上佩戴着标有纹章的绶带，手里捧着蜡烛；儿子、孙子、曾孙等亲属都穿着重孝服。谁也没有哭，流泪也许是一种虚情假意[24]的表现。伯爵夫人已到耄耋之年，她的死决不会使任何人感到震惊，而且她的亲属早就认为她活得太长久了。一个年轻的主教致了悼词。他朴素而又动人地讲到这位年高德劭的女信徒的平静辞世，说她数十年如一日默默地进行了感人至深的修行，如今才能像一个基督徒那样告别人世。“司死亡的天使接纳了她这位通宵怀着美好意愿、等待新郎半夜来临的信徒。”[25]演讲者说。仪式在充满悲伤气氛的礼节中完成了。亲属们首先向遗体告别。然后是无数的客人向前移步，他们都是专程前来哀悼这位长期参加他们的浮华玩乐的老太太的。接下去是全体婢仆，最后上前行礼的是一个和死者同年的老太太。她由两个年轻的使女搀扶着。她已经无法深深地鞠躬，只是独自掉下几滴老泪，吻了吻夫人冰冷的手。老太太离去之后，赫尔曼决定到灵柩跟前去。他深深地鞠了一躬，在撒满松枝的冰冷的地板上俯伏了几分钟。最后他稍稍抬起身子，脸色白得像那个死者，登上灵台的台阶，俯下身子……这时，他似乎感到死去的伯爵夫人眯起一只眼睛，带着嘲笑看了他一眼。赫尔曼急忙往后退，他踩空了一脚，咕咚一声仰面朝天跌倒在地上。人们把他扶起来。就在这同一时刻，丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜也昏倒了，被人抬到教堂门前的台阶上。这件事把肃穆的丧礼扰乱了几分钟。来客中掀起了一阵低沉的窃窃私语，死者的近亲，一个瘦削的宫中侍从官对站在身旁的英国人咬了咬耳朵，告诉他这个年轻的军官是她的私生子，对此那个英国人只冷冷地回答了一声：噢！[26]

一整天，赫尔曼的心情都非常懊丧。他在一家僻静的饭馆吃饭，一反平常的习惯，喝了许多酒，想要借此压下内心的烦恼。但是喝了酒，他更加心烦意乱。他回到家里，衣服也不脱，一头扑倒在床上，立即沉沉睡去。他醒来的时候已是深夜，月光照亮了他的房间。他看了看表，两点三刻。他睡意尽失，坐在床上，想着老伯爵夫人的丧礼。

这时有个人在街上朝他的窗户看了看，立即走开了。赫尔曼一点儿都没注意他。过了一会儿，他听见前房的开门声。赫尔曼以为是他的勤务兵照常在外面喝醉了酒，夜游回来了。但是他听见一阵陌生的脚步声，有个人在走路，鞋子发出轻轻的沙沙声。门打开了，走进一个穿白衣服的妇人。赫尔曼以为是他的老奶妈，对她在这个时刻到他这里来感到奇怪。但穿白衣服的妇人突然飘然来到他面前——赫尔曼定睛一看，竟是伯爵夫人！

“我是违反本意到你这儿来的。”她用坚定的声音说，“我是奉命来满足你的要求的。三、七、王牌A，这三张牌会使你连续赢钱，但是有一个条件：一昼夜之内只能押一张牌，从此一辈子再也不赌博。你吓死我，我可以宽恕你，但是你要和我的养女丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜结婚……”

说完她便轻轻转过身子，向房门走去，随着鞋子的沙沙声隐没了。赫尔曼听到门廊的门砰的一声关上，接着又看见有人朝他的窗口瞧了一眼。

赫尔曼好久都不能回过神来。他走进另一个房间。勤务兵睡在地上，赫尔曼费了好大工夫才把他叫醒。勤务兵像平日那样烂醉如泥，从他那里是问不出什么名堂来的。门廊的门锁得好好的。赫尔曼回到自己的房间里，点起蜡烛，把刚才看到的幻象记了下来。

六

“等一等再分牌！”

“您竟敢对我说等一等？”

“大人，我说了，等一等再分牌！”

两种固执的念头不可能同时存在于一个人的脑子里，正像物理学上两个物体不可能同时占据同一个空间一样。三、七、王牌A——三张牌立即把赫尔曼脑子里的死者太太的影子挤走了。三、七、王牌A——三张牌一直萦绕在他的脑子里，并且一直在他的嘴里默念着。看见年轻姑娘，他就说：“她多么秀丽呀！……像红心三一样。”有人问他：“现在几点钟？”他就回答：“差五分七点。”看见大腹便便的男人，他都觉得像个A。三、七、王牌A——三张牌一起跟着他进入梦境，它们都变成各种各样的形状：三点在他面前像一朵艳丽的石榴花，七点像一座哥特式建筑的大门，A是一只硕大无朋的蜘蛛。他的思想全部集中到一点——怎样利用他这个极其宝贵的秘密。他想到退职和旅行。他想到巴黎公开的赌场里去，从诱人的命运女神那里索取一笔财富。一个偶然的机会使他避免了这次远途奔波。

莫斯科组织了一个由有钱的赌徒组成的团体，为首的是名声很大的切卡林斯基，此人一生都在牌桌旁边度过，早就积攒了百万财富，他赢钱时收人家的期票，输钱时给人家现钞。长期的赌博生涯使他取信于众多的牌友，而宽敞的住宅、出色的厨师、亲切和愉快的态度则使他博得公众的尊敬。他来到了彼得堡。青年们蜂拥而来，为了赌牌忘记了舞会，宁可放弃追逐女人的乐趣，也不辜负法拉翁的诱惑。纳鲁莫夫把赫尔曼带到他那里去。

他们走过一长串富丽堂皇的房间，房间里有许多彬彬有礼的仆役。几个将军和三级文官在那里打惠斯特[27]，青年人斜靠在花缎沙发上，吃着冰激凌，抽着烟斗。客厅里，主人坐在一张周围挤着二十来个赌徒的长桌后面分牌。他是个约莫六十岁的老人，外表极其体面，一头银发，饱满而容光焕发的脸显得十分善良，眼睛灵活有神，常带笑意。纳鲁莫夫向他介绍了赫尔曼。切卡林斯基友好地握了握他的手，请他不必拘礼，说完便继续分牌。

牌局持续了好久。牌桌上摊着三十几张牌。切卡林斯基每分完一次牌都要停一停，让赌家安排一下赌注，他自己也好记下输掉的钱，礼貌周到地听听赌家的要求，更加殷勤地打开赌家心不在焉多折的牌角。一圈牌终于打完了。切卡林斯基洗了牌，准备再次分牌。

“让我押一张牌。”赫尔曼从一个也在那里赌钱的胖绅士背后伸出手来，说。切卡林斯基微微一笑，默默地点点头表示遵命。纳鲁莫夫笑着祝贺赫尔曼开了长期的赌戒，并祝愿他旗开得胜。

“就这样！”赫尔曼用粉笔在牌上写下赌注的数目，说。

“请问多少？”庄家眯起眼睛问道，“对不起，先生，我看不清楚。”

“四万七。”赫尔曼回答。

听到这个数目，所有的头一下子都转过来，所有的眼睛都注视着赫尔曼。“他疯了！”纳鲁莫夫心里想。

“请允许我告诉您，”切卡林斯基仍旧笑容满面地说，“您下的注太大了，我们这儿还没有人下过超出二百七十五的注呢。”

“怎么？”赫尔曼不以为然地说，“您不想赢我的牌？”

切卡林斯基仍旧彬彬有礼地点头表示遵命。

“不过我有一事奉告，”他说，“我虽然有幸得到诸位的信任，但没有现钱我不能分牌。我当然相信您的话，但还是请您把钱放在纸牌上，这是赌钱的规矩，同时也是为了计算的方便。”

赫尔曼从口袋里掏出一张支票来交给切卡林斯基，切卡林斯基瞟了瞟手中的支票，把它放在赫尔曼的牌上。

他开始分牌。右边出了九点，左边出了三点。

“赢了！”赫尔曼翻出自己的牌。

赌徒们掀起一阵轻声的议论。切卡林斯基皱了皱眉头，脸上随即恢复了笑容。

“您要现钱吗？”他问赫尔曼。

“费神了。”

切卡林斯基从口袋里掏出几张支票，立即把账结清了。赫尔曼收下钱，离开牌桌。纳鲁莫夫看傻了。赫尔曼喝下一杯柠檬汁，回家去了。

第二天晚上，他又到切卡林斯基那里去。主人在发牌。赫尔曼走到牌桌旁，赌徒们立即给他让出一个座位。切卡林斯基亲切地对他点点头。

赫尔曼等到新的一圈开始，押下牌，把四万七千卢布和昨天赢的钱一起放在纸牌上。

切卡林斯基开始分牌。右边出了杰克，左边出了七点。

赫尔曼翻开自己押的七点。

大家惊叫了一声。切卡林斯基显然慌了神。他数了九万四千交给赫尔曼。赫尔曼冷静自若地接过钱，立即走开了。

次日晚上，赫尔曼又来到牌桌旁。大家都在等他。那几个将军和三等文官都放下惠斯特不打，来看这场不同寻常的赌博。年轻的军官们都从沙发上霍地站起来，所有的仆役都集中在客厅里。大家把赫尔曼团团围住。其他赌徒都不押牌，焦急地等着看赫尔曼这场赌博的结果。赫尔曼站在牌桌旁，准备独自和这位脸色煞白但仍微露笑容的切卡林斯基决一胜负。两个人各自拆开一副牌。切卡林斯基洗洗牌。赫尔曼拿出一张牌，押在桌上，把一沓支票放在纸牌上。这简直像一场决斗。赌场上鸦雀无声。

切卡林斯基开始分牌，他的手在颤抖。右边出了皇后。左边出了王牌。

“王牌赢了！”赫尔曼说着，翻开自己的牌。

“您的皇后输了。”切卡林斯基亲切地说。

赫尔曼浑身一震，果然，他押的牌不是A，而是黑桃皇后。他不相信自己的眼睛，不明白自己怎么会拿错牌。

这时他觉得那个黑桃皇后正眯缝着眼睛对他冷笑了一下。这个不同寻常的相似场面使他感到恐怖……

“老太婆！”他惊叫起来。

切卡林斯基把赢得的支票拿过去。赫尔曼呆若木鸡地站着，他从牌桌旁走开的时候，大厅里掀起了一阵闹哄哄的说话声。“赌得真痛快！”赌徒们说。切卡林斯基又洗好了牌，赌博照常进行下去。

结局

赫尔曼疯了。他住进奥布霍夫医院十七号病房，不能回答任何问题，只会非常快地念叨着：“三、七、王牌！三、七、皇后！……”

丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜嫁给一个很可爱的青年，他在某处供职，有一笔可观的财产——他是老伯爵夫人前任管家的儿子。丽莎维塔·伊凡诺夫娜还收养了一个穷亲戚的女儿。

托木斯基升为骑兵上尉，娶了波利娜公爵小姐为妻。

[1]维纳斯是罗马神话中爱和美的女神。此句原文为法语。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明之外，均为译者注。）

[2]黎塞留（1696-1788），法国元帅，波旁王朝枢机主教，第一任黎塞留公爵的侄孙。

[3]一种牌戏。

[4]或称美人膏，用药膏或小黑布片贴在脸上，妇女以此做装饰品。

[5]18世纪50年代出现在巴黎上流社会的冒险家。

[6]指阿加斯菲尔，传说中古代一个终身漂泊的犹太人。

[7]原文为法语。

[8]对话原文为法语。

[9]原文为法语，后面托木斯基在称呼祖母时，均使用了法语，不再特别标注。——编者注

[10]保罗是巴维尔的法语名字，巴维尔是托木斯基的名字。原文为法语。以下凡称保罗，均同此。

[11]丽桑卡是丽莎（即丽莎维塔）的爱称。

[12]原文为法语。

[13]指看门的人。——编者注

[14]原文为法语。

[15]勒布朗夫人（1755-1842），法国画家。原文为法语。

[16]勒鲁瓦（1686-1759），法国著名钟表匠。原文为法语。

[17]18世纪末发明气球的法国人。

[18]梅斯梅尔（1733-1815），奥地利医生，发明催眠术。

[19]原文为法语。

[20]歌德长诗《浮士德》中的魔鬼。

[21]让对方选择舞伴的代号。原文为法语。

[22]原文为法语。

[23]斯维登堡（1688-1772），瑞典哲学家，神秘主义神智学家。

[24]原文为英语。

[25]典出《圣经》故事，见《马太福音》第二十五章第一至十三节。

[26]原文为英语。

[27]一种牌戏。

The Queen of Spades

THE QUEEN OF SPADES BETOKENS THE EVIL EYEModern Guide to Fortune-Telling

1

When bleak was the weather

They would meet together

For cards-God forgive them!

Some would win, others lost,

And they chalked up the cost

In bleak autumn weather

When they met together.

There was a card party in the rooms of Narumov, an officer of the Horse Guards. The long winter night had passed unnoticed and it was after four in the morning when the company sat down to supper. Those who had won enjoyed their food; the others sat absent- mindedly in front of empty plates. But when the champagne appeared conversation became more lively and general.

‘How did you fare, Surin?' Narumov asked.

‘Oh I lost, as usual. I must confess, I have no luck: I stick to mirandole, never get excited, never lose my head, and yet I never win.'

‘Do you mean to tell me you were not once tempted to back the red the whole evening? Your self- control amazes me.'

‘But look at Hermann,' exclaimed one of the party, pointing to a young officer of the Engineers. ‘Never held a card in his hands, never made a bet in his life, and yet he sits up till five in the morning watching us play.

‘Cards interest me very much,' said Hermann, ‘but I am not in a position to risk the necessary in the hope of acquiring the superfluous.'

‘Hermann is a German: he's careful, that's what that is!' remarked Tomsky. ‘But if there is one person I can't understand it is my grandmother, Countess Anna Fedotovna.'

‘Why is that?' the guests cried.

‘I cannot conceive how it is that my grandmother does not play.'

‘But surely there is nothing surprising in an old lady in the eighties not wanting to gamble?' said Narumov.

‘Then you don't know about her?'

‘No, nothing, absolutely nothing!'

‘Well, listen then. I must tell you that some sixty years ago my grandmother went to Paris and was quite the rage there. People would run after her to catch a glimpse of la Vénus moscovite ; Richelieu was at her beck and call, and grandmamma maintains that he very nearly blew his brains out because of her cruelty to him. In those days ladies used to play faro. One evening at the Court she lost a very considerable sum to the Duke of Orleans. When she got home she told my grandfather of her loss while removing the beauty spots from her face and untying her farthingale, and commanded him to pay her debt. My grandfather, so far as I remember, acted as a sort of major- domo to my grandmother. He feared her like fire; however, when he heard of such a frightful gambling loss he almost went out of his mind, fetched the bills they owed and pointed out to her that in six months they had spent half a million roubles and that in Paris they had neither their Moscow nor their Saratov estates upon which to draw, and flatly refused to pay. Grandmamma gave him a box on the ear and retired to bed without him as a sign of her displeasure. The following morning she sent for her husband, hoping that the simple punishment had had its effect, but she found him as obdurate as ever. For the first time in her life she went so far as to reason with him and explain, thinking to rouse his conscience and arguing with condescension, that there were debts and debts, and that a prince was different from a coach- builder. But it was not a bit of good - grandfather just would not hear of it. "Once and for all, no!" Grandmamma did not know what to do. Among her close acquaintances was a very remarkable man. You have heard of Count Saint- Germain, about whom so many marvellous stories are told. You know that he posed as the Wandering Jew and claimed to have discovered the elixir of life and the philosopher's stone, and so on. People laughed at him as a charlatan, and Casanova in his Memoirs says that he was a spy. Be that as it may, Saint- Germain, in spite of the mystery that surrounded him, had a most dignified appearance and was a very amiable person in society. Grandmamma is still to this day quite devoted to his memory and gets angry if anyone speaks of him with disrespect. Grandmamma knew that Saint- Germain had plenty of money at his disposal. She decided to appeal to him, and wrote a note asking him to come and see her immediately. The eccentric old man came at once and found her in terrible distress. She described in the blackest colours her husband's inhumanity, and ended by declaring that she laid all her hopes on his friendship and kindness. Saint- Germain pondered. "I could oblige you with the sum you want," he said, "but I know that you would not be easy until you had repaid me, and I should not like to involve you in fresh trouble. There is another way out - you could win it back."

‘ "But, my dear count," answered grandmamma, "I tell you I have no money at all."

‘ "That does not matter," Saint- Germain replied. "Listen now to what I am going to tell you."

‘And he revealed to her a secret which all of us would give a great deal to know ...'

The young gamblers redoubled their attention. Tomsky lit his pipe, puffed away for a moment and continued:

‘That very evening grandmamma appeared at Versailles, at the jeu de la reine. The Duke of Orleans kept the bank. Grandmamma lightly excused herself for not having brought the money to pay off her debt, inventing some little story by way of explanation, and began to play against him. She selected three cards and played them one after the other: all three won, and grandmamma retrieved her loss completely.'

‘Luck!' said one of the party.

‘A fairy tale!' remarked Hermann.

‘Marked cards, perhaps,' put in a third.

‘I don't think so,' replied Tomsky impressively.

‘What!' said Narumov. ‘You have a grandmother who knows how to hit upon three lucky cards in succession, and you haven't learnt her secret yet?'

‘That's the deuce of it!' Tomsky replied. ‘She had four sons, one of whom was my father; all four were desperate gamblers, and yet she did not reveal her secret to a single one of them, though it would not have been a bad thing for them, or for me either. But listen to what my uncle, Count Ivan Ilyich, used to say, assuring me on his word of honour that it was true. Tchaplitsky - you know him, he died a pauper after squandering millions - as a young man once lost three hundred thousand roubles, to Zorich, if I remember rightly. He was in despair. Grandmamma was always very severe on the follies of young men, but somehow she took pity on Tchaplitsky. She gave him three cards, which he was to play one after the other, at the same time exacting from him a promise that he would never afterwards touch a card so long as he lived. Tchaplitsky went to Zorich's; they sat down to play. Tchaplitsky staked fifty thousand on his first card and won; doubled his stake and won; did the same again, won back his loss and ended up in pocket ...

‘But, I say, it's time to go to bed: it is a quarter to six already.'

And indeed dawn was breaking. The young men emptied their glasses and went home.

2

‘Il paraît que monsieur est décidément pour les suivantes.'

‘Que voulez- vous, madame? Elles sont plus fraîches.'

From a society conversation

The old Countess X was seated before the lookingglass in her dressing- room. Three maids were standing round her. One held a pot of rouge, another a box of hairpins, and the third a tall cap with flame- coloured ribbons. The countess had not the slightest pretensions to beauty - it had faded long ago - but she still preserved all the habits of her youth, followed strictly the fashion of the seventies, and gave as much time and care to her toilette as she had sixty years before. A young girl whom she had brought up sat at an embroidery-frame by the window.

‘Good morning, grand'maman!' said a young officer, coming into the room. ‘Bonjour, Mademoiselle Lise. Grand'maman, I have a favour to ask of you.'

‘What is it, Paul?'

‘I want you to let me introduce to you a friend of mine and bring him to your ball on Friday.'

‘Bring him straight to the ball and introduce him to me then. Were you at the princess's last night?'

‘Of course I was! It was most enjoyable: we danced until five in the morning. Mademoiselle Yeletsky looked enchanting!'

‘Come, my dear! What is there enchanting about her? She isn't a patch on her grandmother, Princess Daria Petrovna. By the way, I expect PrinPrincess Daria Petrovna must have aged considerably?'

‘How do you mean, aged?' Tomsky replied absentmindedly. ‘She's been dead for the last seven years.'

The girl at the window raised her head and made a sign to the young man. He remembered that they concealed the deaths of her contemporaries from the old countess, and bit his lip. But the countess heard the news with the utmost indifference.

‘Dead! I didn't know,' she said. ‘We were maids of honour together, and as we were being presented to the Empress ...'

And for the hundredth time the countess repeated the story to her grandson.

‘Well, Paul,' she said at the end; ‘now help me to my feet. Lise, where is my snuff- box?'

And the countess went with her maids behind the screen to finish dressing. Tomsky was left à deux with the young girl.

‘Who is it you want to introduce?' Lizaveta Ivanovna asked softly.

‘Narumov. Do you know him?'

‘No. Is he in the army?'

‘Yes.'

‘In the Engineers?'

‘No, Horse Guards. What made you think he was in the Engineers?'

The girl laughed and made no answer.‘Paul!' the countess called from behind the screen. ‘Send me a new novel to read, only pray not one of

those modern ones.'

‘How do you mean, grand'maman ? '

‘I want a book in which the hero does not strangle either his father or his mother, and where there are no drowned corpses. I have a horror of drowned persons.'

‘There aren't any novels of that sort nowadays. Wouldn't you like something in Russian?'

‘Are there any Russian novels? ... Send me something, my dear fellow, please send me something!'

‘Excuse me, grand'maman : I m ust h urry ... Good- bye, Lizaveta Ivanovna! I wonder, what made you think Narumov was in the Engineers?'

And Tomsky departed from the dressing- room.

Lizaveta Ivanovna was left alone. She abandoned her work and began to look out of the window. Soon, round the corner of a house on the other side of the street, a young officer appeared. Colour flooded her cheeks; she took up her work again, bending her head over her embroidery- frame. At that moment the countess came in, having finished dressing.

‘Order the carriage, Lise,' she said, ‘and let us go for a drive.'

Lizaveta Ivanovna rose from her embroidery- frame and began putting away her work.

‘What is the matter with you, my child, are you deaf?' the countess cried. ‘Be quick and order the carriage.'

‘I will go at once,' the young girl answered quietly, and ran into the ante- room.

A servant came in and handed the countess a parcel of books from Prince Paul Alexandrovich.

‘Good! Tell him I am much obliged,' said the countess. ‘Lise, Lise, where are you off to?'

‘To dress.'

‘There is plenty of time, my dear. Sit down here. Open the first volume and read to me.'

The girl took the book and read a few lines.

‘Louder!' said the countess. ‘What is the matter with you, my dear? Have you lost your voice, or what? Wait a minute ... Give me that footstool. A little closer. That will do!'

Lizaveta Ivanovna read two more pages. The countess yawned.

‘Throw that book away,' she said. ‘What nonsense it is! Send it back to Prince Paul with my thanks ... What about the carriage?'

‘The carriage is ready,' said Lizaveta Ivanovna, glancing out into the street.

‘How is it you are not dressed?' the countess said. ‘You always keep people waiting. It really is intolerable!'

Liza ran to her room. Hardly two minutes passed before the countess started ringing with all her might. Three maids rushed in at one door and a footman at the other.

‘Why is it you don't come when you are called?' the countess said to them. ‘Tell Lizaveta Ivanovna I am waiting.'

Lizaveta Ivanovna returned, wearing a hat and a pelisse.

‘At last, my dear!' said the countess. ‘Why the finery? What is it for? ... For whose benefit? ... And what is the weather like? Windy, isn't it?'

‘No, your ladyship,' the footman answered, ‘there is no wind at all.'

‘You say anything that comes into your head! Open the window. Just as I thought: there is a wind, and a very cold one too! Dismiss the carriage. Lise, my child, we won't go out - you need not have dressed up after all.'

‘And this is my life!' Lizaveta Ivanovna thought to herself.

Indeed, Lizaveta Ivanovna was a most unfortunate creature. ‘Another's bread is bitter to the taste,' says Dante, ‘and his staircase hard to climb'; and who should know the bitterness of dependence better than a poor orphan brought up by an old lady of quality? The countess was certainly not bad- hearted but she had all the caprices of a woman spoiled by society, she was stingy and coldly selfish, like all old people who have done with love and are out of touch with life around them. She took part in all the vanities of the fashionable world, dragged herself to balls, where she sat in a corner, rouged and attired after some bygone mode, like a misshapen but indispensable ornament of the ball- room. On their arrival the guests all went up to her and bowed low, as though in accordance with an old- established rite, and after that no one took any more notice of her. She received the whole town at her house, observing the strictest etiquette and not recognizing the faces of any of her guests. Her numerous servants, grown fat and grey in her entrance hall and the maids' quarters, did what they liked and vied with each other in robbing the decrepit old woman. Lizaveta Ivanovna was the household martyr. She poured out tea and was reprimanded for using too much sugar; she read novels aloud to the countess and was blamed for all the author's mistakes; she accompanied the countess on her drives and was answerable for the weather and the state of the roads. She was supposed to receive a salary, which was never paid in full and yet she was expected to be as well dressed as every one else - that is, as very few indeed. In society she played the most pitiable role. Everybody knew her and nobody gave her any thought. At balls she danced only when someone was short of a partner, and the ladies would take her by the arm each time they wanted to go to the cloak- room to rearrange some detail of their toilette. She was sensitive and felt her position keenly, and looked about impatiently for a deliverer to come; but the young men, calculating in their empty- headed frivolity, honoured her with scant attention though Lizaveta Ivanovna was a hundred times more charming than the cold, brazen- faced heiresses they ran after. Many a time she crept away from the tedious, glittering drawing- room to go and weep in her humble little attic with its wall- paper screen, chest of drawers, small looking- glass and painted wooden bedstead, and where a tallow- candle burned dimly in a brass candle stick.

One morning, two days after the card party described at the beginning of this story and a week before the scene we have just witnessed - one morning Lizaveta Ivanovna, sitting at her embroidery- frame by the window, happened to glance out into the street and see a young Engineers officer standing stock- still gazing at her window. She lowered her head and went on with her work. Five minutes afterwards she looked out again - the young officer was still on the same spot. Not being in the habit of coquetting with passing officers, she looked out no more and went on sewing for a couple of hours without raising her head. Luncheon was announced. She got up to put away her embroidery- frame and, glancing casually into the street, saw the officer again. This seemed to her somewhat strange. After luncheon she went to the window with a certain feeling of uneasiness, but the officer was no longer there, and she forgot about him ...

A day or so later, just as she was stepping into the carriage with the countess, she saw him again. He was standing right by the front door, his face hidden by his beaver collar; his dark eyes sparkled beneath his fur cap. Lizaveta Ivanovna felt alarmed, though she did not know why, and seated herself in the carriage, inexplicably agitated.

On returning home she ran to the window - the officer was standing in his accustomed place, his eyes fixed on her. She drew back, consumed with curiosity and excited by a feeling quite new to her.

Since then not a day had passed without the young man appearing at a certain hour beneath the windows of their house, and between him and her a sort of mute acquaintance was established. Sitting at her work she would sense his approach, and lifting her head she looked at him longer and longer every day. The young man seemed to be grateful to her for looking out: with the keen eyes of youth she saw the quick flush of his pale cheeks every time their glances met. By the end of a week she had smiled at him ...

When Tomsky asked the countess's permission to introduce a friend of his the poor girl's heart beat violently. But hearing that Narumov was in the Horse Guards, not the Engineers, she regretted the indiscreet question by which she had betrayed her secret to the irresponsible Tomsky.

*

Hermann was the son of a German who had settled in Russia and who left him some small capital sum. Being firmly convinced that it was essential for him to make certain of his independence, Hermann did not touch even the interest on his income but lived on his pay, denying himself the slightest extravagance. But since he was reserved and ambitious his companions rarely had any opportunity for making fun of his extreme parsimony. He had strong passions and an ardent imagination, but strength of character preserved him from the customary mistakes of youth. Thus, for instance, though a gambler at heart he never touched cards, having decided that his means did not allow him (as he put it) ‘to risk the necessary in the hope of acquiring the superfluous'. And yet he spent night after night at the card tables, watching with feverish anxiety the vicissitudes of the game.

The story of the three cards had made a powerful impression upon his imagination and it haunted his mind all night. ‘Supposing,' he thought to himself the following evening as he wandered about Petersburg, ‘supposing the old countess were to reveal her secret to me? Or tell me the three winning cards! Why shouldn't I try my luck? ... Get introduced to her, win her favour - become her lover, perhaps. But all that would take time, and she is eighty- seven. She might be dead next week, or the day after tomorrow even! ... A nd t he s tory i tself? I s i t l ikely? N o, economy, moderation and hard work are my three winning cards. With them I can treble my capital - increase it sevenfold and obtain for myself leisure and independence!' Musing thus, he found himself in one of the main streets of Petersburg, in front of a house of old- fashioned architecture. The street was lined with carriages which followed one another up to the lighted porch. Out of the carriages stepped now the shapely little foot of a young beauty, now a military boot with clinking spur, or a diplomat's striped stockings and buckled shoes. Fur coats and cloaks passed in rapid procession before the majestic- looking con cierge. Hermann stopped.

‘Whose house is that?' he asked a watchman in his box at the corner.

‘The Countess X's,' the man told him. It was Tomsky's grandmother.

Hermann started. The strange story of the three cards came into his mind again. He began walking up and down past the house, thinking of its owner and her wonderful secret. It was late when he returned to his humble lodgings; he could not get to sleep for a long time, and when sleep did come he dreamed of cards, a green baize table, stacks of bank- notes and piles of gold. He played card after card, resolutely turning down the corners, winning all the time. He raked in the gold and stuffed his pockets with bank- notes. Waking late in the morning, he sighed over the loss of his fantastic wealth, and then, sallying forth to wander about the town again, once more found himself outside the countess's house. It was as though some supernatural force drew him there. He stopped and looked up at the windows. In one of them he saw a dark head bent over a book or some needlework. The head was raised. Hermann caught sight of a rosy face and a pair of black eyes. That moment decided his fate.

3

Vous m'écrivez, mon ange, des lettres de quatre pages plus vite que je ne puis les lire.

From a correspondence

Lizaveta Ivanovna had scarcely taken off her hat and mantle before the countess sent for her and again ordered the carriage. They went out to take their seats. Just as the two footmen were lifting the old lady and helping her through the carriage door Lizaveta Ivanovna saw her Engineers officer standing by the wheel. He seized her hand; before she had recovered from her alarm the young man had disappeared, leaving a letter between her fingers. She hid it in her glove, and for the rest of the drive neither saw nor heard anything. It was the countess's habit when they were out in the carriage to ask a constant stream of questions: ‘Who was that we met?' - ‘What bridge i this?' - ‘What does that signboard say?' This time Lizaveta Ivanovna returned such random and irrelevant answers that the countess grew angry with her.

‘What is the matter with you, my dear? Have you taken leave of your senses? Don't you hear me or understand what I say? ... I speak distinctly enough, thank heaven, and am not in my dotage yet!'

Lizaveta Ivanovna paid no attention to her. When they returned home she ran up to her room and drew the letter out of her glove: it was unsealed. She read it. The letter contained a declaration of love: it was tender, respectful and had been copied word for word from a German novel. But Lizaveta Ivanovna did not know any German and she was delighted with it.

For all that, the letter troubled her greatly. For the first time in her life she was embarking upon secret and intimate relations with a young man. His boldness appalled her. She reproached herself for her imprudent behaviour, and did not know what to do: ought she to give up sitting at the window and by a show of indifference damp the young man's inclination to pursue her further? Should she return his letter to him? Or answer it coldly and firmly? There was nobody to whom she could turn for advice: she had neither female friend nor preceptor. Lizaveta Ivanovna decided to reply to the letter.

She sat down at her little writing- table, took pen and paper - and began to ponder. Several times she made a start and then tore the paper across: what she had written seemed to her either too indulgent or too harsh. At last she succeeded in composing a few lines with which she felt satisfied. ‘I am sure', she wrote, ‘that your intentions are honourable and that you had no wish to hurt me by any thoughtless conduct; but our acquaintance ought not to have begun in this manner. I return you your letter, and hope that in future I shall have no cause to complain of being shown a lack of respect which is undeserved.'

Next day, as soon as she saw Hermann approaching, Lizaveta Ivanovna got up from her embroideryframe, went into the drawing- room, opened the little ventilating window and threw the letter into the street, trusting to the young officer's alertness. Hermann ran forward, picked the letter up and went into a confectioner's shop. Breaking the seal, he found his own letter and Lizaveta Ivanovna's reply. It was just what he had expected and he returned home engrossed in his plot.

Three days after this a sharp- eyed young person brought Lizaveta Ivanovna a note from a milliner's establishment. Lizaveta Ivanovna opened it uneasily, fearing it was a demand for money, and suddenly recognized Hermann's handwriting.

‘You have made a mistake, my dear,' she said. ‘This note is not for me.'

‘Oh yes it is for you!' retorted the girl boldly, not troubling to conceal a knowing smile. ‘Please read it.'

Lizaveta Ivanovna glanced at the letter. In it Hermann wanted her to meet him.

‘Impossible!' she cried, alarmed at the request, at its coming so soon, and at the means employed to transmit it. ‘I am sure this was not addressed to me.' And she tore the letter into fragments.

‘If the letter was not for you, why did you tear it up?' said the girl. ‘I would have returned it to the sender.'

‘Be good enough, my dear,' said Lizaveta Ivanovna, flushing crimson at her remark, ‘not to bring me any more letters. And tell the person who sent you that he ought to be ashamed ...'

But Hermann did not give in. Every day Lizaveta Ivanovna received a letter from him by one means or another. They were no longer translated from the German. Hermann wrote them inspired by passion and in a style which was his own: they reflected both his inexorable desire and the disorder of an unbridled imagination. Lizaveta Ivanovna no longer thought of returning them: she drank them in eagerly and took to answering - and the notes she sent grew longer and more affectionate every hour. At last she threw out of the window to him the following letter:

There is a ball tonight at the Embassy. The countess will be there. We shall stay until about two o'clock. Here is an opportunity for you to see me alone. As soon as the countess is away the servants are sure to go to their quarters, leaving the concierge in the hall but he usually retires to his lodge. Come at half past eleven. Walk straight up the stairs. If you meet anyone in the ante- room, ask if the countess is at home. They will say ‘No', but there will be no help for it - you will have to go away. But probably you will not meet anyone. The maids all sit together in the one room. Turn to the left out of the ante-room and keep straight on until you reach the countess's bedroom. In the bedroom, behind a screen, you will find two small doors: the one on the right leads into the study where the countess never goes; and the other on the left opens into a passage with a narrow winding staircase up to my room.

Hermann waited for the appointed hour like a tiger trembling for its prey. By ten o'clock in the evening he was already standing outside the countess's house. It was a frightful night: the wind howled, wet snow fell in big flakes; the street-lamps burned dimly; the streets were deserted. From time to time a sledge drawn by a sorry- looking hack passed by, the driver on the watch for a belated fare. Hermann stood there without his great- coat, feeling neither the wind nor the snow. At last the countess's carriage was brought round. Hermann saw the old woman wrapped in sables being lifted into the vehicle by two footmen; then Liza in a light cloak, with natural flowers in her hair, flitted by. The carriage doors banged. The vehicle rolled heavily over the wet snow. The concierge closed the street- door. The lights in the windows went out. Hermann started to walk to and fro outside the deserted house; he went up to a street- lamp and glanced at his watch: it was twenty minutes past eleven. He stood still by the lamp- post, his eyes fixed on the hand of the watch. Precisely at half past eleven Hermann walked up the steps of the house and entered the brightly lit vestibule. The concierge was not there. Hermann ran up the stairs, opened the door of the ante- room and saw a footman asleep in a soiled, old- fashioned arm- chair by the side of a lamp. With a light, firm tread Hermann passed quickly by him. The ball- room and drawing- room were in darkness but the lamp in the ante- room shed a dim light into them. Hermann entered the bedroom. Ancient icons filled the icon- stand before which burned a golden lamp. Arm- chairs upholstered in faded damask and sofas with down cushions, the tassels of which had lost their gilt, were ranged with depressing symmetry round the walls hung with Chinese wall- paper. On one of the walls were two portraits painted in Paris by Madame Lebrun: the first of a stout, red- faced man of some forty years of age, in a light- green uniform with a star on his breast; the other - a beautiful young woman with an aquiline nose and a rose in the powdered hair drawn back over her temples. Every corner was crowded with porcelain shepherdesses, clocks made by the celebrated Leroy, little boxes, roulettes, fans and all the thousand and one playthings invented for ladies of fashion at the end of the last century together with Montgolfier's balloon and Mesmer's magnetism. Hermann stepped behind the screen. A small iron bedstead stood there; to the right was the door into the study - to the left, the other door into the passage. Hermann opened it and saw the narrow winding staircase leading to poor little Liza's room. But he turned about and went into the dark study.

The time passed slowly. Everything was quiet. The drawing- room clock struck twelve; the clocks in the other rooms chimed twelve, one after the other, and all was still again. Hermann stood leaning against the cold stove. He was quite calm: his heart beat evenly, like that of a man resolved upon a dangerous but inevitable undertaking. The clocks struck one, and then two, and he heard the distant rumble of a carriage. In spite of himself he was overcome with agitation. The carriage drove up to the house and stopped. He heard the clatter of the carriage- steps being lowered. In the house all was commotion. Servants ran to and fro, there was a confusion of voices, and lights appeared everywhere. Three ancient lady's maids bustled into the bedroom, followed by the countess who, half dead with fatigue, sank into a Voltaire arm- chair. Hermann watched through a crack in the door. Lizaveta Ivanovna passed close by him and he heard her footsteps hurrying up the stairs to her room. For a moment something akin to remorse assailed him but he quickly hardened his heart again.

The countess began undressing before the looking- glass. Her maids took off the cap trimmed with roses and lifted the powdered wig from her grey, closely cropped head. Pins showered about her. The silver- trimmed yellow dress fell at her puffy feet. Hermann witnessed the hideous mysteries of her toilette; at last the countess put on bed jacket and night- cap, and in this attire, more suited to her age, she seemed less horrible and ugly.

Like most old people the countess suffered from sleeplessness. Having undressed, she sat down in a big arm- chair by the window and dismissed her maids. They took away the candles, leaving only the lamp before the icons to light the room. The countess sat there, her skin sallow with age, her flabby lips twitching, her body swaying to and fro. Her dim eyes were completely vacant and looking at her one might have imagined that the dreadful old woman was rocking her body not from choice but owing to some secret galvanic mechanism.

Suddenly an inexplicable change came over the death- like face. The lips ceased to move, the eyes brightened: before the countess stood a strange young man.

‘Do not be alarmed, for heaven's sake, do not be alarmed!' he said in a low, clear voice. ‘I have no intention of doing you any harm, I have come to beg a favour of you.'

The old woman stared at him in silence, as if she had not heard. Hermann thought she must be deaf and bending down to her ear he repeated what he had just said. The old woman remained silent as before.

‘You can ensure the happiness of my whole life,' Hermann went on, ‘and at no cost to yourself. I know that you can name three cards in succession ...'

Hermann stopped. The countess appeared to have grasped what he wanted and to be seeking words to frame her answer.

‘It was a joke,' she said at last. ‘I swear to you it was a joke.'

‘No, madam,' Hermann retorted angrily. ‘Remember Tchaplitsky, and how you enabled him to win back his loss.'

The countess was plainly perturbed. Her face expressed profound agitation; but soon she relapsed into her former impassivity.

‘Can you not tell me those three winning cards?' Hermann went on.

The countess said nothing. Hermann continued:

‘For whom would you keep your secret? For your grandsons? They are rich enough already: they don't appreciate the value of money. Your three cards would not help a spendthrift. A man who does not take care of his inheritance will die a beggar though all the demons of the world were at his command. I am not a spendthrift: I know the value of money. Your three cards would not be wasted on me. Well? ...'

He paused, feverishly waiting for her reply. She was silent. Hermann fell on his knees.

‘If your heart has ever known what it is to love, if you can remember the ecstasies of love, if you have ever smiled tenderly at the cry of your new- born son, if any human feeling has ever stirred in your breast, I appeal to you as wife, beloved one, mother - I implore you by all that is holy in life not to reject my prayer: tell me your secret. Of what use is it to you? Perhaps it is bound up with some terrible sin, with the loss of eternal salvation, with some bargain with the devil ... Reflect - you are old: you have not much longer to live, and I am ready to take your sin upon my soul. Only tell me your secret. Remember that a man's happiness is in your hands; that not only I, but my children and my children's children will bless your memory and hold it sacred ...'

The old woman answered not a word.

Hermann rose to his feet.

‘You old hag!' he said, grinding his teeth. ‘Then I will make you speak ...'

With these words he drew a pistol from his pocket. At the sight of the pistol the countess for the second time showed signs of agitation. Her head shook and she raised a hand as though to protect herself from the shot ... Then she fell back ... and was still.

‘Come, an end to this childish nonsense!' said Hermann, seizing her by the arm. ‘I ask you for the last time - will you tell me those three cards? Yes or no?'

The countess made no answer. Hermann saw that she was dead.

4

7 mai 18-

Homme sans moeurs et sans religion!

From a correspondence

Lizaveta Ivanovna was sitting in her room, still in her ball dress, lost in thought. On returning home she had made haste to dismiss the sleepy maid who reluctantly offered to help her, saying that she would undress herself, and with trembling heart had gone to her own room, expecting to find Hermann and hoping that she would not find him. A glance convinced her he was not there, and she thanked fate for having prevented their meeting. She sat down without undressing and began to recall the circumstances that had led her so far in so short a time. It was not three weeks since she had first caught sight of the young man from the window - and yet she was carrying on a correspondence with him, and he had already succeeded in inducing her to agree to a nocturnal tryst! She knew his name only because he had signed some of his letters; she had never spoken to him, did not know the sound of his voice, had never heard him mentioned ... until that evening. Strange to say, that very evening at the ball, Tomsky, piqued with the young Princess Pauline for flirting with somebody else instead of with him as she usually did, decided to revenge himself by a show of indifference. He asked Lizaveta Ivanovna to be his partner and danced the interminable mazurka with her. And all the time he kept teasing her about her partiality for officers of the Engineers, assuring her that he knew far more than she could suppose, and some of his sallies so found their mark that several times Lizaveta Ivanovna thought he must know her secret.

‘Who told you all this?' she asked, laughing.

‘A friend of someone you know,' Tomsky answered, ‘a very remarkable person.'

‘And who is this remarkable man?'

‘His name is Hermann.'

Lizaveta Ivanovna said nothing; but her hands and feet turned to ice.

‘This Hermann', continued Tomsky, ‘ is a t ruly romantic figure: he has the profile of a Napoleon and the soul of a Mephistopheles. I think there must be at least three crimes on his conscience. How pale you look!'

‘I have a bad headache ... Well, and what did this Hermann - or whatever his name is - tell you?'

‘Hermann is very annoyed with his friend: he says that in his place he would act quite differently ... I suspect in fact that Hermann has designs upon you himself; at any rate he listens to his friend's ecstatic exclamations with anything but indifference.'

‘But where has he seen me?'

‘In church, perhaps, or when you were out walking ... heaven only knows! - in your own room maybe, while you were asleep, for there is nothing he -'

Three ladies coming up to invite Tomsky to choose between ‘oubli ou regret?' interrupted the conversation which had become so painfully interesting to Lizaveta Ivanovna.

The lady chosen by Tomsky was the Princess Pauline herself. She succeeded in effecting a reconciliation with him while they danced an extra turn and spun round once more before she was conducted to her chair. When he returned to his place neither Hermann nor Lizaveta Ivanovna was in Tomsky's thoughts. Lizaveta Ivanovna longed to resume the interrupted conversation but the mazurka came to an end and shortly afterwards the old countess took her departure.

Tomsky's words were nothing more than the usual small- talk of the ball- room; but they sank deep into the girl's romantic heart. The portrait sketched by Tomsky resembled the picture she had herself drawn, and thanks to the novels of the day the commonplace figure both terrified and fascinated her. She sat there with her bare arms crossed and with her head, still adorned with flowers, sunk upon her naked bosom ... Suddenly the door opened and Hermann came in ... She shuddered.

‘Where were you?' she asked in a frightened ‘In the old countess's bedroom,' Hermann answered. ‘I have just left her. The countess is dead.' ‘Merciful heavens! ... what are you saying?' whisper.

‘And I think', added Hermann, ‘that I am the cause of her death.'

Lizaveta darted a glance at him, and heard Tomsky's words echo in her soul: ‘... there must be at least three crimes on his conscience'. Hermann sat down in the window beside her and related all that had happened.

Lizaveta Ivanovna listened to him aghast. So all those passionate letters, those ardent pleas, the bold, determined pursuit had not been inspired by love! Money! - that was what his soul craved! It was not she who could satisfy his desires and make him happy! Poor child, she had been nothing but the blind tool of a thief, of the murderer of her aged benefactress! ... She wept bitterly in a vain agony of repentance. Hermann watched in silence: he too was suffering torment; but neither the poor girl's tears nor her indescribable charm in her grief touched his hardened soul. He felt no pricking of conscience at the thought of the dead old woman. One thing only horrified him: the irreparable loss of the secret which was to have brought him wealth.

‘You are a monster!' said Lizaveta Ivanovna at last.

‘I did not mean her to die,' Hermann answered. ‘My pistol was not loaded.'

Both were silent.

Morning came. Lizaveta Ivanovna blew out the candle which had burned down. A pale light illumined the room. She wiped her tear- stained eyes and looked up at Hermann: he was sitting on the window- sill with his arms folded, a menacing frown on his face. In this attitude he bore a remarkable likeness to the portrait of Napoleon. The likeness struck even Lizaveta Ivanovna.

‘How shall I get you out of the house?' she said at last. ‘I had thought of taking you down the secret staircase but that means going through the bedroom, and I am afraid.'

‘Tell me how to find this secret staircase - I will go alone.'

Lizaveta rose, took a key from the chest of drawers and gave it to Hermann with precise instructions. Hermann pressed her cold, unresponsive hand, kissed her bowed head and left her.

He walked down the winding stairway and entered the countess's bedroom again. The dead woman sat as though turned to stone. Her face wore a look of profound tranquillity. Hermann stood in front of her and gazed long and earnestly at her, as though trying to convince himself of the terrible truth. Then he went into the study, felt behind the tapestry for the door and began to descend the dark stairway, excited by strange emotions. ‘Maybe some sixty years ago, at this very hour,' he thought, ‘some happy youth - long since turned to dust - was stealing up this staircase into that very bedroom, in an embroidered tunic, his hair dressed à l'oiseau royal, pressing his three- cornered hat to his breast; and today the heart of his aged mistress has ceased to beat ...'

At the bottom of the stairs Hermann saw a door which he opened with the same key, and found himself in a passage leading to the street.

5

That night the dead Baroness von W. appeared before me. She was all in white and said: ‘How do you do, Mr Coun cillor?'

Swedenborg

Three days after that fatal night, at nine o'clock in the morning, Hermann repaired to the Convent of * * * *, where the last respects were to be paid to the mortal remains of the dead countess. Though he felt no remorse he could not altogether stifle the voice of conscience which kept repeating to him: ‘You are the old woman's murderer!' Having very little religious faith, he was exceedingly superstitious. Believing that the dead countess might exercise a malignant influence on his life, he decided to go to her funeral to beg and obtain her forgiveness.

The church was full. Hermann had difficulty in making his way through the crowd. The coffin rested on a rich catafalque beneath a canopy of velvet. The dead woman lay with her hands crossed on her breast, in a lace cap and a white satin robe. Around the bier stood the members of her household: servants in black clothes, with armorial ribbons on their shoulders and lighted candles in their hands; relatives in deep mourning - children, grandchildren and great- grandchildren. No one wept: tears would have been une affectation. The countess was so old that her death could not have taken anybody by surprise, and her family had long ceased to think of her as one of the living. A famous preacher delivered the funeral oration. In simple and touching phrases he described the peaceful passing of the saintly woman whose long life had been a quiet, touching preparation for a Christian end. ‘The angel of death', he declared, ‘found her vigilant in devout meditation, awaiting the midnight coming of the bridegroom.' The service was concluded in melancholy decorum. First the relations went forward to bid farewell of the corpse. They were followed by a long procession of all those who had come to render their last homage to one who had for so many years been a participator in their frivolous amusements. After them came the members of the countess's household. The last of these was an old woman- retainer the same age as the deceased. Two young girls supported her by the arms. She had not strength to prostrate herself - and she was the only one to shed tears as she kissed her mistress's cold hand. Hermann decided to approach the coffin after her. He knelt down on the cold stone strewed with branches of spruce- fir, and remained in that position for some minutes; at last he rose to his feet and, pale as the deceased herself, walked up the steps of the catafalque and bent over the corpse ... At that moment it seemed to him that the dead woman darted a mocking look at him and winked her eye. Hermann drew back, missed his footing and crashed headlong to the floor. They picked him up. At the same time Lizaveta Ivanovna was carried out of the church in a swoon. This incident momentarily upset the solemnity of the mournful rite. There was a dull murmur among the congregation, and a tall thin man in the uniform of a court- chamberlain, a close relative of the deceased, whispered in the ear of an Englishman who was standing near him that the young officer was the natural son of the countess, to which the Englishman coldly replied, ‘Oh?'

The whole of that day Hermann was strangely troubled. Repairing to a quiet little tavern to dine, he drank a great deal of wine, contrary to his habit, in the hope of stifling his inner agitation. But the wine only served to excite his imagination. Returning home, he threw himself on his bed without undressing, and fell heavily asleep.

It was night when he woke and the moon was shining into his room. He glanced at the time: it was a quarter to three. Sleep had left him; he sat on the bed and began thinking of the old countess's funeral.

Just then someone in the street looked in at him through the window and immediately walked on. Hermann paid no attention. A moment later he heard the door of his ante- room open. Hermann thought it was his orderly, drunk as usual, returning from some nocturnal excursion, but presently he heard an unfamiliar footstep: someone was softly shuffling along the floor in slippers. The door opened and a woman in white came in. Hermann mistook her for his old nurse and wondered what could have brought her at such an hour. But the woman in white glided across the room and stood before him - and Hermann recognized the countess!

‘I have come to you against my will,' she said in a firm voice: ‘but I am commanded to grant your request. The three, the seven and the ace will win for you if you play them in succession, provided that you do not stake more than one card in twenty- four hours and never play again as long as you live. I forgive you my death, on condition that you marry my ward, Lizaveta Ivanovna.'

With these words she turned softly, rustled to the door in her slippers, and disappeared. Hermann heard the street- door click and again saw someone peeping in at him through the window.

It was a long time before he could pull himself together and go into the next room. His orderly was asleep on the floor: Hermann had difficulty in waking him. The man was drunk as usual: there was no getting any sense out of him. The street- door was locked. Hermann returned to his room and, lighting a candle, wrote down all the details of his vision.

6

‘Attendez!'

‘How dare you say "Attendez!" to me?'

‘Your Excellency, I said "Attendez", sir.'

Two idées fixes cannot co- exist in the moral world any more than two physical bodies can occupy one and the same space. ‘The three, the seven, the ace' soon drove all thought of the dead woman from Hermann's mind. ‘Three, seven, ace' were perpetually in his head and on his lips. If he saw a young girl he would say, ‘How graceful she is! A regular three of hearts!' Asked the time, he would reply, ‘Five minutes to seven.' Every stout man reminded him of the ace. ‘Three, seven, ace' haunted his dreams, assuming all sorts of shapes. The three blossomed before him like a luxuriant flower, the seven took the form of a Gothic portal, and aces became gigantic spiders. His whole attention was focused on one thought: how to make use of the secret which had cost him so dear. He began to consider resigning his commission in order to go and travel abroad. In the public gambling- houses in Paris he would compel fortune to give him his magical treasure. Chance spared him the trouble.

A circle of wealthy gamblers existed in Moscow, presided over by the celebrated Tchekalinsky, who had spent his life at the card- table and amassed millions, accepting promissory notes when he won and paying his losses in ready money. His long experience inspired the confidence of his fellow- players, while his open house, his famous chef and his gay and friendly manner secured for him the general respect of the public. He came to Petersburg. The young men of the capital flocked to his rooms, forsaking balls for cards and preferring the excitement of gambling to the seductions of flirting. Narumov brought Hermann to him.

They passed through a succession of magnificent rooms full of attentive servants. The place was crowded. Several generals and privy councillors were playing whist; young men smoking long pipes lounged about on sofas upholstered in damask. In the drawing- room some twenty gamblers jostled round a long table at which the master of the house was keeping bank. Tchekalinsky was a man of about sixty years of age and most dignified appearance; he had silvery- grey hair, a full, florid face with a kindly expression, and sparkling eyes which were always smiling. Narumov introduced Hermann. Shaking hands cordially, Tchekalinsky requested him not to stand on ceremony, and went on dealing.

The game continued for some while. On the table lay more than thirty cards. Tchekalinsky paused after each round to give the players time to arrange their cards and note their losses, listened courteously to their observations and more courteously still straightened the corner of a card that some careless hand had turned down. At last the game finished. Tchekalinsky shuffled the cards and prepared to deal again.

‘Will you allow me to take a card?' said Hermann, stretching out his hand from behind a stout gentleman who was punting.

Tchekalinsky smiled and bowed graciously, in silent token of consent. Narumov laughingly congratulated Hermann on breaking his long abstention from cards and wished him a lucky start.

‘There!' said Hermann, chalking some figures on the back of his card.

‘How much?' asked the banker, screwing up his eyes. ‘Excuse me, I cannot see.'

‘ Forty- seven thousand,' Hermann answered.

At these words every head was turned in a flash, and all eyes were fixed on Hermann.

‘He has taken leave of his senses!' thought Narumov.

‘Allow me to point out to you', said Tchekalinsky with his unfailing smile, ‘that you are playing rather high: nobody here has ever staked more than two hundred and seventy- five at a time.'

‘Well?' returned Hermann. ‘Do you accept my card or not?'

Tchekalinsky bowed with the same air of humble acquiescence.

‘I only wanted to observe', he said ‘that, being honoured with the confidence of my friends, I can only play against ready money. For my own part, of course, I am perfectly sure that your word is sufficient but for the sake of the rules of the game and our accounts I must request you to place the money on your card.'

Hermann took a bank- note from his pocket and handed it to Tchekalinsky, who after a cursory glance placed it on Hermann's card. He began to deal. On the right a nine turned up, and on the left a three.

‘I win!' said Hermann, pointing to his card.

There was a murmur of astonishment among the company. Tchekalinsky frowned, but the smile quickly reappeared on his face.

‘Would you like me to settle now?' he asked Hermann.

‘If you please.'

Tchekalinsky took a number of bank- notes out of his pocket and paid there and then. Hermann picked up his money and left the table. Narumov could not believe his eyes. Hermann drank a glass of lemonade and departed home.

The following evening he appeared at Tchekalinsky's again. The host was dealing. Hermann walked up to the table; the players immediately made room for him. Tchekalinsky bowed graciously. Hermann waited for the next deal, took a card and placed on it his original forty- seven thousand together with his winnings of the day before. Tchekalinsky began to deal. A knave turned up on the right, a seven on the left.

Hermann showed his seven.

There was a general exclamation. Tchekalinsky was obviously disconcerted. He counted out ninetyfour thousand and handed them to Hermann, who pocketed them in the coolest manner and instantly withdrew.

The next evening Hermann again made his appearance at the table. Every one was expecting him; the generals and privy councillors left their whist to watch such extraordinary play. The young officers leaped up from their sofas and all the waiters collected in the drawing- room. Every one pressed round Hermann. The other players left off punting, impatient to see what would happen. Hermann stood at the table, prepared to play alone against Tchekalinsky, who was pale but still smiling. Each broke the seal of a pack of cards. Tchekalinsky shuffled. Hermann took a card and covered it with a pile of bank- notes. It was like a duel. Deep silence reigned in the room.

Tchekalinsky began dealing; his hands trembled. A queen fell on the right, an ace on the left.

‘Ace wins!' said Hermann, and showed his card.

‘Your queen has lost,' said Tchekalinsky gently.

Hermann started: indeed, instead of an ace there lay before him the queen of spades. He could not believe his eyes or think how he could have made such a mistake.

At that moment it seemed to him that the queen of spades opened and closed her eye, and mocked him with a smile. He was struck by the extraordinary resemblance ...

‘The old woman!' he cried in terror.

Tchekalinsky gathered up his winnings. Hermann stood rooted to the spot. When he left the table every one began talking at once.

‘A fine game, that!' said the players.

Tchekalinsky shuffled the cards afresh and the game resumed as usual.

CONCLUSION

Hermann went out of his mind. He is now in room number 17 of the Obuhov Hospital. He returns no answer to questions put to him but mutters over and over again, with incredible rapidity: ‘Three, seven, ace! Three, seven, queen!'

Lizaveta Ivanovna has married a very pleasant young man; he is in the civil service somewhere and has a good income. He is the son of the old countess's former steward. Lizaveta Ivanovna in her turn is bringing up a poor relative.

And Tomsky, who has been promoted to the rank of captain, has married the Princess Pauline.

October- November 1833

纳塔内尔致洛塔尔

我这么久，这么久没有写信，你们大家一定满怀不安。母亲或许很气愤，克拉拉则可能以为我在这儿生活得穷奢极欲，把她那铭肌镂骨的、天使般的可爱形象给忘得一干二净。但事情并非如此。我每一日、每一刻都念着你们；我可爱的克莱辛[1]，她那亲切的模样不时出现在我甜蜜的梦中，并朝我柔美地微笑，明眸善睐，每当我回到你们身边时，她都那样笑。唉，我多么想给你们写信，但精神上撕裂般的情绪一直使我心烦意乱！有什么可怕的不祥之物闯进了我的生活！令人毛骨悚然的厄运威胁着我，对它的不祥预感如阴云般笼罩在我的头顶，阻隔了每一束宜人美好的阳光。

我应该告诉你，我都遭遇了什么。我很清楚我必须这么做，然而只要我一琢磨这事，我就会禁不住发疯似的大笑。唉，我心爱的洛塔尔！我究竟该如何讲述，才让你多少能够感同身受：几日之前发生在我身上的事情，当真会像敌人一般摧毁我的生活！要是你在这儿，你就能亲眼目睹，但现在你肯定把我当作一个发了疯、见了鬼的人。简而言之，发生在我身上的怪事——我竭力摆脱它所带来的致命影响，但只是徒劳——并非别的，而是这么一回事：几天前，也就是十月三十日的中午十二点，一个卖天气瓶[2]的小贩走进我的房间，朝我兜售他的商品。我什么也没买，还威胁要把他从楼梯上扔下去，但他倒自己走下去了。

你或许会猜，我之所以认为这倒霉小贩会与我作对，是因为这出事件与我的一些个人经历有关，它们曾深深地影响了我的生活。事实也的确如此。我得尽全力使自己镇定下来，才能心平气和、耐心地向你讲述我的许多童年经历，这样就能使一切都化作清楚明晰的画面，浮现在你活跃的脑海中了。在我想要开口的这当儿，我听见你笑了，而克拉拉则说：“这实在太幼稚了！”笑吧，我请求你们，发自内心地取笑我吧！我恳求你们！但是天主做证！我在令人发狂的绝望中毛骨悚然，正像弗朗茨·摩尔乞求丹尼尔[3]那样乞求你们取笑我。现在说正事吧！

由于父亲工作繁忙，除了午餐时间外，我和我的兄弟姐妹们整日都不太能见到他。按老规矩，晚饭一般在七点端上餐桌，饭后我们所有人——母亲与我们——便到父亲的书房里去，围坐在一张圆桌旁。父亲一边抽着烟，一边喝着一大杯啤酒。他常常给我们讲一些奇妙的故事，讲得那样起劲，以至他的烟斗老是熄灭，我便把引火纸递给他，将烟斗重新点燃，这曾是我的一大乐趣。然而很多时候他只会丢给我们一些绘本，自己沉默而僵直地坐在沙发椅上吞云吐雾，于是我们所有人都会陷进烟雾中。在那样的夜里，母亲总是很悲伤；时钟刚敲过九点，她便说：“好了，孩子们！上床去吧！上床去吧！沙人来了，我已经察觉到了。”而我每一次都真的听见有谁迈着沉重的步伐缓缓爬上楼梯，发出沉闷的嗒嗒声，那想必就是沙人了。有一次我感觉那沉闷的脚步声格外恐怖，便在母亲带我们离开时问她：“哎，妈妈！那总是把我们从父亲身边赶走的可恶沙人究竟是谁呀？他到底长什么样？”“没有什么沙人，我亲爱的孩子，”母亲回答道，“我说沙人来了，只是想说你们困到连眼睛都睁不开，就好像眼里被人撒了沙子一样。”

母亲的回答并未使我满意，我稚气的心里清晰地浮现出这样一个想法：母亲只是担心我们被沙人吓着，才否定他的存在。我可是一直能听见他走上楼梯的。我满怀好奇，想更近一步了解沙人，还有他与我们这些小孩子的关系。终于我去询问了那个照料我小妹妹的老婆子：“沙人究竟是什么人呢？”

“哎，小纳塔内尔，”她回答，“你还不知道吗，那是一个邪恶的家伙，如果有孩子不肯上床睡觉，他就找到他们，往他们眼里撒一把沙子，让充血的眼睛从脑袋上掉出来。他把这些眼睛扔进袋子，在夜半时像喂鸟那样喂给他自己的小孩儿，沙人的小孩儿们坐在巢里，有猫头鹰嘴一般尖尖的喙，这样他们就能叼走不听话的孩子们的眼睛。”

我于是在脑海里为残暴的沙人描绘出阴森的肖像。而每当沉闷的脚步声在夜里传来时，恐怖与惊惧总是令我浑身哆嗦。对此，母亲能从我口中问出的，除了一句抽噎的“是沙人！是沙人！”外，再无其他。然后我便奔进卧室，整晚都因沙人的可怕模样而备受煎熬。

后来我长得足够大了，也看透老婆子所告诉我的——沙人，以及夜半时分他那些待在巢里的孩子——大概并不完全属实。尽管如此，沙人于我而言仍然是可怕的鬼怪。每当听见他不光爬上楼梯，还猛地闯入我父亲的房间时，恐惧便会攫住我。有时沙人很久不来，之后他又一次次来得更加频繁。这样持续了好些年，我却仍然无法对这阴森的怪物习以为常，沙人的骇人形象在我心中从未淡化。

我花越来越多的时间与精力去想象沙人与父亲的关系，无法战胜的胆怯使我不敢开口询问父亲，于是我打算自己去探寻那秘密，去见传说中的沙人。几年来，对沙人的兴趣在我心中变得愈加强烈。沙人使我对一切奇妙探险之事都格外着迷，这些东西本来就容易引发孩子的兴趣。我最爱听或读有关科博尔特[4]、女巫与拇指人[5]的惊悚故事；但在这些惊悚故事中，沙人永远是我的最爱，我在桌上、柜子上与墙面上用粉笔和煤块画满了他那最为古怪、最为可恶的模样。

我满十岁的时候，母亲让我从孩子们的卧房搬到另一间小室，它与父亲的房间在同一条走廊上，并且相距不远。每当钟声敲响九下，屋里传出那个陌生人的声音时，我们还是不得不尽快离开。我在自己的小室里听见沙人走进父亲的房间，不久后便觉得有一股香气在整个家里弥散开来，它闻着奇怪却又美妙。随着好奇心的累积，我的勇气也不断增加了——不管通过什么方式，我都要认识沙人。我常在母亲经过房门后悄悄溜出房间，来到走廊上，但我从没偷听到一丝一毫，因为每当我赶到自认为可以窥见沙人的位置上时，他都早已进门去了。无法克制的渴望驱使着我，我终于下定决心要藏在父亲的房间里，并在那儿等候沙人。

一个晚上，父亲的沉默与母亲的忧伤使我意识到沙人即将到来，我便借口自己太过困倦，在九点之前就离开了房间，并躲在紧挨房门的一个藏身之处。家里的大门嘎吱作响，缓慢而沉重的脚步声隆隆地穿过走廊，靠近了楼梯。母亲带着我的兄弟姐妹们急匆匆地从我躲藏的地方经过。悄悄地——悄悄地，我打开了父亲的房门。他背对着门，像往常一样沉默而僵直地坐在那儿。他没有发现我，我便迅速溜了进去，躲在窗帘后；窗帘掩着一个刚好挨着门的衣柜，它敞开着，里面挂着父亲的衣物。

近了，隆隆的脚步声愈加近了，他在房门外发出奇怪的呼哧声、擦刮声与嗡嗡声。恐惧与期待让我心若擂鼓，紧挨房门的地方传来尖锐的脚步声，门把被粗暴地扭动，门嘎吱一声猛地弹开了！我竭力鼓起勇气，小心翼翼地向外窥去。房间中央，沙人立在父亲面前，明亮的灯光在他脸上燃烧！沙人，那可怕的沙人，是那个有时会与我们共进午餐的老律师科佩留斯！

正因那阴森、恐怖至极的形象是这个科佩留斯，我心中的恐惧更深了。试想一个高个儿、宽肩的男人，有一个奇形怪状的胖脑袋，一张黄蜡石般的脸庞与一双浓密的灰眉毛，眉毛下面一对绿色猫眼尖锐地闪烁着，嘴唇之上则是一只硕大而牢固的鼻子。他那歪斜的嘴常常露出阴险扭曲的笑容，接着脸上的暗红色斑点便清晰可见，他咬紧的齿间也传出奇怪的嘶嘶声。

科佩留斯总是穿着一件裁剪过时的暗灰色外套，还有同样款式的背心和裤子，脚上搭配的却是黑色长袜和带有小搭扣的鞋子。他的小假发几乎遮不住头盖骨，卷发高高地贴在又大又红的耳朵上面，宽大密实的发髻从脖颈处伸出来，露出了用来固定衬衫领子的银色扣子。他的整个模样既令人生厌，又叫人恐惧；但最惹我们孩子厌恶的，还是他那一双指节凸出、毛茸茸的手，只要是他用这双手碰过的东西，我们就都不想要了。他发觉了这点，便以这样或那样的借口去碰这一小块糕点，或那一个香甜的水果。它们本是母亲悄悄替我们放在盘子里的。这些甜食本应使我们快乐，他却弄得我们泪盈满眶，出于恶心与厌恶而不愿再享用它们。在假期里，当我们从父亲那儿得到一小杯甜酒后，他也这么做。他会迅速伸手过来，或者直接把玻璃杯送到他青紫的唇边，我们只能抽噎着敢怒不敢言，这种时候他便会发出魔鬼般的笑声。他习惯称我们为小浑蛋。但凡有他在场，我们都一声也不能吭，只在心里诅咒这个丑陋的男人，因为他是我们的敌人，而且存心要糟蹋我们微小的快乐。母亲似乎和我们一样憎恨这个可恶的科佩留斯，因为每当他现身后，她欢欣愉悦的心情就变得悲伤阴郁，原本无拘无束的性格也变得严肃。面对科佩留斯，父亲则自欺欺人，就仿佛科佩留斯是更加高贵的存在，必须容忍他的无礼，而且无论如何，人们都得以良好的心情接纳他。对此父亲从未明说，只通过准备其最喜欢的菜肴，并配以稀罕的好酒来稍作暗示。

而此刻，当我看见那个科佩留斯时，心中油然而生出一个惊悚可怕的想法：除了他以外，其他任何人都不可能是沙人。对我来说，沙人从此不再只是吓人的睡魔——那个会把孩子们的眼珠作为饲料，在夜半时分带去猫头鹰巢里的怪物——并且不只会出现在逗弄小孩儿的无稽之谈中。不！他是一个丑陋的、鬼怪般的恶棍，给所到之处带去悲痛与绝望，带去短暂或永恒的厄运。

我着了魔似的一动不动。我清楚地知道自己会受到严厉的惩罚，但仍冒着被发现的危险站在那儿，把头伸出窗帘偷听。我的父亲郑重接待了科佩留斯。“起来！去干活！”科佩留斯声音嘶哑，呼噜噜地说着，扔开了外套。父亲面色阴沉，默默地脱去睡袍。两人都穿上了黑色长罩衫。我没看见他们是从哪儿拿来这些罩衫的。父亲打开了壁橱的侧门；我却发现，那并非如我一直以为的是个壁橱，而更像个黑色的洞。洞里有一只小炉子，旁边围着各式各样奇异的小工具。哦，上帝啊！当我的父亲朝那炉火弯下腰时，他看上去完全变了样。他柔和正直的面孔仿佛在一阵可怕的、痉挛般的痛楚中扭曲，变成一张丑陋又令人作呕的魔鬼的面庞。他看上去很像那科佩留斯了。而这家伙挥舞着烧红了的钳子，用它从浓烟里取出一些亮闪闪的物质，接着不知疲倦地锻打它们。我觉得似乎能在那四周瞧见人的面孔，但他们却没有眼睛——取而代之的，是丑恶的、深深的黑窟窿。

“眼睛快出来，眼睛快出来！”科佩留斯用沉闷的隆隆声低喊道。

惊恐疯狂地捕获了我，我尖叫起来，从躲藏处跌了出来，摔在地板上。这时科佩留斯一把抓住我：“小浑蛋！小浑蛋！”他龇牙咧嘴地咯咯笑了起来！他用力揪着我，把我往炉子上扔。炉火烧焦了我的头发。“现在我们有眼睛了——眼睛——一对漂亮的孩童眼睛。”科佩留斯悄声说着，从火里抓来一把烧红了的晶粒，打算扔进我的眼睛里。

这时我父亲恳求地抬高了双手，喊道：“大师！大师！放过我的纳塔内尔的眼睛吧！放过他的眼睛吧！”科佩留斯发出刺耳的笑声，喊道：“那就让这少年保住他的眼睛吧，他会得到教训，他痛哭的声音要传遍全世界。但现在我们得好好观察手与脚的运动机制。”这么说着，他粗暴地抓着我，以至关节都咔咔作响；并拧过我的手足，将它们一会儿这么摆，一会儿那么摆。“它们怎么放都不对！还是以前那样好！上年纪的人懂这个！”科佩留斯嘶嘶地轻声说道。我身边的一切都变得黑暗阴森，一阵突如其来的痉挛掠过神经与四肢百骸——我什么也感受不到了。

柔和、温暖的气息拂过我的脸庞，我从死一般的沉睡中惊醒，见母亲朝我俯下身来。“沙人还在吗？”我结结巴巴地问。“不，我亲爱的孩子，他老早老早就走了，他不会再伤害你了！”母亲这么说着，亲昵地拥吻她失而复得的宝贝。

我何必要使你厌烦呢，我心爱的洛塔尔！我何必这样事无巨细地叙述，何况还有那么多没讲？够了！我在偷听的时候被发现了，还被科佩留斯残忍地对待。恐惧与惊吓使我发起高烧，我在床上躺了好几周。“沙人还在吗？”这是我说的第一句神智清醒的话，也象征着我的康复与救赎。我要向你讲述的，只剩下我少年时期最骇人的时刻；然后你就会相信，并非因为我的眼睛出了毛病，才使得一切在我眼里都暗淡无光，而是阴暗的厄运在我人生的天空中投下了一片晦暗不清的阴翳，我或许只能以死将其粉碎。

科佩留斯不再出现了，据说他离开了这座城市。

那之后过去了约莫一年，一天晚上我们仍按老规矩围坐在圆桌旁，父亲兴致勃勃地讲述了他年轻时旅途中的许多趣事。当时钟敲响九点的时候，我们听见门的枢轴突然嘎吱作响，铁一般沉重的脚步声隆隆地穿过门廊，走上楼梯。“是科佩留斯。”母亲面色惨白地说。“对！……是科佩留斯。”父亲用虚弱的、断断续续的声音重复道。“但是孩子他爸，孩子他爸！”母亲的泪涌出了眼眶，她叫道，“非得这样不可吗？”“最后一次了！”父亲回答，“这是他最后一次来找我，我向你保证。走吧，带着孩子们走！……走吧……上床去！晚安！”

我仿佛被压进了坚硬冰冷的岩石里——我的呼吸停滞了！我站着一动不动，这时母亲抓过我的胳膊：“来吧，纳塔内尔，快过来！”我被她带走了，带进自己的小室。“放心，放心，躺上床去！睡吧，睡吧。”母亲离开时说道。但不可名状的恐惧与不安在心里折磨着我，让我根本无法合上眼睑。那可恨又可怕的科佩留斯就站在我跟前，他目光如炬，恶毒地嘲笑我，我竭力想摆脱他的幻影，但只是徒劳。

那或许已是午夜时分，忽然一声骇人的巨响传来，就跟一颗炮弹发射了似的。整座房子都轰隆作响，我的门前掠过一阵嘎吱声与沙沙声，紧跟着房屋大门嘭的一声关上了。“那是科佩留斯！”我惊恐地喊道，从床上一跃而起。此时传来刺耳又绝望的惨叫，我横冲直撞地奔向父亲的房间。门敞开着，令人窒息的浓烟迎面席卷而来，女佣的尖叫声传来：“唉呀，先生他……先生他！”

在蒸汽滚滚的炉子前，我的父亲倒在地板上。他已经死了，一张脸被烧得焦黑变形，很是丑陋。我的姐妹们围在他身旁哀号痛哭，而母亲晕倒在一旁！“科佩留斯，该死的撒旦，是你杀害了父亲！”我大喊一声，便失去了意识。

两天过后，父亲入了棺。那时他的面目又重新变得温柔和蔼了，就像活着时那样。我在心中欣慰地想，这说明他与科佩留斯那个魔鬼签订的契约没有使他陷入永恒的堕落。

爆炸惊醒了邻居，这起事故惹得谣言四起，还引得当局介入——他们要传唤科佩留斯并追究他的责任，但他却消失得无影无踪。

若我现在告诉你——我心爱的朋友——那个卖天气瓶的小贩正是可恶的科佩留斯，那么你便不会奇怪，为什么我认为这个敌人的出现将招致大难了。他的穿着打扮虽变了样，但科佩留斯的身形与面貌都深深地烙在了我的心中，绝无可能出错。此外，科佩留斯甚至未曾改过名字。就我所知，他在这儿假装成一个皮埃蒙特[6]来的机械师，并自称吉塞普·科波拉。

我决意与他抗争，无论发生什么，我都要为父亲之死复仇。

请千万别告诉母亲这丑陋的恶魔出现了。替我向亲爱的、可爱的克拉拉问好，我心绪平静些后再给她写信。祝好。

[1]克拉拉的昵称。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2]天气瓶（wetterglas），又称风暴瓶，是欧洲18世纪至19世纪用于天气预报的工具。密闭的玻璃容器中，装入含数种化学物质的透明溶液。根据外界温度、天气的改变，瓶内会展现出不同形态的结晶，预报天气的变化。近代天气瓶已不用作天气预报的工具，而转变为一种趣味性的科学装饰。

[3]弗朗茨·摩尔（Franz Moor）与丹尼尔（Daniel）两个人物源自席勒《强盗》。弗朗茨是主人公卡尔的弟弟，为了篡夺遗产而设计陷害其兄，使卡尔被逐出家门。卡尔成为强盗后，某次乔装打扮混入了弗朗茨的城堡，却被弗朗茨识破。因害怕卡尔带来不利，惊恐万分的弗朗茨恳求仆人丹尼尔杀害卡尔，但后者并未照做。

[4]科博尔特，德语区神话传说中的一种精灵，它寄居于人类家中并守护这个家，偶尔也会对主人做些无伤大雅的恶作剧。

[5]拇指人，源自德语区童话，即身量不超过拇指大小的人，著名童话《拇指姑娘》便是其衍生作品。

[6]意大利西北部的一个区，首府为都灵。

克拉拉致纳塔内尔

你确实很久不曾写信给我了，但即便如此我也相信，你仍然想着我念着我。你明明打算把上一封信寄给我的兄弟洛塔尔，却在信封上写了我的名字，而不是他的，那么你想必是热切地惦记着我了。我愉快地拆了信，直到读到“唉，我心爱的洛塔尔”时才意识到这个错误。我本不该再接着读下去，而应当把信交给我的兄弟。

就像你以前时不时孩子气地打趣我、指责我的那样，我具备女性所特有的好沉思的宁静心性。哪怕房屋有坍塌的危险，在急忙逃离之前，我也会迅速抚平窗帘上那一道难看的褶皱——我就是这样的女人。正因如此，我不能不承认，你这封信的开头是那样深深震撼了我，我差点儿喘不过气，眼前金星直冒。

唉，我心爱的纳塔内尔！怎么会有这样的骇人之物闯入你的生活！一想到要与你分开，再也见不到你，我的胸膛就仿佛被一把烧红的匕首刺穿了。我把信读了又读！那可恶的科佩留斯，你对他的描述真叫人毛骨悚然。直到现在我才知晓，你那位年迈的好父亲竟以这般骇人而暴力的方式死去了。在我把本属于兄弟洛塔尔的信交给他后，他竭力使我恢复平静，然而收效甚微。那个致命的天气瓶小贩吉塞普·科波拉阴魂不散地紧跟着我，我甚至羞于承认，他以各种古怪的模样出现在我的梦中，摧毁了我平时健康安稳的睡眠。但是很快，在第二天时我的感受就截然不同了。我亲爱的，尽管知道你出奇地预感到科佩留斯会对你作恶，我却仍一如既往地欢欣愉悦、无拘无束——如果洛塔尔告诉你这些，你可别生我的气。

我得向你坦承，我认为你所讲述的所有恐怖之事都只发生在你的想象中，它们与真实的外部世界恐怕少有关联。那老科佩留斯确实很令人讨厌，但只是因为他憎恨小孩儿，你们这些孩子才发自内心地怕他。

在你稚气的脑海里，当然会把童话里可怕的沙人同老科佩留斯联系起来，因为就算你不相信沙人，科佩留斯在你眼中也是一个鬼怪般的坏蛋，对小孩子尤其危险。你父亲在夜里所做的骇人勾当或许不过是暗地里进行的炼金实验，你的母亲当然会心怀不满，因为炼金会挥霍掉许多钱财。此外，父亲的心智完全被那骗人的渴望蒙蔽了，一心以为自己能得到更高的智慧，却因此疏远了家人——这也是那种炼金作坊里常会出现的情况。你父亲的死亡很可能归咎于他自己的不小心，而科佩留斯对此并无责任。你相信吗，我昨天甚至询问了隔壁那位经验颇丰的药剂师：“进行化学实验时，这种致命的爆炸是否可能在一眨眼间就发生？”他答道：“哎，当然了。”他还以特有的风格向我详尽又拖沓地描述它如何发生，其间提到了好些听起来稀奇古怪的名字，我一个也没记住。

现在你可能对你的克拉拉心存不满了。你会说：“实际上，奥秘常常伸出隐形的双臂拥抱世人，但没有任何一丝奥秘的光芒能穿透这般冷漠的想法；世人仅仅看见缤纷多彩的表象世界就觉得开心，就像幼稚的儿童会为了镀金的水果而开心，却浑然不知其中暗藏致命的毒药。”

唉，我心爱的纳塔内尔！你难道不相信，就算是开朗快活、无拘无束又无忧无虑的人，也会对那黑暗力量心中有数，也知道它是我们的敌人，并能导致我们自我毁灭？但请原谅，我这样一个头脑简单的小姑娘，也要斗胆试着告诉你我对这场内心之战的看法。也许直到最后我也做不到措辞得当，但就算你会取笑我，那也不是因为我的想法愚蠢，而是因为我表达得如此笨拙。

假设存在这样的黑暗力量，它就像我们的敌人，阴险狡诈地在我们心中埋下一根线，用它来紧紧束缚我们，操纵我们走上一条危险堕落的道路，而这样的道路我们原本是绝不会踏上的。如果真的存在这样的力量，那么它必然会在我们心中把自己塑造成与我们相仿的模样。也就是说，它会成为我们自身。因为唯有如此，我们才会相信它，并如它所愿在心里为它腾出一块地方，使它能够进行那些隐秘的勾当。但假使我们始终拥有足够坚强的意志，能够认清那外来的邪恶影响，并通过积极地生活来加强这种意志，同时遵循我们的个人偏好与职业所指引的道路，坚定不移地笃定前行，那么这阴森可怖的力量便只能徒劳地追逐我们的虚假镜像，直至消亡。

洛塔尔补充说，这黑暗的精神力量常会化装为我们在外部世界里所遇到的阻碍，一旦我们在自己心中臣服于它，那么它必然会以这副模样侵入我们的内心。这样一来，我们就会精神错乱，在玄之又玄的错觉中误以为那黑暗力量的声音是我们自己的声音。它是我们自身的鬼影，它与我们的自我相仿，并深刻地影响我们的内心，使我们或堕入深渊或飘飘欲仙。

我心爱的纳塔内尔！你想必察觉到，我与我的兄弟洛塔尔确确实实讨论过那黑暗的强大力量，在我费尽心思写下这些重要内容后，它们在我心中变得更深刻且条理清晰了。洛塔尔最后的话我并没有完全理解，我只能猜测他的意思，但尽管如此，我仍认为这些看法都十分正确。我请求你，别再揣测那个丑陋的律师科佩留斯，或是兜售天气瓶的吉塞普·科波拉了，他们都是那黑暗力量的化装，你要坚信它们无法对你做什么；只有当你相信它们那满怀敌意的强大力量时，它们才会真正危害到你。别再让信中的每一行都诉说你心底的混乱，别再让我从灵魂最深处为你的处境感到痛心。真的，我可能会拿那个是沙人的律师与天气瓶小贩科佩留斯来寻开心。你要开朗些，开朗些！我已决定前往你身旁，就像你的守护精灵一样。如果丑恶的科波拉企图扰人清梦，我就要开怀大笑，将他驱赶。我毫不畏惧他和他那粗暴讨厌的拳头，无论他是律师还是沙人，他都糟蹋不了我的甜食，更伤不了我的眼睛。

永远永远，我心爱的纳塔内尔。

纳塔内尔致洛塔尔

由于我的马虎大意，克拉拉前阵子收到了本应给你的信，还把它读完了，这让我很不愉快。她写来一封内涵深刻的哲学信件，在其中详尽地证明了科佩留斯与科波拉只存在于我的内心，是我自身的鬼影；只要我认清这点，它即刻就会化为齑粉。说实话，她那含笑又明亮的双眼常常如孩童眸子一般甜美梦幻，这样一双眼中却闪烁出如此理智杰出的思想之光，像个文科硕士一样，真令人难以置信。你们谈到了我，她还引用了你的话，或许你给她读了些逻辑学的学术著作，好让她明察明辨吧。算了！

另外，或许那天气瓶小贩吉塞普·科波拉确实不是老律师科佩留斯。我是从一位最近才来到这里的物理学教授那儿听说的，这个教授同那个出名的自然研究者一样，名叫斯帕兰扎尼[7]，来自意大利，并且是学术圈的一分子。他认识那个科波拉已经好几年了。另外，从科波拉的口音也能听出，他确实来自皮埃蒙特。科佩留斯倒是个德国人，不过我认为他对此撒了谎。我心中的大石仍未落地。你和克拉拉，你们到底还是把我当成了一个阴郁的幻想家，可是科佩留斯那张该死的脸实在给我留下了太深的印象，我无法摆脱它。斯帕兰扎尼说科波拉已经离开了这座城市，这让我挺开心的。

这位教授也是个怪人。他是个矮小的、圆滚滚的男人，颧骨突出的脸上，有着精致的鼻子、噘起来的厚嘴唇和一对目光刺人的小眼睛。或许这么形容更好：要是你在任意一个柏林口袋日历上见到乔多维茨基[8]画的卡廖斯特罗[9]，你就是见到了斯帕兰扎尼——他看上去就是那副模样。

不久前有一次，我上楼梯的时候发现平日里都严严实实合着的窗帘被拉到了一旁，缝隙中露出了挡在窗帘后的一扇玻璃门。就连我自己也不知道，我怎么就好奇地瞥了过去。那房间里，一名女郎坐在一张小桌前，她出落得高挑纤瘦，但身材却相当匀称，且衣着华贵。她的手臂搭在桌上，双手交叠。她面对着门，因此她那天使般美丽的面庞尽收眼底。她看上去并没有察觉到我，而且目光有点儿呆滞——我几乎可以这么说：就好像根本没有视力一样。在我看来，她仿佛在睁着眼睛睡觉。我有点儿毛骨悚然，所以快速地悄悄溜进了一旁的大堂里。后来我听说，我所见到的那个人是斯帕兰扎尼的女儿奥林匹娅。他用特殊而又过分的方式把她关了起来，以至没有任何人能靠近她。正因如此，她最终变得似乎痴呆，或者有了其他毛病。

但是，我干吗要告诉你这些呢？我原本可以对你口述得更好、更详细，你要知道，十四天后我就会回到你们身边了。我必须再次见到我亲爱的、可爱的天使——我的克拉拉，然后我的恶劣情绪就会烟消云散。在读过那封理智得过分的信后，我险些被这些恶劣情绪（我必须承认）淹没。因此我今天也不给她写信了。

千万次祝福。

再也找不到比这更离奇、更奇妙的见闻了。这便是发生在我可怜的朋友——年轻的大学生纳塔内尔——身上的故事，这故事才刚开头，而我要接着为你讲述。好意的读者！最富同情心的人啊，你可曾有过这般体验：有什么占据了你的胸腔、心灵与脑海，把其他一切思绪都排挤了出去？它们在你的心里翻滚蒸煮，直到那份炽热触及沸点，于是你体内热血奔涌，双颊变得绯红。你的目光是那么古怪，就仿佛它在空荡荡的房间内捕捉到了一个人影，而其他所有人却都对其视而不见；你的话语最终消融于一声晦暗的喟叹。这时你的朋友则询问你：“您怎么了，尊敬的人？您遇上什么事了，亲爱的朋友？”

你渴望吐露你脑海中的画面，运用所有炽烈的色彩与光影去描绘它，然而光是为开头找到合适的词句就已经使你精疲力竭。但你感到必须把那奇妙壮丽的、骇人听闻的、引人入胜的、惊悚恐怖的——把要诉说的一切都浓缩于你吐出的第一个词中，就像闪电那样在一瞬击中万物。然而任何能说出口的词在你眼里都黯然失色，如死一般冰冷僵硬。你找啊找啊，说得断断续续、吞吞吐吐；你的朋友们又提出许多理智的问题，它们就如同凛冽的寒风直吹进你的心房，冷却了那滚烫的热流。或者，你可以像个不拘一格的画家，仅凭大胆奔放的寥寥几笔便描绘出心中画面的轮廓，接着轻轻松松地为其增添愈加鲜艳的色彩，用栩栩如生的各式形象来吸引你的朋友们。于是他们便能目睹，你——你自己正是这画面的中心——如何呈现出了自己的心中所想！

而我，好意的读者！我必须向你坦白，从未有人向我询问过年轻的纳塔内尔的故事。你或许知道，我也属于作家这一类古怪的人。正如我之前所描述的那样，这些人心里藏着故事，只要有谁——不管是他们身边的人，还是来自世界各地的人——来到他们身边，并且问：“这到底是怎么回事？您给我讲讲吧，亲爱的？”他们就会兴高采烈。这份强烈的倾诉欲也驱使我对你讲述纳塔内尔那不幸的一生。它那么奇妙又古怪，占据了我的整颗心灵。但正因如此，也因为我必须使你——我的读者——能够承受这并非微不足道的奇妙故事，我才绞尽脑汁，要给纳塔内尔的故事一个意味深长、与众不同且动人的开头：“从前”——这是所有小说最漂亮的开头，不过太生硬了！“在一座名为S的偏远小城里住着……”——好些了，至少在一点点向着高潮推进。或者直接从故事中间切入：“‘让他见鬼去吧！’大学生纳塔内尔喊道，疯狂的眼神中写着暴怒与惊恐，当那卖天气瓶的吉塞普·科波拉……”说实话，这些句子我都已经写下来了，却又觉得能从“大学生纳塔内尔那疯狂的眼神”里嗅出几分滑稽，但这绝不是一个滑稽的故事。我的脑海中压根没有浮现出什么词句能多多少少反映我心中的画面，并重现其光彩与色泽。我决定索性不开这个头了。

拿去，好意的读者！拿走这三封信，它们是朋友洛塔尔友好地分享与我的。有了这些信，你便能窥见那画面——我竭力想通过叙述来为其增添色彩——的轮廓。或许我能像一位优秀的肖像画家那样去呈现画面中的形象，使它们贴近原型，这样就算你未曾见过真人，也会觉得这个人物鲜活得仿佛就在眼前。哦，我的读者！也许你就会相信，没有什么会比真实的生活更加神奇美妙，而诗人们只能利用一面打磨得暗淡无光的镜子，照出生活的影子罢了。

为了让读者们深入了解故事前情，除了这些信件外，还有一些内容需要补充：纳塔内尔的父亲死后不久，克拉拉与洛塔尔——他们本是纳塔内尔一位远亲的孩子，后来这位远亲也亡故了，他们就成了孤儿-便被纳塔内尔的母亲收留在了家中。克拉拉与纳塔内尔互相怀有强烈的好感，这世上没人能够反对这份感情，因此在纳塔内尔离开家乡前往G市念大学时，他们便订婚了。写最后一封信时，他仍在G市，是著名的物理学教授斯帕兰扎尼的学生。

现在我能放心地继续讲述这个故事了。然而眼下，克拉拉的形象又那么活灵活现地出现在我眼前，叫我没法移开目光。当她亲切又满含笑意地瞧着我时，这种情况便总是发生。从主流审美观来看，克拉拉绝不漂亮。然而，建筑师们会称赞她那匀称曼妙的身段；画家们则会认为她颈部、肩膀与胸脯的线条都那么天真纯洁，会爱上她那不逊于抹大拉的玛利亚[10]的秀美金发，并就巴托尼[11]的色彩大侃特侃。他们其中一位，一个真正的幻想家，又别出心裁地把克拉拉那双眼睛比作雷斯达尔[12]画中的大海，倒映着如洗的湛蓝碧空，以及森林与鲜花盛放的原野，映照着自然景观之丰美与明艳多彩的勃勃生机。诗人与大师们则更进一步，感叹道：“这是怎样的汪洋，这是怎样的明镜啊！只要我们端详这名少女，看见她的目光向我们闪烁，天堂般美妙的音乐与歌声便会笼罩我们。这乐音涌入我们的心房，使一切复苏并活跃起来。我们也斗胆在克拉拉面前像鸟儿那般啁啾歌唱，以为自己唱的是首真正的歌谣，然而实则不过是由单调无聊的声响胡乱组成的产物。但克拉拉唇角露出的美好微笑却告诉我们，就算我们无法咏唱出什么高明的内容，也并非我们的过错。”

正是如此。克拉拉如同无忧无虑、无拘无束的孩子，有着天马行空的想象力，同时也有着女性深切柔和的心性，以及明晰敏锐的睿智。任何神秘的把戏都无法糊弄她；尽管她天性沉默且从不健谈，但无论是她那明亮的目光，还是那略带嘲讽的柔和微笑，都无不在诉说：“亲爱的朋友啊！你们怎么会以为，我会觉得你们口中那稍纵即逝的幻影都活灵活现，甚至把它信以为真？”许多人因此责备她冷漠无情，平淡乏味；但另外一些人则能更清楚深刻地认识生活——其中最甚者莫过于纳塔内尔，他总是快活有力地徜徉于科学与艺术之中——从而热烈地爱上这样一位感情丰富、通情达理、如孩子般天真的少女。

克拉拉全身心地依赖着自己的爱人，与后者的分别是她人生中出现的第一道阴霾。而正如纳塔内尔在信中告诉洛塔尔的那样，当他真正回到家乡，踏入母亲的房间时，她是怀着怎样的惊喜飞奔着投入了他的怀抱啊！如他所料，在重新见到克拉拉的那一瞬间，无论是律师科佩留斯，抑或是克拉拉那封过于理性的信件给他带来的不快，都统统在他的脑海中烟消云散了。

但纳塔内尔对朋友洛塔尔说的并没有错：可恶的天气瓶小贩科波拉的出现确实危及了他的生活。所有人都察觉到了这一点，因为纳塔内尔在回来的第一天就仿佛完全变了一个人。他沉浸在阴郁的幻想中，行为举止都古怪得令人无法适应。一切的一切，甚至就连生活本身，于他而言都成了华胥一梦。他越来越频繁地提到，每个人都误以为自己是自由的，实际上却陷入了残酷的游戏，不过是那黑暗力量手中的一枚棋子罢了；人们徒劳地反抗，终究也只能屈服于命运的安排。对此他谈得非常深入，并声称如果以为艺术与科学创作皆是个人发挥主观能动性的结果，那么就太愚蠢了，因为唯有灵感能使人创作，而这灵感并非源自我们的内心，而是来自我们身外的更高法则。

理智的克拉拉极其反感这些神秘的白日梦，然而她的反驳似乎也只是徒劳。纳塔内尔力图证明科佩留斯确实是那邪恶势力，早在他躲在窗帘后偷听时，它便伸出自己的魔爪攫住了他，而且这可恶的魔鬼还将用恐怖的手段摧毁他的爱情，他的幸福。每当这时，克拉拉都会十分严肃地回应：“是啊，纳塔内尔！你是对的，科佩留斯是那邪恶势力，是一股魔鬼般的力量。显而易见，它侵入生活并造成了可怕的后果，但这也只是因为你没有把他逐出脑海与内心。只要你仍对他深信不疑，那么他就是真的，还会对你施加影响；只有你的相信才是他的力量。”

纳塔内尔被彻底激怒了，因为克拉拉认定魔鬼只存在于他的内心。他想搬出自己那一整套关于魔鬼与黑暗力量的神秘学说，克拉拉却不悦地打断他，并插嘴说些鸡毛蒜皮、无关紧要的事情。纳塔内尔因此更加愤怒了。他明白冷漠保守的人无法领会如此艰深的奥秘，却没清楚地意识到自己其实也把克拉拉归为了这一类人，因此仍锲而不舍地试图向她透露这些奥秘。

清晨克拉拉正忙着准备早餐的时候，他便站在她身旁，为她朗读各式各样的神秘学书籍，直到克拉拉恳求道：“但是亲爱的纳塔内尔，如果我说你是那个糟蹋我咖啡的邪恶势力呢？因为倘若如你所愿，我放下手头的所有事情，在你朗读的时候注视着你的眼睛，那么我的咖啡便会烧煳，你们可就都没有早饭吃了！”

纳塔内尔把书啪地一合，闷闷不乐地跑回他的房间去了。从前他尤其善于撰写生动优美的故事，而克拉拉则会津津有味地聆听。然而现在他的文章却变得阴沉了，内容莫名其妙、乱七八糟。尽管克拉拉体贴地缄口不言，他还是能察觉到，她很难对这些作品做出积极的评价。对克拉拉来说，没有什么比沉闷无聊更致命了，她的每一句话和每个眼神都诉说着精神上无法抵挡的睡意——纳塔内尔的文章其实无聊透顶。克拉拉那冷漠平淡的思维使纳塔内尔愈感不悦。至于他那黑暗晦涩、沉闷无聊的神秘学，克拉拉也无法克制自己对它们的厌烦。久而久之，尽管他们自己尚未察觉，但他们的两颗心已然渐行渐远。

纳塔内尔必须承认，科佩留斯的模样已在他的幻想中渐渐苍白。他想让科佩留斯这骇人的睡魔在自己的作品中登场，但常常要煞费苦心才能将其渲染得栩栩如生。后来他决定作一首诗，主题便是他那不祥的预感：科佩留斯会摧毁他的爱情与幸福。诗中他与克拉拉原本在忠贞的爱情中紧密结合。但之后某天，仿佛一只黑暗的拳头猛地砸进了他们的生活，把他们全部的幸福都彻底捣毁了。最后他们终于站上了婚礼的圣坛，那可怕的科佩留斯却突然出现，挖走了克拉拉那双可爱的眼睛。鲜血淋漓的眼睛掉在纳塔内尔的胸膛上，如同灼热的血红色火星一样燃烧起来。科佩留斯抓住他，把他抛进一个熊熊燃烧的火轮。它如旋涡般快速旋转，翻滚呼号着吞噬了他，并发出一声惊天动地的咆哮。那情形就仿佛飓风狂怒地拍击浪花四起的海面，海浪在暴怒的抗争中涌起，形成白首黑身的庞然大物。在一片隆隆巨响中，他却听见克拉拉的声音传来：“你难道不能看看我吗？科佩留斯骗了你，在你胸口燃烧的并非我的眼睛，而是你自己那几滴炽热的心头血——我的双眼还在，你快看看我啊！”纳塔内尔想：这是克拉拉的声音，我永远属于她。这一想法强劲地穿透了他置身的火轮，漆黑深渊中的巨响变得沉闷，终于渐渐消失。

纳塔内尔看向克拉拉的双眼。然而此时用克拉拉的双眼友好地瞧着他的，却是死神。

纳塔内尔作诗时十分平静，他深陷沉思，对每一行都孜孜不倦地精雕细琢，而且重视韵律规则，不使所有诗行都和谐动听、斐然成章，他便决不罢休。然而当他终于完成诗作并高声朗读时，强烈的恐怖与惊惧却又攫住了他，他大喊起来：“这阴森恐怖的声音是谁的？”但不久后，整首诗在他眼中又成了佳作，他感觉它必能在克拉拉那冷漠的思维中点燃火星，尽管他并不清楚自己究竟为什么要刺激克拉拉，也不清楚用那阴森可怖的内容——它预言了可怕的厄运，这厄运会摧毁他们的爱情——去吓唬她的后果会是什么。

此刻纳塔内尔与克拉拉坐在母亲那小巧的花园中。克拉拉心情十分愉悦，因为纳塔内尔在写诗的三天里都没有再用自己的幻梦或不祥的预感去折磨她，他甚至像从前一样兴致勃勃、绘声绘色地讲起了许多趣事。于是克拉拉说：“现在我熟悉的那个你总算完完全全地回来了，看来你已经见识到，我们怎样驱赶了那丑恶的科佩留斯。”而直到这时，纳塔内尔才想起自己揣在衣兜里的诗，他原本打算朗读它的。于是他立刻抽出那些纸页，并开始诵读。克拉拉以为它一如既往地无聊，想着由他去吧，自己便安安静静地一心做起了手头的针线活儿。然而那诗作所带来的阴霾变得愈渐黑暗，终于她丢下针线，定定地看进纳塔内尔的眼里。他仍一刻不停地念着，心中炽热的感情染红了脸颊，泪珠从他的眼眶中簌簌滚落。他终于念完了，疲惫地沉沉悲叹起来，并握住克拉拉的手，就好像他在绝望的痛苦中崩溃了一般。他呻吟道：“唉！克拉拉……克拉拉！”克拉拉温柔地把他拥入怀中，轻轻地，却缓慢又严肃地说道：“纳塔内尔，我心爱的纳塔内尔！把那愚蠢的……胡言乱语的……疯狂的无稽之谈扔进火里吧。”纳塔内尔这时却愤怒地跳了起来，一把推开克拉拉，喊道：“你这了无生趣的、该死的机器人！”他飞奔着离开了。深受伤害的克拉拉在痛苦中泪如泉涌，大声抽噎起来：“唉，看来他从未爱过我，因为他根本不理解我。”

这时洛塔尔走进凉亭，克拉拉向他诉说了发生的一切。洛塔尔全心全意地爱着自己的妹妹，她的每一句控诉都如火星一般烧进他心中；他对纳塔内尔的胡思乱想早已心怀不满，这份不满被那火星点燃了，终于形成了熊熊燃烧的愤怒。洛塔尔冲向纳塔内尔，严词指责他竟那样荒唐地对待自己心爱的妹妹。怒火中烧的纳塔内尔则同样用狠话回击。他们一个是耽于幻想的愚蠢傻瓜，另一个则是痛苦而平凡的普通人，两人的决斗在所难免。他们决定按当地的传统规矩，在第二天早晨以花剑为武器进行决斗。他们阴沉地、静悄悄地走来走去。克拉拉听说了这场激烈的争吵，也在黎明时分看见击剑师傅带来剑，便猜到将会发什么。在决斗场上，洛塔尔与纳塔内尔面色阴沉，默默脱去外套，眼中燃烧着嗜血好战的光芒，都想把对方击倒在地。这时克拉拉冲进花园，抽泣着大声喊道：“你们这两个可怕的疯子！你们与其互相攻击，倒不如把我击倒好了！倘若我的爱人谋杀了我的哥哥，或是我的哥哥谋杀了我的爱人，我又怎么能继续活在这世上！”

洛塔尔丢下了武器，垂眼沉默地看向地面。而爱情又在纳塔内尔的心中再度掀起撕裂般的痛楚，他想起自己那美好的少年时代，在那些快乐的日子里从可爱的克拉拉那儿获得过怎样的爱意啊。谋杀的武器从他手中落下，他扑倒在克拉拉脚边：“你能原谅我吗，我唯一的、我心爱的克拉拉！……你能原谅我吗，我心爱的哥哥洛塔尔！”洛塔尔被朋友这份沉重的苦痛触动了，他们三人彼此宽恕，不禁潸然泪下、互相拥抱，发誓永远忠诚相爱、绝不分离。

纳塔内尔感到肩上那快要压垮他的重担已然卸下，他似乎已经成功地反抗了笼罩自己的黑暗力量，也彻底挽救了濒临毁灭的自己。他在爱人身边又度过了三天幸福时光，随后便返回G市。他还得在那儿待上一年，但等学成之后，他便能永远留在自己的故乡了。

在纳塔内尔的母亲面前，所有人都绝口不提有关科佩留斯的一切。他们知道，勾起对他的回忆势必会使她陷入惊恐，因为同纳塔内尔一样，她也认为丈夫的死应归罪于科佩留斯。

纳塔内尔返回了自己在G市的住所，却惊愕万分地见它着了火。整幢房子在大火中坍塌了，从堆砌的瓦砾上望去，只剩下隔火墙光秃秃地立着。房屋底层住着一名药剂师，大火毫无疑问是在他的实验室里爆发的，并迅速往楼上蔓延，把整幢房子都点燃了。尽管火势凶猛，纳塔内尔那些强壮勇敢的朋友仍冲进他楼上的房间，把书、手稿与各式仪器及时抢救了出来，又将这些东西都完好无损地转移到另外一幢房内。他们在那儿另寻了一间屋子，纳塔内尔之后便搬了进去。

纳塔内尔自然注意到，如今他正好住在斯帕兰扎尼教授的对面；当他发现自己透过窗子正好能看进奥林匹娅所在的房间时，也没特别惊讶。奥林匹娅一如既往孤零零地坐在那儿。他能清楚地看见她的身形，但那张面庞显得朦胧不清。久而久之，他终于发觉奥林匹娅总保持着同样的姿势，什么也不干，在桌旁一坐就是好几个小时，就像他之前在玻璃门外发现她时那样。但她显然正目不转睛地朝他凝望，而他也不得不承认自己从未见过谁出落得如此美丽。但他心中念着的仍是克拉拉，对生硬呆板的奥林匹娅没什么兴趣；偶尔他会透过窗帘草草地瞥一眼那貌美的雕塑，但也仅此而已。

房门发出一声轻响时，他正给克拉拉写着信。门随即打开了，他发出一声惊呼——科波拉从门后露出那张可恶的脸，正往里看。纳塔内尔内心深处感到一阵地动山摇。但他又想到，斯帕兰扎尼曾告诉他说自己与科波拉是同乡，而且他也对爱人庄重宣誓过，不会再相信沙人科佩留斯，于是他又为自己害臊了，觉得自己简直像个害怕鬼怪的孩子一样。他竭力镇定下来，并尽量平静放松地说道：“我不买天气瓶，亲爱的朋友！您走吧！”

这时，科波拉却整个人踏入房间，宽大的嘴咧出一个丑陋的笑容，一双小眼睛在长长的灰色睫毛下闪烁，目光刺人。他声音沙哑地说：“哎，不要天气瓶，不要天气瓶！……那还有好看的眼镜，好看的眼镜！”纳塔内尔听后惊恐地叫起来：“你这疯子，你怎么还卖眼睛？……眼睛……眼睛？！”但与此同时，科波拉把他所有的天气瓶推到一旁，在宽大的上衣口袋中翻来找去，掏出长柄眼镜与一般样式的眼镜，放在桌上。“喏，喏……这，这架在鼻子上的，这就是我卖的眼镜！好看的眼镜！”说着，他不断地掏出眼镜来，直到它们堆满整个桌面，在桌上奇异地闪闪发光。千百双眼睛眨巴着，拼命地闪烁着，凝望着纳塔内尔。他无法把目光从桌面上移开，而科波拉仍一刻不停地往桌上堆眼镜。无数道冒着火光的目光交织在一起，显得愈加疯狂，它们血红的视线直穿纳塔内尔的胸膛。剧烈的惊恐席卷了他，他叫喊起来：“停下！停下，可怕的家伙！”

他一把抓住科波拉的胳膊，而科波拉依然不停地掏着口袋，往桌上堆眼镜，压根不管整个桌面早已被覆满了。科波拉轻笑起来，嘶哑地说道：“哎呀！您啥也不要……那这儿还有好看的望远镜。”他把所有眼镜拢成一摞收回包内，又从大衣的边袋里掏出一堆大大小小的望远镜。眼镜被收走后，纳塔内尔完全平静了下来。他想起克拉拉，意识到恐怖的鬼魂只会在他的心中出现；而科波拉想必是个非常诚实的机械师和光学器具制造者，不可能是那该死的科佩留斯或鬼魂。此外，科波拉放在桌上的望远镜也没什么特别的，不似眼镜那般诡异，而且总体上来说，它们制作得相当精良。

为了让一切回到正轨，纳塔内尔真的决定向科波拉买些什么了。他拿起一副打造得十分干净透明的口袋望远镜放到眼前，试着望向窗外。他这一生中还从未见过这样的镜片，它能使一切都清晰纯粹地近距离呈现于眼前。不经意间，他望进了斯帕兰扎尼的房间：奥林匹娅坐在那儿，像往常一样挨着小桌，胳膊搭在桌面上，双手交叠。直到现在，纳塔内尔才终于看清她那张美得惊人的脸庞，只是那双眼睛有些古怪，显得呆滞又死气沉沉。奥林匹娅的模样在镜片后变得越来越清晰，与此同时，她的眼中似乎也升起了湿漉漉的月光，就好像她的视觉在这一刻被点燃了似的，那如火的目光逐渐绽放出生机。纳塔内尔完全着了迷，他倚在窗旁，身体越来越往前倾，端详着美若天仙的奥林匹娅。一阵咳嗽声与窸窣声把他从梦中惊醒，科波拉站在他身后，说：“三……三个杜卡特[13]。”

纳塔内尔把他忘得一干二净，他迅速付了钱。“对吧？……好看的镜片，好看的镜片！”科波拉用他那讨厌而嘶哑的声音问道，露出一个阴森的微笑。“对，对，对！”纳塔内尔不耐烦地回答道。“再见[14]，亲爱的朋友！”科波拉说着，又古怪地斜乜了纳塔内尔几眼，这才离开房间。纳塔内尔听见他大笑着走下楼梯。“好吧，”他说，“这家伙嘲笑我，因为我为这副小望远镜付了太高的价钱，太高的价钱！”他这么低声说着，心中蓦地感到一阵恐惧袭来，房间里响起一声沉重的、死一般的叹息，他的呼吸凝滞了——他发觉，那声叹息是他自己发出的。“克拉拉，”他自言自语道，“她把我视作一个乏味无聊的、见了鬼的人，或许她是对的。但这太滑稽了——不，也许比滑稽更甚。我为那望远镜向科波拉支付了太高的价钱，这愚蠢的想法竟会使我这么害怕，而我全然不知为何。”

这会儿他坐下来，想写完给克拉拉的信，但投向窗外的一瞥又让他坚信奥林匹娅仍坐在那儿。就在那一瞬间，他不能自已地一跃而起，抓起科波拉的望远镜望向奥林匹娅。他无法从她那诱人的外表上移开视线，直到他的朋友兼兄弟齐格蒙德叫他去斯帕兰扎尼教授那儿开会。

之后的两天里，那间令人窒息的房间都窗帘紧闭。尽管他几乎从未离开过窗边，而且一刻不停地透过科波拉的望远镜瞧着，却没怎么见到房间里的奥林匹娅。到第三天，连整扇窗户都被遮挡了。如火的爱欲与渴望驱使他绝望地冲出大门——奥林匹娅的模样在他眼前游荡，一会儿出现在半空中，一会儿又从灌木丛里走出来，或伫立于明亮的溪流，用闪闪熠熠的大眼睛瞧着他。

克拉拉在他心中被抹得一干二净，除了奥林匹娅，他什么都不去想了。他带着哭腔高声控诉道：“唉！你，我高高在上的、美若天仙的爱人。既然你向我显身，为何又转瞬即逝，留我一人度过这幽暗绝望的漫漫长夜？”

在他打算回到自己的住处时，斯帕兰扎尼家中的嘈杂吸引了他的注意。所有的门都敞着，各式各样的器具被搬进屋内；一楼的窗户也开着，女佣们举着鸡毛掸子忙里忙外，造桌的木匠与糊裱匠们在室内弄出叮铃咣啷的敲击声。纳塔内尔惊讶地伫立在街上。这时齐格蒙德笑着朝他走来，问他：“哎，你怎么看我们的老斯帕兰扎尼？”

纳塔内尔断言他没有任何可说的，因为他对教授几乎一无所知。只是这座静谧阴森的房子里竟传来如此巨大的动静，进行着这样不同寻常的活动，着实令他吃惊。齐格蒙德于是告诉他，斯帕兰扎尼计划于明日举行一场盛宴，包括音乐会与舞会，几乎半个大学的人都受到了邀请。大家都在传，斯帕兰扎尼那平时不敢让任何人见到的女儿奥林匹娅，也会在舞会上首次亮相。

当晚许多马车驶至教授宅邸门前，灯光把精心布置过的大厅照得亮堂堂的。纳塔内尔设法弄到一封邀请函，揣着一颗怦怦直跳的心准时出席了教授的晚会。受邀者人数众多，都打扮得光鲜靓丽。奥林匹娅也登场了，她衣着华丽且十分有品位，那漂亮的面容与身段都令人惊叹。她的背脊弯曲得有些不同寻常，苗条的身形如蜂一般，看着像是束腰的结果。她的姿势与步伐有些僵硬，像是精心设计好的，这让一些人感到很不舒服，但大家只把这归咎于在人前抛头露面所带来的压力。

音乐会开始了。奥林匹娅娴熟地弹起钢琴，并通过一曲咏叹调展示了自己高超的唱功。她歌声嘹亮，几乎如敲击玻璃一般尖锐。纳塔内尔听得心醉神迷。他站在最后一排，在炫目的烛光下没法完全看清奥林匹娅的面容。于是他悄悄把科波拉的望远镜举到眼前，透过它望向美丽的奥林匹娅。哎！——他发现她正多么渴望地盯着他。在爱的目光中，她的歌声变得愈发高昂，燃烧着涌入他的内心。在纳塔内尔听来，那巧妙的颤音一如天国传来的欢呼，是爱情使得这声音的主人容光焕发；终于，拖长的颤音在华彩乐段过后，尖锐地穿透并震颤了整个大厅。纳塔内尔就像被一双火热的手臂紧紧抓住了，他既痛苦又陶醉，不能自已地放声大喊起来：“奥林匹娅！”所有人都看向他，其中一些笑了笑。那位管风琴演奏者却摆出比之前更难看的脸色，只说道：“行吧，行吧！”

音乐会结束了，舞会随之开始。“同她跳舞！同她！”这便是纳塔内尔唯一的目的，是他的追求与企盼。但究竟如何才能鼓起勇气，去邀请这场盛宴的女王？然而——就连他自己也不知道这是如何发生的——在舞曲开始的时候，他已站在奥林匹娅身旁，而她尚未受到邀请。他握住她的手，甚至连一句结巴的话也吐不出来。奥林匹娅的手是冰凉的，这阴森的、死一般的冰冷使他浑身颤抖。他凝望奥林匹娅的双眼，它们朝他闪烁着，满含爱意与渴望。就在那一瞬间，他感到那冰凉的手上出现了脉搏的震颤，生命的血液也开始温暖地流动。

纳塔内尔心中的爱欲滚烫地涌了上来，他环抱住美丽的奥林匹娅，与她穿过人群。他本以为自己跳舞时很擅长踩节拍，但奥林匹娅那规律准确的舞步总使他步伐出错，然后他才意识到自己是多么不会踩拍子。他再也不想同别的女人跳舞了；而要是有谁靠近奥林匹娅并向她邀舞，他就会想立刻杀了那人。然而这样的情况只发生了两次。他惊讶地发现奥林匹娅在每场舞之间都坐着，他便不厌其烦地一次又一次把她拉起来。若非纳塔内尔眼里只有奥林匹娅，那么各式各样灾难般的口角与争吵都将在所难免，因为年轻人中响起了此起彼伏的窃笑，它们被刻意压低了，但显然针对美丽的奥林匹娅；他们全都好奇地盯着她，却没人知道究竟为什么。

舞蹈与大量的美酒使纳塔内尔心绪高涨，让他克服了平时的腼腆。他坐在奥林匹娅身旁，紧握着她的手。爱情激发了他的表达欲，他热情似火地滔滔不绝，虽然无论他自己还是奥林匹娅都不明白他究竟在说些什么。不过奥林匹娅可能听懂了，因为她坚定地望进他的眼中，一遍又一遍地轻叹：“唉，唉，唉！”纳塔内尔于是说道：“噢，美丽的、天使般的女子！你便是爱之光芒，闪耀在那应许的彼岸……你的心深不可测，如明镜映出我的整个倒影。”他还继续说了些其他诸如此类的话，但奥林匹娅只一味叹道：“唉，唉！”

斯帕兰扎尼教授在此间曾几次经过这对幸福的人，并奇怪地微笑起来，显得很满意。尽管纳塔内尔的精神还徜徉在另一个世界，但他仍一下子就发现斯帕兰扎尼的屋里明显变得昏暗了；他朝四周望去，惊恐地发现大厅已然变得空空荡荡，剩下的最后两盏灯也逐渐暗淡，即将熄灭。音乐与舞蹈早已结束了。

“分别，分别。”绝望中他发疯似的叫了起来，亲吻起奥林匹娅的手，又凑向她的唇，用他火热的嘴唇去吻她那冰冷的嘴！就像他碰到她那冷冰冰的手时那样，心中一阵恐怖攫住了他，他猛地想起传说中的亡灵新娘。但他仍紧紧拥着奥林匹娅。而在亲吻中，她的嘴唇似乎也像活过来一般变得温暖了。

斯帕兰扎尼教授缓缓穿过空荡荡的大厅。他的脚步声在厅中空洞地回响，跳动的光影环绕着他，使他看上去就像一个阴森可怖的幽灵。

“你爱我吗……你爱我吗，奥林匹娅？就一句话！——你爱我吗？”纳塔内尔悄声问道。但奥林匹娅却站起身来，叹息道：“唉，唉！”

“是的，你，我美丽动人的最爱，”纳塔内尔说道，“你在我的心间升起，如星辰那般璀璨，永远驱散了我心中的阴霾！”

“唉，唉！”奥林匹娅一边往前走去，一边答道。纳塔内尔跟着她，一起来到了教授面前。“您与我的女儿聊得尤其火热，”教授笑着说，“嗯，嗯，亲爱的纳塔内尔先生，既然您乐意接近这笨丫头，那么我们非常欢迎您前来拜访。”

晚宴结束后，纳塔内尔便离开了他心中那光芒四射的天堂。之后的几天里，斯帕兰扎尼举办的宴会一直是人们的谈资。尽管教授把一切都安排得井井有条，但聪明狡黠的家伙们仍会挑出各种各样奇怪又不得体的事情来说。首先浮现在人们脑海中的，便是那死一般僵硬又沉默的奥林匹娅。尽管她面容姣好，但人们仍说她完全是个呆头呆脑的傻小姐，并想探明斯帕兰扎尼隐藏她这么久的原因。纳塔内尔也听见了这些流言，心中不无怒火，却保持沉默。他心想，就算向这群家伙证明愚蠢的其实是他们自己，是他们认识不到奥林匹娅的美好与深沉，又有什么用呢？

有一天，齐格蒙德对他说：“帮我个忙，兄弟。请告诉我，你这个腼腆害羞的小子怎么可能会爱上那座蜡像，那个木偶娃娃？”纳塔内尔险些暴跳如雷，但他很快冷静下来，回答道：“你倒是告诉我，齐格蒙德，平时你头脑灵光、目光明晰，能捕捉到一切美的事物，为何竟会忽视奥林匹娅那迷人的魅力？不过我也得因此感谢命运没有让你成为我的情敌，否则我们二人之一必将倒在血泊中。”

齐格蒙德察觉到自己朋友的心理状况，便迅速让步了，表示他并非要针对纳塔内尔的恋爱对象，然后又补充道：“但这确实奇怪。我们许多人对奥林匹娅的评价几乎都是一样的，在我们看来——请别对我生气，兄弟！——她僵硬得有些古怪，看着像没有灵魂。她的身材平平无奇，她的脸也一样，这是真的！要是她的目光并非那么缺乏生机——或者说像个盲人——的话，她可能还算得上漂亮。她的步伐奇怪得仿佛是设计好的，她的一举一动都让她像个上了发条的齿轮机。她的演奏与演唱都如机器般节奏准确，却显得毫无灵魂，令人不适。她跳舞时亦是如此。我们觉得这个奥林匹娅非常吓人，也不想与她扯上关系；在我们看来，她只是表现得像个活物而已，她和真正的活物间一定有什么特别的联系。”

齐格蒙德的一席话使纳塔内尔十分不悦。他深陷在恶劣的情绪中，但终于还是克制住它，十分严肃地回应道：“对你们这些冷漠又乏味的人来说，奥林匹娅或许是可怕的。充满诗意的性情中人只会在同类面前展现自我，她妩媚的目光只会投在我身上，照亮我的身心。只有在奥林匹娅的爱里我才能找回自己。你们不喜欢她，是因为她不像其他庸人一样，会同你们无聊地瞎扯淡。确实，她并不健谈，但她的寥寥数语都来自那充满爱的内心世界，它们如同神秘的象形文字，象征了对精神生活的超验认识。不过你们对这一切毫无概念，我的话对你们而言也没有意义。”

“上帝保佑你，我的兄弟，”齐格蒙德轻轻地，几乎痛苦地说道，“我觉得你走上了邪路。你可以相信我，如果……不，我不想再说下去了！”

纳塔内尔突然感到，那冷漠且乏味的齐格蒙德对自己其实非常真诚，因此他也真挚地握住了齐格蒙德朝他伸来的手。

纳塔内尔完全忘记了世上还有克拉拉，这个他曾经深爱的人；母亲和洛塔尔也都在他的记忆中消失了，他只为奥林匹娅活着。他每天花好几个小时坐在她身旁，幻想着他的爱情，幻想着他们间炽热鲜活的共情与精神上的契合，而奥林匹娅则聚精会神地听着这一切。纳塔内尔从自己的桌肚深处找出他写过的所有东西：诗歌，长篇与短篇小说，虚构的幻想作品。他又新创作了各式各样玄幻空洞的十四行诗、八行诗与抒情诗，他的作品数量日益增加。他会花上好几个小时，不知疲倦地为奥林匹娅一首接一首地朗读。他还不曾拥有过一位如此美好的聆听者，她不会在倾听的时候做针线活儿，也不会望向窗外；她不喂鸟，不同袖珍犬或可爱的猫咪玩耍；她不摆弄碎纸片或手里的其他任何东西；她也不会刻意轻咳，来防止自己打呵欠。简而言之，几小时里她都眼神呆滞，目不转睛地看进爱人的双眼，而且一动不动；她的目光也变得越来越炽热，越来越鲜活。只有当纳塔内尔终于站起身来，亲吻她的手或嘴唇时，她才说：“唉，唉！”接着却道：“晚安，我的爱人！”

“噢，你这美丽的，深沉的人儿！”纳塔内尔在他的房间中喊道，“只有你，只有你一个人才能完全理解我！”只要一想到他与奥林匹娅之间存在怎样奇妙的共鸣，而这份共鸣又日益显著时，他的身躯便因心中的狂喜而震颤。在他眼里，奥林匹娅能对他的小说与诗歌做出真正深刻的评价，就好像她说出了他的心声一般。想必事实也确实如此，因为除了上文中提过的那些话外，奥林匹娅连一句别的话也没说过。在纳塔内尔还理智清醒的时候——比如说，早晨刚醒来时——他自己也会想起，奥林匹娅整个人都那么被动又沉默寡言，但他却这么说：“话语究竟算得了什么——话语！她那双美丽的眼睛和她的目光，能比任何语言表达出更多的内容。难道一个天使会屈尊挤进凡人那逼仄的圈子，去迎合可悲的世俗需求？”

斯帕兰扎尼教授似乎对纳塔内尔与自己女儿的关系相当满意，他毫不含糊地向纳塔内尔表达了自己的好意。在纳塔内尔终于鼓起勇气，委婉地暗示他想与奥林匹娅结合时，斯帕兰扎尼的整张脸布满了笑容，并表示他完全尊重女儿的选择。

这些话给了纳塔内尔勇气，心中燃烧的渴望也促使他决定第二天就立刻去看望奥林匹娅。之前她用妩媚且满含爱意的眼神倾诉了许久内心的情愫，而他要敦促她直截了当、清楚明白地把它们都说出口，并且宣布她愿永远属于他。他找起了母亲在分别时给他的戒指，打算送给奥林匹娅，它象征着他的献身，也象征他们那萌芽抽条、灿烂绽放的生活。他收到了克拉拉与洛塔尔写来的信件，却漠不关心地将它们搁在一旁。

他找到了那枚戒指，把它揣在身上后就往奥林匹娅那儿奔去。还在楼梯和走廊上时，他就听见一阵奇怪的咆哮，它似乎是从斯帕兰扎尼的研究室中传来的。有谁跺脚——链条嘎啦作响——一声碰撞——什么东西撞上了门，其间夹杂着咒骂：放开我，放开我……你这卑鄙的家伙，可耻的东西！……为它费尽心血？哈哈哈哈！我们可不是这样约定的！是我，是我造了眼睛，我造了那齿轮机……让你的齿轮机见鬼去吧，制表匠的愚蠢走狗……滚开，撒旦！……停下……人偶的发条……见鬼的浑蛋！……停下……滚开……放开我！

那是斯帕兰扎尼和可怕的科佩留斯的声音，他们的吼叫声嘈杂而此起彼伏。纳塔内尔在不可名状的恐惧中冲进房间。教授紧紧抓着一个女人身形的人偶的肩膀，意大利人科波拉则抓着她的脚，两人把她拉过来扯过去，在盛怒中争夺她。纳塔内尔认出了奥林匹娅，深深的惊恐使他猛地向后倒去。他的怒火疯狂地燃烧起来，盛怒中他想从那两个暴徒手中夺回自己的爱人。然而就在下一刻，科波拉用上九牛二虎之力，把人偶从教授的手中扭出来，并用它给了教授狠狠一记重击。教授因此向后撞上了桌子，摇摇晃晃，最后倒下了。桌上的梨状瓶、曲颈瓶等瓶子与玻璃圆柱体都摔下来，碎成了千万片。这时，科波拉把那人偶扛在肩上，在骇人的尖笑中猛冲下楼梯。人偶丑陋的双脚耷拉下来，硬邦邦地磕在一级级台阶上，发出恼人的声响。

纳塔内尔僵在原地。他看得清清楚楚——奥林匹娅死一样惨白的脸上没有眼睛，只有两个黢黑的窟窿。她是个没有生命的人偶。斯帕兰扎尼在地上打着滚，玻璃碴割伤了他的脑袋、胸膛与胳膊，血液像泉水那般汩汩涌出。他鼓足力气喊起来：“追他，追他！你愣着干什么？科佩留斯，科佩留斯，他抢走了我最好的机器人！我造了它二十年，我为它费尽心血……这个齿轮机……能说话，也能行走……我的……眼睛，被偷走了眼睛！该死的，该诅咒的家伙……追上他，把奥林匹娅还给我……她的眼睛就在那儿！”

这时，纳塔内尔见一对眼睛正躺在地板上，血淋淋地朝他凝望。斯帕兰扎尼伸出那只无恙的手抓走眼睛，朝纳塔内尔掷去。眼睛砸中他的胸膛。那一瞬间，疯癫伸出炽热的爪子攫住了他，把他的身心、理智与情感统统撕了个粉碎：“嚯！嚯！嚯！火轮——火轮！转起来，火轮——好玩儿，好玩儿！木偶娃娃，嚯，漂亮的木偶！木偶娃娃，转起来！”

他嚷嚷着扑倒在教授身上，一把掐住他的咽喉，差点儿把教授掐死。然而喧闹声引来了很多人，他们冲进屋子，扯开暴怒的纳塔内尔，救出教授并立即给他包扎伤口。就连身强体壮的齐格蒙德也无法制服这癫狂的疯子。纳塔内尔用恐怖的声音不断叫喊着：“木偶娃娃，转起来！”并用攥紧的拳头朝周围的人砸去。最后，好几个人一起上阵把他按在地上绑起来，才总算制服了他。他的吼叫渐渐减弱，变成野兽般骇人的咆哮。就在这发狂的咆哮声中，他被送入了疯人院。

不幸的纳塔内尔后来又遭遇了什么？在我接着为你讲述之前，好意的读者，我可以先放心地告诉你——要是你有些同情那技艺精湛的机械师与机器人制造家斯帕兰扎尼的话——他的伤都痊愈了。后来他不得不离开大学，因为纳塔内尔的事件引起了轰动。人们普遍认为斯帕兰扎尼触犯了法律，因为他把一个木偶人带入理智的社交圈中，并让它装作真人，这是不能容忍的欺骗行径。法学者甚至称之为一场精妙的骗局，并要加以严厉的惩罚，因为它愚弄公众，而且狡猾地成功了，几乎没有人（除了一些非常机敏的大学生）察觉到真相。

所有人都做起了事后诸葛亮，想通过各式各样的事实来证明自己在当时就感到可疑，然而这些所谓的“证据”却并不高明。比如受邀参加宴会的某个有修养的人就说：奥林匹娅打喷嚏比打呵欠更频繁，而这违反常理——有任何人会因此感到可疑吗？这位有修养的人认为，这驱动装置实际上在自动上发条，因此它会发出明显的咔啦声，诸如此类的。而文学与修辞学教授则取了一撮鼻烟，啪的一声合上烟盒，清了清嗓子，然后庄重地宣布：“尊敬的先生们、女士们！你们难道未曾发觉，问题的症结究竟在哪里？这一切是一个比喻——一个贯穿始终的隐喻！你们明白我的意思就够了，无须多余的解释[15]！”

但许多尊敬的先生并不满足于此。机器人的故事烙在了他们的灵魂深处，对人偶的惧怕与不信任在公众间悄然而生。仅仅为了证明自己所爱的并非人偶，许多人便要求自己的爱人不着调地唱歌或毫无节奏地跳舞，要求她们在倾听时做针线活儿，或与狮子狗玩耍之类的。最重要的是，她们不能只是倾听，而且说出的话中要包含真正的思想感情。一些恋爱关系因此而变得更加亲密动人，而另一些情侣却因此渐渐疏远，他们都这么说：“这世上，很难有谁值得信任。”聚会中人们打呵欠的频率高到难以置信，但却绝不打喷嚏，以免遭人怀疑。而正如之前所说，为了躲避用机器人欺骗大众而招致的刑事调查，斯帕兰扎尼溜走了，科波拉也消失得无影无踪。

纳塔内尔仿佛从沉重可怕的梦境中醒来，他抬起眼皮，感到难以名状的幸福宛若暖流一般，柔和美妙地流经他的全身。他在父亲的那座房子里，正躺在自己房间里的床上，克拉拉朝他俯下身来，洛塔尔与他的母亲则站在不远处。

“终于，终于！哦我亲爱的纳塔内尔，你的重病终于痊愈了！你又属于我了！”克拉拉从灵魂深处发出一声感叹，紧紧抱住纳塔内尔。纳塔内尔则在痛苦与惊惧中泪如泉涌，落下晶莹滚烫的泪水，沉沉喟叹一声：“我的……我的克拉拉！”齐格蒙德这时走了进来，他在这场大难中仍忠诚地对自己的朋友不离不弃。纳塔内尔对他伸出手，道：“我忠实的兄弟，你没有丢下我！”

疯癫的症状已然无迹可寻了，在母亲、爱人与朋友的照料下，纳塔内尔很快强壮了起来。幸福重新回到了这个家庭中，因为一位年迈而贫穷的叔叔过世了，人们原本对他一无所求，却没料到他留下了颇丰的遗产，还有一座小农场，坐落于离城不远的一处宜人地带。他们——母亲，纳塔内尔与他的克拉拉，还有洛塔尔——想搬去那里，纳塔内尔也打算与克拉拉结婚。

纳塔内尔变得像从前那样温柔纯真了，并终于清楚地认识到克拉拉的纯洁可爱与美丽动人。任何人都不曾使他想起过去的一丝一毫，只是在齐格蒙德与他道别时，纳塔内尔说：“上帝保佑你，我的兄弟！我曾步入绝境，但有天使及时带领我走上光明的小道！唉，她便是我的克拉拉！”齐格蒙德不让他接着说下去了，因为他担心纳塔内尔那沉痛的回忆又会强烈而清晰地浮现。

这四个幸福的人搬往农场的日子到了。中午时分他们走在城里的街道上，购置了一些物品。市政府所在的高塔在集市上投下了一片阴影。“哎！”克拉拉提议说，“我们不如上塔楼去，看看远处的山峦！”说到做到，纳塔内尔与克拉拉上了塔，母亲与女佣回家去了，而洛塔尔不愿爬那么多楼梯，便在塔下等候。这对恋人挽着彼此的胳膊，来到塔顶的回廊，俯瞰笼着薄雾的森林，眺望远方黛色的山峦——它们耸立着，如同一座大都会。

“你看见那一片昏暗又奇怪的小树林了吗？”克拉拉问道，“它们简直像在朝着我们缓步行进。”纳塔内尔闻言后机械地翻起了外套兜，他找到科波拉的望远镜，透过它朝一旁看去-克拉拉正站在镜前！顿时他浑身的血管都痉挛般抽搐起来，他盯着克拉拉，面色死一般惨白。但很快，一阵滚烫的热流汹涌地流经他转动的眼珠，他眼里射出火星，像被追猎的野兽那样骇人地狂吼起来。他猛地一跃，发出令人毛骨悚然的尖声大笑，一边吼道“木偶娃娃转起来……木偶娃娃转起来”，一边暴力地抓住克拉拉，要把她抛下塔去。但克拉拉在绝望与死的恐惧中紧紧抓住了塔沿。

洛塔尔听见了疯子的咆哮声，也听见了克拉拉惊恐的尖叫，不祥的预感在他心中油然而生。他冲上塔去，通往第二道楼梯的门却紧锁着。克拉拉痛苦的尖叫声更加响亮了。盛怒与恐惧使洛塔尔疯了一样朝门撞去，这才终于弹开。而克拉拉的声音则变得越来越虚弱：“帮帮我……救命……救命……”最后渐渐消散在空气中。

“她死了——她被那疯子谋杀了！”洛塔尔大喊起来。通往回廊的门也是紧锁的。绝望使他爆发出洪荒之力，把门从枢轴上撞了下来。上帝啊！克拉拉被那发了疯的纳塔内尔揪着，悬在回廊外的半空，只剩一只手还紧紧抓着铁栏杆。洛塔尔闪电般地抓住自己的妹妹，把她拉回来，紧接着用握紧的拳头狠狠揍向疯子的脸。纳塔内尔踉跄着倒退几步，松开了自己的猎物。

洛塔尔抱着昏迷的妹妹冲下塔。她得救了。而这时纳塔内尔却爬上塔沿，高高跃起至半空中，大喊道：“火轮转起来……火轮转起来！”

这疯狂的喊声使人们纷纷奔至塔下，身材高大的科佩留斯在他们中格外显眼——他也来到了这座城市，正好在往集市这边走。人们想冲上塔去制服那疯子，这时科佩留斯却笑道：“哈，哈！等着吧，他马上就会自己下来的。”说罢，便像其他人一样抬起头来望向塔顶。

纳塔内尔突然浑身僵住了。他站在原地，弯下腰去，发现了科佩留斯。随即他尖声吼道：“哈！好看的眼睛……好看的眼睛！”说着，他朝塔下纵身一跃。

纳塔内尔摔碎了脑袋，躺在石砌路面上。在那之后，科佩留斯便消失在了混乱的人群中。

许多年过后，或许人们能在一个遥远的地方瞧见克拉拉，她与一个快乐的男人手挽着手，坐在一座漂亮的小房子门前，两个活泼的小男孩儿在他们面前玩耍。可以得出结论，克拉拉还是找到了那份安宁的家庭幸福，这也符合她那开朗且热爱生活的心性；而这份幸福，是那内心撕裂的纳塔内尔绝无可能给予她的。

[7]拉扎罗·斯帕兰扎尼（1729-1799），意大利生物学家、生理学家。

[8]乔多维茨基（1726-1801），波兰人，后加入德国籍，18世纪著名画家。

[9]卡廖斯特罗（1743-1795），意大利神秘学家、炼金术士、冒险家。

[10]抹大拉的玛利亚，《圣经·新约》中耶稣的女追随者。

[11]巴托尼（Pompeo Girolamo Batoni，1708-1787），意大利著名画家，尤善肖像画。曾绘有《抹大拉的玛利亚》，画中的女性有着一头美丽的金色长发。

[12]雷斯达尔（Jakob van Ruisdael，1629-1682），荷兰著名画家，尤善风景画，是荷兰古典主义风景画的先驱之一。

[13]杜卡特，旧时神圣罗马帝国的货币。

[14]原文为法语。

[15]原句为拉丁文。

NathaNiel to lothar

You must surely all be worried sick not to have had word from me in such a long, long time. Mother is, no doubt, upset with me, and Clara may well believe that I am liv-ing the high life here, and have forgotten the face of my beloved angel so deeply and indelibly graven in my heart and mind. But it isn't so; every day of the week and every hour of the day I think of you all and my lovely little Clärchen's friendly figure floats past me in my dreams, smiling so sweetly at me with her bright eyes as she is wont to do whenever I walk in. Oh how could I put pen to paper in this wretched state that till now distracted my every thought! Something awful came into my life! Dark premonitions of a terrible impending fate cast their pall over me like the shadows of black storm clouds impermeable to any friendly rays of sunlight. Let me tell you then what happened to me. I have to tell you, that much I know; but just to think about it makes it spill out like a mad burst of laughter. Oh my dearest Lothar! How should I begin to make you fathom that what befell me just a few days ago could have such a devastating effect on my life! If only you were here, you could see for your-self; but by now you must surely take me for a crack-brained spook seer. In short, the terrible thing that happened to me, whose fatal impression I have tried in vain to erase from my consciousness, consists in nothing else than that a few days ago, namely on 30 October, at twelve noon, a barometer salesman stepped into my room and offered me his wares. I bought nothing and threat-ened to throw him down the stairs, whereupon, however, he promptly left of his own accord.

You suspect, I imagine, that only the most extraordin-ary life-altering relations could have lent this occurrence such signi ficance, indeed that it was the very person of that miserable pedlar that surely had such a poisonous effect on me. And that is just what happened. I will pull myself together, with all the strength of my will-power, quietly and patiently to recount the circumstances of my early youth as plainly and precisely as possible so that you, with your alert mind, may take everything in and paint as clear as possible a picture of my condition. But even now as I begin, I can hear you laughing and Clara remarking: ‘What childish notions!' Laugh, if you like, have yourself a right hearty laugh at my expense! Be my guest! But God in heaven, my hair stands on end, and it seems to me as if I were begging you in my mad desper-ation to make me sound ridiculous, like Franz Moor did Daniel. But it's time to begin!

Except for at lunchtime, we, my siblings and myself, saw little of my father during the day. He must have been very busy. After supper, which, according to long-standing custom, was served at seven o'clock, all of us, my mother and us, gathered in my father's study, and each took our place at a round table. Father smoked and drank a tall glass of beer. Often he told us many wondrous tales and would get so involved in the telling that his pipe went out, and it was my duty to fetch a burning wad of paper for him to relight it, a task that gave me the greatest pleasure. But many times he would just give us picture books to look at and sit there in silence propped up in his easy chair, blowing dense clouds of smoke, so that we all hovered as though in a fog. On such evenings mother was very sad and no sooner did the clock strike nine than she would declare: ‘Now children, to bed! To bed with you! The Sandman's coming, I can sense it!' And every time she said it I really did hear the sound of slow, heavy steps lumbering up the stairs; it must have been the Sandman.

One time the muffed thump and lumbering step sounded particularly grim to me; so I asked mother as she led us away: ‘Mama, who is that evil Sandman who always chases us away from Papa? What does he look like?'

‘There is no Sandman, my dear child,' replied mother; ‘when I say the Sandman is coming, all it means is that you children are sleepy and can't keep your eyes open, as if somebody had scattered sand in them.'

Mother's answer didn't satisfy me - indeed the notion took firm hold of my childish imagination that mother only denied the existence of the Sandman so that we wouldn't be afraid, didn't I hear him with my own two ears coming up the steps? With a burning desire to know more about this Sandman and his connection to us chil-dren, I finally asked the old woman who took care of my youngest sister: ‘What kind of man is that, the Sandman?'

‘Oh, Thanelchen,' she replied, ‘don't you know yet? He's a bad man who comes to visit children when they won't go to sleep and fiings a handful of sand in their eyes, so they scratch themselves bloody, then he fiings them in his bag and carries them off to the half-moon to feed his children; they sit up there in their nest and have crooked beaks like owls with which they pick out the eyes of naughty human brats.'

So in my mind I painted a grim picture of that awful Sandman; as soon as I heard that lumbering step on the stairs I trembled with fear and horror. My mother could get nothing out of me but that one word stuttered amidst tears: ‘Sandman! Sandman!' Then I bounded up to my bedroom and all night long I was tormented by the ter-rible presence of the Sandman.

By the time I was old enough to know that all that business about the Sandman and his children's nest on the half-moon the nanny had told me couldn't possibly be true, the Sandman had become entrenched in my mind as a hair-raising spook, and I was gripped by dread and terror when I heard him not only come clambering up the steps but tearing open the door to my father's study and barging in. Sometimes he stayed away a long time, but then he came more often, night after night. This went on for years, but I was never able to get used to that ghastly spook, nor did the grisly image of the Sandman ever fade from my mind.

I got ever more worked up about his dealings with my father; while some unbridgeable reserve kept me from asking him about it, the desire grew stronger from year to year to find out the secret for myself - to see the fabled Sandman with my own two eyes. The Sandman lured me down the path of wonder, the craving for adventure, that longing that had already taken seed in my childish mind. I liked nothing better than to hear or read fear-tingling tales of goblins, witches, sprites and suchlike; but the Sandman remained at the head of my list of the grisly figures I scribbled with chalk and charcoal on table tops, cupboards and walls.

When I turned ten, my mother moved me from the nursery into a little room off the corridor not far from my father's study. We still had to make ourselves scarce at the strike of nine, when that unseen presence was heard in the house. From my little room I distinctly heard him enter my father's chamber and soon thereafter it seemed to me as if the entire house filled with a strange-smelling vapour. My ever-mounting curiosity stirred my pluck to try and find a way to make the Sand-man's acquaintance. Many times I slipped out into the corridor as soon as mother had passed, but I was too late, since by the time I reached the spot from which I might catch a glimpse of him, the Sandman had invariably already entered. Finally, driven by an overpowering urge, I decided to hide in my father's room and await the Sand-man's appearance.

One evening, by my father's silence and my mother's sadness I surmised that the Sandman was coming; and so, pretending to be very tired, I excused myself before nine o'clock and hid in a nook beside my father's door. The front door creaked, the slow, heavy thud of steps advanced through the vestibule towards the stairs. Mother hastened by me with my brothers and sisters. Quietly then I opened my father's door. He was seated in silence, as usual, with his back to the door; he did not notice me slip in behind the curtain drawn over a closet where he hung his clothes.

Closer, ever closer came the thud of the steps; there was a curious cough and a scraping and a grumbling outside. My heart beat double-time in terror and expect-ation. Right there at the door came a powerful kick, a hefty blow on the latch, the door sprung open with a crash! Gathering all my pluck, I peeked out with great trepidation. The Sandman was standing there in the mid-dle of the room in front of my father, the bright glow of the lamps lighting up his face. So the Sandman, the terrible Sandman, was the old barrister Coppelius who sometimes dined with us for lunch.

But the most hideous figure could not have instilled a deeper sense of horror in me than this Coppelius. Imagine a big, broad-shouldered man with a misshapen clumpish head, an ochre-coloured face and grey, bushy eyebrows, beneath which a pair of piercing, greenish cat's eyes peered forth, a big nose bent down over the upper lip. His crooked mouth often twisted into a crafty snigger, at which dark red spots appeared on his cheeks and a curi-ous hissing tone issued from between his clenched teeth.

Coppelius always dressed in an old-fashioned ash-grey coat, a waistcoat and pants of the same colour, with black socks and shoes affxed with tiny buckles. His minuscule toupee hardly covered his skull, his ear-locks hung out over his big red ears and a big, half-hidden tuft of hair poked out from the scruff of his neck so as to reveal the silver clasp of his collar.

His entire appearance was altogether repulsive and disgusting; but what disgusted us children the most was his big, knotty, hairy fists, so much so that we were repelled by anything he'd touched. He noticed this and consequently took great pleasure in finding this or that excuse to graze a piece of cake or some sweet fruit that our dear mother surreptitiously dropped on our plates, so that, with tears in our eyes, repulsion kept us from enjoying a sweet titbit that we would otherwise have savoured. He did the same thing when, on holidays, our father poured us a little glass of sweet wine. He would then pass his fist quickly over it, even bring the glass to his blue lips and laugh a devilish laugh when we quietly vented a sniffie of anger. He always called us the little beasts; we were not permitted to make a sound in his presence and cursed the hideous and hostile man who intentionally and maliciously spoilt our little pleasures. Our mother seemed to hate that disgusting man as much as we did; for as soon as he appeared her high spirits and easy-going, cheerful manner faded into a sad and dour solemnity. Father behaved in his presence as if he were a higher being whose incivility one had to tolerate and whom one had to humour in every way possible. He only dared make timid suggestions in his presence and was sure to serve his favourite dishes and the finest wines.

So when I set eyes on this Coppelius I felt a grisly shudder in my soul at the sudden realization that no one but he could be the Sandman, but now the Sandman was no longer the fairy-tale bogeyman who dragged children off to feed to his young in the owl's nest on the moon - no! He was a hideous, ghastly fiend who brought misery and want, temporal and eternal rack and ruin wherever he appeared.

Positively paralysed with fear at the thought of being caught and severely punished, I just stood there with my head outstretched, listening through the curtain. My father received Coppelius respectfully.

‘Up now! To work!' the latter cried with a hoarse snarl and threw off his coat. In grim-faced silence father flung off his dressing gown and both pulled on long black smocks. I saw from where they took them. Father opened the folding door of a wall closet; but then I noticed that what I had long taken for a wall closet was not one at all, but rather a dark, hidden space fitted with a small hearth. Coppelius stepped forward and a blue flame flickered forth. All kinds of curious instruments were scattered about. Dear God! When my old father bent down towards the fire he looked altogether different. A ghastly convul-sive pain seemed to have twisted the gentle, honest features of his face into a devilish grimace. He looked just like Coppelius. The latter swung the red-hot tongs and fetched a bright, flickering mass of ore out of the thick vapour, which he then assiduously hammered. It seemed to me as if human faces became visible all about, but without eyes - dreadful, deep, black hollows where the eyes ought to be.

‘Eyes out, eyes out!' Coppelius cried with a muffed, roar-ing voice. Gripped by wild terror, I let out a scream and burst out of my hiding place onto the floor. Whereupon Coppelius grabbed hold of me and, baring his teeth, grum-bled, ‘Little beast! Little beast!' Picking me up, he hurled me at the hearth, so that the flames singed my hair. ‘Now we've got eyes - eyes - a lovely pair of children's eyes,' Coppelius whispered, and with his fists grabbed glowing cinders from the flames which he intended to strew in my eyes.

But then my father pleaded with hands folded in prayer: ‘Master! Master! Let my Nathaniel keep his eyes! Let him keep them, I beg you!'

Whereupon Coppelius gave off a shrill laugh and cried out: ‘Let the boy keep his eyes and whimper his lesson through life; but let us take a close look at the mechanism of the hands and feet.'Whereupon he grasped me so hard that my joints snapped, and twisted off my hands and feet and reinserted them here and there. Coppelius sput-tered and lisped: ‘'Tis not right this way! 'Twas good the way it was! The old man got it right!' and everything around me went dark, a sharp cramp flitted through my nerves and limbs - and then I felt nothing.

A warm and gentle breath wafted over my face, and I awakened, as if out of a deathlike sleep, with my mother bent over me. ‘Is the Sandman still here?' I stammered.

‘No, my dear child, he's been gone a long, long time, he won't hurt you!' my mother said and kissed and cud-dled her recuperated little darling.

Why should I try your patience, my dearest Lothar! Why should I keep babbling in minute detail when there's still so much to be told? Enough! Suffce to say that I was caught eavesdropping and mishandled by Coppelius. Fear and trembling had afflicted me with a high fever, with which I lay sick for several weeks. ‘Is the Sandman still here?'Those were the first clear words to issue from my lips and the sign of my recovery, my salvation. Let me just still tell you the most terrible moment of my youth; then you'll be convinced that it's not the failing of my eyes that makes everything appear colourless, but rather that a dark destiny has draped a veil of clouds over my life, which perhaps I may only rip through in death.

Coppelius stopped coming by; we were told that he'd left town.

It was about a year later, as we sat in the evening, true to our old family custom, at the round table. Father was very chipper and entertained us with delightful stories from the travels of his youth. Then at the strike of nine, we suddenly heard the front door hinges creak and slow, leaden steps thumped through the hallway and up the steps. ‘It's Coppelius,' said mother, going pale in the face.

‘Yes! It is Coppelius,'father confirmed with a weak and broken voice. Tears streamed from mother's eyes.

‘But father, father!' she cried, ‘must it be so?'

‘This one last time,' he replied, ‘it's the last time he comes here, I promise you. Just go, go with the children! Go! Go to bed! Goodnight!'

I felt as if I'd been pressed into cold, heavy stone - my breath stood still! Mother grabbed hold of my arm when I remained standing there: ‘Come, Nathaniel, come along, please!' I let her lead me, I went into my room. ‘Be quiet, be quiet, just go to bed! - sleep - sleep,'mother cried after me; but, torn as I was by my inner fear and turmoil, I could not close an eye. The picture of that hated, repulsive Coppelius stood there sniggering at me with his sparkling eyes; in vain did I try to erase the image from my mind.

It might already have been midnight when a terrible boom went off, as if a cannon had been fired. The whole house rumbled, it rattled and roared past my door, the front door was slammed shut with a mighty clatter. ‘That's Coppelius!' I cried out in terror and leapt from my bed.

Then came a piercing shriek and a wretched wail, and I rushed to my father's room. The door stood open, a suffocating steam hit me in the face, the chambermaid cried out: ‘Oh, the master! The master!'

In front of the steaming hearth my father lay dead on the floor with his terribly contorted face burnt black. My sisters howled and whined around him, my mother lay unconscious at his side. ‘Coppelius, you cursed Satan, you killed my father!' I cried out, whereupon I lost con-sciousness. Two days later, when they laid my father in his coffin, his expression was once again mild and gentle as it had been in life. It was at least comforting to think that his pact with that devilish Coppelius could not have condemned him to eternal damnation.

The explosion had awakened the neighbours; the incident seemed suspicious to them and they informed the authorities, who issued a warrant for Coppelius'arrest. But he had disappeared without a trace.

If I tell you, dearest friend, that that barometer salesman was none other than the accursed Coppelius, you will not, I trust, think ill of me for taking his inimical reappearance as a sign of bad things to come. He was dressed differently, but Coppelius'physique and facial features are too deeply engraved in my memory for me to mistake him for another. Moreover, Coppelius did not even change his name. He now pretends to be a Piedmontese mechanic and calls himself Giuseppe Coppola.

I have resolved to confront him and to avenge my father's death, come what will.

Don't tell mother a thing about that terrible creature. Give a hug to my dear sweet Clara, I'll write to her when I've calmed down a bit. Be well, etc. etc.

Clar a to NathaNiel

It is true that you haven't written to me in quite a while, but I still believe that you think of me and hold me dear. I was surely very much on your mind, for though you intended to send your last letter to my brother Lothar, you unwittingly addressed it to me, not him. I tore open the envelope with joy and only realized the error upon reading the words: ‘Oh, my dearest Lothar' - I know I ought not to have gone on reading after that, but rather to have handed the letter to my brother. But seeing as you sometimes reproached me in a childish, teasing way that I had such a calm, ladylike, sensible disposition that, before fleeing a house about to collapse, I would be inclined quickly to smooth out a wrinkle in the curtain, I dare hardly admit that the first lines of your letter upset me profoundly. I could hardly breathe, my eyes went blank. Oh, my dearly beloved Nathaniel! What terrible thing could have burst into your life! Being separated from you, the possibility of never seeing you again, that thought pierced my breast like the sharp blade of a dag-ger. I read and read! Your description of that disgusting Coppelius is really horrible.

Only now did I fathom that your dear old father died such a terrible, violent death. My brother Lothar, to whom I passed the letter, tried in vain to calm me down. The image of that despicable barometer pedlar Giuseppe Coppola pursued me wherever I went, and I am almost ashamed to admit that he even managed to trouble my ordinarily unruffled and restful sleep with all sorts of nightmarish phantasms. But soon thereafter, in fact by the very next day, my mood calmed down. Don't be upset with me, my dearest one, if Lothar tells you, despite your strange premonition that Coppelius would harm you, that I am once again my old cheerful, carefree self.

Let me confess here and now my firm conviction that all the awful and frightening things you speak of only happened in your imagination, and that the real outside world played little part in it. That old Coppelius may well have been repulsive enough, but the fact that he hated children made you and your siblings develop a real aver-sion to him.

Your childish imagination naturally associated your nanny's nursery account of the terrible Sandman with old Coppelius, who for you, even though you didn't believe in the Sandman, remained a fantastic monster of the kind children fear so intensely. The weird goings-on with your father at night were surely nothing other than alchemical experiments the two conducted together in secret, with which your mother may not have been pleased, since a lot of money was no doubt uselessly squandered in the process - on top of which, as is always the case with such laboratory assistants, your father became so consumed by the elusive craving for higher wisdom that he forgot about the family. Your father probably brought about his own death by a careless mistake, and Coppelius is not to blame. Can you believe that yesterday I asked the pharmacist next door if such a sudden deadly explosion ever occurred during chemical experiments? He said: ‘Yes, indeed,' and described for me in his typical long-winded and minute manner how such a thing could happen, in the process citing all kinds of curious-sounding substances I cannot now recall. Now you'll get angry with your Clara. You'll say: ‘Not a ray of the mysterious that embraces us with its invisible arms could break into that cold nature of yours; it only fastens on the colourful sur-face of things and takes a childish delight in the glittering golden fruit whose flesh contains a deadly poison hidden within.'

Oh my dearly beloved Nathaniel! Don't you think that even a cheerful - unaffected - carefree nature like mine could harbour an inkling of a dark force that insidiously strives to corrupt the sanctum of our inner self? But for-give me if, innocent girl that I am, I dare imply what I really think of that inner battle. I can't find the right words to say it and you're probably laughing at me, not because I mean to say something foolish, but because I am having such a hard time saying it.

If there is a dark force that can insidiously slip a per-fidious filament into our innermost self, wherewith it then grabs hold of us and drags us along on a dangerously destructive path that we would not otherwise have taken - if there is such a force then it must recon figure itself in our image, indeed it must become us; for only in this way will we be inclined to believe in it and give it the space it needs to realize its shadowy end. If we have enough good sense, fortified by healthy living, to recog-nize strange inimical influences as such, and steadfastly to hold to the path our nature and calling prescribe, then that sinister force will fail in the futile attempt to fashion itself in our image. It is also certain, Lothar adds, that that dark physical force to which we surrender ourselves of our own free will often make us internalize strange figures that life flings into our path, so that we merely rouse the spirit which our vivid delusion makes us believe emanates from that figure. It is the phantom of our own self whose deep affinity and profound influence on our state of mind either damns us to hell or uplifts us into heaven. You see, my best beloved Nathaniel, that we, my brother Lothar and I, discussed at length the subject of dark forces and compulsions, which, seeing as I have taken great pains to formulate the essential, now seems to me to be very deep indeed. I don't quite grasp Lothar's last point, though I have a sense of what he means and firmly believe it to be true. I beg you, erase the image of that ugly barrister Coppelius and the barometer pedlar Giuseppe Coppola from your mind. Be assured that these strange figures have no power over you; only your belief in their malevolent power can, in fact, make them malevo-lent to you. If the deep upset of your soul did not cry out in every line of your letter, if your state of mind did not shake me as profoundly as it does, in truth I could make light of your Mr Sandman, Esq. and that barometer ped-lar Coppelius. Be cheerful - cheerful! I have decided to come to you and act as your guardian angel, and should that repulsive Coppelius dare reappear and trouble you again in your dreams, I will exorcize him with loud laughter. I am not in the least bit afraid of him and his loathsome fists; he will not spoil a tender titbit with his barrister's touch or steal my eyes as the Sandman.

Forever, my dearly beloved Nathaniel, etc. etc. etc.

NathaNiel to lothar

I am very sorry that, granted, on account of my own absent-minded mistake, Clara recently tore open and read the letter I wrote to you. She wrote me a very profound philosophical response in which she took great pains to prove that Coppelius and Coppola only existed in my imagination and were phantoms of my own troubled self, phantoms that would be instantaneously reduced to dust if only I recognized them as such. It is indeed hard to believe that the spirit that emanates from such a brightly smiling, sweet child's eyes could display such brilliant insight. She cites you. So you talked about me. You instruct her in logical disputation so that she may learn to sort and filter out the chaff from the grain. Better leave it alone!

By the way, it's certain that the barometer pedlar Giuseppe Coppola is not the old lawyer Coppelius. I've just begun attending the lectures of the recently arrived Professor of Physics who, like the illustrious naturalist, is also named Spalanzani, and is of Italian descent. He has known Coppola for a good many years and, more-over, you can tell from the pedlar accent that he really is Piedmontese. Coppelius was a German, but no true blue one, I think. I'm still not altogether calmed down. Even if you and Clara take me for a dark dreamer, I cannot erase the terrible impression of Coppelius'accursed face. I'm glad, as Spalanzani claims, that Coppelius has flown the coop. This Professor is a wondrous sort, a round, little man with high cheekbones, a finely chiselled nose, pout-ing lips and small piercing eyes. But you can get a clearer picture of him if you look at Chodowiecki's[16] portrait of Cagliostro[17] in any Berlin pocket calendar. That's just what Spalanzani looks like.

I recently discovered while climbing the steps to the lecture hall that the glass door ordinarily covered with a curtain left a visible crack open at the side. A tall, very slender and well-proportioned, splendidly dressed lady sat in a room at a little table on which she rested both her arms, with her hands folded before her. She was seated just opposite the door, so I got a good look at her angelically lovely face. She did not seem to notice me and, in fact, her eyes had something glassy about them - I'd almost be inclined to say they could not see; it seemed to me as if she slept with open eyes. I felt the strangest rush of feeling and, therefore, slipped quietly off to the auditorium next door.

Later I learnt that the lovely figure I spotted was Spalanzani's daughter Olympia, whom for some strange reason he keeps locked up so that no one can come near her. I've begun to think there is something peculiar about her, that perhaps she's simple-minded. But why do I write to you about all this? I could have told it to you more clearly and in greater detail in person. I might as well admit that I'll be visiting you in two weeks'time. I simply had to see my sweet angel-faced Clara again. By then the ill humour brought on (I must admit) by that annoyingly understand-ing letter of hers that sought to sound my depths will have blown over. Which is why I'm not writing to her today.

A thousand greetings, etc. etc. etc.

It would be impossible to imagine anything more incred-ible and strange than what happened to my poor friend, the young student Nathaniel, and which, dear reader, I have undertaken to tell you. Have you, gentle reader, ever experienced anything that so completely permeated your heart, your mind and your thoughts that it supplanted all other notions? Something that simmered and seethed in you, that made your blood boil and flow like lava through your veins and made your cheeks turn a fiery red. A thing that turned your gaze so eerie, as if it sought to grasp the presence of figures imperceptible to all other eyes in an empty room, as your words melted into dark moans. And your intimates asked you: ‘What is it, friend? What on earth is the matter with you?'And then you wanted to describe your state of mind in all the glowing colours and shadows and lights, and strained to find the words, and didn't know where to begin. But it seemed to you as if with your very first word you felt compelled to evoke all the wondrous, beautiful, horrible, laughable, frightening things that happened, so that your account would strike your listeners like an electric shock. But every word that came to mind, anything that language could conjure up, seemed colourless, frigid and dead. You searched and searched, and stuttered and stammered, and the sensible questions of friends struck like icy gusts of wind that soon dissipated in the emotional cauldron within. But had you, like a bold painter, begun with a few audacious brush strokes to set down the rough outline of your state, you would have been able to apply with great ease ever brighter dabs of colour, and so to dazzle your friends with the living swirl of multifarious figures, and they would see themselves, as you see yourself, in the middle of the picture that issued from your imagination.

No one, I must admit, gentle reader, ever actually asked after the story of young Nathaniel; but as you well know, I am one of those rum writers to whom, if burdened with impressions of the kind I've just described, it seems as if anyone who happens to cross their path, indeed the whole world, were dying to know: ‘What's bothering you? Pray tell us if you please!' So I felt a pressing need to speak to you of Nathaniel's fateful path. The very wondrousness and strangeness of it consumed my consciousness, but for that very reason - and because I needed to make you, dear reader, likewise inclined and, therefore, able to bear the things I am about to tell, which is no small feat - I tormented myself as to how to begin my account in a significant, original, gripping fashion.

‘Once upon a time' - the nicest start to any tale - seemed too vapid!‘In the small provincial town of S. there lived ……' sounded a bit better, at least informative enough to pave the way for the climax. Or to begin right off in medias res: ‘"The devil take you!"the young student Nathaniel cried out with a wild-eyed look of anger and dread at the sight of the barometer pedlar Giuseppe Coppola' - this I had, in fact, already written down when I was suddenly struck by something droll in the wild-eyed look of the young student Nathaniel; but the story is not in the least bit comical. I could find no words to reflect even the faintest glimmer of the burning heart of the matter. So I decided to dispense with the beginning.

Just take the three letters, gentle reader, that my friend Lothar was kind enough to pass on to me, as the outline of the picture, to which I will take pains to add more and more colour in the telling. Maybe I will manage, like a good portrait painter, to conjure up a character such that you will find a convincing resemblance without knowing the original; indeed that it will seem to you as if you had seen that person many times with your own two eyes. Maybe then, dear reader, you will believe that there is nothing more wondrous and strange than life itself, and that all that the poet can do is convey a dark reflection of it in a lightly buffed mirror.

So as to clarify what the reader needs to know from the start, I must add to the aforementioned letters that shortly after the death of Nathaniel's father, Clara and Lothar, the children of a distant relative who likewise died and left them orphaned, were taken in by Nathan-iel's mother. Clara and Nathaniel took a great liking to each other, to which no person on earth objected; they were therefore betrothed when Nathaniel left home to pursue his studies in G. , which is where we find him in his last letter, attending lectures by the famous professor of physics Spalanzani.

Now I could confidently press on with the tale; but at the moment I have such a vivid image of Clara's face before my eyes that I cannot look away, which is what always happened when she looked my way with her lovely smile. Clara could by no means have been considered beautiful; such was the opinion of all those who claimed to know a thing or two about beauty. And yet the archi-tects of beauty praised the sleekness and symmetry of her stature, the painters found her neck, shoulders and bust almost too maidenly, but were all enamoured of her Magdalene hair and raved about her luminous colouring. But one of them, a real fantast, strangely enough com-pared Clara's eyes to a Ruisdael lake in which the azure blue fundament of a cloudless sky and the forest and flowering flora of the lush landscape of life were mirrored. But the poets and thinkers were even more ebullient and said: ‘What lake - what mirror! Can one gaze at this girl without perceiving heavenly songs and notes come streaming from her eyes, music that reaches deep into our innermost selves, awakening and bestirring all our dormant passions?'If we ourselves try to sing her praises and the song falls flat, a crude croon masquerad-ing as a serenade with haphazard tones carelessly warbled, the fault is ours and Clara's lips say it all in their delicately elastic smile. That's the way it was.

Clara had the healthy imagination of a cheerful, unaffected child, a deep womanly gentle disposition, and a downright sparkling, sharp-sighted intelligence. The mystics and conjurors failed to impress her; for without saying much - idle chatter was anathema to her quiet nature - her bright gaze and that hint of irony in her smile said:dear friends, do you really expect me to take your ephemeral shadow figures for real live people with impulses and emotions? For that reason, Clara was scorned by many as cold, emotionless, prosaic; but others with a sober grasp of all the twists and turns of life had a powerful affection for that tender, understanding, child-ish girl, none more so than Nathaniel, a young man seriously and passionately committed to the study of sci-ence and the arts. Clara was attached to her beloved with all her heart and soul; the first storm clouds troubled their life when he went away to study. With what rapture, then, you can well imagine, did she fly into his arms, when, as he let slip in his last letter to Lothar, he actually showed up in his home town at his mother's doorstep. It was just as Nathaniel expected; for as soon as he saw Clara again he forgot all about the lawyer Coppelius and Clara's letter, and his upset disappeared.

But Nathaniel was indeed right when he wrote to his friend Lothar that the appearance of that odious barom-eter pedlar Coppola had had a detrimental effect on his life. Everyone felt within days of his arrival that Nathan-iel was a changed man. He fell into dark brooding spells and began to behave so strangely, in ways that one would never have expected of him. Everything, his entire life, had become the stuff of dream and premonition; he kept saying that everyone who gave free rein to his fancies merely served as a plaything in the terrible game of dark forces, that all resistance was in vain, and all one could do was meekly to submit to the will of fate. He went so far as to maintain that it was foolish to believe that spon-taneity could affect the arbitrary outcome of artistic and scientific investigations; for the passion needed to pursue such work does not come from our innermost selves, but rather derives from the external in fluence of a higher principle independent of our own free will.

Such mystical musings were altogether repugnant to the sensible Clara, yet it seemed futile to attempt to prove him wrong. But it was only when Nathaniel insisted that Coppelius was the incarnation of the evil principle that had taken hold of him, pulling the strings from behind an invisible curtain, that Clara suddenly fathomed that this disgusting demon threatened to disrupt their happy love, grew very serious and said: ‘Yes, Nathaniel, you're right, Coppelius is an evil inimical principle, a devilish force that infiltrated your life able to do dreadful things, but only if you refuse to banish him from your thoughts and feelings. As long as you believe in him he does indeed exist and affect you, only your belief gives him power over you.'

Furious that Clara only accepted the existence of demons as a function of his state of mind, Nathaniel wanted to counter with a disquisition on the entire mys-tical teachings of devils and uncanny forces; but, vexed in turn, Clara cut him short by suddenly bringing up some altogether irrelevant matter, which made Nathaniel all the more angry.

Cold, unreceptive spirits do not open their hearts to such deep secrets, Nathaniel thought, without fully fathoming that he counted Clara among those lesser natures, which is why he did not stop trying to initiate her into those eso-teric teachings. Early in the morning when Clara helped prepare breakfast, he stood by her and read to her from all sorts of mystical texts, whereupon Clara protested: ‘But my dear Nathaniel, what if I were to blame you for the evil principle that's keeping my coffee from brewing? For if, as you wish, I were to drop everything and look you in the eyes as you read to me, then my coffee will boil over and burn and you won't get your breakfast!'

Nathaniel slammed the book shut and ran in a rage to his room. In the past he had had a charming, lively talent for reading aloud the stories that he jotted down, to which Clara listened with the greatest pleasure; but now his writings were dark, incomprehensible, shapeless, so that even though, not wanting to hurt him, Clara said nothing, he nevertheless sensed how unreceptive she was. Nothing was more deadly for Clara than this boring stuff; in every look and word she revealed her insurmountable intellectual ennui. Nathaniel's writings were indeed a crashing bore. His chagrin at Clara's cold prosaic spirit grew; she simply could not shake off her displeasure at Nathaniel's dark, morbid, boring mysticism, and so the two drifted inwardly further and further apart without noticing it.

The figure of that repulsive Coppelius faded in his imagination, as Nathaniel himself had to admit, so that he had to take great pains to paint a vivid picture of him in his writings, in which he appeared as the bogeyman. Finally one day he felt impelled to express that dark pre-monition that Coppelius would disrupt his happy love as the subject of a poem. In the poem he represented him-self and Clara as bound by true love, but every now and then it was as if a dark fist reached into their life and ripped out any seed of joy that sprouted in the garden of their hearts. Finally, when they were already standing together at the marriage altar, that terrible Coppelius appears and touches Clara's sweet smiling eyes; they burst open against his breast, searing and burning like bloody sparks, where-upon Coppelius seizes Nathaniel and flings him into a flaming circle of fire that spins at the speed of lightning and hurls him about in a blue blaze. Then comes a roar, as if the angry tempest whipped up the foaming waves of the sea that rear up in battle like white-hooded black giants. But through this wild roar he hears Clara's voice: ‘Can you not see me? Coppelius deceived you, those were not my eyes that burned in your breast, they were the glowing drops of your own heart's blood - I still have my eyes, just look at me!' And Nathaniel thinks:it is Clara, and I am hers for ever. Then it is as if the thought reaches into the circle of fire, stops suddenly, and the roar fades into a dull thud in the black abyss. Nathaniel peers into Clara's eyes; but it is the face of death that smiles back at him with Clara's eyes.

While engaged in the composition of this poem Nathaniel remained very quiet and collected; he polished and tinkered with every line, and since he chose to follow the rule of metre, he did not rest until everything fitted together and sounded just right. When he was neverthe-less finally done with it and read the poem out loud to himself he was totally appalled and, gripped by a wild sense of horror, cried out: ‘Whose terrible voice is this?'But soon the whole thing just seemed to him to be a very successful poetic text, and he was convinced that it would excite Clara's cold heart, although he failed to consider just where her excitement might lead and to what end he wished to frighten her with such gruesome images, fore-shadowing a terrible fate that would tear their love apart.

They, Nathaniel and Clara, sat together in his mother's little garden, Clara as cheerful as could be because Nathaniel had not tormented her with his dreams and dark premonitions for the last three days, which he'd spent tinkering with the poem. Even Nathaniel spoke in a lively and spirited manner of funny things, like before, so that Clara said: ‘Now at last I have you all to myself again, you see how we drove out that repulsive Coppe-lius?'That reminded Nathaniel of the poem in his pocket, which he'd intended to read aloud. He promptly pulled out the pages and started reading.

Expecting the same tedious stuffas before, and pre-pared to endure it, Clara started quietly knitting. But as the storm cloud of his verse grew ever darker and darker around them she let the knitted stocking sink into her lap and looked Nathaniel hard in the eye. Swept along by the fire of his poetry, his cheeks tinted bright red by the cauldron of turbulent emotions, tears welled up in his eyes. Having finally reached the conclusion, he heaved a heavy sigh of exhaustion, gripped Clara's hand and sobbed, as though dissolving in inconsolable sadness: ‘Oh, Clara!……Clara!'

She pressed him gently to her breast and said quietly, but very slowly and succinctly: ‘Nathaniel - my dearly beloved Nathaniel! Throw that raving - senseless - insane fairy tale into the fire.'

Whereupon, shoving Clara away from him, Nathaniel leapt up in a fury and cried out: ‘You lifeless, accursed automaton!' He ran off, leaving Clara completely morti-fied, weeping bitter tears.

‘He never loved me, he doesn't understand me!' she wailed at the top of her lungs. Lothar came striding into the arbour. Clara felt compelled to tell him what had happened. Lothar loved his sister with all his heart; every word of her accusation struck him like a spark, so that the ill will he'd long felt for that muddle-headed Nathaniel now flared up into wild anger. He ran to find him, reproached him with harsh words for his inexplicable treatment of his beloved sister, and the irascible Nathaniel replied in kind. A wild and crazy fop faced off with a miserable, mundane man of the people. A duel was inev-itable. They decided, according to the local academic custom, to meet behind the garden and draw sharp-bladed rapiers.

Silently and stealthily they slipped by; Clara had heard and seen the heated argument, and spotted the duelling master bringing the rapiers at dusk. She guessed what was about to happen. Lothar and Nathaniel had just reached the duelling ground and flung off their coats in brooding silence, a bloodthirsty fury pouring from their burning eyes, when Clara came bounding through the garden gate. Sobbing she cried out: ‘Oh you barbaric beastly men! Cut me down right this moment before going at it with each other; for how am I supposed to go on living in this world if my beloved murders my brother, or my brother my beloved!'

Lothar let his sword sink and peered at the ground in silence, and all the heart-rending love Nathaniel had felt in the sweet days of youth for his precious Clara once again flared up in him. The deadly weapon fell from his hand and he flung himself at Clara's feet. ‘Can you ever forgive me, my only, my ever so dearly beloved Clara! Can you forgive me, my dearest brother Lothar!' Lothar was stirred by the profound pain of his friend; the three young people, now reconciled, embraced in a flood of tears and swore henceforth faithfully to hold by their love.

Nathaniel felt as though a heavy weight that had pressed him to the ground had been lifted from his shoulders - indeed as though in resisting the dark force that had held him in its sway he had saved his entire being from the threat of annihilation. He spent three more blissful days with his loved ones and then rode back to G. , where he had to complete another year of study, after which he planned to return for good to his native town.

Everything having to do with Coppelius was kept from his mother; since the three friends knew all too well that she could not think of him without trembling, for, like Nathaniel, she too blamed him for the death of her husband.

Imagine how stunned Nathaniel was when, intending to return to his apartment, he found the entire house burnt to the ground, so that only the charred walls still rose from the rubble heap. Braving the fire that had started in the laboratory of the apothecary on the first floor and engulfed the house in flames from the bottom up, a few resolute friends had nevertheless managed in the nick of time to dash up to Nathaniel's room and save his books, manuscripts and instruments. They succeeded in carrying everything intact to another house, where they rented a room for him, into which Nathaniel promptly moved.

He was not particularly surprised to discover that he lived directly opposite Professor Spalanzani, nor did it seem strange to him when he realized that from his window he could peer directly into the room in which Olympia often sat alone, positioned in such a way that he could clearly recognize her figure, while her facial features remained blurred and vague. But after a while it did indeed strike him as strange that Olympia often sat for hours on end in the same stance she had assumed when he once glimpsed her through the glass door, perched before a small table, apparently engaged in no activity, and that she clearly cast a fixed gaze in his direction. He likewise had to admit to himself that he had never set eyes on a lovelier female figure; but, holding true to Clara in his heart, he remained largely oblivious to Olympia's stiff, stone-cold allures, and only every now and then did he cast furtive looks over his open compendium at the comely statue - that was all.

He was just writing to Clara when he heard a light knock; upon his invitation to enter, the door swung open a crack and Coppola's repulsive face peered in. Nathaniel felt a shudder of terror run through him; mindful, how-ever, of what Spalanzani had told him about his compatriot Coppola, and that he had given his sacred word to his beloved to lend no more credence to the Sandman Coppelius, he himself was ashamed of his childish fears. With a great effort he pulled himself together and spoke as calmly as possible: ‘I'm not going to buy a barometer, my dear friend, so you might as well be going!'

At which, however, Coppola stepped squarely into the room and spoke with a hoarse voice, his broad mouth twisted into an ugly laughter, his sparkling little eyes casting a piercing look beneath the wink of his long grey lashes: ‘Forget barometer, bah! I bring pair o'lovely peepers!'

Horrified, Nathaniel cried out: ‘Strange man, how can you have eyes for sale? Eyes? Eyes?'

But then and there Coppola shoved aside his barom-eters, reached into his deep coat pocket and pulled out spectacles and eyeglasses which he laid out on the table. ‘Look - glass - glass - what you put on you nose, eyes a pretty - eyes a pretty!' Whereupon he pulled out more and more eyeglasses, so that the entire table was soon flickering and sparkling.

A thousand eyes peeped and twitched and stared at Nathaniel; but he was unable to turn away from the table, and Coppola kept laying out more and more eyeglasses, and ever wilder and wilder did those glaring gazes land, helter-skelter, shooting their blood-red rays at Nathaniel's breast. Overcome by frantic horror, he cried out: ‘Stop it! Stop it, you wretched creature!' He grabbed Coppola by the arm as the latter, oblivious, reached yet again into his pocket to fetch more glasses to add to the heap that covered the table.

But Coppola shook himself free, and with a hoarse, repulsive laugh, muttered: ‘Oh! This not for you! But look here, lovely glass!' - wherewith he swept up all the eyeglasses, shoved them back into his coat pocket, and from another pocket pulled out a number of big and little telescopes and field glasses.

As soon as the eyeglasses were out of sight Nathaniel grew calm again and, mindful of Clara's words, had to admit to himself that the terrible spook was a figment of his own imagination, and that Coppola was an altogether honest craftsman and lens grinder and could not possibly be Coppelius'cursed doppelgänger and shadow figure. He realized, furthermore, that there was nothing strange about all the lenses that Coppola now laid out on the table, nothing ghastly like the eyeglasses, and to make amends Nathaniel now decided actually to buy something from him. He reached for a small, very finely crafted pocket looking-glass and, to test it, peered out of the window.

Never in his life had he come upon a looking-glass that so clearly and sharply brought distant objects before his eyes in such clear focus. He unintentionally peered into Spalanzani's room; Olympia sat there, as usual, at the little table, with her arms resting on it and her hands folded. Now for the first time Nathaniel espied Olympia's exquisitely lovely face. Only the eyes appeared strange, blank and dead. But as he brought her face into greater and greater focus in the looking-glass, it seemed to him as if Olympia's eyes flashed open in moist moonbeams. It was as if she had only now acquired the power of sight; her glances grew livelier and livelier. Nathaniel lingered at the window, trans fixed, unable to take his eyes off the stunningly lovely Olympia. He was awakened, as if out of a deep dream, by the sound of throat-clearing and scraping.

Coppola stood behind him: ‘Tre zecchini - three ducats!' Nathaniel, who had completely forgotten the optician, quickly counted out the asking price. ‘Fine glass - fine glass - is it not?'asked Coppola with his repulsive hoarse voice and his crafty smile.

‘Yes, yes, indeed!' Nathaniel replied, greatly vexed. ‘Adieu, dear friend!'

But Coppola cast several strange sidelong looks at Nathaniel and his room before taking his leave. The young man could still hear him laughing out loud on the staircase. ‘All right,' Nathaniel muttered to himself, ‘he's laughing at me because I no doubt paid far too much for the little looking-glass - paid far too much!' As he quietly whispered these words, a deep and terrible deathly groan resounded in the room. Nathaniel was so frightened he stopped breathing. But the groan had emanated from his own throat, he fathomed after the fact. ‘Clara's quite right,' he said to himself, ‘to take me for a ridiculous ghost-haunted idiot; it's perfectly insane - completely ridiculous of me to let the thought that I paid Coppola too much for the looking-glass unnerve me to such a degree; and for no reason at all.'Now he sat himself down to finish writing the letter to Clara, but a fleeting glance out of the window confirmed that Olympia was still seated there; and then and there, driven by an irresistible urge, he jumped up, grabbed Coppola's looking-glass and remained glued to the window, riveted by Olympia's alluring visage, until a friend and fellow student, Siegmund, called out to remind him that it was time to come along to Professor Spalanzani's lecture.

But the next day the curtain was pulled shut in that fateful room across the way, and he could not catch sight of Olympia on that day or on the following two days, despite the fact that he seldom left his own window and constantly kept peering over with Coppola's looking-glass. On the third day even the blinds were pulled. Desperately pining and driven by a burning desire, he ran out to her front door. Impressions of Olympia's lovely figure hung in the air everywhere he looked; she stepped out from behind the bushes and the reflection of her big, sparkling eyes beamed out at him from the clear brook. Clara's image had been totally erased from his heart, he thought of nothing but Olympia and wailed and complained at the top of his voice: ‘Oh you, my shining star of love, did you appear before me only to vanish again and leave me in the dark and desperate night?'

As he was about to return to his room, he became aware of noisy goings-on in Spalanzani's house. The doors were open, all kinds of devices were being carried in, the windows on the first floor were open wide, busy housemaids swept and dusted the window boxes with big brooms; inside, meanwhile, carpenters and decorators banged and hammered. Stunned, Nathaniel remained standing there in the street; then Siegmund came over to him and said, laughing: ‘So what do you say about our old Spalanzani?'Nathaniel assured him that he had nothing to say since he knew absolutely nothing about the Pro-fessor, but that he was rather surprised to discover such a wild to-do and housekeeping frenzy in that ordinarily dark and silent house; whereupon Siegmund informed him that Spalanzani was going to throw a big party the next day, including a concert and ball, and that half the university was invited. The word was that Spalanzani was going to let his daughter Olympia, whom he'd fearfully kept sheltered from view, appear for the first time in public.

Nathaniel received an invitation and presented himself at the Professor's at the appointed hour with a fast-beating heart, as carriages rolled up to the door and lights shim-mered in the elegantly decorated rooms. The company was numerous and glamorous. Olympia appeared richly and tastefully attired. Everyone had to admire her finely chiselled face and graceful figure. The strange stoop of her back and her bone-thin waist appeared to be the consequence of a girdle tied too tight. There was a meas-ured stiffness in her stance and step that some found displeasing; but that was ascribed to the stress of appear-ing in society. The concert began. Olympia played the grand piano with great skill and likewise brought off a bravura aria with a clear, almost bell-glass-like, pitch-perfect voice. Nathaniel was completely captivated; he stood in the last row and could not clearly make out Olympia's features in the candlelight. Without attracting notice, he therefore pulled out Coppola's looking-glass and gazed through its lens at the lovely Olympia. Oh God! He now fathomed how ardently she peered in his direction, how every note only seemed to sound envel-oped in a loving look that surged through his burning heart. The artful trills rang out in Nathaniel's ear like the heavenly Hosannas of the spirit trans figured by love; and when at last, following the cadenza, the long trill pierced the air all around him, feeling as though suddenly envel-oped by her warm embrace, and no longer able to control himself, he cried out in rapture and pain: ‘Olympia!' All heads turned to look at him, some laughing.

But the cathedral organist's face twisted into an even dourer grimace than before and he merely remarked: ‘Well, well!' The concert came to an end, the ball began. Only to dance with her - with her! That was now the object of Nathaniel's deepest desire, all that he strove for; but how would he get up the courage to ask her, the queen of the evening, for a dance? Nevertheless - he himself had no idea how it happened - finding himself all of a sudden standing right there beside Olympia, once the music had already started up, and she not yet having been invited to dance, hardly able to stammer a few words, he reached for her hand. Olympia's hand was ice-cold; he felt a terrible deathly frost surge through him; he looked into her eyes, which greeted his gaze with love and longing, and at that very moment it was as if the pulse began to beat in her cold hand and the lifeblood began to glow warm within. And love's longing welled up, glowing hotter and hotter in Nathaniel's breast; he wrapped his arm around lovely Olympia and led her down the rows of dancers. He had always thought himself to be a good dancer, able to hold to the beat; but from the precise rhythmic steadiness of Olympia's step, which often caused him to falter, he soon fathomed the failing of his sense of beat. And yet he no longer wanted to dance with any other woman in the world, and felt as if he would have killed on the spot anyone else who dared approach her to ask for a dance. But this happened only twice, and thereafter, to his amazement, Olympia always remained seated between dances and he did not hesitate to reach for her hand and pull her up again and again.

Had Nathaniel had eyes for anything but the lovely Olympia, countless tussles and tangles would have been unavoidable; for clearly the quiet, painstakingly muffed laughter that emanated here and there among the groups of young people was directed at the lovely Olympia, whom they followed with the strangest looks - it was hard to say why. Fired up by the dance and by the wine of which he'd pleasantly partaken, Nathaniel shed his innate shyness. He sat beside Olympia, his hand in hers, and spoke fervently of his love for her in words that nei-ther he nor she understood.

But she perhaps grasped their meaning; for she peered without flinching right into his eyes and sighed again and again: ‘Oh - Oh - Oh!'

Whereupon Nathaniel replied: ‘Oh you beautiful, heavenly woman! You ray of hope from the Promised Land of love - you deep spirit in which my entire being is mirrored,' and more of the same.

In response to which Olympia kept sighing the same‘Oh, Oh!'

Professor Spalanzani walked several times past the blissful pair and smiled with a strange look of satisfac-tion. And though Nathaniel's spirit hovered elsewhere in another world, all of a sudden it seemed to him as if it grew curiously dark down here below in Professor Spalanzani's house; he looked around and fathomed with a start that the last two lights in the empty hall were burning down to the wick and threatened at any moment to go out. Music and dance had stopped long ago. ‘Time to part, time to part,'he cried out in a wild and desperate voice, kissed Olympia's hand and leant forward to kiss her on the mouth with his burning lips, but her lips were ice-cold! And, just as when he'd first touched Olympia's cold hand, he felt a shudder run through him, the legend of the dead bride suddenly flashing through his mind; but Olympia pressed him tightly to her, and in that kiss her lips seemed to come alive with warmth. Professor Spalanzani paced slowly through the empty hall; his steps sounded muffed and, ringed by dancing shadows, his fig-ure appeared terrifying and ghostlike. ‘Do you love me - do you love me, Olympia? Just that one word! Do you love me?'whispered Nathaniel.

But, standing up, Olympia only sighed: ‘Oh! Oh!'

‘Oh yes, my precious, my beautiful star of love,'said Nathaniel, ‘you rose in the firmament of my heart and will evermore light up and trans figure the darkness within!'

‘Oh, Oh!' Olympia responded, walking away.

Nathaniel followed her; they stood before the Profes-sor. ‘You sweet-talked my daughter in a right sprightly manner,'he said with a smile. ‘Well then, my dear Mr Nathaniel, if conversing with the simple-minded girl gives you pleasure, you're welcome to visit whenever you like.'

Nathaniel staggered off starry-eyed, with all of heaven's splendour bursting from his breast. Spalanzani's party was the talk of the town in the days that followed. Not-withstanding the Professor's great pains to make it a splendid occasion, the chatterboxes nevertheless dwelt on all sorts of unseemly and strange goings-on, saving their sharpest barbs for the stiff and silent Olympia, who, despite her lovely exterior, was saddled by the wagging tongues with a lot of completely nonsensical notions as to her sanity - the reason, it was said, that Spalanzani kept her hidden for so long. Needless to say, Nathaniel was not pleased to learn of this, and he said nothing; what was the point, he reasoned, in proving to these dullards that it was their own nonsense that kept them from recognizing Olympia's profound and beautiful spirit!

‘I beg you, my friend,'Siegmund said to him one day, ‘tell me how in heaven's name an intelligent man like you ever fell for the wax face of that wooden doll?'

Nathaniel was about to explode in anger, but then he pulled himself together and calmly responded: ‘Why don't you tell me, brother Siegmund, how a fellow with an eye for beauty could be blind to Olympia's heavenly charms? But then again, it's just as well fate didn't make you a rival; for one of us would have to fall in blood.'

Fathoming how things stood with his friend, Siegmund backed off and, after observing that in matters of beauty and love all is in the eye of the beholder, he added: ‘Still it's funny that so many of us feel pretty much the same way about Olympia. She seemed to us - don't take it badly, my friend! - strangely stiff and soulless. Her fig-ure's regular, just like her face, it's true! She might well be considered beautiful, if her gaze were not so devoid of life, so totally lacking, you might say, the power of sight. Her step is strangely measured, every movement seems prescribed by clockwork gears and cogs. Her play-ing and singing have the unpleasantly precise soulless rhythm of a machine, which is true of her dance step too. This Olympia seemed completely odd to us, we didn't know how to take her; it was as if she were only acting like a living being, and yet she unquestionably has her own way about her.'

Nathaniel refused to give in to the bitter feelings that welled up in his heart at Siegmund's words. He checked his mood and simply replied, deadly serious: ‘Olympia may indeed seem odd to you cold, prosaic types. The poetic temperament only reveals itself to like-minded souls! Her loving look fell on me alone, lighting up my senses and thoughts; only in Olympia's love can I find myself again. You all think ill of her because she doesn't babble banalities like all the other shallow souls. It's true, she speaks little; but those few words seem like true hiero-glyphs revealing an inner world replete with love and a profound intellectual grasp of the eternal beyond. But you just don't understand, all these words are lost on you.'

‘Beware, my brother,'said Siegmund very softly, almost sadly, ‘it seems to me you're heading in a dangerous dir-ection. You can count on me, if all else - no, I dare not say any more!' Nathaniel suddenly fathomed that the cold, prosaic Siegmund was being very sincere with him, and so he took and shook the proffered hand with all his heart.

Nathaniel had completely forgotten that there was a Clara in this world whom he once loved; his mother, Lothar, everyone had slipped from his consciousness, he only lived for Olympia, beside whom he sat for hours every day, and to whom he held forth on his love, on a life flushed with sympathy, on their psychic affinity - to all of which Olympia listened with deep devotion. From the depths of his desk drawers Nathaniel fetched out everything he had ever written. Poems, fantasies, visions, novels, stories, to which were added daily all sorts of high-flown sonnets, stanzas,canzone - all of it he tire-lessly read to Olympia for hours on end.

But he had never had such a lovely listener. She did not embroider and knit, she did not peer out of the win-dow, she fed no birds, she played with no lapdogs or cuddly cats, she practised no paper-cutting or did any-thing else with her hands, she held back no furtive yawns with a quiet, forced cough - in short, for hours and hours she peered with a fixed and steady gaze into the eye of her beloved without fidgeting or budging, and her gaze grew ever livelier and more intense. Only when Nathaniel finally stood up and kissed her on the hand, and even on the mouth, did she respond: ‘Oh, oh!' Followed with: ‘Good night, my dear!'

‘Oh you beautiful, oh you profound spirit,'Nathaniel cried out when he reached his room, ‘only you, you alone completely understand me.' He experienced an inner bliss when he pondered what a wondrous harmony manifested itself ever more each day between his and Olympia's spir-its; for it seemed to him as if Olympia had grasped his works, his poetic gift, from the depths of her soul, indeed that her voice came from the bottom of her innermost self. That must be true, he thought; for Olympia never uttered any more words than those already noted above. But when, at his most lucid moments, for instance in the morning upon waking, Nathaniel really pondered Olym-pia's total passivity and laconic manner, he shrugged it off: ‘What are words - words! Her heavenly gaze says more than any hollow language. Can any child of heaven fit herself into the narrow compass of a pitiful earthly need?'

Professor Spalanzani seemed to be absolutely delighted by the relationship between his daughter and Nathaniel; he gave them all sorts of unequivocal signs of his approval and when Nathaniel finally dared to allude to a future bond with Olympia, a smile spread over Spalanzani's face and he replied that he would leave it to his daughter to decide of her own free will. Emboldened by these words, with burning desire in his heart, Nathaniel decided to implore Olympia the very next day to declare clearly in plain words what her dear loving look had long since told him, that she wished to be his for evermore. He searched for the ring that his mother had given him when he left home to give to Olympia as a symbol of his commitment to their budding, blossoming life together. While looking for it he happened on Clara's and Lothar's letters; indifferent, he flung them aside, found the ring, stuffed it in his pocket and ran over to see Olympia.

Even from the doorstep, and from the vestibule, he heard a strange din; it appeared to emanate from Spalan-zani's study. A stamping of feet - a clatter - a shoving - a pounding on the door, interspersed with coarse words and hurled imprecations. ‘Let go! Let me go! You wretch! You cursed creature! Did I put my life and limb on the line for that?' - ‘Ha ha ha ha! - that was not our arrangement - it was me, me who made the eyes!' - ‘And I the mechanical clockwork!' - ‘Poor devil with your clockwork-you filthy cur of a simple-minded clockmaker!' - ‘Get out! - Satan! - Stop!' - ‘Organ grinder!' - ‘Devilish beast! - Stop - Get out - Let go!' It was the voices of Spalanzani and that disgusting Coppelius that screeched and raged.

Nathaniel burst in, gripped by an unspeakable terror. The Professor held a female figure by the shoulders, the Italian Coppola held her by the feet; they tugged and tore her here and there, furiously fighting for possession. Nathaniel recoiled in profound horror when he recog-nized the figure as Olympia; flaring up in a wild fit of anger, he was about to tear his beloved out of their strug - gling grip - but at that very moment, with a mighty burst of strength, Coppola managed to yank the figure free of the Professor's hands and, with a pivot, swinging her in his direction, managed to land Nathaniel such a stunning blow that it made him tumble backwards over the work table, toppling and knocking down the phials, retorts, bottles and measuring glasses. All the equipment smashed in a thousand pieces on the floor. Then Coppola flung the figure over his shoulder and raced with a repulsive, shrill laugh down the steps, so that the ugly dangling feet of the figure banged with a wooden thud and thump on the steps. Stunned, Nathaniel stood up - he had seen all too clearly that Olympia's deathly pallid wax face had no eyes, but black hollows in their stead; she was a lifeless doll.

Spalanzani thrashed around on the floor; glass shards had cut his head, chest and arms, blood spurted as though from a fountain. But he pulled himself together. ‘After him - after him - why do you waver? Coppelius - Coppelius has robbed me of my finest automaton-twenty years'work - life and limb invested - the clockwork - speech - step - all mine - the eyes - the eyes robbed from you. Cursed hellhound! After him-fetch me back Olympia-there are her eyes!'

Then Nathaniel spotted a pair of bloody eyes peering at him from the floor. Spalanzani grasped them with his uninjured hand and flung them at him so that they struck him on the breast. Then madness grabbed him with its burning claws and bored its way into his heart of hearts, tearing his thinking and feeling to shreds. ‘Hopla - hopla - hopla! - ring of fire - ring of fire! Spin around, ring of fire - merrily - merrily! - wooden doll, hopla, lovely little wooden doll - turn turn!' - whereupon he flung himself at the Professor and pressed his fingers to his throat. He would have strangled him, but, roused by the racket, many people stormed in, tore the raging Nathaniel from the Professor's neck, managed to revive the old man and thereby saved his life. As strong as he was, Siegmund was not able to restrain the madman, who kept on screaming in a terrifying voice: ‘Wooden doll, turn, turn!' and lashed about him with balled fists. Finally, it took the combined strength of many men to overpower him, fling him to the floor and tie him up. His words dissolved in a terrible beastly bellowing. In this pitiful state, still raving in a ghastly frenzy, he was taken to the madhouse.

But before I continue, gracious reader, with my account of the fate of that poor unfortunate, Nathaniel, those of you who took an interest in the masterful mechanic and maker of automatons, Spalanzani, can rest assured that he completely recuperated from his wounds. He was forced to leave the university, as Nathaniel's story had stirred up a public uproar and it was commonly held to be an altogether fraudulent swindle to try to pass off a wooden doll for a living person in proper society (for Olympia had effectively pulled the wool over their eyes). Jurists went so far as to call it a refined, and, therefore, all the harder to punish, swindle, which he succeeded in pulling off so skilfully that everyone (except for a few sharp-eyed students) was taken in, although they now put on a smart façade and pointed out all sorts of things that seemed suspicious to them at the time. But such smart-alecs ultimately brought no hard and fast evidence to the case. For instance, could it possibly have aroused anyone's suspicion that, according to the testimony of one elegant invitee, Olympia more often sneezed than yawned? This, maintained said elegant invitee, was the automaton's hidden rewind mechanism that noticeably creaked in the process, etc.

A professor of poetry and rhetoric took a pinch of snuff, snapped the tin shut, cleared his throat and launched into his erudite discourse: ‘Most honoured ladies and gentlemen, can't you see where the shoe pinches? The whole thing is an allegory - a long-drawn-out metaphor! You catch my drift! Sapienti sat!'

But many honoured gentlemen derived little consola-tion from this view; the story of the automaton had taken root and a dreadful distrust of human figures seeped into their souls. In order to be completely convinced that they were not in love with a wooden doll, quite a few lovers demanded that their beloved sing something off-key and dance out of step, that they embroider and knit while being read to, play with Bowser, etc. , and above all that they not just listen, but also occasionally say something in such a way as to demonstrate that their words necessar-ily derive from actual thought and feeling. Consequently the loving bond of many couples grew stronger and all the more attractive, but others quietly drifted apart. ‘One can hardly be held accountable for this,' was the common excuse. Yawning was all the rage at social teas, but people refrained from sneezing, so as to dispel any suspicions. Spalanzani was obliged to leave the town, as has already been said, to escape the criminal investigation into his fraudulent introduction of an automaton into human soci-ety. Coppola also vanished.

When Nathaniel awakened, as though from an oppres-sive and terrible dream, he batted his eyes open and felt himself infused with an indescribable sense of well-being and heavenly warmth. He lay in his bed in his room in his father's house; Clara was bent over him and his mother and Lothar stood close by.

‘At last, at last, oh my dearly beloved Nathaniel, you've pulled through at last, and now you're mine again!' Clara spoke the words with all her heart and took Nathaniel in her arms.

But bright, burning tears of sadness and rapture poured from his eyes and he moaned deeply: ‘My Clara, my Clara!' Siegmund, who had faithfully stood by his friend in dire moments, entered the room. Nathaniel held out his hand: ‘You, my faithful brother in need, you never abandoned me.'

Every last trace of madness was gone, and soon Nathaniel got better in the painstaking care of his mother, his beloved and his friends. Fortune had in the meantime returned to the house; for a miserly old uncle, from whom no one hoped to inherit a penny, had died and left Nathaniel's mother, in addition to a considerable fortune, a small estate in a pleasant district not far from the city. There they intended to move together, mother, Nathaniel with his Clara, whom he now planned to marry, and Lothar. Nathaniel had become more gentle and childlike than ever and only now really recognized Clara's heavenly pure, radiant spirit. No one reminded him, not even breathing the slightest hint, of the recent past.

It was only when Siegmund prepared to leave that Nathaniel spoke up: ‘By God, my brother, I was heading down the path of no return, but in the nick of time an angel made me find the right way! It was my Clara, after all!' Siegmund cut him off, fearing that bitter memories might once again make him start raving.

The time approached when the four happy people planned to move out to the small country estate. At mid-day they went walking through the streets of the city, having bought some things. The tall town hall tower cast a long shadow over the market place. ‘Oh!' said Clara, ‘let's climb it one last time and gaze out at the distant mountains!' No sooner said than done! Nathaniel and Clara both climbed the steps, mother went home with the maid, and Lothar, who was disinclined to mount the many steps, stayed down below. Now the two lovers stood arm in arm at the tower's highest lookout gallery and peered at the sweet-scented ring of woods, beyond which the blue mountains loomed like a giant city.

‘Will you look at that strange little grey bush that seems to be slowly drawing near?' asked Clara.

Nathaniel mechanically reached into his coat pocket; he found Coppola's looking-glass and turned it sideways. There was Clara standing in the eye of the lens. A spas-modic quiver started up in his veins and arteries - turning deathly pale, he peered at Clara, but soon sparks of fire flashed from his rolling eyes; he let out a horrible cry like a hunted animal, jumped high in the air and with a curi-ous cackle proceeded to scream out shrilly: ‘Turn, little wooden doll, turn!' - and with a great burst of strength he grabbed hold of Clara and tried to hurl her off the balcony, but Clara clung for dear life to the metal railing.

Hearing the madman raving and Clara's terrified screams, and gripped by a terrible foreboding, Lothar clambered up the stairs, but the door to the second flight of steps was locked. Clara's piteous screams sounded louder and louder. Consumed with anger and fear, Lothar hurled himself against the door, which finally gave way.

Clara's cries grew fainter and fainter: ‘Help! Save me! Save me!' till her voice went silent.

‘She's done for - murdered by that madman!' Lothar screamed. The door to the lookout gallery was also locked. Desperation turned him into a lion; he broke down the door. God in heaven! Clara dangled in Nathaniel's mad grip over the edge of the railing, only holding on to the cast-iron railing by one hand. Quick as lightning, Lothar grabbed his sister, pulled her to safety and at the very same moment heaved a balled fist into the madman's face so that he tumbled backwards and let go of his prey.

Lothar raced back down the steps, his unconscious sister in his arms. She was saved. Meanwhile, Nathaniel kept flailing about on the lookout gallery and jumped high in the air and cried: ‘Ring of fire, turn! Ring of fire, turn!'

Aroused by the screams, a throng gathered below, including the lawyer Coppelius, who had just come to town and made straight for the market place. Some people wanted to climb the tower to capture the madman, whereupon Coppelius laughed and said: ‘Ha ha, just be patient, he'll be down shortly on his own initiative!' and looked on as the others raced up the steps.

Nathaniel suddenly stopped dead in his tracks. He leant down, spotted Coppelius below and with a shrill shriek - ‘Ha! Eyes a pretty! Eyes a pretty!' - he leapt over the parapet. As Nathaniel landed, his skull smashed on the cobblestones, while Coppelius disappeared in the crowd.

Some years later Clara was said to have been spotted in some distant town seated, hand in hand, with a friendly man on a bench before the door of a lovely little country house, two bouncing boys playing at her feet. It might, therefore, be fair to suppose that Clara finally found the quiet domestic bliss that suited her cheerful, life-loving spirit and that Nathaniel in his torn and troubled state could never have given her.

[16]Daniel Niklaus Chodowiecki (1726-1801), Polish-German painter and printmaker.

[17]Count Alessandro di Cagliostro, aka Giuseppe Balsamo (1743-95), Italian occultist, forger and adventurer.

断篇残句，略记迷思

*

错误比真理更易被发现。前者流于表面，因而更易掌控；后者扎根深处，并非人人都可探知。

*

我们都以过去为生，又因过去而亡。

*

当我们需要学习某个伟大的事物时，便会立刻用我们与生俱来的可怜与不足来逃避学习。尽管如此，我们总还能学到些东西。

*

德国人根本不在乎与人共处，而是重视独处。无论是谁，都有一种专属自己的独处方式，不愿被他人剥夺。

*

经验的道德世界大部分都只由恶意和嫉妒构成。

*

迷信是生活的诗学，所以诗人迷信不是坏事。

*

信任是一个神奇的东西。仅听信一人之言，此人有可能出错或自欺欺人；而听信众人之言，众人也会发生同样的事情。所以人们往往不能发现真相。

*

我们不该心怀恶念，希望他人遭遇不快的生活。然而对于那些偶然陷入其中的人而言，这恰恰是他们性格的试金石，也考验着他们生而为人的最核心品质。

*

一个见识有限的老实人往往能看穿最精明的骗子。

*

一个人如果感受不到爱意，那么就必须学会阿谀奉承，否则他将无法应付生活。

*

面对批评，人们既不能自卫，也无法反抗。必须蔑然视之，这样就能渐渐接受批评的存在。

*

群体离不开能干的人，却又总是感受到来自能者的压力。

*

不管是谁，哪怕是我的仆人，只要指出了我的错误，那么他就是我的主人。

*

自上而下或自下而上的往事，最终总会彼此相遇。

*

如果要求人们履行义务，却不赋予其任何权利，那么就必须开出丰厚的报酬。

*

一个地方的所谓浪漫，是一种宁静的崇高之感，这种感觉以历史的形式呈现，或者与之等同地，表现为孤独、疏离、避世。

*

辉煌雄壮的教堂圣歌《降临吧，造物之神》实际上完全是对天才的召唤，正因如此，它在精神强大的人们之中引起了强烈共鸣。

*

美体现了自然法则的奥秘，如果没有美这样具象化的呈现，我们将永远无从知晓自然法则的内涵。

*

我能保证直白坦率，却无法承诺不偏不倚。

*

不念恩义始终是一种弱点。我从未见过心无感激的能干之人。

*

我们是如此的目光短浅，总以为自己很有道理。于是可以想象，一个思维超群的人不但会犯错误，甚至还会为之欣喜。

*

我们很少看到仅凭温和的方式能够达到美好而正确的目的。相反，实际情况往往是迂腐导致迟滞不前，狂妄导致仓促行事。

*

文字和图像是相关联的，它们总在找寻彼此，就像我们在比喻与寓言中充分了解到的那样。一直以来，耳朵听到的话语或音乐，同样也会浮现在眼前。所以当我们还是小孩子时，在法典和上帝的施恩书中、在《圣经》和插图课本中，总能看到文字和图片均衡分布。说出无法用图像描绘的事物，或者画出无法用语言阐明的东西，这是完全合理的。然而人们经常错误地认识两者的关系，明明该使用图像，却要用语言表述，从而诞生了象征意义上加倍邪恶的神秘怪物。

*

任何投身于科学研究的人，都会先后受困于外界的阻挠与关注。人们一开始不愿承认我们研究成果的价值，而后又装模作样，好像已经知晓我们将会研究出什么成果。

*

一本逸事和格言汇编对于老于世故的人们来说价值连城，前提是他知道如何恰当地在对话中穿插前者，在合适的情景下想起后者。

*

人们说：“艺术家们，研究自然吧！”然而从平凡中提炼高贵、用畸形锻造美丽，并非小事。

*

失去判断，也就失去了记忆。

*

世界是一座有裂缝的钟，只会吱嘎作响，不能鸣声报时。

*

人们一定要善意地容忍青年业余爱好者的鲁莽冒失，因为待到日后年岁稍长，他们会成为艺术和大师们最忠实的拥趸。

*

对于坏到骨子里的恶人而言，幸灾乐祸是他们唯一的乐趣。

*

聪慧之人永远是最好的百科全书。

*

有些人从不犯错，因为他们从不做理性的事。

*

当我认识到我与自身、我与外部世界的关系时，我就称其为真理。如此一来，人人都有一个属于自己的真理，而且它永远不会改变。

*

特殊总会被普遍打败，而普遍总要让自己适应特殊。

*

没有人能主宰真正的创造力，只能任由它天马行空，自由发挥。

*

无论是谁，只要大自然开始向他揭示其公开的奥秘，他就会不可抗拒地向往自然最高贵的诠释者——艺术。

*

时间本身就是一种元素。

*

一个人永远无法知道，自己被赋予了多少人性。

*

对于理解毫无助益的差别，就不是差别。

*

显花植物[1]中仍然保留着许多隐花植物[2]的性状，即使用数百年的时间也不足以破解其中的奥秘。

*

混淆两个辅音，可能是因为发音器官不够灵活；而混淆单元音和双元音，则是因为自负而头脑发热。

*

一个人如果打算学习全部的法律，那么就根本不会有时间去触犯法律。

*

人不能为所有人而活，尤其不能为那些自己不愿与之相处的人而活。

*

对于后世的召唤来源于一种纯粹的生动感受，即确有永恒不朽的存在，即便不能立时得到认可，但必将为小众所喜爱，最终受到大众的追捧。

*

秘密还不是奇迹。

*

演员们俘获观众的心，却不会付出真情，他们是优雅的骗子。

*

草率而狂热地追捧有问题的天才，是我早年犯过的错误，而我永远也无法彻底摆脱它。

*

我愿与你坦诚相待，不想一拍两散，然而却无法做到。你行为不端，脚踩两只船，不仅没有吸引来追求者，还失去了自己的朋友。这该如何收场啊！

*

无论身居高位，还是出身卑微，人人都始终要为自己的人性买单。

*

自由作家如今炙手可热，全体公众都拜倒在他们脚下。

*

每当我听到人们谈论自由的创意想法时，都惊讶于人们竟如此热衷那些空洞无物的言论：一个想法是不可能自由的！它是强劲有力、自成一体的，如此便完成了上帝交付与它的神圣使命——富有创造力。相比而言，一个概念就更加不自由，因为它被赋予了另一个完全不同的使命。

*

然而，若要找寻自由的踪迹，那么就必须观察人们的态度，态度是有生命力的情绪。

*

但是态度很少是自由的，因为它直接来源于人本身，来源于人身边最亲近的关系和他的需求。

*

我们就此搁笔。我们应该以此为标准，衡量每天所听到的言论！

*

（面对自然，）我们一直以来只能利用自己的眼睛和想象事物的方式来加以探索。而自然本身就知道它现在想要什么，它曾经想要什么。

告诉我，你所在的地方！——阿基米德

去开发，你所在的地方！——诺泽[3]

去说明，你所在的地方！——歌德

*

事物的旁观者总在竭力找寻普适的因果关系，并把所有类似的现象都归结于某一个共同的诱因，却很少考虑最直接的缘由。

*

聪明之人不会遭遇微小的蠢事。

*

任何一件艺术品，无论大小，及至最微小的细节，都全部取决于创作理念。

*

不存在没有比喻的诗，因为诗本身就是个比喻。

*

一位好脾气的老考官对一名学生耳语道：“你还什么都没学到呢。[4]”然后让他通过了考试。

*

卓越的事物往往深不可测，你可以用自己喜欢的方式开始接触它。

*

最平庸的小说也总好过平庸的读者，最差的小说也会对这一体裁做出些许贡献，使其整体精彩绝伦。

*

我在普遍的事物上花费了大量时间，直至我意识到优秀的人们在特殊领域取得的成就。

*

其实，只有当人们所知甚少时，才会以为自己了解某个事物。随着知识的积累，怀疑也会逐渐加深。

*

实际上，一个人的可爱之处在于他所犯下的错误。

*

德国人知道如何修正他人，却不知道如何施以援手。

*

有些人爱着自己的同类并在人群中找寻他们；有些人则爱着并追求与自己完全相反的人。

*

长期厌世之人必将变得凄惨可悲，比如视我们为敌的那些人就是这种情况。

*

妒忌与憎恶将观察者的视野限制在事物表面，哪怕他们已经具备了洞察力也无法深入。而如果借助善良与爱心的力量，就可以看穿世界和人心，如此他便可以期望达到至高境界了。

*

一位英国批评家称赞我拥有“全面的能力”，对此我必须致以最诚挚的感谢。

*

对于每一个友好的德国人而言，些许诗学天赋是有可取之处的，有了它就可以通过正确的方式，利用一定程度的尊重和不满来掩盖自己内心的真实想法，不管这是一种怎样的想法。

*

物质本身呈现在所有人的眼前，其内涵只有行家里手才能发掘，而其组成形式对于大多数人来说，就是一个谜。

*

人们偏爱生机与活力，青春又通过一颗不老的心得以实现。

*

我们以自己选择的方式认知世界，它总有黑白两面。

*

在实际生活中，人们总是一错再错，因此我们必须不厌其烦地重复说教正确的做法。

*

在罗马，除了全体罗马人之外，还有一群由雕像组成的民众。类似地，在我们所处的真实世界之外，还有一个几乎更加强大的幻想世界，那里居住着大多数的人。

*

人类就像红海：一条界线无法将他们彻底隔绝，就在界线的末端处，他们又会彼此交融。

*

辨别真实与虚假，区分确定与模糊，判定某件事应该受到怀疑还是谴责，这是历史学家的职责所在。

*

只有重视当下的人才会写出编年史。

*

思想一再重现，信念传播蔓延，形势一去不回。

*

在所有民族中，希腊人对生活的幻想最为美妙。

*

译者好比忙碌的皮条客，极力向我们推荐一位半遮半掩的美女，这是因为他们激起了我们对原著无法抗拒的向往。

*

我们乐于推崇先人，却不愿夸奖后代。只有父亲才不会嫉妒儿子的才能。

*

自谦不是什么难事，然而在虎落平阳的下坡路上，当你已经落后，还能承认不如你的人实则在你之上，就十分难得了。

*

我们的所有成就，都是舍弃自身，以求存在。

*

我们的所作所为都会令人倦怠，那些不知疲倦的人是幸福的！

*

希望是不幸之人的第二灵魂。

*

那些快乐地做事，并欣喜于自我成就的人，是幸福的。

*

人们心中同样存在着一种臣服于人的渴望，因此法国人的骑士制度实为一种“奴役”[5]。

*

剧院里的视觉和听觉快感极大地限制了人们的反思。

*

经验可以无限延伸，而理论则不能在相同意义上净化并完善。对于前者，整个宇宙向着各个方向展开；而后者则封闭在人类能力的边界之内。因此，所有构建理论的模式都必定重现，这也解释了为什么会出现那样奇怪的现象：在丰富广博的经验中，一个狭隘的理论却能重新赢得人们青睐。

*

摆在我们眼前的永远是同一个世界，我们一直观察它或者猜度它。而生活在真实或虚假之中的也永远是同一批人，置身于后者的人们感到更加舒适。

*

真理与我们的天性相悖，谬误则不然，原因很简单：真理要求我们意识到自己的狭隘，而谬误却讨好我们，仿佛我们以某种方式脱离了局限。

*

自德国人“崛起”[6]已有将近二十年的时间。一旦他们注意到了这点，他们就一定能意识到自己有多奇怪了。

*

相信自己可以做到曾经能够做到的事，是很自然的；而有些人相信自己可以做到自己从未做到过的事，这可能很奇怪，但并不罕见。

*

古往今来，对科学进步做出贡献的都是个人，而非时代自身。毒死苏格拉底也好，烧死扬·胡斯[7]也罢，都是时代的所作所为，它是一成不变的。

*

真正的象征主义，用特殊表现一般，并非把普通事物演绎为梦境或幻影，而是在片刻之间生动地揭示玄妙莫测的东西。

*

所有理想的事物，一旦现实对其提出要求，就会将现实事物与其自身一并吞没。信贷（纸币）与白银的关系、信贷与自身的关系就是这样。

*

技艺精湛常被视为利己主义。

*

一旦优秀的作品和它们值得颂扬的美德宣告终结，新教徒的多愁善感就立马取而代之。

*

如果人们能够挑选出好的建议，那么仿佛他自己就已经具备完成这件事的能力了。

*

所有智慧之事都已经被思考过了，人们只需将它们再思考一遍。

*

人如何认识自我呢？思考永远不会有用，而应该通过行动认知。着手尝试履行你的义务，很快你就会发现自己是什么样的人。

*

不过你的义务是什么呢？是时代对你的要求。

*

理性世界可以被看作一个巨大的永生个体，他不停地造就必要的事物，甚至通过这种方式主宰了偶然的事物。

*

随着年龄增长，我愈发讨厌一些了不起的人，他们本应该约束自己的本性，从而把自己和身边人从专横的必要性中解放出来。我愈发讨厌他们出于某一个先入为主的错误概念，做着与自己愿望完全矛盾的事。最终，由于整体构想坍塌了，他只能在细节之处兀自烦恼，浪费时间。

*

精明能干之人，期待着吧！你有资格：

从伟人身上——获得仁慈

从当权者身上——获得优待

从务实和善良的人身上——获得帮助

从群体中——获得青睐

从个体中——获得爱！

*

那些业余爱好者习惯在他们竭尽所能之后找借口，说作品还没完成。不言而喻，他们永远也无法完成，因为他们从未真正地开始创作。大师只需寥寥数笔，就大功告成；无论细致与否，作品都已经完成了。最聪明的门外汉在不确定中摸索，越做越怀疑自己最初的设计。直到最后，无法弥补的错误才暴露出来，这样自然无法完成作品。

*

真正的艺术领域中不存在预备学校，只有事先准备。最好的准备其实是让资质平庸的学生参与大师的创作。许多研磨颜料的助手最终成为伟大的画家。

*

另一种准备的方式是模仿，通过模仿一位化繁为简的大师，不经意地激发人们与生俱来的能力。

*

我们坚信艺术家研究自然的必要性和价值，然而也不否认，当意识到这种值得表扬的努力被滥用时，我们有多心痛。

*

我们深信，如果年轻的艺术家在研究自然的同时，不会思考如何打磨每一处细节，使其融为一体，从而转变为一幅美丽的图画，最后用画框装裱，那么他们就应该少接触甚至完全放弃对自然的研究，心甘情愿地把这份工作交给爱好者或者专家。

*

世界上的许多美是遗世独立的，但灵魂需要发现它们彼此之间的关联并以此创作出艺术品。花朵的魅力来源于停在它身旁的昆虫，来源于滋润它的露水，来源于为它提供养分的容器。每一丛灌木、每一棵树，都是因为周围的岩石和小溪而获得意义，都是因为一个适度的距离而增强了魅力。对于人类和所有动物而言，也是如此。

*

通过这种方法，年轻艺术家获得的好处是多样的。他学会了将彼此相关的事物组合在一起的最佳方式，而当他按照这种方式聪明地构思时，一定会贡献不少发明创造，一定会具备利用单一个体创造丰富整体的能力。

*

除了满足艺术教育的应有之义，他还取得了一个巨大的、不容忽视的优势：他学会了如何创作畅销的、在艺术爱好者看来优美而生动的画作。

*

这种类型的作品不必精雕细琢、尽善尽美，只要构思精巧、结构完整，它就能赢得艺术爱好者的青睐，效果甚至超过了那些更加大气磅礴、内容更为详尽的作品。

*

让每一个年轻艺术家都去翻看他素描本和画夹里的草稿，想想运用上面的方法，能从中创作出多少赏心悦目、备受欢迎的作品吧！

*

我们这里探讨的不是更高层次的艺术，当然也可以对其进行讨论。我们不过是给艺术家一个警示，让他们迷途知返，为他们指明通往高级艺术的道路。

*

让艺术家们实践半年，不用炭笔，不用画刷，除非他有描绘眼前自然事物或风景的强烈愿望。如果他有天赋，那么我们所暗示的目的，很快就会显现出来。

*

告诉我你与谁交往，那么我就能说出你是什么样的人；如果我了解你正在做什么，我就能知道你会成为什么样的人。

*

每个人都必须按照自己的方式思考，因为他总能依据自己的思路发现某一个或者某一类真理，令他一生受益。但他不可以放任自己的思想恣意妄为，而应该时时自我监督，赤裸裸的本能并不适合人类。

*

无限制的行为，无论属于哪种类型，都会让人堕落。

*

人造和自然的作品中，最值得注意的是创作它的目的。

*

人们会迷失自我，也会在与他人相处时犯错，因为他们把手段当成了目的，而后徒劳无功，甚至令人讨厌。

*

我们的所思、所做，都是如此完美的纯粹和美好，外界的干预只会破坏它。于是我们可以保持优势，接下来只需要把错放的东西归位，将毁掉的东西复原。

*

甄别不同程度的错误，并将正确的内容替换在相应的部分，是一件困难而辛苦的工作。

*

真理不必总以具象出现，它只要作为一种精神四处游荡，在所到之处促成和谐，那就足够了，就像钟声庄严而友善地回响在空中一样。

*

当我询问一些年轻的德国画家，甚至包括那些曾经旅居意大利的画家，为什么他们总要使用那样令人生厌的艳俗色调（尤其是在风景画中），为什么在画中丝毫不见和谐之美的踪迹，他们就以傲慢无礼的口吻振振有词地回答说，自己就是这样看待自然的。

*

康德为我们指出，存在一种理性批判，它是人类所具备的最高能力，也是人类自我反省的原因。康德的言论为我们带来了多大好处，人人都可自行查看。而我在此意义上也要提出一个观点，即一种感性批判也是必需的，如果艺术——尤其是德国艺术——还想以某种方式复苏并且以一种令人愉快的活泼步调向前进步的话。

*

为理性而生的人们需要接受大量的教育，这种教育会通过父母和老师的悉心照顾、通过温和的示范和严格的训练渐渐显现。同样地，还有正在逐渐成长的艺术家，但不是天生完美，他们可能天生具有清晰的观察力，向形状、比例、动作投去欣喜的目光，但对于更高级的组合、姿态、光线、阴影、颜色缺乏天生的洞察力，而自己却不会意识到这一点。

*

如果他不愿向技艺更为高超的前辈和当代艺术家学习，弥补自己的不足，以求成为真正的艺术家，那么他就会误入歧途，抱残守缺，还以为这是在保护自己的原创性。因为我们所拥有的不仅仅是与生俱来的禀赋，还有后天能够习得的技能，这两者共同造就了我们。

*

普遍概念和狂妄傲慢总有可能酿成恐怖的悲剧。

*

光凭吹气是不能演奏笛子的，你们还必须让手指动起来。

*

植物学家们有一个植物种类库，他们称其为“不完全的[8]”。人们也可以说，存在不完整的、不全面的人，这些人的渴望及追求与他们的行动及成果不成比例。

*

资质最差的人可能是完满的，前提是他们要在自己的能力范围内活动。然而如果缺失了最重要的恰当比例，即便是最优秀的长处也会暗淡、失效和破碎。这种灾难性的缺失现在愈发常见，因为又有谁能跟得上这个日益膨胀、发展极度迅猛的当下，满足它提出的所有要求呢？

*

有些人既聪明又主动，还能了解并恰当而巧妙地利用自己的能力，只有他们才能了解世界的真实面目。

*

大错特错：高估自己的能力，低估自己的价值。

*

我时不时会遇到这样一种年轻人，在他身上我不期望看到任何改变和提升。然而让我担心的是，我看到一些十分优秀的人在时代的浪潮中随波逐流，我一直想要提醒他们的是：正因为一个人的舢板易碎，他的手上才会拿着船桨。这样他就不会被暴虐的风浪裹挟，而可以按照自己的想法行动。

*

但是一个年轻人如何才能看清，那些人人追求、赞同、支持的东西，实则是有害而应该受到谴责的？为什么他不该放任自我以及自己的天性一起跟随潮流？

*

我们这个时代等不及任何事物的成熟，最大的悲哀是下一秒会将上一秒吞噬，虚度光阴的人们总是生活拮据，勉强糊口，无所作为。用来填满报纸版面的新闻已经足够多了！一个聪明的人或许还能够插入一两条。这样一来，一个人所做的事、所付出的努力、所写的文字，包括他计划中的创作，都会被公之于众。没有人被允许快乐或忧伤，除非作为他人的消遣，于是新闻就这样在街头巷尾传播，进而在城市之间、国家之间扩散，最终在各个大洲之间流行开来。这一切都基于速度至上的原则。

*

就像蒸汽机很难被压制一样，人们的行为也很难被规范：商贸蓬勃繁荣，纸币迅速流通，人们债台高筑，为的却是偿还之前的欠款。这一切对于现在的年轻人而言，都是可怕的东西。如果他天生性情沉静，既不会向世界索取无度，也不会任由外界定义自己，那么他将无比幸福！

*

然而当下的主流观念在方方面面威胁着他，所以最为重要的是及早让他看清自己的本心，明确自己的方向。

*

随着人年岁渐长，天真无邪的话语和行为变得愈发珍贵。我一直试图向身边人说明真诚、直白和轻率之间的区别，以及与其说三者之间有什么不同，莫不如说是一种从最无害到最有害的过渡，对其必须加以观察或者更多地去感受。

*

于是我们必须要训练自己为人处世的技巧，否则我们就有可能在无意间失去从别人那里获得的好意。人们或许能在生活中自己逐渐意识到这一点，不过事先一定会付出巨大的代价。可惜的是，我们并不能为后人省下这笔学费。

*

艺术和科学之于生活，是一种多变的关系，受到艺术和科学所处的层次、时代的特性以及其他众多偶然因素的影响。因此，要说明这一切并非易事。

诗学往往在各种情况的最初阶段发挥作用，无论这里所说的情况是完全原始的，还是半开化的，抑或是指某一文化通过认知外来文化而正在转变。在这些情况下，人们可以说，新事物的作用完全得以发挥。

*

而音乐领域的上佳之作则并不需要多少创新，实际上，一个音乐作品越是经典，人们就越熟悉它，因而它能发挥的作用也就越大。

*

或许，音乐将艺术的价值体现得最为淋漓尽致，因为它的创作不需要用量精准的原材料，它是纯粹的形式和内容，使表达的一切东西变得高级而尊贵。

*

音乐要么是神圣的，要么是世俗的。音乐的神圣完全与音乐的价值相称，它也实现了音乐对生活影响的最大化，这种影响历经漫长的岁月却始终如一。世俗的音乐则应该完全是令人愉悦的。

*

杂糅了神圣和世俗特质的音乐是亵渎上帝的、粗制滥造的，它喜欢宣泄脆弱、可怜和悲哀的情绪，听上去乏味无聊。因为一方面，它不够庄重肃穆，称不上神圣；另一方面，它又缺乏世俗音乐的主要特征——令人愉悦。

*

教堂音乐的神圣庄严与世俗音乐的活泼欢快是两个核心，真正的音乐都围绕在它们周围。在这两点核心上，音乐总会不可避免地催生出虔诚或舞蹈。将两者混合会导致错误，将两者削弱会导致乏味，而如果音乐寻求与教育性的、描写性的以及其他类似的诗歌结合起来，那么就会变得冰冷。

*

事实上，雕塑艺术中，只有那些顶级的作品才能发挥作用。诚然，出于一两个原因，中等水平的作品会给我们留下深刻印象，但是它们导致的困惑多于它们带来的快乐。

因此，雕塑艺术必须寻找对于素材的兴趣，这种兴趣往往出现在名人画像中。然而如果雕塑艺术打算同时兼顾真实和高贵的话，那么在此方面它也要达到一定的高度。

*

绘画是所有艺术中最自由、最闲适的一种。说它最自由，是因为虽然从原料和创作对象的角度出发，有些作品只能算作手工艺品，几乎称不上艺术，但是也会有许多人宽容它，喜欢它。还有一部分原因在于，不管一个人是否接受过教育，都会对一个工于技法而空洞无物的作品赞叹不已。只需要稍稍接近一些艺术，便可以更受欢迎。真实的颜色、外表和可见对象彼此之间的关系已经令人赏心悦目，而既然人眼已经对任何事物见怪不怪，那么一个错误形象或者画面对于视觉的冲击，就不如杂音对听觉的冲击大。人们可以容忍最糟糕的图画，因为人们对那些外表更加丑陋的东西都已经司空见惯了。一个画家只要和艺术家稍稍沾边，就已经可以比同样层次的音乐家更受欢迎了；此外，一个资质平庸的画家至少可以按照自己的意愿单干，而一个资质平庸的音乐家必须通过与人合作来寻求一些共鸣。

*

当我们探讨艺术作品时，是否应该比较它们孰高孰低？我的回答是：艺术鉴赏家应该比较，因为他们的脑海中存在这样的概念，知道艺术可以并应该创作出什么样的作品。对于还在接受艺术教育的业余爱好者们来说，如果想收获最多，那么就不应比较，而应该单独鉴赏每一个作品：这样一来，他会渐渐形成对于普遍事物的直觉和观念。外行之人对于艺术品的比较，实则只会方便他们骄傲自负地妄下论断。

*

对于真理的热爱表现为到处发现并珍惜美好的事物。

*

历史学的人情味表现为歌颂当代的美德与成就时，也不忘考虑前人的功德。

*

历史给我们的最好的东西，就是它所激起的热情。

*

特质唤醒特质。

*

人们必须想到，许多人也想表达一些有意义的东西，即便内容不多，但依旧为世界带来了一些特别的东西。

*

深入而认真思考的人们与大众关系不佳。

*

如果要我倾听别人的观点，那这一观点一定是以一种积极的方式表达的。那些麻烦的想法在我自己的脑子里已经够多了。

*

迷信是人类本性的一部分，当我们想要将其彻底驱逐时，它会逃到最奇怪的角落里，等它以为安全了一些时，又从那里突然冒出来。

*

如果我们不追求过于细致地了解事物，那么我们会掌握更多知识。只有当一个物体以四十五度角的姿态呈现时，我们才能理解它。

*

显微镜和望远镜实则扰乱了人类天生的感官。

*

我对很多事情保持沉默，因为我不想误导人们。如果惹我生气的事情让他们感到高兴，我就会心满意足。

*

任何解放我们的思想却没有让我们主宰自我的东西，都会使人堕落。

*

一件艺术品的内容比它的创作方式更令人感兴趣。人们可以详细地了解前者，却无法完整地掌握后者。所以人们在欣赏作品时会找出重点，最终当人们仔细观察这些地方，就会发现整体的效果并没有缺失，只是无人知晓而已。

*

“诗人是从哪里想出这一句的？”这一问题也仅仅是对内容的提问，没有人能从中读出有关方式的东西。

*

想象力只有通过艺术，尤其是诗歌，才能得以规范。最可怕的是没有品位的想象力。

*

矫揉造作是一种畸形的理想主义，一种主观的意识，因此它往往并不缺乏智慧的成分。

*

文献学家依赖传世文本的一致性。比如有一份手稿，它存在真实的漏洞和笔误，导致文义中断，以及其他可能被人指责的不足之处。而后又出现了一份抄本，接着冒出来了第三个，比较这些版本对于理解和理性看待原作的意义越来越大。他进一步深入研究，要求自己在不借助外界工具的情况下，更多地掌握并描述所讨论问题的一致性。因为这需要一种特殊技巧，要求对已故作者格外深入的了解和一定程度的创造力。所以人们不该责备文献学家对于鉴赏品位品头论足，即使他们在这方面并非每次都成功。

*

诗人依赖描写。描写的最高境界是可以与真实媲美，这意味着诗人的描写如此活灵活现，以至于人人都以为那与真实情况一般无二。最高水平的诗歌是表现外在的，它越是想回归内在，质量就越是下降。有些诗歌只描绘内在世界而不通过外在使其具象化，或者没有让读者透过内在而感受到外在，这两种诗歌都是诗学堕落至平庸的最后一步。

*

雄辩术依赖于诗歌的所有优势和权利，它抢占了诗歌的地位，还滥用诗歌，以求获得市民生活中某些眼前的、合乎或违背道德的外在优势。

*

文学是断篇的碎片。在发生的事情和人们说出的话中，只有最微小的部分会被书面记录下来。而在人们所记录的内容中，只有极为微小的部分会留存下来。

*

尽管拜伦勋爵的天赋是狂野奔放的、不讨人喜欢的，但几乎没有人能比得上他与生俱来的真实与大气。

*

所谓民歌的真正可贵之处在于，它们的创作主题直接取材于自然。受过良好教育的诗人如果方法得当，也能利用这一优势。

*

但是民歌的优点总有一个前提，即相比于受过教育的人们，普通人能更好地理解简洁的事物。

*

尚未成熟的天才阅读莎士比亚是危险的，莎翁的读者会不由自主地去模仿他，并且误认为自己是在独立创作。

*

只有历史的亲历者才有资格评判历史。这是放诸四海皆准的道理。德国人只有先拥有了自己的文学，才有资格评判文学。

*

一个人只有在享受他人善意的时候，才是真正有生命力的。

*

虔敬不是目的，而是手段，凭借精神最为纯洁的宁静抵达最高级的文化。

*

正因如此，我们发现那些把虔敬当成目的和终点的人们，大多变成了伪君子。

*

当一个人老去时，他需要做的事情比年轻时更多。

*

已经履行义务的人们总感觉自己依然背负着债务，那是因为人们永远无法满足对自我的期待。

*

只有冷酷无情的人才会感受到人性的缺陷，所以为了认清这些缺陷，人们必须变得冷酷，但仅仅是出于这个目的，不能过头。

*

终极的幸福是，我们的不足得到改进，我们的错误得到修正。

*

有三种人只有在特定的时机才能看清：

战争中见真英雄，

愤怒中见真智者，

患难中见真朋友。

*

三种愚人：

傲慢的男人，

恋爱的少女，

嫉妒的妇人。

*

疯子是：

教育蠢材的人，

反驳智者的人，

被空话感染而热血沸腾的人，

相信妓女的人，

与不靠谱之人分享秘密的人。

*

人们只能与自己的同类生活，然而又不能，因为时间一长，他便不能忍受有人与他相同。

*

无论从哪一个角度观察自然，它都能孕育出无限。

*

如果有人想要知道一个东西的位置，那么他此前必定已经找到过它。

[1]显花植物：多指被子植物，花是其特有的生殖器官。

[2]隐花植物：又称孢子植物，在繁殖阶段不形成显著花，通过孢子进行繁殖。

[3]卡尔·威廉·诺泽（Karl Wilhelm Nose, 1753—1835），德国医生、矿物学家。

[4]原文为拉丁语。

[5]原文为法语servage。

[6]指1813年莱比锡民族大会战中，俄罗斯、普鲁士、奥地利及其他各国联军在莱比锡击败拿破仑。

[7]扬·胡斯（约1369—1415），捷克基督教思想家、哲学家、改革家，宗教改革先驱。他认为一切应该以《圣经》为唯一的依归，否定教皇的权威性，反对赎罪券，因此被天主教会视为异端，处以火刑。

[8]原文为意大利语。

Sketchy, Doubtful, Incomplete Jottings

It is much easier to recognize error than to find truth; the former lies on the surface, this is quite manage-able; the latter resides in depth, and this quest is not everyone's business.

*

We all live on the past and perish by the past.

*

When we are called to learn something great, we at once take refuge in our native poverty and yet have still learnt something.

*

The Germans are indifferent about staying together, yet they do want to be on their own. Each person, never mind who he may be, has his own way of being alone and is unwilling to be deprived of this.

*

The empirical-moral world consists largely of bad will and envy.

*

Superstition is the poetry of life; so it does the poet no harm to be superstitious.

*

Trust is a curious matter. Listen only to one person: he may be wrong or deceiving himself; listen to many: they are in the same case, and as a rule you don't really discover the truth.

*

One should not wish anyone disagreeable conditions of life; but for him who is involved in them by chance, they are touchstones of character and of the most decisive value to man.

*

A limited, honest man often sees right through the knavery of the sharpest tricksters.

*

One who feels no love must learn to flatter, otherwise he won't make out.

*

You can neither protect nor defend yourself against criticism; you have to act in defiance of it and this is gradually accepted.

*

The crowd cannot do without efficient people and always finds efficiency burdensome.

*

Anyone who tells on my faults is my master, even if it happens to be my servant.

*

Memoirs from above downwards, or from below upwards: they are always bound to meet.

*

If you demand duties from people and will not con-cede them rights, you have to pay them well.

*

When a landscape is described as romantic, this means that there is a tranquil sense of the sublime in the form of the past, or, what amounts to the same, of solitude, remoteness, seclusion.

*

The splendid liturgical song ‘Veni Creator Spiritus’ is in actual fact a call addressed to genius; and this is also why it appeals powerfully to people who are spirited and strong.

*

Beauty is a manifestation of secret natural laws which without this appearance would have remained eter-nally hidden from us.

*

I can promise to be candid, not, however, to be impartial.

*

Ingratitude is always a kind of weakness. I have never known competent people to be ungrateful.

*

We are all so blinkered that we always imagine we are right; and so we can imagine an extraordinary spirit, a person who not only makes a mistake but even enjoys being wrong.

*

Completely moderate action to achieve what is good and right is very rare; what we usually see is pedantry seeking to retard, impertinence seeking to precipitate.

*

Word and image are correlatives which are always in quest of one another as metaphors and comparisons show us clearly enough. Thus, from of old, what is inwardly said or sung for the ear is at the same time intended for the eye. And so in ages which seem to us childlike, we see in codes of law and salvational doctrine, in bible and in primer, a continual balance of word and image. If they put into words what did not go into images, or formed an image of what could not be put into words, that was quite proper; but people often went wrong about this and used the spoken word instead of the pictorial image, which was the origin of those doubly wicked symbolically mystical monsters.

*

Anyone who devotes himself to the sciences suffers, firstly through retardations and then through preoc-cupations. To begin with, people are reluctant to admit the value of what we are providing; later on they act as though they already knew what we might be able to provide.

*

A collection of anecdotes and maxims is the greatest treasure for a man of the world-as long as he knows how to weave the former into apposite points of the course of conversation, and to recall the latter on fitting occasions.

*

People say, ‘Artist, study nature!' But it is no small matter to develop what is noble out of what is com-mon, beauty out of what lacks form.

*

Where concern is lost, memory fares likewise.

*

The world is a bell that is cracked: it clatters, but does not ring out clearly.

*

One must put up kindly with the pressing overtures of young dilettantes: with age they become the truest votaries of art and of the master.

*

When people really deteriorate, their only contribu-tion is malicious joy in the misfortune of others.

*

Intelligent people are always the best encyclopaedia.

*

There are people who never make mistakes because they never have sensible projects.

*

Knowing my attitude to myself and to the world outside me is what I call truth. And so everyone can have his own truth and yet it remains the self-same truth.

*

What is particular is eternally defeated by what is general; the general has eternally to fit in with the particular.

*

No one can control what is really creative, and every-body just has to let it go its own way.

*

Anyone to whom nature begins to unveil its open mystery feels an irresistible yearning for nature's noblest interpreter, for art.

*

Time is itself an element.

*

Man never understands how anthropomorphic he is.

*

A difference which gives reason nothing to register is not a difference.

*

In phanerogamy there is still so much of what is cryp-togamic that centuries will not suffice to unriddle it.

*

Exchanging one consonant for another might per-haps be due to some organ deficiency, transforming a vowel into a diphthong the result of conceited pathos.

*

If one had to study all laws, one would have no time at all to transgress them.

*

One can't live for everyone, more especially not for those with whom one wouldn't care to live.

*

A call to posterity originates in the clear vital feeling that there is such a thing as permanence and that even if this is not immediately acknowledged it will, in the end, win the recognition of a minority and finally of a majority. bear the though that anyone is like him.

*

Mysteries do not as yet amount to miracles.

*

Actors win hearts and don't give away their own; they cheat, but do it with charm.

*

Reckless, passionate favouritism of problematic men of talent was a failing of my younger years of which I could never completely rid myself.

*

I would like to be honest with you without us parting company; but this isn't possible. You are acting wrongly and trying to sit between two stools, not getting any followers and losing your friends. What's to come of this!

*

No matter whether you're of high rank or low, you can't avoid paying the price of your common humanity.

*

Writers of a liberal persuasion are now on to a good game; they have the whole public at their feet.

*

When I hear talk about liberal ideas, I'm always amazed how people like to delude themselves with the sound of empty words: an idea is not allowed to be liberal! Let it be forceful, doughty, self-enclosed, so as to fulfil its God-given mission of being product-ive. Still less is a concept allowed to be liberal; for its commission is completely different.

*

But where we have to look for liberality is in people's attitudes and these are their feelings come to life.

*

Attitudes, however, are seldom liberal because an attitude springs directly from the person, his imme-diate context and his needs.

*

We'll leave it at that; by this yardstick we should measure what we hear day after day!

*

It's always only our eyes, the way we imagine things; nature quite alone knows what it wills, what it intended.

‘Give me where I stand!'

Archimedes.

‘Take where you stand!'

Nose.

Declare where you stand!

G.

It is general causal relationships which the observer will explore, and he will attribute similar phenomena to a general cause; rarely will he think of the imme-diate cause.

*

No intelligent man experiences a minor stupidity.

*

In every work of art, great or small, and down to the smallest detail, everything depends on the initial conception.

*

There is no such thing as poetry without tropes as poetry is a single trope writ large.

*

A kindly old examiner whispers into a schoolboy's ear: ‘Etiam nihil didicisti' [you haven't learnt anything as yet] and gives him a pass-mark.

*

Excellence is unfathomable; tackle it in what way you will.

*

The most mediocre novel is still better than mediocre readers, indeed the worst novel still participates in some way in the excellence of the genre as a whole.

*

I was intent on pursuing what is general until such time as I came to comprehend the achievement of outstanding people in what is particular.

*

You really only know when you know little; doubt grows with knowledge.

*

It's really a person's mistakes that make him endearing.

*

The Germans know how to correct, but not how to give supportive help.

*

There are people who love and seek out those like themselves, and, then again, those who love and pur-sue their opposites.

*

Anyone who had always allowed himself to take so poor a view of the world as our adversaries make out would have turned into a rotten subject.

*

Envy and hatred limit the observer's view to the sur-face even if this is also associated with acumen; if this, however, goes hand in hand with kindliness and love, the observer can see right through the world and mankind; indeed, he can hope to reach the Allhighest.

*

An English critic credits me with ‘panoramic ability', for which I must tender my most cordial thanks.

*

A certain measure of poetical talent is desirable for every German as the right way to cloak his condition, of whatever kind it may be, with a certain degree of worth and charm.

*

The subject-matter is visible to everyone, content is only discovered by him who has something to con-tribute, and form is a mystery to most.

*

People's inclinations favour what is vitally alive. And youth again forms itself by youth.

*

We may get to know the world however we choose, it will always keep a day and a night aspect.

*

Error is continually repeated in action, and that is why we must not tire of repeating in words what is true.

*

Just as in Rome, besides the Romans, there was also a people of statues, so, too, apart from this real world, there is also an illusory world, mightier almost, where the majority live.

*

People are like the Red Sea: the staff has hardly kept them apart, immediately afterwards they flow together again.

*

The historian's duty: to distinguish truth from false-hood, certainty from uncertainty, doubtful matters from those which are to be rejected.

*

Only someone to whom the present is important writes a chronicle.

*

Thoughts recur, convictions perpetuate themselves; circumstances pass by irretrievably.

*

Among all peoples, the Greeks have dreamt life's dream most beautifully.

*

Translators are to be regarded as busy matchmak-ers who exalt the great loveliness of a half-veiled beauty: they kindle an irresistible longing for the original.

*

We like to rate Antiquity higher than ourselves, but not posterity. It's only a father who doesn't envy a son's talent.

*

It's not at all hard to subordinate yourself; but when you are set on a declining course, in the descendant, how hard it is to admit that what is, in fact, below you is above you!

*

Our whole achievement is to give up our existence in order to exist.

*

All we devise and do is exhausting; happy the man who doesn't get weary.

*

‘Hope is the second soul of those who are unfortunate.'

*

He who acts as though he's glad, and is glad about what he has done, is happy.

*

There is, too, in man a desire to serve; hence French chivalry is a form of service, ‘servage’.

*

‘In the theatre visual and aural entertainment greatly limit reflection.'

*

Experience can be extended into infinity; in not quite the same sense theory can be purified and perfected. To the former the universe is open in all directions; the latter remains locked within the confines of human capacity. This is why all modes of conceptual thinking are bound to reappear, and that is why, strangely enough, a theory of limited value can regain favour in spite of wider experience.

*

It is always the same world which lies open to our view, is always contemplated or surmised, and it is always the same people who live in truth or wrong-headedly, more comfortably in the latter way than in the former.

*

Truth is contrary to our nature, not so error, and this for a very simple reason: truth demands that we should recognize ourselves as limited, error flatters us that, in one way or another, we are unlimited.

*

It is now nearly twenty years since all Germans ‘tran-scend'. Once they notice this, they are bound to realize how odd they are.

*

It is natural enough that people should imagine they can still do what they were once able to do; that others imagine themselves capable of doing what they never could do is perhaps strange but not infrequent.

*

At all times only individuals have had an effect on scientific knowledge, not the epoch. It was the epoch that did Socrates to death by poison, the epoch that burnt Huss: epochs have always remained true to type.

*

This is true symbolism, where the particular repre-sents the general, not as dream and shadow, but as a live and immediate revelation of the unfathomable.

*

As soon as the ideal makes a demand on the real, it in the end consumes it and also itself. Thus credit (paper money) consumes silver and its own self.

*

Mastery is often seen as egoism.

*

As soon as good works and their merit cease, senti-mentality immediately takes over in the case of Protestants.

*

If you can seek out good advice, it's as though you yourself have the capacity for action.

*

There's nothing clever that hasn't been thought of before - you've just got to try to think it all over again.

*

How can we learn self-knowledge? Never by taking thought but rather by action. Try to do your duty and you'll soon discover what you're like.

*

But what is your duty? The demands of the day.

*

The reasonable world is to be seen as a great individ-ual not subject to mortality and forever bringing about what is needed, in this way even mastering chance events.

*

The longer I live, the more depressing I find the spec-tacle of a man, whose optimal function is to be a lord over nature so as to free himself and his fellow men from tyrannical necessity, doing the exact opposite of what he really wants to do, and all because of some preconceived false notion; and in the end, because the structure of the project as a whole has been ruined, he just muddles on miserably with odd details.

*

Man of ability and action, be worthy of, and expect:

grace　-from those who are great

favour　-from the powerful

a helping hand　-from those who are active and good

affection　-from the crowd

love　-from an individual

*

When a dilettante has done what lies within his capacity to complete a work, he usually makes the excuse that of course it's as yet unfinished. Clearly, it never can be finished because it was never properly started. The master of his art, by means of a few strokes, produces a finished work; fully worked out or not, it is already completed. The cleverest kind of dilettante gropes about in uncertainties and, as the work proceeds, the dubiousness of the initial structure becomes more and more apparent. Right at the end the faulty nature of the work, impossible to correct, shows up clearly and so, of course, the work can never be finished.

*

For true art there is no such thing as preparatory schooling, but there are certainly preparations; the best, however, is when the least pupil takes a share in the master's work. Colour-grinders have turned into very good artists.

*

Copycat work, casually stimulating people's natural activity in imitating an important artist who achieves with ease what is difficult, is quite a different matter.

*

We are quite convinced that it is essential for the artist to make studies from nature; we won't however deny that it often grieves us to perceive the misuse of such praiseworthy endeavours.

*

We are convinced that the young artist should rarely, if at all, set out to do studies from nature without at the same time considering how he might round off every sheet and make a whole of it, transforming this unit into a pleasing picture set within a frame, and offer it courteously to the amateur and the expert.

*

Much that is beautiful stands as an isolated entity in the world, but the spirit has to discover connections and thus to create works of art. The flower unfolds its full beauty only through the insect that clings to it, through the dewdrop that makes it glisten, through the calix from out of which it may be drawing its last sustenance. No bush, no tree whose charm may not be enhanced by a neighbouring rock or brook, by a simple prospect in the distance. And so it is with human figures and so with animals of every kind.

*

The advantages accruing to a young artist in this way are indeed manifold. He learns to think out the best way of fitting together related things and, when he thus composes intelligently, he will, in the end, assuredly not lack what is termed invention, the cap-acity to develop a manifold whole out of single units.

*

And, as well as conforming to the tenets of art peda-gogy, he gains the great advantage, by no means to be despised, of learning to create saleable pictures that are a pleasure and delight to the art lover.

*

A work of this kind need not be complete down to the last detail; if it is well envisaged, thought out and finished, it is often more appealing to the art lover than a larger, more fully completed picture.

*

Let every young artist take a look at the studies in his sketch book and portfolio and consider how many of these sheets he might have been able to make enjoyable and desirable in this way.

*

We are not talking about the higher regions of art which might of course also be discussed; this is no more than a warning to recall the artist from a devious path and point the way to higher regions.

*

Let the artist put this to a practical test, if only for half a year, and not make use of either charcoal or brush unless he has the firm intention of actually structuring a picture out of the natural object or scene confronting him. If he has inborn talent, what we intended by our comments will soon be revealed.

*

Tell me with whom you consort and I will tell you who you are; if I know how you spend your time, then I know what might become of you.

*

Every individual must think in his own personal way; for on his way he always finds a truth or a kind of truth which helps him get through life. But he mustn't let himself go, he has got to keep a check on himself; purely naked instinct is unseemly.

*

Absolute activity, of whatever kind, ultimately leads to bankruptcy.

*

In the works of man as in those of nature, what most deserves notice is his intention.

*

People are at a loss with regard to themselves and one another because they use means as ends, and then, because of sheer busyness, nothing whatever happens or perhaps, even worse, something which is disagreeable.

*

What we think out, what we undertake, should have achieved such perfect clarity and beauty that any-thing the world could do to it could only spoil it; this would leave us with the advantage of only having to adjust what has been misplaced and refashion what has been destroyed.

*

Whole, half-and quarter-errors are most difficult and wearisome to put right, to sort out.

*

Truth need not always take corporeal form; enough for it to be around in spiritual form, bringing about harmony as it floats on the breeze as a spiritual pres-ence like the solemn-friendly sound of bells.

*

When I ask young German artists, even those who have spent some time in Italy, why they use such crudely bright colours, especially in their landscapes, and seem to shun anything like harmony, they are apt to answer boldly and cheerfully that this is pre-cisely how they see nature.

*

Kant has drawn our attention to the fact that there is such a thing as a Critique of Reason, and that this, the highest faculty possessed by man, has cause to keep watch over itself. Let everyone judge for himself what great advantages the voice of Kant has brought him. I, for my part, would similarly like to urge that a Critique of the Senses should be worked out, if art, especially German art, is in any way to recover and to proceed and progress at a pleasing and lively pace.

*

Man, born to be a creature of reason, nevertheless needs much education, whether this comes gradually by way of careful parents and tutors, by peaceful example or by stern experience. Similarly, there is such a thing as a born potential artist, but no one is born perfect. He may have an inborn clarity of vision, a happy eye for shape, proportion, movement: but without becoming aware of this lack, he may be with-out a natural instinct for composition in its higher aspects, for correct tonal proportion, for light, shade and colouring.

*

Now if he is not inclined to learn from more highly skilled contemporary or earlier artists what he himself lacks in order to be a true artist, he will lag behind his own potential because of a wrong-headed idea that he is safeguarding his own originality; for we own not just what we are born with, but also what we can acquire, and this is what we are.

*

General notions and great conceit are always poten-tial creators of shocking misfortune.

*

‘You don't play the flute just by blowing - you've got to move your fingers.'

*

Botanists have a plant-category which they call 'Incompletae'; similarly one can say that there are incomplete and uncompleted people. These are the ones whose longings and strivings are out of propor-tion with what they actually do and what they achieve.

*

The least gifted man can be complete if he keeps within the limits of his capacities and skills, but real excellence is obscured, cancelled out and destroyed if there is not that absolutely essential sense of pro-portion. This disastrous lack is bound to crop up frequently in our own day; for who can possibly keep up with the demands of an exorbitant present, and that at maximum speed?

*

Only those people who are both clever and active, who are clear about their own capacities and can use them with moderation and common sense, will really get on in the world as it is.

*

A great failing: to see yourself as more than you are and to value yourself at less than your true worth.

*

From time to time I meet a young man whom I wouldn't wish different or improved in any way; but what worries me is that some of these people seem to me just the kind who let themselves drift along with the current of the stream of time, and this is where I keep wanting to point out that man is put at the helm of his own fragile craft precisely so that he may not follow the whim of the waves, the determination of his own insight.

*

But how is a young man independently to reach the insight that what everyone else pursues, approves and furthers may be reprehensible and damaging? Why shouldn't he let himself and his own natural disposition go the same way?

*

The greatest evil of our time - which lets nothing come to fruition - is, I think, that one moment con-sumes the next, wastes the day within that same day and so is always living from hand to mouth without achieving anything of substance. Don't we already have news-sheets for every point of the day! A clever man might well be able to slip in one or two more. In this way everything that anyone does, is working at or writing, indeed plans to write, is dragged out into the open. No one is allowed to be happy or mis-erable except as a pastime for the rest of the world, and so news rushes from house to house, from town to town, from one country to another, and, in the end, from one continent to the next, and all on the principle of speed and velocity.

*

As little as steam engines can be quelled, so little is this possible in the behavioural realm: the lively pace of trade, the rapid rush of paper-money, the inflated increase of debts made in order to pay off other debts, these are the monstrous elements to which a young man is now exposed. How good for him if nature has endowed him with a moderate and calm attitude so that he makes no disproportionate claims on the world nor yet allows it to determine his course!

*

But the spirit of the day threatens him in every sphere and nothing is more important than to make him realize early enough the direction in which his will should steer.

*

As one grows older, the most innocent talk and action grow in significance, and to those I see around me for any length of time I always try to point out the shades of difference between sincerity, frankness and indis-cretion, and that there is really no difference between them, but just an intangible transition from the most harmless comment to the most damaging, and that this subtle transition has to be observed or indeed felt.

*

In this matter we have to use tact, else we run the risk of losing people's favour without being in the least aware of this and precisely in the way we came by it. This we probably come to understand in the course of life, but only after we have paid a high price for our experience, and from this we cannot, alas, spare those who come after us.

*

The relationship of the arts and the sciences to life is very varied according to the way their temporal stages are related to the nature of their epoch and a thou-sand other chance contingencies; which is why it isn't easy to make sense of all this.

Poetry is most effective at the start of any set of circumstances, irrespective of whether these are quite crude, half-cultured, or when a culture is in the pro-cess of change as it begins to become aware of a foreign culture; in such cases one can claim the effect of the new is definitely to be felt.

*

Music at its best hardly needs to be new; indeed, the older it is, the more familiar to us, the more effective it can be.

*

The dignity of art perhaps appears most eminent in music because it has no material of a kind for which detailed accounting might be needed. It is all form and content and it heightens and ennobles all it expresses.

*

Music is either sacred or profane. What is sacred accords completely with its nobility, and this is where music most immediately influences life; such influence remains unchanged at all times and in every epoch. Profane music should be altogether cheerful.

*

Music of a kind that mixes the sacred with the pro-fane is godless and shoddy music which goes in for expressing feeble, wretched, deplorable feelings, and is just insipid. For it is not serious enough to be sacred and it lacks the chief quality of the opposite kind: cheerfulness.

*

The numinous nature of church music, the cheerful-ness and playfulness of folk melodies are the two pivots of true music. At these two focal points music always and inevitably leads either towards reverence or else to dance. Any mixture of the two is confusing, dilution is boring, and if music consorts with didactic or descriptive poems and texts of that kind, the result is coldness.

*

Plastic art is really only effective at its highest level; it is true that the middle zone can perhaps impress us for more reasons than one, but all middle-range art of this kind is more confusing than gladdening. Sculpture therefore has to discover subject-matter of interest and this is to be found in the portraits of people of some significance. But here, too, it has to reach a high degree of excellence if it is to be at the same time true and dignified.

*

Painting is the slackest and most easy-going of all the arts. The slackest because, on account of the material and subject-matter, we condone and enjoy much that is no more than skilled craftsmanship and can hardly be called art. In part it is also because a good tech-nical performance, even though it may be dull, can be admired by the cultured as well as the uneducated, and need only remotely resemble art in order to be highly acceptable. True colours, surfaces and a true relationship of visible objects - all this is in itself pleasing; and, since the eye is in any case used to seeing everything, it does not find misshapen or mistaken form as objectionable as a jarring note is for the listening ear. We tolerate the worst por-trayal because we are used to seeing even worse originals. So the painter need only be remotely artistic so as to find a bigger public than a musician of equal merit; the minor painter can at least always operate on his own, whereas the minor musician has to associate with others in order to achieve some sort of resonance by means of a combined musical effort.

*

The question ‘Are we to compare or not to compare when considering works of art' is one we would like to answer as follows: the trained connoisseur should make comparisons, for he has a general idea, a pre-conceived notion of what could be and should be achieved; the amateur, still involved in the process of being educated, can make the best progress if he does not compare but judges each achievement on its individual merit: this gradually forms an instinct and idea for the general situation. Comparison by the unknowing is really only a lazy and conceited way of avoiding judgement.

*

To find and to appreciate goodness everywhere is the sign of a love of truth.

*

The sign of a historical feeling for humanity is that, at the same time as we appreciate the merits and attainments of the present, we also take into account the merits of the past.

*

The best we get from history is that it rouses our enthusiasm.

*

Idiosyncrasy calls forth idiosyncrasy.

*

One has to remember that there are quite a lot of people who would like to say something significant without being productive, and then the most peculiar things see the light of day.

*

People who think deeply and seriously are on bad terms with the public.

*

If I'm to listen to someone else's opinion, it must be put in a positive way; I have enough problematic speculations in my own head.

*

Superstition is innate in the human make-up, and when you think you have completely ousted it, it takes refuge in the strangest nooks and crannies and then suddenly emerges when one thinks one is toler-ably safe.

*

We would know much more about things if we weren't intent on discerning them too precisely. For, surely, an object can only be comprehensible to us when viewed at an angle of forty-five degrees.

*

Microscopes and telescopes really only serve to con-fuse the unaided human senses.

*

I hold my peace about many things; for I don't like to confuse people and am quite content if they are happy while I am cross.

*

Everything that liberates our mind without at the same time imparting self-control is pernicious.

*

The ‘what' of a work of art interests people more than the ‘how'; they can grasp the subject-matter in detail but not the method as a whole. That is why they pick out individual passages, in which, if you observe closely, the total effect is not actually lost but remains unconscious to all.

*

And the question, too, ‘Where has the poet got it from? 'gets no further than the ‘what'; it helps no one to understand the ‘how'.

*

Imagination is only ordered and structured by poetry. There is nothing more awful than imagination devoid of taste.

*

Mannerism is an ideology gone wrong, a subjective ideology; that's why, as a rule, it isn't without wit.

*

The philologist is dependent on the congruence of what has been handed down in written form. There is a basic manuscript and this has real gaps, errors of transcription which lead to a break in the meaning and to other difficulties common to manuscript tradition. Then a second copy is found, a third one; collating these leads to growing perception of what makes sense and meaning in the transmitted material. Indeed, the philologist goes further and requires that it should increasingly reveal and structure its inner meaning and the congruence of its subject-matter without depend-ence on philological aides. This calls for a special degree of sensitive judgement, a special absorption in an author long dead and a certain amount of inventive power; one cannot, therefore, take it amiss if the phil-ologist allows himself to make a judgement in matters of taste even if this doesn't always succeed.

*

The poet is dependent on representation, the cli-max of which is reached when it vies with reality, that is, when the descriptions are so full of living power that everyone can see them as being actually present. At the summit of its excellence poetry appears as something completely external; the more it withdraws into the inner realm, the more it is on its way towards sinking. The kind of poetry which concentrates on the inner realm without giving it outward substance or without allowing the out-ward to be perceived through the inward - both are the last steps from which poetry steps down into ordinary life.

*

Oratory is dependent on all the advantages of poetry, on all its rights. It takes possession of these and mis-uses them in order to get hold of certain outer momentary advantages, whether moral or immoral, in civic life.

*

Literature is the fragment of fragments; only the least amount of what has happened and has been spoken was written down, the least of what has been recorded in writing has survived.

*

Although Lord Byron's talent is wild and uncomfort-able in its structure, hardly anyone can compare with him in natural truth and grandeur.

*

The really important value of folksong, so called, is that its themes are taken directly from nature. But the educated poet too might well avail himself of this advantage if only he knew how to set about it.

*

But the advantage inherent in folksong is that natural people, as distinct from the educated, are on better terms with what is laconic.

*

Shakespeare is dangerous reading for talents in the process of formation: he forces them to reproduce him, and they imagine they are producing themselves.

*

Nobody can make judgements about history except those who have experienced history as a part of their own development. This applies to whole nations. The Germans have only been able to judge literature since the point they themselves have had literature.

*

One is really only alive when one enjoys the good will of others.

*

Piety is not an end but a means to attain by the great-est peace of mind the highest degree of culture.

*

This is why we may say that those who parade piety as a purpose and an aim mostly turn into hypocrites.

*

'When one is old one has to do more than when one was young.'

*

A duty absolved still feels like an unpaid debt, because one can never quite live up to one's expectations.

*

Human failings are only descried by an unloving person; that is why, in order to realize them, one has to become unloving oneself, but not more than is strictly to the purpose.

*

It is our greatest good fortune to have our failings corrected and our faults adjusted.

*

Three things are not recognized except in the due course of time:

a hero in wartime,

a wise man in a rage,

a friend in need.

*

Three classes of fools:

men because of pride,

girls by love,

women by jealousy.

*

The following are mad:

he who tries to teach simpletons,

contradicts the wise,

is moved by empty speeches,

believes whores,

entrusts secrets to the garrulous.

*

Man can only live together with his own kind and not with them either; for in the long run he cannot bear the thought that anyone is like him.

*

Whichever way you look at nature, it is the source of what is infinite.

*

You have to have actually found a thing if you want to know where it is situated.

译后记

承蒙企鹅兰登之托，本人翻译了松尾芭蕉俳句集《怎奈唇寒口难开》一书。虽然有三十余载的日语从业经历和十几年的长期驻日工作、生活积累，但翻译俳句，本人还是初出茅庐，也不失为有益的尝试。

首先这本书因版权原因，原译本[由卢西恩·斯特雷克（Lucien Stryk）译于1985年]为英语，书名为Lips too chilled，出版社的编辑按英语去翻查了日语原著（岩波书店1962年版的《芭蕉句集》），我再由日语原文翻译成中文。在此过程中发现英译本可能因为语言体系的差别，很难准确表达出原意，大多是直译过来的，所以给查找原文带来了一定难度。

第二，由于俳句用日语诵读时，会表现为575的自然韵律，即一首由17个假名[1]组成的正常俳句，分别会在5、7、5的假名处自然断句（受措辞或语法结构的影响，部分俳句会出现增字或减字的情况）。且日语中的单词可以一词多义、一字多音，所以一首俳句也可能只有三个词汇，但意蕴较深，这也是俳句的魅力所在。如同中国的写意画虽草草几笔，但会给人带来无限遐想。而松尾芭蕉在日本被奉为俳圣，他的“古池や蛙飛び込む水の音”（见本书第4页）更是成为俳句之冠。由于中日文化的差异，如果简单直译则读者很难悟出其中意境，而完全意译又会脱离575的格式，失去俳句的原本特色，且目前在国内出版的俳句集大多不是575的格式。

在试译过程中我与编辑反复沟通、斟酌，决定仍以575的格式译出。这样，不但给翻译工作带来一定难度，还要尽可能如诗歌般押韵，需要一定的创作性。为此我参考了大量有关松尾芭蕉的俳句注释、创作背景，并结合在日本的生活经历尝试进行再创作，逐步适应后有了渐入佳境之感，感觉这样译既不破坏原结构，又能将原作中的意境转达给读者，还有译者的发挥空间，不失为俳句汉译的一种积极探索。

第三，由于英译本的问题，经查有个别句子不是芭蕉的原作，我们进行了调换。同时为更便于读者理解正确的原意，我们将日文原文一并刊出，请读者参考、指正。

另外，在这里我还要特别感谢责任编辑和译审给予的非常有价值的意见和建议，本书同样包含了她们的心血和汗水。

[1]日文所用的字母。有平假名、片假名两种字体。—译者注

沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特　致父亲利奥波德·莫扎特（萨尔茨堡）

奥格斯堡，1777年10月17日[1]

我亲爱的父亲！

现在我得开始跟您说说施泰因[2]的钢琴了。在看到它们之前，施佩特[3]的钢琴是我的最爱；但现在我更喜欢施泰因钢琴，因为它的制音效果比雷根斯堡钢琴（即施佩特钢琴）还要好得多。在我用力弹奏时，不管我把手指放在琴键上还是抬起，声音都会在我敲响它们的那一瞬间立刻消失。随便以哪种方式触键，音质都很稳定-不会发出杂音，不会变强或是变弱，或者完全不出声。总之，所有乐音都十分均衡。毫无疑问，这样一台钢琴施泰因至少要卖300弗罗林。但他投入的努力和勤奋是无法用金钱来衡量的。他的钢琴有一个独一无二的优点，就是安装了擒纵器[4]（Auslösung）。这样的制琴师真的是百里挑一。但如果没有擒纵机件，一架钢琴根本就不可能没有杂音或回声；触键时，琴槌会落下，但一敲过琴弦，不管你这时把手指放在琴键上还是移开，都会立刻向上跳起。施泰因告诉我，只有在他完成了这样一架钢琴的时候，才会坐下来尝试弹奏各种走句[5]，流动的、跳跃的，一直调试到这架钢琴什么都能演奏。因为他的工作纯粹是为了提高音乐品质，而不仅仅为了赚钱，不然他立刻就能完工。

他经常说：“如果我自己不是这样狂热的音乐爱好者，不能在钢琴上弹点什么的话，我早就对我的工作失去耐心了。但我本身就喜欢不会让演奏者失望并且经久耐用的乐器。”他的钢琴确实非常耐用。他保证他的音板不会破损或者断裂；每当他完成了一个钢琴音板，他就放到室外，让它日晒夜露，风吹雨打，以致破裂。然后他就在裂缝里嵌进楔子，黏合起来，这样音板就会变得非常坚实牢固。他喜欢看到音板开裂，因为这之后就能确保不会再发生这种情况了。为了让音板更加坚固，他甚至经常亲手切割它，再将它黏合起来。现在他一共制作完成了三架这样的钢琴。直到今天我才又弹奏了其中一架。

今天是17号，我们和年轻的加斯纳先生一起吃饭，他是一位年轻英俊的鳏夫，亡妻也年轻美丽，他们才结婚两年。这个年轻人非常正派而有礼貌，盛情款待了我们。一同吃饭的还有阿贝·亨利·布林格先生和维斯霍费尔先生的一个同事，他是一位前耶稣会会士，目前担任这儿的大教堂乐长[6]。他和沙赫特纳先生（萨尔茨堡的宫廷小号手）很熟，因为他曾是沙赫特纳先生在因戈尔斯塔特[7]时的唱诗班指挥。他叫帕特尔·格布尔。我会写信向沙赫特纳先生转达他的问候。加斯纳先生和他的一个小姨子，妈妈，我，还有我们的堂妹[8]，吃完饭后就去了施泰因先生那里。4点钟的时候，乐长先生和施米德鲍尔先生也来了。施米德鲍尔先生是圣乌尔里希修道院的资助者，一位非常好的老先生，说话很文雅；我在那儿视奏[9]了一首贝克[10]的奏鸣曲，一如既往地艰难，令人痛苦。简直无法形容这让乐长先生和修道院资助者多么震惊，以至于得在胸前画十字呼唤主。在这儿和在慕尼黑，我经常凭记忆演奏我的全部六首奏鸣曲[11]。在之前的农舍音乐会[12]上，我已经演奏过那首G大调第五号。最后一首D大调在施泰因的钢琴上产生了无与伦比的效果。那个需要由膝盖压住的踏板机械，施泰因也做得比其他人都好。我几乎不需要怎么碰它，就能让它起作用；稍稍把膝盖移开一点点，就听不见一点儿回声了。明天我可能会去演奏他的管风琴，也就是说，我明天看了之后会跟您说说这件事；至于他的小女儿我打算最后再谈。当我对施泰因先生说，我很想演奏他的管风琴，因为管风琴是我的挚爱。他惊讶不已：“什么？您这样一位出色的钢琴家，想要演奏管风琴这种乐器？它既缺乏柔美和表现力，也弹不出弱音和强音变化，听起来老是一个样子。”“这些都说明不了什么，在我看来、听来，管风琴就是所有乐器之王。”“好吧，那我没意见。”于是我们就一起去了。我从他的话里察觉到，他认为我在他的管风琴上弹不出什么名堂，比方说，只能完全像弹钢琴那样来弹弹。他告诉我，他也曾应舒巴特[13]的要求，把他带来演奏管风琴。“我当时很害怕，”他说，“因为舒巴特告诉了所有人，教堂里坐得满满当当。我认为他接下来会精神饱满、激情洋溢，弹奏速度很快，而这些都不适合管风琴。但在他开始的那一刻，我的想法就完全变了。”我只说了一句：“施泰因先生，您觉得，我会在管风琴上狂奔是吗？”“啊，瞧您说的！这压根不是一回事。”然后我们就去了管风琴演奏台。我开始即兴弹奏，这时他已经笑了，随后我又弹了一个赋格。“现在我相信您喜欢演奏管风琴了，”他说，“如果您能以这种方式演奏的话。”起初，踏板对我来说有点儿陌生，因为它没有被划分开。它从c小调开始，然后d小调、e小调，它们都在同一排。在我们的钢琴上，上面一排应该是D大调和E大调，在这里却是降E大调和升F大调。但我很快掌握了这些。

我还去看了圣乌尔里希圣殿古老的管风琴，通往它的楼梯简直是噩梦。我请求其他人为我演奏管风琴，因为我想下楼去听，管风琴在楼上的空间里根本产生不了效果。但是我的期待落空了。那位年轻的唱诗班指挥，一位牧师，只在管风琴上演奏不知所谓的琶音[14]。而当他想演奏和声时，产生的只有不和，因为音全不准。那之后我们不得不去接待室，因为妈妈、堂妹和施泰因先生也在那里，还有一位神父埃米利安，一头自负的驴子，头脑简单的卖弄聪明者，人倒也挺不错的。他一直想和堂妹开玩笑，但她却拿他开心。最后，他喝醉了（这件事很快就发生了），他开始谈论音乐。他唱了一首卡农，我说：“我这辈子没听过比这更美的歌曲。”我接着说：“很遗憾我不能和你一起唱，因为我天生发不出乐音。”“这没关系。”他说。于是他开始唱了。我第三个唱，但是我编了完全不同的内容，压低声音唱给堂妹听：“埃米利安神父，哦！你这个笨蛋！舔舔我的屁股吧！[15]”然后我们又笑了半个小时。埃米利安神父对我说：“如果我们能一起待得久一点儿该多好，我还想和你们谈谈音乐作曲艺术。”“那样的话，我们的谈话很快就会结束。”我说，“吃你自己的拇指去吧！[16]”就先写到这里吧，下次再聊。

沃·阿·莫扎特

[1]1777年8月，莫扎特辞去了萨尔茨堡的宫廷乐师职务，在母亲的陪同下，于9月23日踏上寻找工作机会的旅途，先后访问了慕尼黑、奥格斯堡、曼海姆、巴黎，其中奥格斯堡乃其父利奥波德·莫扎特的出生地。莫扎特和母亲在慕尼黑遭到选帝侯婉拒后，于1777年10月11日到达奥格斯堡，暂居在叔叔弗朗茨·阿洛伊斯·莫扎特家中。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明之外，均为译者注。）

[2]约翰·安德烈亚斯·施泰因（1728-1792），著名德国钢琴制造师。他师从德国管风琴制作大师戈特弗里德·西尔伯曼，是钢琴制造史上的关键人物，设计制造了维也纳式击弦机钢琴。

[3]弗兰兹·雅各布·施佩特（Franz Jakob Späth，1714-1786），管风琴、钢琴制造师，生活在雷根斯堡，故下文以雷根斯堡钢琴指代其所制作的钢琴。

[4]或称擒纵结构，即钢琴击弦装置。在琴槌击打钢琴琴弦使其振动后，擒纵器立即使其停止振动，恢复到原来的位置，准备再次受击振动，而演奏者的手指仍可按在键上。

[5]指流畅连续的连奏。

[6]德语原文Kapellmeister，又译为乐团指挥，作为德国宫廷乐团的领导者，乐长起初不仅担任指挥，也负责作曲、编曲、组织管理等。因Meister有“师傅”之意，将Kapellmeister译为“乐长”更贴近德文原意。

[7]德国巴伐利亚州的一座城市，位于多瑙河沿岸。

[8]即莫扎特叔叔之女玛丽亚·安娜·泰克拉·莫扎特（1758-1841）。莫扎特常亲昵地以Bäsle（施瓦本方言，意为小堂妹）唤她，两人关系十分亲密。

[9]指在没有排练的情况下直接看着乐谱演奏。

[10]弗朗茨·伊格纳茨·冯·贝克（1733-1803），德国古典音乐作曲家。

[11]即莫扎特在这次旅行中的全部演奏曲目：C大调第一号钢琴奏鸣曲K.279/189d,F大调第二号钢琴奏鸣曲K.280/189e，降B大调第三号钢琴奏鸣曲K.281/189f，降E大调第四号钢琴奏鸣曲K.282/189g,G大调第五号钢琴奏鸣曲K.283/189h,D大调第六号钢琴奏鸣曲K.284/205b。

[12]前一天（1777年10月16日），莫扎特参加了由奥格斯堡城市贵族在农舍举办的音乐会，他们认为这个地点与莫扎特相配，可以给他“带来荣耀”，暗示了将其视为农民。

[13]克里斯蒂安·弗里德里希·丹尼尔·舒巴特（1739-1791），德国音乐家、诗人、作家，自1774年起在奥格斯堡出版反对教会的杂志《德国编年史》（Deutsche Chronik），1775年被驱逐出奥格斯堡，1777年被捕入狱。

[14]琶音指一串和弦音从低到高或从高到低依次连续奏出，可视为分解和弦的一种。通常作为一种专门的技巧训练用于练习曲中，有时作为短小的连接句或经过句出现在乐曲旋律声部中。

[15]莫扎特有一首卡农就叫《舔舔我的屁股吧》（Leck mich im Arsch，K.231/382c）。

[16]巴伐利亚俚语，表示没兴趣再继续对话或提供信息，用来摆脱纠缠而好奇的人。

利奥波德·莫扎特　致儿子沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特（曼海姆）

萨尔茨堡，1777年11月24日

我亲爱的儿子！

我实在不知道该说些什么，你16号的那封信太让我震惊了。你用最轻率的语气告诉我，施马尔茨先生，可能是施马尔茨先生在慕尼黑皮革厂的父亲、兄弟或者朋友，或者干脆就是他本人，向你道歉说他没有得到把钱给你的指令。这我相信。他说得对，你应该去恳求赫尔佐克先生或者诺克与希德尔银行，继续借你一小笔贷款，就像我一贯做的那样。因为哈格瑙尔先生没给他们异地使用这笔贷款的指令[18]，生意人只按字面指令办事。但在你的恳求下，他可以为你这么做。只是你那么自然、那么无所谓地跟我说了这件意外的事，就好像我有成箱成箱的钱，仿佛这件事能让我觉得即使眼下拿不到钱也没那么可怕。我就不浪费时间跟你细讲我们现在的处境了，你心知肚明，妈妈也一样。在我20号的信里，我已经把所有主要债款列出来了，尽管还是忘了有一批东西的钱我们还没付给哈格瑙尔，但目前我们没有欠他钱。你上一封信最让我惊讶的是，你冷不丁地跟我说起这件事，之前却丝毫未提。之前的信里只是说，比起奉承，钱才是旅行中更必要的好东西，因为你们那时就知道你们的经济状况很糟糕。可你们没有透露一点点消息，我那时也没有料到这一切。我本打算硬着头皮去解决异地使用贷款指令这件事，如果施马尔茨先生一直这么好说话的话。如果是这样该有多好！我请你从我的角度好好想一想，从奥格斯堡你写信告诉我，你们最多花了27弗罗林。现在我来算笔账，如果你们花了30弗罗林，那么就还剩170弗罗林。如果途经瓦勒斯泰因去曼海姆的傻旅行花了70弗罗林，那么你们手里应该还剩下100弗罗林。如果这段旅途花费了更多，剩下的钱是不是就应该不够旅行去美因茨了？但等到了曼海姆，你们离法兰克福就近了，必要的时候可以用你第二封贷款信用证从法兰克福的博隆加罗先生那里取点钱。你们只要随便去问一个跟博隆加罗有来往的美因茨生意人，他就会负责把信用证寄给博隆加罗先生，然后拿到你们要的钱。

这难道不比待在曼海姆毫无好处地挥霍你们的钱更明智吗，因为这些钱可能够你们做一次花费15或者16弗罗林的旅行。到沃尔姆斯只要1.25站，到奥彭海姆要2站，到美因茨只要1站。因此总共只有4.25站。如果你们到了美因茨，钱已经剩得不多或者没钱了，那里也有熟人可以帮助你们。没有绅士会为口袋里没有一分钱但可以出示贷款信用证而感到羞愧。即使在最富有最重要的人物身上也可能发生这种事。旅行的一大原则就是，只要情况允许，就只随身携带必要的钱财。我一直盲目谈论着美因茨，只是出于想当然的猜测，因为从你们之前的信中，我没能有荣幸得知你们打算去哪里旅行，直到最后一刻你才从奥格斯堡给我写了信：明天我们要去瓦勒斯泰因。斯坦因先生写信告诉我，他们星期天七点半动身去了瓦勒斯泰因和曼海姆。这种事情应该提前写信告诉我，因为我有时候能做些有用的准备，给你一些提醒。就像我之前那么煞费苦心地给法兰克福的奥托先生和普法伊尔先生写信一样。当然，你们的旅行跟我没关系！不是吗？你们当然还可以从曼海姆走一条完全不一样的路，你们可以先去维尔茨堡，再从那儿经过马克伽芬去达姆斯塔特，最后到法兰克福-美因茨。但我怎么能猜中你们的想法呢，怎么能给你们建议呢，因为你们从来也没征求过我的建议。根据你的来信，我也不知道曼海姆的事情如何了，你在信上写了有机会和选帝侯[19]亲密交谈，我忍不住猜想你是否打算在那里留一段时间。此外，你的意见、态度、打算等，所有这一切都应该及时且如实地向我报告，因为即使在最顺利的情况下，收到并回复一封信也要12天。即便是这一点你也没有动脑子想想，竟然在16号的那封信里告诉我，我可以继续往曼海姆给你写信，而你最快也要12天以后，也就是28号才能收到。这期间赫尔佐克先生早就回复了我的信，告诉我你将动身去旅行。但直到21号也就是星期五，我才收到你的来信，作为我和你母亲结婚纪念日当天的礼物，因此我24号之前都不能回复你。要到12月1号或2号，你才会读到这封信，天知道你那时在哪里。你们两个知道我很清楚旅行中有多少额外开销，尤其当人们太慷慨或者太友善的时候，花钱会怎样快得如流水。我亲爱的妻子还很自豪地说她会早起，不磨磨蹭蹭，麻利又省钱地安排一切。在慕尼黑待了16天，在奥古斯堡待了14天，按照你16号信里说的，接下来将要在曼海姆待17天，再加上等待奥格斯堡回复的时间，也就是3周。这简直就像巫术。你们已经走了8周，也就是2个月了，现在已经到曼海姆了？这真是难以理解的飞速！我们当时去英国的时候，在慕尼黑待了9天，拜访了选帝侯和克莱门特公爵，因为我们必须等待恩赐的礼物。之后我们在奥格斯堡待了15天，在那里演了3场音乐会，也就是6月28号、6月30号和7月4号。6月9号我们从萨尔茨堡动身，由于必须在因河畔瓦瑟堡做马车的新轮子，所以12号才到慕尼黑。尽管我们也在乌尔姆、路德维希堡和布鲁萨尔逗留了些许，但13号也就到了施韦青根。所以你们看到了，你们那些又长又没有必要的各处逗留把一切都搞砸了，公认的金秋就这么过去了，而直到现在你们还在做散心之旅，把时间都花在了娱乐消遣上面。现在好了，糟糕的暴风雨，短暂的白天，最冷的时候已经来了，还有更多更糟糕的天气在后面。你们的目的地现在看起来既昂贵又遥远。

你不能一整个冬天都在旅行，你的逗留地必须是一个大城市，人多，有赚钱的希望和机会。像这样的地方上哪儿去找呢？只有巴黎。但在巴黎就完全是另一种生活方式，另一种思考方式了-你必须保持注意力高度集中，每天琢磨赚钱的途径，练就各种繁文缛节以讨好上层阶级。关于这些我会在下一封信中细说。为了让你更快到达巴黎，下次我会说说我关于另一条旅行路线的想法，它和之前说的完全不一样，但值得一试-也就是从科布伦茨到特里尔、卢森堡、色当，曾经和瓦勒尔先生一起拜访过我们的齐根哈根先生在色当有个手绢厂，他人可能现在就在那里。然后是勒泰勒、兰斯、苏瓦松，再到巴黎。请你注意，从巴黎到勒泰勒一共有22个法国站点。从勒泰勒到色当很近，到卢森堡也不远，而特里尔就在卢森堡边上。卢森堡是一个气势恢宏的要塞，那里会有很多军官。兰斯和苏瓦松都是大城市。在这些地方赚回一些旅行费用还是比较容易的，因为艺术大师很少造访这些地方。相比之下，从布鲁塞尔到巴黎要经过34站，将花费我们6匹马20路易斯，而且赚不到一分钱。因为从科布伦茨到布鲁塞尔没什么可做的，除了或许能拜访柯尼赛格选帝侯。也许这也不错？布鲁塞尔有什么呢？

在此期间，无论你选择哪条路线，都要拿到一些去巴黎的推荐信，谁写的不重要，商人、官员等都可以。你是否知道还有没有法国大使或者法国人在美因茨或科布伦茨？我觉得是没有。你现在连一封推荐信都还没有，而我有很多封。为了能立刻获得庇护，建立起关系网，你绝对需要这些推荐信。这样的旅行一点儿乐趣都谈不上，你还没有经历过。一个人脑子里必须想着其他更重要的事情，而不是只会玩愚蠢的把戏。你必须一直考虑上百件事情，不然就会突然陷入困境，一分钱都没有。没有了钱，你也就不再有朋友，即使你免费教了上百节课，即使你写奏鸣曲，即使每晚10点到12点跟朋友鬼混，而不去做重要的事情。再去问问贷款的事！所有的消遣都可以停止了，所有的嬉皮笑脸眼下也都可以收起来了。我绝不是责怪你通过友善的举动和坎纳比希一家建立关系，这做得很好。但是你应该把晚上的一些闲散时间献给如此牵挂你的父亲，不要只给他一封匆忙写就的大杂烩，而是写一份有条有理的可信的报告，比如写写你们的旅行花费，你们还剩下多少钱，未来的旅程计划以及你在曼海姆的打算，等等。这些都应该事无巨细地写下来，并且征求我的建议。我希望你能够明智地看到这一点，如果不是你可怜的老父亲，谁会来最终承担这一切呢？正如前面所说，我21号收到了你的信，在今天之前都没时间回复。昨天23号，我向三位一体的上帝忏悔，满含泪水地为你们祈祷全能天主的庇佑。下午有一场卡耶坦·安特雷特举办的射击练习，我得了一等奖。布林格先生向你们问好，你的信也让他有点儿惊讶。我觉得，在目前这个严肃的情况下，他不大高兴你关于公共债务的玩笑。五点半我还去了哈格瑙尔先生那里，请求他今天就给奥格斯堡那边写信，如果诺克与希德尔银行没通知他已向你汇款的话。今天早晨我再次去了店里跟哈格瑙尔的儿子约瑟夫先生聊天。我发现他们虽然从诺克与希德尔银行那里收到了信，但没看到上面有关于你的消息。他承诺我今天写信去问问。现在我已经把我能做的都做了，只希望你在此期间已收到了一些钱。直到诺克与希德尔银行知道你已经拿到了多少钱，他们才会通知我。请注意，拿钱的时候最好不要接受弗罗林而是接受当地货币，比如金路易或者卡罗林等。现在我已经把压在心头的事情都说完了，这些都是来自上帝的真理。你会知道的，像这样依靠不稳定的经济收入去旅行毫无乐趣可言。但无论如何，你一定要虔诚地向天主祈求健康，请求他在坏人面前庇护你。此外要通过所有你知道的方式挣钱，同时省吃俭用。对于以后再也不会见到的旅伴，我总是倾向于少给点钱，宁愿他在背后说我小气，也不愿给了他很多钱，他还在背后为此嘲笑我。纸已经写不下了，而且我眼睛也累了。

我和南妮儿[20]希望你们身体健康，真心吻你们一百万次，我是你们的老丈夫，老父亲，注意——不是你们的儿子

莫扎特

希望你们收到了我20号的信，我在上面写了你可以给巴黎的格林男爵写信，也应该给慕尼黑的基姆湖侯爵写信。下一封信我会把去巴黎的所有沿途站点和我的意见都写下来，再附上一份我们在巴黎的旧友名单。再见。

[18]这件事的前因如下：哈格瑙尔在奥格斯堡的诺克与希德尔银行贷给莫扎特一笔钱，但是没授权这家银行异地使用这笔钱。因此赫尔佐克的银行，即诺克与希德尔银行，只给了莫扎特一封致施马尔茨先生（曼海姆）的推荐信，而非可贷出钱款的贷款信用证。

[19]选帝侯是德国历史上一种特殊现象，指代那些拥有选举“罗马人的皇帝”权利的诸侯。此制度严重削弱了皇权，加深了政治分裂。-编者注

[20]即莫扎特的姐姐，玛利亚·安娜·沃布尔嘉·伊格娜提亚·莫扎特（1751-1829），昵称南妮儿，钢琴家，天赋过人，早年同年幼的莫扎特一同旅行演出。

沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特　致父亲利奥波德·莫扎特（萨尔茨堡）

曼海姆，1777年11月29日

我亲爱的父亲！

今天上午我收到了您24号的来信，依我看来，面对突如其来的好运或歹运，您没能做到处之泰然。到目前为止，事实证明我们一家四口从来没有特别幸运但也没有特别不幸，为此我感谢天主。但您对我和妈妈如此一番责备，实在不公平。我们没有任何不必要的花销，至于旅途中的必要开支，您知道得很清楚，比我们都清楚。我们在慕尼黑待了那么久，除了我自己不能怪任何人。如果我是一个人出来的话，我一定干脆就留在那里了。至于说我们为什么在奥格斯堡待了14天？我不禁怀疑，您大概没收到我从奥格斯堡寄出的信？我本来想举办一场音乐会。但他们让我失望了，这时就已经过去了8天。我决定无论如何得动身离开了，他们却不让我走，他们希望我能举办一场音乐会，我希望他们求我，然后他们这么做了，我便办了音乐会。这就是您说的14天。为什么我们直接就去了曼海姆？这个问题我在上一封信里已经回答了。至于我们为什么还在这里？您真的认为我没有任何正当理由留在这里吗？但是我可以告诉您，我的父亲……好，您的确应该知道原因和整件事情的来龙去脉。但是上帝做证，我现在并不想说这件事，因为我今天没法说出一丁点儿细节，只能告诉您一些不确定的消息。以我对您的了解，这只会让您徒增担心、忧虑，而这正是我一直以来努力避免的。但是如果您把这归结于我的疏忽、轻率和懒惰，那我只能谢谢您对我的评价。我打心里感到遗憾，因为您根本不了解我，不了解您的儿子。

我并不是无忧无虑，我只是准备好承受一切情况。因此，只要无损于我的荣誉和莫扎特这个好名声，我就可以耐心等待并忍受一切。因为如果必须如此，那也只好顺其自然了。但我现在就请您不要总是过早地高兴或苦恼，因为无论发生什么事，只要我们身体健康，就一切都好。因为幸福只存在于我们的想象之中。上个星期四即18号，也就是圣伊丽莎白瞻礼日[21]的前一天上午，我去拜访了萨维奥利伯爵，问他选帝侯泰奥多尔是否可以让我今年冬天留在曼海姆，因为我想给小王子上课。他回答道：“好，我会向选帝侯提议的，如果这件事取决于我的话，那一定没问题。”下午我去了坎纳比希那儿，因为拜访伯爵是他向我建议的，所以他立刻就问我是否去过了。我就把情况都跟他说了。他说：“我非常希望您能留下来和我们一起过这个冬天，但我更希望您能在这里有份适合您的长久职位。”我回答说：“没什么能比在您这里安顿下来更好了，但我真的不知道有没有可能长留下来。您已经有两个乐长了。我不知道我能做些什么，我不想地位还不如福格勒[22]！”“这是不会的，”他说，“这里没有一个乐手在乐长之下，更不会在乐团负责人之下。选帝侯可以任命您为室内乐作曲家。您再等等，我会和萨维奥利伯爵谈谈这件事。”星期四举行了一场盛大的音乐会。伯爵一看到我就请我见谅，他还没和选帝侯说那件事，因为现在仍在选帝侯命名日庆典期间。等庆典一结束，也就是下周一，他一定和选帝侯说这件事。然后我又等了3天，什么消息也没等到。当我去找他询问时，他说：“我的好莫扎特先生，昨天是星期五，今天是狩猎日，所以我不可能问选帝侯这件事，但明天这个时候我肯定会给您一个答复。”我请求他不要忘记了。说实话，我离开的时候相当生气，于是决定把我最简单的6首关于J.C.费舍尔小步舞曲的变奏曲[23]呈现给年轻伯爵（我就是为了这个目的才把谱子重新誊抄了1份），以便有机会亲自与选帝侯交谈。您无法想象那位家庭女教师见到我来访有多高兴，礼数周全地接待了我。当我拿出变奏曲乐谱，并告诉她这是为伯爵而创作的曲子时，她说：“啊！您太好了。不过您是否也为伯爵夫人写点什么了？”“还没有，”我说，“但如果我在这里待得够久，有时间写点什么的话，我自然会的。”“顺便跟您道贺一句，”她说，“我非常高兴您能留在这里过冬。”“我？我还不知道这件事！”“真令人吃惊。太奇怪了！选帝侯最近这么亲口跟我说的。‘顺便一提，’他说，‘莫扎特整个冬天都留在这里。’”好了，如果他真的这么亲口说了，那就是说唯一可以说这句话的人已经同意了，如果没有选帝侯的许可，我当然不能留在这里。然后我就把整件事情都告诉了那位家庭女教师。我们商量好第二天（也就是今天）我4点钟过去，给伯爵夫人带点乐谱。她会在我来之前和选帝侯说话，这样我就一定能见到他。我今天去了，但他没来。明天我会再去一次。我为伯爵夫人写了一个回旋曲。现在您说说看，我没有正当理由留在这里等待结果吗？我应该现在就动身离开这个有重大进展的地方吗？我现在可是有机会能与选帝侯本人交谈。我想这个冬天我很可能会在这里度过了，因为选帝侯喜欢我，欣赏我，并且知道我能做些什么。我希望下一封信能给您带来好消息。我再次请您不要过早高兴或是苦恼，并且不要向任何人透露这件事，除了布林格先生和姐姐。这里我寄给姐姐我为坎纳比希夫人写的奏鸣曲[24]快板和行板乐谱。回旋曲下回再寄，不然这次的信就太厚了。您必须保留原件。您可以以每张6分钱的价钱让别人誊抄这些乐谱，而我在这儿得花每张24分。您不觉得这很贵吗？再见了！吻您的双手十万次，真心拥抱我的姐姐。

我是您听话的儿子

沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特

您可能已经听过这首奏鸣曲的一些片段了。因为这首曲子在坎纳比希那里每天至少被吹拉弹唱演奏三遍！不过当然都是低声演奏的。

玛丽亚·安娜·莫扎特补充：

我亲爱的丈夫，我吻你和南妮儿一千次，请你向所有朋友转达我们的祝福。我下次再多写一点儿，现在已经是夜里12点了，再见。

我依旧是你忠实的妻子

玛丽亚·安娜·莫扎特

[21]圣人瞻礼日起源于非常早期的基督教传统，即每年在殉道者逝世的日子或者在天堂出生的日子纪念殉道者。伊丽莎白是匈牙利的安德鲁二世国王和米拉尼亚的格特鲁德的女儿，因“玫瑰奇迹”而闻名。

[22]乔治·约瑟夫·福格勒（1749-1814），德国作曲家、管风琴师、音乐教育家、理论家。

[23]选自由J.C.费舍尔所作的小步舞曲的变奏曲12首，K.179/189a。

[24]C大调第七号钢琴奏鸣曲，K.309/284b。

利奥波德·莫扎特　致儿子沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特（曼海姆）

萨尔茨堡，1777年12月4日

我亲爱的妻子，亲爱的儿子！

关于上封信里你们所说的必须等待的事情，我没有任何反对意见。至于你们旅行中那些违背我的意见，给我们带来不利甚至造成明显损害的事情，也没什么好说的了，因为这些都过去了，没法改变了。只是你，我的儿子，竟然写信跟我说，一切打算都是多余的，没有任何用，因为我们不知道究竟会发生什么。这种话绝对是不经思考，轻率写下的。没有一个基督徒，不，我应该说没有一个理智的人会否认，一切都必将遵循天主的意志发生。但这样就能得出结论说，我们应该闭着眼睛行动，无忧无虑地活着，不为未来做打算，只等着事情降临头顶吗？难道天主和这个理性的世界不曾要求过我们，不管做什么，都应该用人类的理智尽量全面地考虑后果，并且尽力为未来做准备吗？如果这些对我们的一切行为来说都是必要的，那考虑到我们目前的处境，对于一场旅行来说，周全考虑难道不是更有必要吗？或者你还没经历过这种后果？光是采取行动让选帝侯这个冬天把你留在那里，对你来说就已经够了吗？难道你不必……难道你不该早点考虑可以采取的计划，以防事情进展不顺利吗？难道你不该早点告诉我这件事，听听我的意见吗？现在好了，现在你终于写信了。可你写了什么？“如果我们无论如何要动身离开这里，那我们就直接去魏尔堡找拿骚-魏尔堡公主（你为她在荷兰写了奏鸣曲[25]等）。”还有“只要那里官员的饭菜合我们口味，我们就留下来。”这是何等的趣闻！这种语言，和你之前的那些信一样，只有一个绝望的人才会这么说话，用以安慰自己和我。不过你还有希望得到6个金路易，这些钱会让一切都好转起来。现在我的问题是，你是否真的确定公主在那里？她不会无缘无故地去那里，因为她丈夫在管理军队，目前在海牙。你难道不应该早点告诉我这件事吗？另一个问题是，你不觉得先去美因茨，再从那里经过法兰克福去魏尔堡更好吗？毕竟，从曼海姆去魏尔堡的路线会经过法兰克福，而且因为你不会一直在魏尔堡待着，去美因茨的路又会再次经过法兰克福。但是如果你先去美因茨再去魏尔堡，那你也许可以抄一条经过拿骚的近路从魏尔堡到科布伦茨。或者你想绕开美因茨吗？我们在那里有那么多好朋友。那时候即使我们没有去拜访生病的选帝侯，也演了3场音乐会，赚了200弗罗林。告诉我吧，我亲爱的儿子，现在这些都是没必要的打算吗？你亲爱的好妈妈告诉我，她之后会为你们的开支勤快地记账。很好！详细的账单我不要求，也从没想过要这么一份。但是你们在到达奥格斯堡的时候就应该写信给我，告诉我你们在慕尼黑的阿尔贝特那里花了多少钱，在路途上花了多少钱，现在还剩下多少多少钱。你从奥格斯堡写信告诉我，加上音乐会的收入之后，你们总计大概花了20弗罗林。在你从曼海姆寄来的第二封信里，你至少应该告诉我，这段路途花了你们多少多少数目，你们现在还剩下……这样我就能及时做好准备。我为你准备一份贷款信用证寄到奥格斯堡也是没必要的打算吗？如果你不给我的故交赫尔佐克先生一份信用证，你真的认为他会因为你从曼海姆寄去的那些信给你汇钱吗？想都不要想！他最有可能做的事情是先来问我的意见。为什么只有当你们陷入困境里，我才能知道你们需要钱？你想等等看选帝侯会给你什么不是吗？也许你是为了不给我添堵，但事实上只有当你向我及时如实地报告一切，才能给我少添点堵，因为我比你们俩都清楚，在这样的旅行中，一个人必须怎样为一切可能的状况做好准备，才不至于哪天就陷入意想不到的可怕窘境。在这种时刻，所有的朋友都会消失！一个人必须快乐，必须享受生活！但是一个人也必须花时间去慎重考虑，这一点必须是你旅行过程中的头等大事，哪一天都不能让自己处于不利境地。日子一天天过去了，不过无论如何现在旅行的时间还很短，但这些在旅馆里度过的日子都花费不菲。公正的上帝啊！你让我现在不要为未来打算，哪怕我已经因为你们欠了450弗罗林的债。你也许觉得跟我说上百个愚蠢的笑话，就能给我带来好心情。我很高兴你心态很好，但是如果你能用理性写下你去魏尔堡的原因，你现在的处境，以及你接下来怎么打算的，最重要的是如果你能在任何情况下都听取我的意见，而不是写下按字母排序的问候语[26]，我会更加开心。这些都能在邮寄日之前做完，因为你不可能现在才有了这个主意，也不可能自己就知道了公主在那里，如果没人给你提个醒的话。总之一句话！这些都不是多余的打算，因为只有当一个人脑子里同时有两三个计划，并事先做出必要的准备，才能保证如果一个计划失败了，还可以毫不耽搁地采取另一个。不这么做的人，就是一个不理性的人，一个轻率的人。在今天这个世界，这样的人不管有多聪明，也总是会落于人后，甚至会变得很不幸，因为他总是被谄媚者、小人或嫉妒者所愚弄。注意到这一点吧，我的儿子，如果能在1000人中发现一个人可以不图私利跟你做真正的朋友，那就是这个世界最大的奇迹。好好研究一下那些自称是你朋友，或者炫耀他是你朋友的人，你就会知道他们为什么跟你交往。如果他们在你身上没有任何好处可捞，那他们就会去找下一个对他们有用的人当朋友。或者还有一种情况，他们跟你做朋友，是为了通过抬举你来惹恼第三个人。如果在曼海姆最后毫无结果，你们就要计划去美因茨，法兰克福，魏尔堡，科布伦茨等地。你们必须始终尽量寻找彼此相邻的地方，这样的话，可能的情况下，做个短途旅行，就可以很快再到一个有收入来源的地方。如果这封信寄到曼海姆的时候，你们已经去了魏尔堡，那我也无能为力了。但如果你们还在曼海姆，并且必须动身离开，妈妈会在地图上发现你们的最佳路线是先去美因茨，不然你们就会错过美因茨或者折回去一段路。在魏尔堡你们得记住，那里找不到一个天主教教堂，因为那里所有人都是新教徒或者加尔文教徒。我希望你们在那里不要逗留太久。

谁告诉你们从维尔茨堡到曼海姆必须穿过施佩萨尔特森林，就因为这个森林在富尔达和法兰克福之间的阿沙芬堡？这估计又是贝克先生骗你们的。阿沙芬堡和维尔茨堡之间相距10里路。可能去曼海姆的时候，人们得花几个小时从右边穿过森林。但是维尔茨堡附近什么都没有，无论你们是否去过。

注意：关于从魏尔堡到科布伦茨的旅程，我还有一个新发现，就是，这条路穿过乡间，会比从美因茨去科布伦茨的路要安全，那条路太靠近莱茵河了。我现在想听听你们接下来的打算，我从来没有想到，我亲爱的妻子竟然没有及时地向我报告旅行的精确花销，因为我已经要过两次阿尔贝特那里的账单了，并且你们也应该告诉我在拉姆旅馆那里花费了多少。但是你们的所有开销我目前都一无所知。我请妈妈一定要就这一点给我写一封机密信，我不要啰里啰唆的解释，但是我得看到房东的账单，看看他们是怎么招待你们的，所有钱都花在了哪里。现在我们必须认真严肃考虑一下怎么让你们摆脱眼下的处境，怎样尽可能经济地旅行，并且做出合理准备，但是所有的坏消息和好消息你们都必须立刻让我知道。你们一定不能卖了马车。

愿天主保佑你们和我，南妮儿和我吻你们一亿次，我是你们的老丈夫和老父亲

莫扎特

切尔宁伯爵让我转达他对你们的问候。有传言说大主教不仅要送海登去意大利[27]，而且还想送他和特林德尔去博尔扎诺。但是特林德尔先生婉拒了。我的好沃尔夫冈，我请你考虑周全一切，不要总是只给我写已经过去了的事情。不然我们两个都不开心。

[25]即小提琴奏鸣曲K.26-31。

[26]在莫扎特和妈妈1777年11月26日致利奥波德信的末尾，他们请父亲向萨尔茨堡的亲朋好友转达问候，并将所有人的名字按首字母顺序排列写下。

[27]大主教想送米夏埃尔·海登去意大利找一位乐长和可靠的管风琴师、钢琴师。

利奥波德·莫扎特　致儿子沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特（曼海姆）

萨尔茨堡，1778年2月5日

我亲爱的儿子！

按我的推测，这应该是你在曼海姆能收到的最后一封信了，所以这封信是单独写给你的。尽管你可能会想到，要和你分离得更远这件事对我来说多么难以接受，但是你还是不可能对我心头的沉重感同身受。如果你愿意花时间回忆一下，在你们娇嫩的少年时代，我带着你们两个孩子一起做了些什么，你就不会指责我胆怯，而是会像其他人一样，承认我是个男人，并且是一个一直敢于冒险的男人。只是我做事总是尽量地三思而后行，因为人不能阻止意外发生，只有上帝能预见未来。当然，直到现在我们既算不上幸福也算不上悲哀，感谢天主，让我们走了一条平平安安的中间道路。我们尽自己所能来让你幸福，也希望通过你让我们更幸福，至少让你的人生有一个坚实的根基。但是我们的命运事与愿违。正如你所知，我们的最后一步让我深陷泥潭，你知道，现在我大概欠了700弗罗林的债款，以我微薄的月俸，我不知道现在该怎么养活自己、妈妈和你姐姐。因为我活到现在都没指望过从大主教那里拿到更多的钱。现在你一定一清二楚了，你年迈的双亲，打心里爱着你的姐姐，我们未来的命运都在你一个人手里。从你们出生起，或者说更早，打从我结婚起，我就无比艰难地靠着20弗罗林的固定月俸度日，一点一点供养妻子和7个孩子，2个仆人还有外婆，此外还要支付分娩、葬礼和看病费用。如果你考虑到了这些，你就会相信，我不仅从来没有花过一分钱让自己有一点点享受，而且因为没有得到天主的特别眷顾，尽管我如此周全打算，如此拼命，还是从未摆脱掉负债的生活。但即便如此，我也从未像现在这样债台高筑。我把我所有的时间都献给了你们两个，只希望确保你们能够养活自己，让我拥有一个安宁的晚年，能够对你们的教育问心无愧，不用操太远的心，只需关心我自己的灵魂救赎，平静地迎接死亡。但是命数和天主的意志让我现在再次接受这份讨厌的上课工作，并且是在这样一个地方-付出那么艰辛的努力，收入却如此微薄，以至于每个月都挣不够足以养活自己和家庭的钱。尽管如此，我还是会保持心情愉快，自我宽慰，为了至少能获得一点儿微薄的收入。我亲爱的沃尔夫冈，我现在不但不会不信任你，一点儿也不，相反，我完全信赖你并且希望你能孝顺。这一切都取决于你必然具备的理智，只要你愿意倾听它，即使在幸福的时刻也要倾听它。最后这点不能强求。但你一定要用理智考虑一切，我希望也请求你这么做。

你现在要进入一个完全不一样的世界了：你千万不要认为我说巴黎很危险是出于偏见，相反，根据我个人的经验，我没有任何理由认为巴黎危险。但我那时的处境和你现在的处境天差地别。我们当时住在一位使臣家里，第二次是在一个独立的房子里。我那时人到中年，你们还是孩子，我避免一切社交，尤其避免和我们这个行业的人熟识。你记得我在意大利也是这么做的。我只和上层阶级结识、交往，其中都是中年人，我不和年轻人结识，即使他们也属于顶级阶层。我不常邀请任何人来家里做客，以便保持自己的自由，我一直认为在我方便的时候去拜访别人是更加明智的做法。如果我不喜欢那个人，或者我有工作和别的安排，我就可以直接离开。但如果别人来拜访我，并且举止粗鲁，我就不知道该怎么摆脱他们了。即使是一个并不讨厌的人，也总是会影响我去做重要的工作。你还是个22岁的年轻人，没有老年人的那种严肃态度，无法阻止别人来结识你，好把你带入他的社交圈，慢慢利用你。这样的人可以来自任何阶层，可能是冒险家、吹牛大王或者骗子，可能是个年轻人也可能是个年纪大的。一个人会不知不觉地进入这样的圈套，然后就无法抽身了。至于女人的问题，我其实一点儿也不想去谈，因为这需要极度的克制和理智，天性本身就是我们的敌人。一个人如果没有运用他的全部理智去进行必要的克制，之后就算再怎么努力想走出这个迷宫也是徒劳。这种悲剧常常会以死亡收场。我们经常多么愚蠢地被起初并不起眼的笑料、阿谀者和小丑蒙骗，一旦后来理智察觉到了，我们就会对此十分难为情。你可能已经尝到了一些苦头。我不想责备你。我知道你不仅把我当作父亲来爱，也把我当作一位最值得信赖的朋友来爱。现在你看到了，我们的幸与不幸，我的后半生甚至是我将要来临的死亡，都放在了你的手里，就像放在上帝手里一样。如果我了解你的话，我当然只希望你快乐，你不在的日子里，这个心愿就能宽慰我，因为我已经被剥夺了属于父亲的幸福，无法听你说话、看到你，也不能拥抱你。像一个虔诚的天主教徒那样生活吧！爱并敬畏天主，热忱且虔诚地向他祈祷，过基督徒应该过的生活。这样就算我再也见不到你了，我临死之时也不会忧惧不安。

真心给你来自父亲的祝福，我至死都是你忠实的父亲和最可靠的朋友

利奥波德·莫扎特

这里是我们在巴黎的熟人名单。他们都会很期待见到你。

给妻子（补写在信封上）

我亲爱的妻子！

因为你们会在11号或者12号收到这封信，我不得不怀疑沃尔夫冈在曼海姆是否还能再收到一封信。通过这段附记，我向他道别！我满含泪水写下这些话。南妮儿亲吻她亲爱的兄弟沃尔夫冈一百万次。她本来要在我的信上再写点什么来道别，但信已经写得太满了，而且我不能让她读这封信。我们请沃尔夫冈照顾好自己的身体，保持家里的饮食习惯，不然他一到巴黎就会脸色苍白。所有的辛辣食物对他的健康都有害。我希望他带上那本大拉丁语祈祷书，上面找得到圣母小日课的所有赞美诗。如果他想在曼海姆买德语版的圣母小日课，以便能用德语读，那他必须找遍所有版本。因为拉丁语的赞美诗很难理解，如果他有德语版的在手边会好一点儿。宗教音乐会也会演出模仿对位法赞美诗[28]，他可以通过这种方式来获得巨大声誉。也许他还能在那里演出他的《主之仁慈》[29]。歌剧歌手不来萨尔茨堡了，他们要去施特劳宾取悦奥地利官员。大主教再次要求长官举行9场舞会，昨天是第1场，有30个人出席。舞会一直开到1点半，但9点半前都没有人来，直到10点钟才有人开始跳舞。我们吃了只阉鸡，喝了6大杯葡萄酒。我希望你们收到了誊抄好的两首四手联弹奏鸣曲[30]，费舍尔变奏曲和回旋曲[31]，都打包在了一个信封里。阿德加瑟先生的灵魂在死后再也找不到好的风箱师傅了。因为教堂的老风箱师，80岁的托马斯也随他而去了。最近最大的新闻是，巴利桑尼夫人为她可敬的老丈夫不可思议地争风吃醋，就因为他和儿子凯科好几个晚上都去了英俊的弗赖绍夫先生家里演出，而他有一个比她更漂亮但头脑简单的妻子。这真是难以置信的小题大做。再见。我们吻你们千百万次。

莫扎特

所有人都向你们致以最美好的祝福，尤其是布林格先生，警官中士克莱斯先生和韦伯·莫克的妻子等人。

[28]对位法采用的方法有两种，即模仿与对比，赋格曲是用模仿方法创作的最高级形式。

[29]宗教音乐《主之仁慈》，K.222/205a。

[30]降B大调四手联弹钢琴奏鸣曲，K.358/186c；D大调四手联弹钢琴奏鸣曲，K.381/123a。

[31]指的是《C大调第七号钢琴奏鸣曲》最后一个乐章，K.309/284b。

沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特　致父亲利奥波德·莫扎特（萨尔茨堡）

曼海姆，1778年7月3日

先生

我亲爱的父亲！

我有一个非常悲伤痛苦的消息要告诉您，这也是我直到现在才回复您上个月11号那封信的原因。

亲爱的妈妈病得很厉害，她像以往那样放过血了，这确实很有必要，这之后她状态很不错。但几天后她就开始抱怨打寒战，同时还发烧，然后腹泻、头痛也来了。起初我们只使用我们的家庭药方-抗痉挛药粉。我们本来也想用黑色药粉，但手边没有，这里也买不到，连抗癫痫药粉这个名字都没人知道。但妈妈的情况越来越糟，几乎说不了话，也失去了听力，以至于我们不得不对她大喊大叫，因此格林男爵派他的医生来看她。她非常虚弱，仍然发着烧，神志不清。医生让我对她抱有希望，但我实在无法太乐观。这么多天以来，我日夜徘徊在恐惧和希望之间，但我已完全皈依天主的意志，并希望您和亲爱的姐姐也能如此。不然还有什么别的方法能让我们保持平静呢？我是说，相对平静一点儿，因为我们不可能完全保持平静。这样一来，无论结果如何，我心里都会感到安慰，因为我知道天主会为我们做出最好的安排，即使是那些违背我们意愿的事情，也一样是为了我们好。因为我相信（我不会改变这个想法），没有哪个医生、个人，也没有什么不幸、意外真的可以给予或夺走一个人的生命。只有上帝可以做到。那些只是他最常使用的工具，但并不是全部。毕竟我们有时会看到有的人昏厥、倒下，一会儿就死了。当我们的时辰来临时，一切手段都是徒劳的，这些手段与其说阻止死亡不如说是加快了死亡。我们的亡友黑夫纳已经印证了这一点！我说这些并不意味着妈妈已经没希望了，马上或者一定会死。她可以重新恢复健康，但只有当主也这么希望之时才能如此。在尽力为亲爱的妈妈向主祈求健康和生命之后，我喜欢这样想想来自我安慰，因为这真的会让我感到更加开朗、平静和宽慰。您很容易能想到我多么需要这些！但现在说说别的吧。让我们抛开这些悲伤的想法，我们仍然要抱有希望，但不要太多；我们要信赖上帝，自我宽慰-如果这是全能之主的意志，那一切安排都是好的，因为他最了解什么有利于我们暂时的福分，什么有助于我们永恒的福祉和救赎。

我为宗教音乐会的开幕写了一部交响曲[32]，它在基督圣体节[33]上演时受到了热烈欢迎。我还听说在《欧洲信使报》（Courrier de l'Europe）上有一篇相关报道，可见人们多么喜欢它。排演的时候我非常害怕，因为我这辈子还没听到过比这更糟糕的演奏。您无法想象他们如何接连两次敷衍、拉锯似的演奏这首曲子。我当时真的害怕极了。我很想再排演一次，但是因为要排演的曲目那么多，最后就没有时间了。所以我只好惴惴不安，怀着不满和气愤的心情上床睡觉。第二天我决定不去音乐会演出了。但是傍晚时天气很好，我最终还是下定决心过去，并打定主意，如果一切还像排演时那么糟糕，我就走到乐团里，把小提琴从首席小提琴手拉乌斯先生的手里夺过来，自己亲自来指挥。我向上帝祈祷一切可以顺利进行，因为这一切都是为了他的荣耀光辉。看吧，交响曲开始了，拉夫[34]站在我旁边。在第一乐章快板的中间，有一段我知道一定会取悦听众的段落。他们果然都为之痴狂，掌声雷动。因为我写的时候就知道会产生什么样的效果，所以我在结尾处又弹了一遍这一段落。这时观众们开始齐喊“从头再奏”。他们也喜欢行板，但更喜欢最后的快板。我注意到这里演出的作品，所有的终曲快板都像开场快板一样，总是让所有乐器齐奏[35]。于是我决定别出机杼，在开始的前八小节只让两把小提琴和钢琴弱奏，紧接着立刻是一段强音响奏。不出所料，听众们在钢琴弱奏部分发出嘘声要求安静，然后强音一响起来，他们就开始齐刷刷地鼓掌。我非常高兴，所以交响曲一演奏完毕，我就去皇宫里要了一份精美的冰激凌。然后如我所承诺的那样做了念珠祷告，之后就回家了，因为我总是在家时最开心，也最愿意待在家里。或者待在一个善良又可靠的德国人家里也行，只要他未婚时过着典范的基督徒生活，结婚后挚爱妻子并好好教育孩子。

现在我要说一条您可能已经知道的新闻。那个不信天主的头号流氓伏尔泰像狗一样，像一头畜生那样翘辫子了。这就是他的报应！您说得对，我们已经欠了特蕾泽5个季度的工资。您很早就看出来我不喜欢这里，原因很多，但是因为我现在人已经在这里，再去细说它们也没什么用。但这错不在我，永远都不会是我的过错，因为我愿意倾尽全力做到最好。好吧，上帝会安排好一切的！目前我脑子里盘算着一些事情，为此我每天都向天主祈祷，如果这也符合他的意志，那事情就会如愿发生的，如果不符合，我也不会不满意，因为至少我做了自己能做的。但如果一切如我所愿进展顺利，那您也必须尽您那份力，不然整件事情就无法圆满办成。凭您对我的爱，我相信您一定会尽力而为的。只是关于这件事，您现在不要做无谓的猜想。我早就求您给我这份恩典-在时机成熟前，不要催我说清楚一切想法。

至于歌剧，现在的情况是这样的，目前很难找到优秀的歌词。那些老歌词是一流的，但不适合现代风格，新歌词又都没什么价值。歌词本来是法国人唯一能引以为傲的东西，现在却每况愈下，但在这里，歌词正是唯一必须出色的东西，因为法国人不理解音乐。现在我有两部咏叹调歌剧可以写，一个两幕剧，一个三幕剧。两幕剧是《亚历山德拉和罗克珊》（Alexandra et Roxane），但剧本作者目前还在乡下。三幕剧是从梅塔斯塔齐奥[36]《得摩丰》（Demofonte）翻译过来的，其中穿插着合唱和舞蹈，整体风格很适合法国舞台，但是这个剧本我至今还没能看到。

写信告诉我您在萨尔茨堡是否已买到施罗特的协奏曲，或者是胡尔曼德尔的奏鸣曲？我想买下它们寄给您。这两部作品都非常美。至于凡尔赛宫，它决不在我的考虑范围内。为此我也征求了格林男爵和其他好朋友的意见，他们都和我想得一样。薪水不多，但你却必须在那个地方煎熬6个月，什么额外收入都没有，最终白白埋没自己的才华。谁在巴黎为王室服务，谁就会被遗忘。但我想当一位管风琴师！我非常想要一个体面的工作，但只能是乐长，并且收入丰厚。

那么再见了！保重您的身体，信赖上帝，您就能得到安慰。我亲爱的妈妈现在在全能之主的手中。如果他仍要把她送还我们，如我们所愿，我们自然感恩不尽，但如果他要把她带去他身边，任凭我们怎样恐惧、担心或者绝望，都是无济于事的。还是让我们坚定地皈依上帝那神性的意志吧，相信这一切都是为了我们好，因为他不会无缘无故地做出安排。再见，最亲爱的爸爸！为了我，您要好好保重身体。我亲吻您的双手一千次，全心拥抱我的姐姐。

我是您听话的儿子

沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特

[32]D大调第三十一（巴黎）交响曲，K.297/300a。

[33]基督圣体节（5月底或6月初）圣灵降临节（复活节后第50天）后的第二个星期四。

[34]安东·拉夫（1714-1797），德国男高音。

[35]指所有乐器或人声按同度或相隔八度演奏。

[36]皮特罗·梅塔斯塔齐奥（Pietro Metastasio），原名皮特罗·安东尼奥·多梅尼科·特拉帕西（Pietro Antonio Domenico Trapassi，1698-1782），意大利著名正歌剧作家。

沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特　致父亲利奥波德·莫扎特（萨尔茨堡）

曼海姆，1778年7月9日

我希望您已经准备好坚强地接受这个最悲痛的消息。我上一封3号的信就让您做好心理准备，不要期待听到好消息。因为就在那一天，3号晚上的10点21分，妈妈安息主怀了。事实上，在我给您写信的时候，她已经在享受天堂之福了。一切都结束了。我是在那天夜里给您写信的，希望您和亲爱的姐姐能原谅我这小小的但十分必要的欺骗。因为想到你们定会和我一样伤心痛苦，我实在不忍心立刻告诉你们这个可怕的消息。但是我希望你们两个已经准备好了接受最坏的消息，愿你们在所有自然而适度的痛苦和哭泣过后，终能皈依天主的意志，尊崇他那不可探究、深不可测的全知神意。您不难想象我经受了些什么，需要多少勇气和坚强才能镇定地忍受一天天每况愈下的这一切。然而是仁慈的上帝赐予了我这个恩典-痛苦我体尝够了，也哭够了，但是这些有什么用呢？我必须试着自我宽慰。亲爱的父亲，亲爱的姐姐，你们也要这样做！哭吧，尽情地痛哭，但最后你们要安慰好自己。不要忘记，全能的上帝已经决定了这件事，我们能做什么来反抗他呢？还是向主祈祷并感谢他的仁慈安排吧，因为妈妈是非常幸福地死去的。在那些伤心的时刻，我有三个聊以自慰的想法。一是完全信赖上帝并且皈依他的意志。二是妈妈那从容、美丽的死亡让我不禁想到她在那一瞬间变得多么幸福，也让我想到她现在不知道比我们幸福多少倍。那一瞬间我甚至希望可以和她一起走。这个愿望、这个渴望反过来成了我的第三个慰藉之源-我们不是永远失去了她，我们会再次见到她，并且会比在人世间更加幸福快乐地相聚在一起。只是我们不知道我们的时辰什么时候会到，但我一点都不为此焦虑。当天主决定了，我就服从他的安排。现在，他最神圣、圣洁的意志已经实现了。让我们为妈妈的灵魂虔诚祷告吧，然后就让我们继续前行，去面对其他事情。每件事情都有它自己的时辰。现在我在德皮奈夫人和格林先生家里写这封信，我目前住在这里，有一个漂亮的房间，窗外风景宜人。就眼下这个状况而言，我在这里称得上愉快了。如果能听到我亲爱的父亲和姐姐镇定而坚强地完全皈依上帝的意志，全心全意地信赖他，坚信他为我们做出了最好的安排，这对我来说将是莫大的帮助和安慰。我最亲爱的父亲，要保重身体！最亲爱的姐姐，你也要保重！你还不曾体尝过你弟弟的好心肠，因为他还没有机会展现这一点。我的亲人，照顾好自己的身体，要记住你们还有一个儿子，一个兄弟，他会竭尽全力让你们幸福。同时他也知道，有一天你们将不再否定他那些必将带来荣耀的心愿和快乐[37]，你们也会同样竭尽所能地使他幸福。噢！然后我们就尽可能地在这人世间平静、快乐地生活在一起。当天主最终决定了时辰，我们就在彼岸再次相聚，正是为了这个目的我们才被选中和创造出来。

您上一封6月29号的信我已经收到，知道你们两个都身体健康，我很高兴，感谢赞美主。读到您写的海登醉酒那段[38]，我忍不住哈哈大笑。如果我在场的话，我一定会立刻在他耳边低语：“阿德加瑟。”这实在是个耻辱，这么能干的一个人竟然由于个人过错而无法履行职责，在这样一个为荣耀天主而设立的职位上犯下过错，而且是当着大主教和整个宫廷官员的面，教堂里都是人。这真的太可怕了。这也是我厌恶萨尔茨堡的主要原因之一。那些粗俗、无礼、放荡的宫廷乐师，没有一个诚实有教养的人可以和他们一起生活。真的，没人能接受与他们为伍，都会为他们感到羞耻。可能正是出于这个原因，音乐家在我们那儿既不受欢迎，也不受人尊重。如果他们能像曼海姆管弦乐团那样被组织起来该多好！那是一支被纪律主宰的乐团！指挥坎纳比希先生很有权威，所以一切事情都能被认真执行。坎纳比希是我见过的最棒的指挥，下属对他又爱又怕。他在整座城市都享有盛名，他的小兵们名声也很好。他们的行为举止自然十分不同，他们很有教养，衣着得体，不去酒馆，也不酗酒。但这些在萨尔茨堡永远也做不到，除非大主教信任您或我，将管弦乐团交给我们全权掌管，这非常必要，不然一切都是徒劳。因为在萨尔茨堡，每个人都-或者不如说没有人-关心管弦乐团。如果要我接受这个职位，那就要让我在行动上有完全的自由，宫廷音乐负责人不能在管弦乐团以及所有与乐团有关的事情上对我指手画脚。因为一位朝臣不能当乐长，但一位乐长可以是朝臣。顺便告诉您，选帝侯泰奥多尔现在又回到曼海姆了。坎纳比希夫人和坎纳比希本人都和我保持着通信。我担心管弦乐团要大大缩编，如果真是这样，那将是永远的遗憾，但如果不致如此，我就仍然会抱有希望。您知道，我不再要别的什么了，除了一个体面的工作、良好的声誉和可观的收入，无论在哪里，只要是在一个天主教国家里。您在整个事件中与施塔尔亨贝格伯爵巧妙周旋，简直就像尤利西斯一样[39]。您只管按照您的打算进行下去吧，注意别让自己被蒙骗了。尤其是当您要与那只傲慢的蠢鹅谈话时，要更加警惕。我是知道她的，相信我，她绝对是个口蜜腹剑的人。这很正常，毕竟整件事情还处在悬而未决的状态。在我真正能够下定决心之前，还有许多条件要被许可。但即使一切都进展顺利，我也宁愿待在萨尔茨堡以外的任何地方。不过我也不太为之发愁，因为他们不大可能会准许我的所有要求，我要得太多了。但也不是完全不可能。如果一切都进展顺利，安排妥当，我会毫不犹豫地答应下来，哪怕只是为了享受和您一起生活的快乐。但是如果萨尔茨堡人想要我，他们就必须满足我的一切心愿，不然他们决计得不到我。巴姆堡格修道院院长像一位修士那样死去了！[40]但我没听说圣十字修道院院长也死了。我很遗憾，他是那么正派可敬的一个人。您之前没有想过奥格斯堡教区主教策辛格会当上修道院院长吗？我以我的名誉担保，我从未想过他之外的任何人选，我不知道除了他还有谁能担任修道院院长。而且他对管弦乐团来说自然是一个好院长！年轻的施托克哈默小姐与她忠实的施塔尔亨贝格伯爵之前的每日散步终究开花结果了！他们真的很勤奋，一点儿也不懒。懒惰是一切恶习的开端。这个业余戏团最后竟然真的上台演出了！但是他们能演多久呢？我想，洛德龙女伯爵再也不想开这样一场音乐会了。切尔宁是一个过于欢快的年轻人，布鲁内蒂则很粗俗。

我的朋友拉夫明天就离开了，但是他要途经布鲁塞尔去亚琛和水疗中心，然后再从那儿去曼海姆，等他一到就会立刻告诉我，因为我们想保持通信。他向您和姐姐致以问候，虽然他不认识您。您说您很久没听我谈及跟我学作曲的女学生了，的确如此，但我能对您说些什么呢？她永远不会成为作曲家；我所有的努力都是徒劳的，因为首先她愚蠢透顶，其次她懒惰透顶。关于歌剧的情况，我上封信回答过您。至于诺韦尔[41]的芭蕾舞，我只说过他可能会写一个新的舞剧，其中只有半场以芭蕾舞形式上演，我正是为这部分舞蹈写乐曲[42]。也就是说，这部剧有六段是其他人写的，充满了可怕的法国陈腐气息，而交响曲和行列舞，大约有12段由我来创作。这个芭蕾舞剧目前已经上演了四次，大受欢迎。但我现在绝对什么都不写了，除非我事先知道我能得到什么。这个芭蕾舞剧音乐只是作为朋友送给诺韦尔的礼物。5月的最后一天，文德林先生离开了这里。如果我要见巴格男爵，那我必须有千里眼，因为他目前在伦敦，不在这儿。我是不是没有告诉您这些？您等着看吧，我以后一定会尽快回复您所有的信件。不过据说巴格男爵很快就会回来，我很高兴，原因很多，最重要的是在他家里总有机会认真排练。巴赫乐长很快也会来到这里，我觉得他会写一部歌剧。法国人就是蠢驴，永远都是。他们什么都不会，必须依靠外国人。我在宗教音乐会与皮钦尼[43]交谈过。无论我们什么时候偶然相遇，他对我都很有礼貌，我对他也是。除此之外我没有结交朋友，不管是和他，还是和其他作曲家。我明白我在做什么，他们也明白，这就够了。我的交响曲在宗教音乐会上获得了无与伦比的反响，这我也已经告诉您了。如果我受到委托要写一部歌剧，无疑会让我十分烦闷，但是我也不那么在意了，因为我已经习惯了，要是这该死的法语对音乐来说不那么可憎该多好！这很令人遗憾。相比之下，德国人则是神圣的。其次这些歌手-他们不配这个名字，因为他们不是在唱歌，而是用他们整个嗓子、鼻子和喉咙乱吼乱叫。为了下一个四旬节，我要给宗教音乐会写一部法国清唱剧。指挥勒格罗先生[44]对我有很深的偏见。您必须知道，复活节以来我再没有去见过他（尽管我之前每天都拜访他），因为他没有上演我的交响协奏曲[45]这件事让我很生气。我经常去拜访和他同住一宅的拉夫先生，每次都要经过他的房间。他的仆人和女仆每次都会看到我，我也每次都让他们代为致敬。他没有上演那部交响曲真的很让人遗憾，它本来会大受欢迎的。而现在他已经没这个机会了，他到哪儿找齐能够演奏这部交响曲的四个人呢？

有一天我去拜访拉夫，却被告知他出去了，不过很快就会回家，所以我打算等他回来。这时勒格罗先生走进房间说：“能再次有幸见到您真是个奇迹。”

“是的，我一直有很多事要做。”“您今天能留下来一起用餐吗？”“很抱歉，我已经有安排了。”“莫扎特先生，我们必须再次一块儿聚聚。”“我也很乐意。”长时间的沉默之后，他说：“顺便问您一句，您愿意为我给基督圣体日写一部大型交响乐吗？”

“为什么不呢？”“一言为定吗？”“哦，当然了！只要我确信它可以上演，不会经受那首交响协奏曲同样的命运就行。”然后话匣子就被打开了。他诚心诚意地道歉，但也知道没太多可说的。简单来说，交响曲得到了他的高度认可。勒格罗对此非常满意，他说这是他演出过的最好的交响曲。然而，行板却没有令他赏识的好运气。他说它转调太多，而且太长了。但他这么说是因为听众忘记了热烈鼓掌和喝彩，像在第一乐章和终曲乐章里一样。可是这里的行板确实受到了我自己、所有行家、音乐爱好者以及大多数听众的高度认可。与勒格罗所说的刚好完全相反，这段行板既自然又简短。但是为了让他（以及他所认为的不少人）满意，我已经重新写了一段新的行板。两段行板就其各自的形式而言都很出色，因为两者具有不同的特点，但我更喜欢新的行板。等我找到合适的机会，就把这个交响曲给您寄去，连同《小提琴演奏指导》、一些钢琴曲、福格勒的《声音科学》和《声音艺术》一起。然后我想听听您的意见，这个交响曲会以新的行板，在8月15号，也就是圣母升天节那天第二次上演。交响曲是re音，行板是sol音，这里的人们不说D大调或g小调。现在勒格罗已经很认可我了。该结尾了。如果您要写信给我，我觉得等您收到格林男爵的信之后再写会更好。格林先生很快就会给您写信。他和夫人都问候您并向您致以最真挚的哀悼。但他们希望您能够在无法改变的事情面前保持冷静。节哀顺变，热诚祈祷，这是我们唯一还能做的事了。我希望您能去马利亚平原朝圣教堂和洛雷托教堂那里做弥撒。我在这里也做了弥撒。至于给贝尔先生的推荐信，我认为这个没有必要寄给我，我从来没见过他。我只知道他是个不错的单簧管演奏者，但是很放荡。我不喜欢和这类人打交道。这得不到什么好名声。我一封推荐信都不想给他。这么做真的会让我很羞愧，即使他可以为我做什么！他在这里的名声并不好，许多人甚至没听说过他。两个施塔米茨里现在只有弟弟[46]在巴黎，大一点儿的那个[47]（真正的作曲家）目前在伦敦。他们是两个可怜的三流角色，赌博、酗酒、嫖妓，不是我会与之打交道的那类人，那个年轻的施塔米茨几乎都没有体面的衣服。顺便一说，如果布鲁内蒂那里的事情落空了，我很愿意推荐我的一个好朋友给大主教做首席小提琴手，他是一个体面、可敬又正派的人，非常可靠。我推测他大约四十岁，是一个鳏夫。他的名字叫罗特费舍尔，现在是拿骚-魏尔堡两个公主在基希海姆博兰登的首席演奏者，但他不太满意（我们私下偷偷说），因为他的选帝侯不喜欢他，或者说不喜欢他的音乐。他向我毛遂自荐，我很乐意帮帮他，因为他是我见过最棒的人。再见。我吻您的双手十万次，全心拥抱我的姐姐。

我是您听话的儿子

沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特

[37]可能暗指莫扎特的结婚打算。

[38]利奥波德在1778年6月29日的信里写道：在圣三一主日庆典上，海登演奏管风琴时手脑无法协作，演奏得十分糟糕，大家都以为他被已故管风琴师阿德加瑟（Adlgasser）的亡灵附体了，因为阿德加瑟正是在晚祷演奏时中风以致演奏失常，但海登的表现其实是醉酒所致。

[39]利奥波德在1778年6月29日的信里谈到自己如何巧妙地使得伯爵主动提出让莫扎特重返任职的想法；尤利西斯，又译俄底修斯，是罗马神话中的英雄，对应希腊神话中的奥德修斯（奥德赛），献木马计里应外合攻破特洛伊。

[40]以下为莫扎特回应父亲上一封信里所提及的家乡新闻。

[41]让-乔治·诺韦尔（Jean-Georges Noverre，1727-1810），法国舞蹈家、舞蹈理论家、芭蕾舞剧编导。

[42]芭蕾音乐《小玩物》。

[43]尼古拉·皮钦尼（Niccola Piccinni，1728-1800），意大利多产作曲家，代表作《伊菲格涅亚在陶罗人里》。

[44]约瑟夫·勒格罗（Joseph Legros），1777-1791年担任宗教音乐会导演。

[45]即降E大调交响协奏曲，K.297b/Anh.C 14.01。

[46]指安东·塔达乌斯·约翰·尼波默克·施塔米茨（Anton Thadäus Johann Nepomuk Stamitz，1750或1754年至1798或1809年），捷克裔德国作曲家、小提琴家。早年从父约翰·施塔米茨（Johann Wenzel Anton Stamitz）学习，1770年随其兄卡尔·施塔米茨访问巴黎，1782-1789年在凡尔赛任职，1798年后不知所终。作品风格与卡尔·施塔米茨类似。

[47]指卡尔·菲利普·施塔米茨（Karl Philipp Stamitz，1745-1801），捷克裔德国作曲家、小提琴家。早年从父学习，1762年进入曼海姆管弦乐团，1770年移居巴黎。其作品为典型的古典主义风格。作有五十余首交响曲，十余首单簧管协奏曲，大量各种体裁的室内乐。

利奥波德·莫扎特　致儿子沃尔夫冈·阿马德乌斯·莫扎特（曼海姆）

萨尔茨堡，1778年7月13日

我亲爱的妻子，亲爱的儿子！

亲爱的妻子，为了不错过你的命名日，我今天就给你写信，这样信一定能在命名日之前到你手里。祝你命名日快乐，岁岁有今朝，希望万能的主保佑你这一天和未来都平安健康，保佑你在这个变幻莫测的人世间尽可能地幸福。我百分百确信，你如果要真正感到幸福，绝对不能少了你的丈夫和女儿。不过上帝会以他深不可测的决定和神意为我们做出最好的安排。你一年之前想过会在巴黎度过下一个命名日吗？这在当时对有些人来说多么难以置信，虽然我们并不这么觉得。因此，在上帝的帮助下，我们很有可能要比我们所预计的更早团聚。现在唯一压在我心头的事情，就是和你们分居两地，相隔千山万水。但是感谢上帝，我们都很健康！我们两个亲吻你和沃尔夫冈一百万次，主要想请你们保重好身体。战争剧如今终于要开始了！[48]你在巴黎应该已经知道了，这个月5号，普鲁士国王[49]入侵波希米亚，他从克沃兹科开始，经过纳霍德，一直进犯到克尼格雷茨。可以确定的是，战争一定会爆发，因为双方都无法不损颜面地撤兵。这几周以来，奥地利利用行军和反向行军，在好几个地方为普鲁士国王创造了实施突袭和发动进攻的位置和时机。但是普鲁士国王认为采取这样的进攻不明智。最近奥地利皇帝[50]在纳霍德建立起一个强大的假军火库，促使普鲁士国王采取进攻。但这个军火库是假的，里面除了一些样子货之外什么都没有。他们必须冒这个险，不管结果如何，因为奥地利既没有能力也不愿意成为进攻方。但克罗地亚人作为先头部队（事实上，这是他们唯一可以被用到的地方）几乎已经管不住了，因为这些人总是希望获得战利品，也因此热衷于打仗。萨克森军队与普鲁士结盟了，他们可能真的加入了亨利亲王的势力，接下来很可能会攻打埃格尔和上普法尔茨。下一个邮车肯定会带来更多的新消息。这条消息是奥地利邮车11号带来的。这场战争无疑会成为最血腥的战争之一，因为普鲁士国王想光荣地死去，而奥地利皇帝想光荣地开启他的沙场人生。

前面这些话是昨天12号写下的。今天13号，上午10点之前我收到了你7月3号那封悲伤的信。你完全可以想象到，我们现在心里是什么感觉。我们一起痛哭，几乎无法读完那封信。你姐姐啊！仁慈的上帝啊！希望你最神圣的意志可以实现！我亲爱的儿子！我一直尽可能地皈依上帝的意志，你知道的，我因为哭泣几乎无法写下去是人性使然。我最后该写些什么来结束这封信呢？没有别的了，除了我想到在我写信的这一刻，她可能已经去世了，或者她已经好转了，因为你是3号写下那封信的，而今天已经13号了。你说在放血之后她有所好转，但是几天之后她开始抱怨打寒战和发烧。你们俩的最后一封信是6月12号写的，她当时写道，我昨天给自己放血了。那也就是11号的事，为什么会在星期天斋戒日做这件事？我猜想她可能吃了点肉。放血这件事她耽搁太久了。我很了解她，我知道她喜欢把所有事情从今天拖到明天，尤其是到了一个陌生地方以后，她必须先去找外科医生咨询一下。事已至此，无法改变了，因为我完全相信你的孝心，知道你已经尽心尽力地照料你的好妈妈了。如果上帝还会把她送给我们，你之后还会一直这么照顾她。对于你的好妈妈来说，你是她眼里的珍宝，她非同寻常地爱着你，深深地以你为傲，这些我比你更清楚，她活着就是为了你。但是如果我们的全部希望都落空了！如果我们真的失去了她！天哪！你需要朋友，可靠的朋友！不然你会失去一切，比如在葬礼费用这一项上！我的上帝！有许多你不了解的花销，如果没有可靠的朋友，一个生人会在这些花费上面被欺骗、包办、糊弄，花上许多不必要的钱，还要被讹诈。你可以不理解这些。如果这个不幸真的降临到你头上，你就去请求格林先生让你把母亲的东西放在他家，这样你就不必看管那么多东西，或者你也可以把一切家当都好好锁起来。因为如果你经常一整天不在家，很可能会遭遇入室盗窃。上帝保佑我的一切担忧都是多余的。但在这些事情上你会承认你父亲是对的。我亲爱的妻子！我亲爱的儿子！如果她在放血几天之后开始病重，那她一定从6月16号或者17号起就开始抱恙了。但是你们等得太久了。她以为她可以通过卧床休息，通过节食，通过她自己的方法好转。我知道这是怎么一回事，你们抱着情况会好转的希望，把事情从今天拖到明天。但是，我亲爱的沃尔夫冈，高烧时如果腹泻需要立刻咨询医生，以便知道应该退烧还是必须顺其自然，因为用来退烧的药会加剧腹泻。而如果在不恰当的时刻腹泻，病情会如同火上浇油。上帝啊！我们都在你的手里。

祝贺你的交响曲在宗教音乐会上取得的成功。我能想象你当时有多紧张。但如果排练不顺利，你就决定闯进管弦乐团实在是一个头脑发热的想法。上帝保佑，你必须将这一类的突发奇想统统排出脑海。它们都是欠考虑的，这样的一步会让你付出沉重代价，没有一个理智的人会为了一部交响曲如此冒险。这样的冒犯，并且是公开的冒犯，不仅肯定会被法国人报复，而且会被所有重视荣誉的人狠狠报复。意大利人会什么都不说，在街角等着，然后一枪毙了你。我从慕尼黑得到了可靠的消息，泽奥伯爵被确立为慕尼黑和曼海姆地区的宫廷音乐负责人。两个管弦乐团的乐手名单已经被送去了曼海姆。这两个乐团会被合并，最差的乐手会被剔除。沃茨卡先生和其他宫廷侍从一起，已经以400弗罗林的退休金被辞退了，这让我很惊讶。桑夫特医生厚颜无耻地为他的治疗要价3000弗罗林，为此他的头衔和薪水都被剥夺了。现在终于有望在8月10号，再次在慕尼黑见到选帝侯泰奥尔多、选帝侯夫人及整个宫廷人员。

这封信是以我的祝福展开的，南妮儿想以她的祝福来收尾，只是你完全想得到，她一个字都没法写，尽管她必须要写点什么了……每个打算写下的字都让她的眼里再次溢满了泪水。你，她亲爱的弟弟，如果你还能做到的话，就如我们所愿，代表她祝福妈妈吧！

哦不！你已经不能再这么做了……她已经去了！你拼命安慰我，一个人如果不是完全失去了希望或者被可怕的处境刺激，是不会这样激动的。现在我要去吃午饭了，但我没有任何胃口。

现在是下午3点半，我开始写下面这些话。我知道我亲爱的妻子现在已经在天国了。我满含泪水地写下这些，但是完全皈依上帝的意志！昨天是圣三一主日的教堂庆典，所以我们平时的射击练习推迟到了今天。我不能也不想因为你那悲伤的信，那么晚才取消活动。我们吃得很少，但南妮儿必须吃点东西，因为她在餐桌上哭得太厉害，吐了，而且头痛欲裂，已经去床上休息了。布林格先生和其他人都发现了我们极度悲伤。我一句话都没说，让他读你的信。他把自己的情绪掩饰得很好，只是问我认为现在情况如何。我告诉他，我确信我亲爱的妻子已经死了。他说，其实他也几乎这么认为。然后他安慰了我，像一个真正的朋友那样，而那些话我已经都对自己说过了。我努力振作起来，让自己皈依于最神圣的神意。结束射击之后，所有人都情绪低落地离开了。布林格先生留了下来，假装不经意地问我，觉得病情目前是否还有转机。我回答他，我认为她已经死了，而且在你写信的当天就死了。但我皈依上帝的意志，必须记得我仍然有两个孩子，我希望他们会继续爱我，就如同我活着是为了他们一样。我已经写信告诉你我确信她已经过世了，还提醒你看管好她的遗物等。对此他说，是的，她已经死了。这件突发意外像是在我眼前蒙上了一层面纱，阻碍了我的判断力，不然我一读你的信就会立刻猜到你已经写信告诉了布林格先生真相。但你的信真的让我愣住了，看到信的那一刻我就被彻底击倒，无法思考。即使是现在，我仍然不知道能写什么！我这边你可以放心，我会像个男人一样面对这件事。但是想想你母亲对你温柔的爱，你就会意识到她有多在乎你。就像当你成熟了，当我死了，你会更加爱我一样。你爱我，这一点我毫不怀疑。那么你要保重身体。我的人生全靠你了，你姐姐未来的生活也依仗你，她全心全意地爱着你。眼睁睁看着自己幸福的婚姻被死亡撕裂，这种痛苦真的令人心碎。但只有真正经历了才能了解。要写信告诉我所有的细节。她是不是放血放得不够？可以确定的是，她太相信自己，请医生请得太迟了。这时她的肠道炎已经病入膏肓了。你要保重身体！不要让我们都不幸福！南妮儿还不知道布林格先生的信。但我准备让她相信她的好妈妈已经过世了。尽快给我写信，告诉我一切。告诉我她何时下葬，葬在哪里。上帝啊！我一定要去巴黎寻找我亲爱的妻子的墓穴！我们发自内心地吻你，我必须说再见了，邮车要走了。

你诚实而极度悲伤的父亲

莫扎特

确保你们的东西不要丢了。

[48]指的是普鲁士与奥地利之间的巴伐利亚王位继承战争（1778-1779年）。

[49]腓特烈二世（Friedrich II，1712-1786），史称腓特烈大帝。普鲁士国王（1740年5月31日-1786年8月17日在位），军事家、政治家、作家及作曲家。

[50]约瑟夫二世（Josef II，1741-1790），哈布斯堡-洛林王朝的奥地利大公，罗马人民的国王（1764-1790年在位），1765年加冕为神圣罗马帝国皇帝（1765-1790年在位），后又为匈牙利国王和波希米亚国王（1780-1790年）。

参考文献：

1. Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart ：My Dearest Father （Penguin Little Black Classics） . trans.Stewart Spencer.London ：Penguin Classics，2015.

2. Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart ：The Letters of Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, Vol. 1. trans. Grace Wallace. Whitefish ：Kessinger Publishing, LLC.2004.

3. Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart ：Briefe und Aufzeichnungen. Gesamtausgabe. Band II.1777-1779.Hrsg.von der Internationalen Stiftung Mozarteum Salzburg.Gesammelt und erläutert von Wilhelm A. Bauer und Otto Erich Deutsch, auf Grund deren Vorarbeiten erläutert von Joseph Heinz Eibl. Kassel ：Bärenreiter；Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag. 2005.

4. Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart ：Briefe und Aufzeichnungen.Gesamtausgabe.Band V. Kommentar I/II 1755-1779. Hrsg. von der Internationalen Stiftung Mozarteum Salzburg. Gesammelt und erläutert von Wilhelm A. Bauer und Otto Erich Deutsch, auf Grund deren Vorarbeiten erläutert von Joseph Heinz Eibl.Kassel ：Bärenreiter；Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag. 2005.

5.沃尔夫冈·莫扎特：《我是你的莫扎特：莫扎特书信集》，钱仁康译，阳军编选，北京：中国财政经济出版社，2016年。

6.沃尔夫冈·莫扎特：《莫扎特家书》，辛丰年译评，济南：山东画报出版社，2006年。

Mozart to his father, 17 October 1777, Augsburg

Mon très cher Père,

I must start with Stein's pianofortes. Before I saw any of Stein's work, I'd always preferred Späth's pianos; but now I prefer Stein's, as they damp so much better than the Regensburg instruments. If I strike hard, it doesn't matter whether I keep my finger down or raise it, the sound ceases the moment I produce it. However I attack the keys, the tone is always even. It doesn't produce a clattering sound, it doesn't get louder or softer or fail to sound at all; in a word, it's always even. It's true, he won't part with a pianoforte like this for under 300 florins, but the effort and labour that he expends on it can't be paid for. A particular feature of his instruments is their escape action. Not one maker in a hundred bothers with this. But without escape action it's impossible for a pianoforte not to produce a clattering sound or to go on sounding after the note has been struck; when you strike the keys, his hammers fall back again the moment they hit the strings, whether you hold down the keys or release them. He told me that only when he's finished making a piano like this does he sit down and try out all the passagework, runs and leaps, and, using a shave, works away at the instrument until it can do everything. For he works only to serve the music, not just for his own profit, otherwise he'd be finished at once.

He often says that if he weren't such a great music lover and didn't have some slight skill on the instrument, he'd long since have run out of patience with his work; but he loves an instrument that never lets the player down and that will last. His pianos will really last. He guarantees that the sounding board won't break or crack. Once he's finished making a sounding board for a piano he puts it outside, exposing it to the air, rain, snow, heat of the sun and all the devils in order for it to crack, and then he inserts wedges, which he glues in, so that it's very strong and firm. He's perfectly happy for it to crack as he's then assured that nothing more can happen to it. Indeed, he often cuts into it himself and then glues it back together again and makes it really strong. He has completed three such pianofortes. Not until today did I play on one of them again. Today - the 17th - we had lunch with young Herr Gasser, a young and handsome widower who's lost his young and beautiful wife. They'd been married for only 2 years. He's a most excellent and polite young man. We were splendidly entertained. Also there was a col‑league of Abbé Henri, Bullinger and Wieshofer, an ex‑Jesuit who's now Kapellmeister at the cathedral here. He knows Herr Schachtner very well, he was his choirmaster in Ingolstadt. He's called Pater Gerbl. I'm to give his best wishes to Herr Schachtner. After lunch Herr Gasser and I went to Herr Stein's, where we were accompanied by one of his sisters‑in‑law as well as Mama and our cousin. At 4 o'clock we were joined by the Kapellmeister and Herr Schmidbaur, the organist at St Ulrich's, a fine old gentleman who's very well‑spoken; and I then sight‑read a sonata by Beecke that was quite hard and miserable al solito; I can't begin to tell you how the Kapellmeister and organist crossed themselves. Both here and in Munich I've played my 6 sonatas many times from memory. I played the fifth one in G at the aristocrats'concert in the Bauernstube. The last one, in D, sounds amazing on Stein's pianoforte. The device that you depress with your knee is also better made on his instrument than on others. I scarcely need to touch it and it works; and as soon as you remove your knee even a little, you no longer hear the slightest reverberation. Tomorrow I may get round to his organs - - I mean, to write about them; I'm saving up his little daughter till the end. When I told Herr Stein that I'd like to play on his organ as the organ was my passion, he was very surprised and said:What, a man like you, so great a keyboard player wants to play on an instrument that has no douceur, no expression, no piano or forte but always sounds the same? - - None of that matters. In my eyes and ears the organ is the king of instruments. Well, as you like. We went off together. I could already tell from what he said that he didn't think I'd do much on his organ and that - for example - I'd play in a way more suited to a piano. He told me that Schubart had asked to be shown his organ, and I was afraid - he said - as Schubart had told everyone, and the church was quite full; for I thought he'd be all spirit, fire and speed, none of which works on the organ; but as soon as he started I changed my mind. I said only this:What do you think, Herr Stein? Do you think I'll run all over the organ? - - Oh, you, that's quite different. We reached the choir. I began to improvise, by which point he was already laughing, and then a fugue. I can well believe - he said - that you enjoy playing the organ if you play like that - - at first the pedal was a little strange as it wasn't divided. It began with C, then D, E in the same row. But with us D and E are above, as E flat and F sharp are here. But I soon got used to it. I also played on the old organ at St Ulrich's. The steps up to it are a nightmare. I asked if someone could play on it for me as I wanted to go down and listen. From up there the organ is totally ineffectual. But I could make nothing of it, as the young choirmaster, a priest, played only scales, so it was impossible to form any impression. And when he tried to play some chords, he produced only discords as it was out of tune. After that we had to go to a coffee‑room as my mother and cousin and Herr Stein were with us. A certain Pater Aemilian, an arrogant ass and a simpleton of his profession, was in an especially hearty mood. He kept wanting to joke with my cousin, but she just made fun of him - - finally, when he was drunk (which didn't take long), he started to talk about music. He sang a canon and I said I'd never in my whole life heard a finer one. I said I'm sorry, I can't join in as I've no natural gift for intoning. That doesn't matter, he said. He started. I was the third voice, but I made up some very different words, for example, O you prick, lick my arse. Sotto voce to my cousin. We laughed about it for half an hour. He said to me:if only we could have spent longer together. I'd like to discuss the art of composition with you. Then the discussion would soon be over, I said.Get lost. To be continued.

W. A. Mozart

Leopold Mozart to his son, 23 October 1777, Salzburg

Mon très cher Fils,

I must congratulate you on your name day! But what can I wish you today that I don't always wish you? - - I wish you the grace of God, that it may accompany you everywhere and never abandon you, as indeed it will never do if you strive to fulfil the obligations of a true Catholic Christian.

You know me. - I'm no pedant, I'm not holier than thou, and I'm certainly no hypocrite:but you surely won't refuse a request from your father? - It is this:that you should be concerned for your soul's welfare and not cause your father any anxiety in his hour of death, so that at that difficult time he won't have to reproach himself for neglecting your soul's salvation. Farewell! Be happy! Lead a sensible life! Honour and esteem your mother, who has much toil in her old age, love me as I love you. Your truly solicitous father

Leop. Mozart

Mozart to his father, 29 November 1777, Mannheim

Mon très cher Père,

I received your letter of the 24th this morning and see from it that you're unable to reconcile yourself to fate, be it good or bad, when it takes us by surprise; until now, and as things stand, the four of us have never been happy or unhappy, and for that I thank God. You reproach us both for many things, without our deserving it. We are not incurring any expenses that are not necessary; and what is necessary when travelling you know as well as we do, if not better. That we stayed so long in Munich was the fault of no one but myself; and if I'd been alone, I'd certainly have stayed in Munich. Why did we spend 2 weeks in Augsburg? - - I'm tempted to think that you didn't receive my letters from Augsburg. - - I wanted to give a concert - I was let down; meanwhile a whole week went by. I was absolutely determined to leave. They wouldn't let me. They wanted me to give a concert; I wanted them to beg me. And so they did. I gave a concert. There are your 2 weeks. Why did we go straight to Mann‑heim? - - I answered this question in my last letter. Why are we still here? - - Yes - - can you really think that I'd remain somewhere for no reason? - - But I could have told my father - - all right, you shall know the reason and indeed the whole course of events. But God knows that I had no wish to speak about it because I was unable to go into detail - any more than I can today - and I know you well enough to appreciate that a vague account would have caused you worry and distress, something I've always tried to avoid; but if you ascribe the cause to my negligence, thoughtlessness and indolence, I can only thank you for your high opinion of me and sincerely regret that you don't know your own son.

I'm not thoughtless but am prepared for anything and as a result can wait patiently for whatever the future holds in store, and I'll be able to endure it - as long as my hon‑our and the good name of Mozart don't suffer in consequence. Well, if it must be so, then let it be so. But I must ask you at the outset not to rejoice or grieve pre‑maturely; for whatever happens, all is well as long as we remain healthy; for happiness consists - - simply in our imagination. Last Tuesday week, the 18th, the day before St Elisabeth's Day, I saw Count Savioli in the morning and asked him if there was any chance that the elector would keep me here this winter? - - I wanted to teach the young princes. He said yes, I'll suggest it to the elector; and if it's up to me, it will certainly happen. That after‑noon I saw Cannabich and as it was at his suggestion that I'd been to see the count, he asked me at once if I'd been there. - I told him all that had happened, he said to me I'd very much like you to spend the winter here with us, but I'd like it even more if you had a proper, permanent appointment. I said that there was nothing I'd like more than to be always near them but that I really didn't know how it would be possible for me to stay permanently. You've already got two Kapellmeisters, so I don't know what I could do, as I wouldn't like to be under Vogler! Nor shall you, he said. None of the members of the orchestra here is under the Kapellmeister or even under the intendant. The elector could make you his chamber composer. Wait, I'll speak to the count about it. There was a big concert on Thursday. When the count saw me, he apologized for not having said anything, but the galas were still going on; but as soon as the galas were over, namely, on Monday, he would certainly speak to the elector. I left it for 3 days, and as I'd heard nothing, I went to see him in order to make enquiries. He said:My dear Monsieur Mozart (this was Friday, namely, yester‑day), there was a hunt today so I've been unable to ask the elector; but by this time tomorrow I shall certainly be able to give you an answer:I begged him not to forget. To tell the truth, I was rather angry when I left him and decided to take the young count my six easiest variations on Fischer's minuet - which I'd already had copied out here for this very purpose - in order to have an oppor‑tunity to speak to the elector in person. When I arrived, you can't imagine how pleased the governess was to see me. I received a most courteous welcome. When I took out the variations and said that they were for the count, she said Oh, that's good of you; but have you also got something for the countess? - - Not yet, I said, but if I were to stay here long enough to write something, I'll - - By the way, she said, I'm glad that you'll be staying here all winter. Me? - - I didn't know that! - - That surprises me. It's curious. The elector himself told me so recently. By the way, he said, Mozart is staying here this winter. Well, if he did indeed say that, then he's the one person who can say it, for without the elector I certainly can't remain here. I told her the whole story. We agreed that I'd return the next day - namely, today - after 4 o'clock and bring something for the countess. You'll speak to the elector - before I arrive - and he'll still be with you when I get there. I went back there today, but he didn't come. But I'll go again tomorrow. I've written a rondeau for the countess. Don't I have reason enough to remain here and await the outcome? - - Should I leave now that the great‑est step has been taken? - - I now have a chance to speak to the elector himself. I think I shall probably remain here all winter as the elector is fond of me, he thinks highly of me and knows what I can do. I hope to be able to give you some good news in my next letter. I beg you once again not to rejoice or worry too soon and to confide this story in no one except Herr Bullinger and my sister. I'm sending my sister the allegro and andante from the sonata for Mlle Cannabich. The rondeau will follow shortly. It would have been too much to send them all together. You'll have to make do with the original; you can have it copied more easily at 6 kreuzers a page than I can at 24 kreuzers. Don't you find that expensive? - - Adieu. I kiss your hands 100, 000 times and embrace my sister with all my heart. I am your obedient son.

Wolfgang Amadé Mozart

You'll probably already have heard a little of the sonata, as it's sung, banged out, fiddled and whistled at least 3 times a day at Cannabich's. - Only sotto voce, of course.

[Maria Anna Mozart's postscript]

My dear husband, I kiss you and Nannerl many 1000 times and ask you to give our best wishes to all our acquaint‑ances, I'll write more next time, but it's turned midnight, addio, I remain your faithful wife

Maria Anna Mozart

Leopold Mozart to his wife and son, 4 December 1777, Salzburg

My Dear Wife and Dear Son,

I've no objection to your having to wait for what you told me about in your last letter, and there's nothing more that can be said about all that has happened on your journey and that has turned out differently from what I'd expected and worked out to our disadvantage and even caused us obvious harm, as it is all over and done with and can no longer be changed. - But the fact that you, my son, write that all speculation is superfluous and of no avail as we cannot know what is to happen - this is indeed ill considered and was undoubtedly written unthinkingly. No sensible person - I shall not say no Christian - will deny that everything will and must happen according to God's will. But does it follow from this that we should act blindly, live carefree lives, make no provisions for the future and simply wait for things to befall us of their own accord? - Does God himself and, indeed, do all rational people not demand that in all our actions we consider their consequences and outcome, at least as far as our human powers of reason enable us to, and that we make every effort to see as far ahead as we can? - - If this is necessary in all our actions, how much more so is it in the present circumstances, on a journey? Or have you not already suffered the consequences of this? - - Is it enough for you to have taken the step with the elector in order to remain there throughout the winter? - - Should you not - shouldn't you long ago have thought of a plan that can be implemented if things don't work out:and shouldn't you have told me about it long ago and learnt my views on it? - - And now you write - what? If we were after all to leave here we'll go straight to Weilburg to the Princess of Nassau‑Weilburg - for whom you wrote the sonatas in Holland - etc. - There we'll stay as long as the offcers'table is to our liking - what sort of a tale is that? Like everything else you wrote, this is the language of a des‑perate man who is trying to console both himself and me. - - But there's still a hope that you'll receive 6 louis d'or, and that will make everything all right. - But my ques‑tion to you now is whether you're certain that the princess is there:she won't be there without good reason as her husband is based in The Hague on account of his military offce. Shouldn't you have told me about this long ago? - Another question:wouldn't you do better to go to Mainz - and from there to Weilburg via Frankfurt? After all, if you go from Mannheim to Weilburg, you'll cross the Frankfurt road:and as you're not staying in Weilburg for ever, the Mainz road will take you back through Frankfurt. If you first go to Mainz and then to Weilburg, you'll have only a short distance from Weilburg to Kob‑lenz, which will presumably take you via Nassau. Or do you intend to avoid Mainz, where we've so many good friends and where we earned 200florins from 3 concerts, even without playing for the elector, who was ill. Tell me, my dear son, are these useless speculations? - - Your dear good Mama told me she'd keep a careful note of your expenses. Good! I've never asked for a detailed account and never thought of demanding one:but when you arrived in Augsburg you should have written to say:We paid such and such at Albert's in Munich, and such and such was spent on travelling expenses, so that we still have such and such a sum. From Augsb. you wrote to say that after taking account of the concert receipts you were about 20 florins out of pocket. In your 2nd letter from Mannheim you should at least have said that the journey cost us such and such an amount and we're now left with - - , so that I could have made arrangements in good time - - was my arrangement to send you a letter of credit in Augsburg a useless speculation? - - Do you really think that Herr Herzog - who's a good old friend of mine - would have provided you with money in response to all your letters from Mannheim if you'd not already given him a letter of credit? - - Certainly not! The most that he would have done would have been to make enquiries with me first. - - Why did I have to discover that you needed money only when you were in trouble?You wanted to wait to see what the elector gave you. Isn't that so? Perhaps in order to spare me the worry - - but it would have caused me less worry if I'd been told everything honestly and in good time, as I know better than either of you how one must be prepared for all eventualities on such a jour‑ney in order not to be placed in some terrible predicament at the very moment when one least expects it. - At such times all your friends disappear! One must be cheerful; one must enjoy oneself! But one must also find time to give serious thought to these matters, and this must be your main concern when travelling and when not a single day should be allowed to pass to your disadvantage - - the days slip past - days which are in any case very short at present and which all cost money at an inn. Merciful heavens! You ask me not to speculate now that I'm 450 florins in debt entirely thanks to you two. - And you think that you may be able to put me in a good mood by telling me a hun‑dred foolish jokes. I'm pleased that you're in good spirits:but instead of the good wishes set out in the form of the alphabet, I'd have felt happier if you'd told me the reasons for, and the circumstances of, your journey to Weilburg and what you planned to do afterwards and, most of all, if you'd listened to my opinion; and this could have been done before a post day, as you can't only just have hit on the idea, nor can you know independently that the prin‑cess is there, unless someone had already suggested the idea to you. In a word, it is no idle speculation when one has something in mind and formulates 2 or 3 plans and makes all the necessary arrangements in advance so that if one plan doesn't work out, one can easily turn to another. Anyone who acts otherwise is an unintelligent or thoughtless person who, especially in today's world, will always be left behind, no matter how clever he is, and who will even be unhappy as he will always be duped by flatterers, false friends and those who envy him. My son, to find one man in a 1000 who is your true friend for rea‑sons other than self‑interest is one of the greatest wonders of this world. Examine all who call themselves your friends or who make a show of friendship and you'll find the reason why this is so. If they're not motivated by self‑interest on their own account, then they'll be acting in the interests of some other friend whom they need; or they are your friends so that by singling you out they can annoy some third party. If nothing comes of Mannheim, you still have your plan to go to Mainz, Frankfurt, Weil‑burg, Koblenz etc.; one should always look for places as close to each other as possible so that, if you can, the journeys should be kept short and you can soon get to a place where you'll find a source of income. If this letter doesn't reach you in Mannheim and you're already in Weil‑burg, I can't help you. But if you're still in Mannheim and have to leave, then Mama will see from the map that your best plan is to go to Mainz first, otherwise you'll either have to forgo Mainz or retrace your steps a little. In Weil‑burg you need to bear in mind that you'll not find a Catholic church there as everyone is Lutheran or Calvinist. So I'd prefer you not to spend too long there.

And who told you that you'd have to go through the forest of Spessart to get from Würzburg to Mannheim as the Spessart is near Aschaffenburg, between Fulda and Frank‑furt? - - This is no doubt some other trick that Herr Beecke has played on you.Aschaffenburg and Würzburg are 10 miles apart. - It may be that one drives past the forest on the right‑hand side for some hours as one approaches Mannheim. But there's nothing near Würzburg, whether you've been there or not.

NB:I've another observation to make about any jour‑ney that you may choose to make from Weilburg to Koblenz, namely, that the road is across country and will be safer than the one from Mainz to Koblenz, which is too near the Rhine. I now want to know all your other plans, I'd never have suspected that my own dear wife wouldn't have given me the occasional accurate account of your travelling expense, as I've twice asked about Albert's bill and should also have been told about the bill from the landlord of the Lamb etc. etc. But I'm not allowed to know about all your expenses.And so I must ask Mama to write me a confidential letter on this point-I don't want a wordy explanation but would just like to see from the landlord's bill how people have been treating you and where all the money has gone. We must now give serious thought to the ways and means of getting you out of the present situation, of travelling as economically as possible and of making sensible arrangements, but at all events you must let me know at once what may be to our detri‑ment or advantage.On no account must you sell the chaise. May God keep both you and me well. Nannerl and I kiss you many 100, 000, 000 times. I am your own husband and father.

Mzt

Count Czernin has asked me to give you his best wishes. There was a rumour not only that the archbishop will be sending Haydn to Italy but that he had already wanted to send him to Bozen with Triendl. But Herr Triendl excused himself. I beg you, my dear Wolfg., consider everything and don't always write about things when they're already over and done with. Otherwise we'll all be unhappy.

Leopold Mozart to his son, 5 February 1778, Salzburg

My Dear Son,

In all probability this will be the last letter that you can be certain of receiving from me in Mannheim, and so it is addressed to you alone. How hard it is for me to accept that you're moving even further away from me is some‑thing you may perhaps be able to imagine, but you cannot feel as acutely as I do the weight that lies on my mind. If you take the trouble to recall what I did with you two children during your tender youth, you'll not accuse me of timidity but, like everyone else, will concede that I am a man and have always had the courage to risk everything. But I did everything with the greatest caution and con‑sideration that were humanly possible: - one can't prevent accidents, for God alone can foretell the future. Until now, of course, we've been neither happy nor unhappy, but, thanks be to God, we've trodden a middle course. We've tried everything to make you happy and, through you, to make ourselves happier and at least to place your destiny on a firmer footing; but fate was against us. As you know, our last step has left me in very deep waters, and you also know that I'm now around 700 florins in debt and don't know how I shall support myself, your mother and your sister on my monthly income, for as long as I live I cannot hope to receive another farthing from the prince. So it must be clear as day to you that the future fate of your old parents and of your sister, who undoubtedly loves you with all her heart, lies solely in your hands. Ever since you were born and, indeed, before that - in other words, ever since I was married - there is no doubt that I've had a diffcult time providing a livelihood for a wife and 7 chil‑dren, 2 servants and Mama's mother, all on a fixed monthly income of only a little more than 20 florins, and to pay for accouchements, deaths and illnesses, expenses which, if you think them over, will convince you not only that I have never spent a farthing on the least pleasure for myself, but that, without God's special mercy, I'd never have managed to keep out of debt in spite of all my hopes and bitter efforts:yet this is the first time I've been in debt. I gave up every hour of my life to you 2 in the hope of ensuring not only that in due course you'd both be able to count on being able to provide for yourselves but that I too would be able to enjoy a peaceful old age and be accountable to God for my children's education, with no more cares but being able to live solely for my soul's salvation and calmly awaiting my end. But God has willed and ordained that I must once again take on the undoubtedly wearisome task of giving lessons and of doing so, moreover, in a town where these strenuous efforts are so badly paid that it is not possible every month to earn enough to support oneself and one's family. Yet one must be glad and talk oneself hoarse in order to earn at least something. Not only do I not distrust you, my dear Wolfgang, no, not in the very least, but I place all my trust and hope in your filial love:all depends on your good sense, which you certainly have - if only you will listen to it - and on fortunate circumstances. This latter cannot be coerced; but you will always consult your good sense - at least I hope so and beg of you to do so.

You're now entering a completely different world:and you mustn't think that it is simply prejudice that makes me see Paris as such a dangerous place, au contraire - from my own experience I've no reason at all to regard Paris as so very dangerous. But my situation then could not be more different from yours now. We stayed with an ambas‑sador, and on the second occasion in a self‑contained apartment; I was a man of mature years and you were children; I avoided all contact with others and in particu‑lar preferred not to become over‑familiar with people of our own profession; remember that I did the same in Italy. I made the acquaintance and sought out the friendship only of people of a higher social class - and among these only mature people, not young lads, not even if they were of the foremost rank. I never invited anyone to visit me regularly in my rooms in order to be able to maintain my freedom, and I always considered it more sensible to visit others at my convenience. If I don't like a person or if I'm working or have business to attend to, I can then stay away. - Conversely, if people come to me and behave badly, I don't know how to get rid of them, and even a person who is otherwise not unwelcome may prevent me from getting on with some important work. You're a young man of 22; and so you don't have that earnestness of old age that could deter a young lad of whatever social class, be he an adventurer, joker or fraud and be he young or old, from seeking out your acquaintance and friend‑ship and drawing you into his company and then gradually into his plans. One is drawn imperceptibly into this and cannot then escape. I shan't even mention women, for here one needs the greatest restraint and rea‑son, as nature herself is our enemy, and the man who does not apply his whole reason and show the necessary restraint will later do so in vain in his attempt to escape from the labyrinth, a misfortune that mostly ends only in death. You yourself may perhaps already have learnt from your limited experience how blindly we may often be taken in by jests, flatteries and jokes that initially seem unimportant but at which reason, when she awakes later on, is ashamed; I don't want to reproach you. I know that you love me not just as your father but also as your staunchest and surest friend; and that you know and realize that our happiness and misfortune and, indeed, my very life - whether I live to a ripe old age or die suddenly - are in your hands as much as God's. If I know you, I can hope for nothing but contentment, and this alone must console me during your absence, when I am deprived of a father's delight in hearing, seeing and embracing you. Live like a good Catholic, live and fear God, pray most fervently to Him in reverence and trust, and lead so Christian a life that, even if I am never to see you again, the hour of my death may be free from care. With all my heart I give you a father's blessing and remain until death your faithful father and surest friend.

Leopold Mozart

Here are our Paris acquaintances, all of whom will be delighted to see you.[……]

[Leopold's postscript to his wife on the envelope]

My Dear Wife,

As you'll receive this letter on the 11th or 12th and as I doubt whether a further letter will reach Wolfg. in Mann‑heim, I'll take my leave of him with this enclosure! I'm writing this with tears in my eyes. Nannerl kisses her dear brother Wolfg. a million times. She would have added a note to my letter and said goodbye, but the letter was already full and in any case I didn't let her read it. We ask Wolfg.to take care of his health and to stick to the diet that he got used to at home; otherwise he'll have to be bled as soon as he arrives in Paris, everything spicy is bad for him. I expect he'll take with him the big Latin prayer book that contains all the psalms for the full offce of Our Lady. If he wants to have the German text of the offce of Our Lady in Mannheim in order to have it in German too, he'll have to try to obtain the very smallest format as the Latin psalms are diffcult to understand. It would be better if he also had them in German. Learned contrapuntal set‑tings of the psalms are also performed at the Concert Spirituel; it's possible to gain a great reputation in this way. Perhaps he could also have his Misericordias per‑formed there. The opera singers aren't coming but have gone instead to Straubing to entertain the Austrian officers. The prince has again forced the magistrature to hold 9 balls, the first one was yesterday and was attended by 30 persons; it lasted till half past one, but not a soul had arrived by half past 9 and it wasn't till 10 that they started dancing; 1 capon and 6 mugs of wine were consumed. I hope you received the 2 sonatas for 4 hands, the Fischer variations and the rondo, which were all parcelled up in the same letter. - - The late Herr Adlgasser hasn't found a decent bellows blower in the afterlife; the cathedral's old bellows blower, the 80‑year‑old Thomas, has followed him into the next world. The main news is that Mme Barisani has become incredibly jealous of her old and respectable husband as he and Checco have on a handful of occasions been to perform at the home of handsome Herr Freysauff, who has a relatively pretty but witless wife. There was an incredible fuss. Farewell. We kiss you millions of times.

Mzt

Everyone sends their best wishes, especially Herr Bull‑inger and the wife of the sergeant of the bodyguards, Herr Clessin, Waberl Mölk etc.

Mozart to his father, 3 July 1778, Paris

Monsieur

mon très cher Père!

I have some very disagreeable and sad news for you, which is also the reason why I have been unable until now to reply to your last letter of the 11th. -

My dear mother is very ill - she was bled, as usual, and very necessary it was, too; she felt very well afterwards - but a few days later she complained of shivering and feverishness - she had diarrhoea and a headache - at first we just used our home remedies, antispasmodic powder, we'd like to have used the black one too, but we didn't have any and couldn't get any here, it's not known here even under the name of Pulvis epilepticus. - But when things started to get worse - she could hardly speak and lost her hearing so we had to shout - Baron Grimm sent his doctor - she's very weak and is still feverish and delirious - I'm told to be hopeful, but I'm not - for long days and nights I've been hovering between fear and hope - but I've resigned myself to God's will - and I hope that you and my dear sister will do the same; what other means is there to remain calm? - or, rather, calmer, as we can't be entirely calm; - come what may, I feel comforted - because I know that God, who orders every‑thing for the best, however contrary it may seem to us, wills it so; for I believe - and I won't be persuaded otherwise - that no doctor, no individual, no misfortune and no accident can give a man his life or take it away, God alone can do that - these are only the instruments that He generally uses, although not always - after all, we can see people fainting, collapsing and dying - once our time comes, all remedies are useless, they hasten death rather than prevent it - we saw this in the case of our late friend Herr Heffner! - I'm not saying by this that my mother will and must die and that all hope is lost - she may yet be hale and hearty again, but only if God so wills it - after praying to my God with all my strength for health and life for my dear mother, I like to think this and derive comfort from such thoughts, as I then feel heartened, calmer and consoled - and you'll easily imagine that I need this! - Now for something different; let's banish these sad thoughts. Let us hope, but not too much; let us put our trust in God and console ourselves with the thought that all is well if it accords with the will of the Almighty as He knows best what is most advanta‑geous and beneficial to our temporal and eternal happiness and salvation -

I've had to write a symphony to open the Concert Spir‑ituel. It was performed to general acclaim on Corpus Christi; I also hear that there was a report on it in the Courrier de l'Europe. - Without exception, people liked it. I was very afraid at the rehearsal as I've never in all my life heard anything worse; you can't imagine how twice in succession they bungled and scraped their way through it. - I was really very afraid - I'd have liked to rehearse it again, but there are always so many things to rehearse and so there was no more time; and so I had to go to bed with a fearful heart and in a discontented and angry frame of mind. The next day I decided not to go to the concert at all; but in the evening the weather was fine and so I decided to go, determined that if it went as badly as it had done during the rehearsal, I'd go into the orchestra, take the fiddle from the hands of the first violin, Herr Lahoussaye, and conduct myself. I prayed to God that it would go well because everything is to His greater glory and honour; and behold, the symphony started, Raaff was standing next to me, and in the middle of the opening allegro there was a passage that I knew very well people were bound to like, the whole audience was carried away by it - and there was loud applause - but as I knew when I wrote it what effect it would produce, I introduced it again at the end - now people wanted to have it encored. They liked the andante, too, but especially the final allegro - I'd heard that all the final allegros and opening ones too begin here with all the instruments playing together and generally in unison, and so I began mine with 2 violins only, playing piano for 8 whole bars, followed at once by a forte - the audience, as I expected, went‘shush'at the piano - then came the forte - and as soon as they heard it, they started to clap - I was so happy that as soon as the symphony was over I went to the Palais Royal - had a large ice - said the rosary, as I'd promised - and went home - just as I'm always happiest at home and always will be - or with some good, true, honest German who, if he's single, lives on his own as a good Christian or, ifmarried, loveshiswifeandbringsuphischildrenwell -

You probably already know that that godless arch ‑ rogue Voltaire has died like a dog, like a beast - that's his reward! - As you say, we owe Tresel her wages for 5 quarters - you'll have realized long ago that I don't like it here - there are many reasons for this, but as I'm here, it would serve no useful purpose to go into them. It's not my fault and never will be, I'll do my very best - well, God will make all things right! - I've something in mind for which I pray to God every day - if it's His divine will, it will happen, if not, then I'm also content - at least I'll have done my part - when all is sorted out and if things work out as I want, you too must do your part or the whole business will be incomplete - I trust in your kind‑ness to do so - but for the present you mustn't waste time thinking about it, the only favour I wanted to beg of you now is not to ask me to reveal my thoughts until it's time to do so.

As for the opera, it's now like this. It's very diffcult to find a good libretto. The old ones are the best but they're not suited to the modern style, and the new ones are all useless; poetry was the one thing of which the French could be proud but this is now getting worse by the day - and yet poetry is the one thing that must be good here as they don't understand music - there are now 2 aria‑based operas that I could write, one en deux actes, the other en trois. The one en deux is Alexandre et Roxane - but the poet who's writing it is still out of town - the one en trois is a translation of Demofoonte by Metastasio, com‑bined with choruses and dances and in general arranged for the French theatre. Of this I've not yet been able to see anything -

Let me know if you've got Schroeter's concertos in Salzburg. And Hüllmandel's sonatas. - I was thinking of buying them and sending them to you. Both sets of pieces are very fine - I never thought of going to Versailles - I asked Baron Grimm and some other good friends for their advice - they all thought like me.

It's not much money, you have to spend 6 months lan‑guishing in a place where you can't earn anything else and your talent lies buried. Anyone in the king's service is forgotten in Paris. And then, to be an organist! - I'd like a decent appointment, but only as a Kapellmeister, and well paid.

Farewell for now - take care of your health, put your trust in God - it's there that you must find consolation; my dear mother is in the hands of the Almighty - if He returns her to us, as I hope, we shall thank Him for this mercy, but if it is His will to take her to Him, our fears and cares and despair will be of no avail - let us rather resign ourselves steadfastly to His divine will, fully con‑vinced that it will be for our own good, for He does nothing without good cause - farewell, dearest Papa, keep well for my sake; I kiss your hands 1000 times and embrace my sister with all my heart. I am your most obedient son.

Wolfgang Amadè Mozart

Mozart to his father, 9 July 1778, Paris

Monsieur

mon très cher Père!

I hope that you are prepared to hear with fortitude a piece of news that could not be sadder or more painful - my last letter of the 3rd will have placed you in the position of knowing that the news, when it came, would not be good - that same day, the 3rd, at 10. 21 in the evening, my mother passed away peacefully; - when I wrote to you, she was already enjoying the delights of heaven - by then it was all over - I wrote to you during the night - I hope that you and my dear sister will forgive me this slight but very necessary deception - concluding from my own grief and sadness what yours must be, I couldn't possibly bring myself to spring such a terrible piece of news on you - but I hope that you're both now ready to hear the worst and that, after giving way to natural and only too justified grief and tears, you will eventually resign yourselves to God's will and worship His inscrutable, unfathomable and all‑wise providence - you'll easily be able to imagine what I have had to bear - what courage and fortitude I needed to endure it all calmly as things grew progressively worse - and yet God in His goodness granted me this mercy - I have suffered enough anguish and wept enough tears - but what use was it all? - and so I had to console myself; you, my dear father and sister, must do the same! - Weep, weep your fill - but ultimately you must take comfort, - remember that Almighty God willed it so - and what can we do against Him? - We should rather pray and thank Him that it all turned out for the best - for she died a very happy death; - in these sad circumstances, I consoled myself with three things, namely, my entire trust and sub‑mission in God's will - then the fact that I was present at so easy and beautiful a death, as I imagined how happy she had become in a single moment - how much happier she is now than we are - so much so that at that moment I wanted to take the same journey as she had just done - in turn this wish and desire gave rise to my third source of consolation, namely, that she is not lost to us for ever - we shall see her again - we shall be happier and more con‑tented to be with her than we have been in this world; we do not know when our time may come - but this is no cause for anxiety - when God wills it, then I too shall will it - well, God's most hallowed will has been done - let us therefore say a devout prayer for her soul and proceed to other matters, there is a time for everything - I'm writing this at the home of Madame d'Épinay and Monsieur Grimm, where I'm now lodging, a pretty little room with a very pleasant view and, so far as my state allows, I'm happy here - it will help me to regain my contentment to hear that my dear father and sister have accepted God's will with composure and fortitude and that they trust in Him with all their hearts in the firm conviction that He orders all things for the best - dearest father! Look after yourself! - Dearest sister - look after yourself - you've not yet enjoyed your brother's kind heart as he's not yet been able to demonstrate it - dearest father and sister - look after your health - remember that you have a son and a brother who is doing everything in his power to make you happy - knowing full well that one day you'll not refuse to grant him his desire and his happiness - which certainly does him honour - and that you'll do everything possible to make him happy - Oh, then we'll live together as peacefully, honourably and contentedly as is possible in this world - and finally, when God wills it, we shall meet again there - for this we are destined and created -

Your last letter of 29 June has arrived safely and I'm pleased to learn that you are both well, all praise and thanks be to God, I couldn't help laughing at your account of Haydn's drunkenness, - if I'd been there, I'd certainly have whispered in his ear:Adlgasser. But it's a disgrace that such an able man should be rendered incap‑able of performing his duties and have only himself to blame for it - in a post that's in God's honour - when the archbishop and the whole court are there - and the whole church is full of people - it's appalling - this is also one of the main reasons why I detest Salzburg - the coarse, ill‑mannered and dissolute court musicians - no honest man of good breeding could live with them; - instead of taking an interest in them, he should be ashamed of them! - also - and this is probably the reason - the musicians aren't very popular with us and are simply not respected - if only the orchestra were organized as it is in Mannheim! - the discipline that obtains in that orchestra! - the authority that Cannabich wields - there everything is taken seriously; Cannabich, who's the best music director I've ever seen, is loved and feared by his subordinates. - He's also respected by the whole town, as are his troops - but they certainly behave very differently - they're well‑mannered, dress well, don't frequent taverns and don't get drunk - but this can never be the case with you, unless, that is, the prince trusts you or me and gives us full authority, at least as far as the orches‑tra is concerned - otherwise it's no good; in Salzburg everyone - or rather no one - bothers about the orchestra - if I were to take it on, I'd have to have a com‑pletely free hand - the chief steward should have nothing to say to me on orchestral matters and, indeed, on any‑thing bound up with the orchestra. A courtier can't stand in for a Kapellmeister, though a Kapellmeister could no doubt stand in for a courtier - by the way, the elector is now back in Mannheim - Madame Cannabich and her husband are in correspondence with me. I'm afraid that the orchestra will be much reduced in size, which would be an eternal shame, but if this doesn't happen, I may still remain hopeful - you know that there's nothing I want more than a good position, good in character and good in terms of the money - it doesn't matter where it is - as long as it's in a Catholic area. - You acted in a masterly way, just like Ulysses, throughout the whole affair with Count Starhemberg - only continue as before and don't allow yourself to be taken in - and in particular you should be on your guard if conversation turns to that arrogant goose - I know her, and you can be assured that she has sugar and honey on her lips but pepper in her head and heart - it's entirely natural that the whole busi‑ness is still open to discussion and that many points must be conceded before I could make up my mind and that even if everything were all right I'd still prefer to be any‑where else but Salzburg - but I don't need to worry, as it's unlikely that everything will be granted to me as I'm asking for so much-. But it's not impossible - I'd not hesitate for a moment if everything were properly organized - if only to have the pleasure of being with you - but if the Salzburgers want me, they must satisfy me and all my wishes - otherwise they'll certainly not get me. - So the abbot of Baumberg has died the usual abbot's death! - I didn't know that the abbot of the Holy Cross had died too - I'm very sorry - he was a good, honest, decent man; so you didn't think that Dean Zösch‑inger would be made abbot? - Upon my honour, I never imagined it otherwise; I really don't know who else it could have been! - Of course, he's a good abbot for the orchestra! - So the young lady's daily walk with her faith‑ful lackey bore fruit after all! - They were certainly busy and haven't been idle - the devil makes work for idle hands: - so the amateur theatricals have finally started up? - But how long will they last? - I don't suppose Countess Lodron will be wanting any more concerts like the last one - Czernin is a young whippersnapper and Brunetti a foul‑mouthed oaf.

My friend Raaff is leaving tomorrow; but he's going via Brussels to Aix‑la‑Chapelle and Spa - and from there to Mannheim; he'll let me know as soon as he gets there, for we intend to stay in touch - he sends you and my sister his good wishes, even though he doesn't know you. You say in your letter that you've heard no more about my composition pupil for a long time - that's true, but what shall I tell you about her? - She's not the sort of person who will ever become a composer - all my efforts are in vain - in the first place, she's thoroughly stupid and also thoroughly lazy - I told you about the opera in my last letter - as for Noverre's ballet, all I've ever said is that he may write a new one - he needed just half a ballet and so I wrote the music for it - in other words, 6 numbers are by others and consist entirely of dreadful old French airs, whereas I've written the symphony and contredanses, making 12 pieces in all - the ballet has already been given 4 times to great acclaim - but I'm now absolutely determined not to write anything else unless I know in advance what I'm going to get for it - I did this just as a favour for Noverre. - Monsieur Wendling left on the last day of May - if I wanted to see Baron Bagge, I'd have to have very good eyes as he's not here but in London - is it possible that I've not already told you this? - You'll see that in future I'll answer all your letters accurately - it's said that Baron Bagge will be returning soon, which I should like very much - for many reasons - but especially because there's always an oppor‑tunityathishousetoholdproperrehearsals - Kapellmeister Bach will also be here soon - I think he'll be writing an opera - the French are asses and will always remain so, they can do nothing themselves - they have to rely on foreigners. I spoke to Piccinni at the Concert Spirituel - he's very polite to me and I to him - whenever we happen to meet - otherwise I've not made any new acquaintances - either with him or with other composers - I know what I'm doing - and so do they - and that's enough: - I've already told you that my symphony was a great success at the Concert Spirituel. - If I'm asked to write an opera, it'll no doubt be a source of considerable annoyance, but I don't mind too much as I'm used to it - if only the confounded French language weren't such a dastardly enemy of music! - It's pitiful - German is divine in comparison. - And then there are the singers - - they simply don't deserve the name as they don't sing but scream and howl at the tops of their voices, a nasal, throaty sound - I'll have to write a French oratorio for the Concert Spirituel next Lent - the director Legros is amazingly taken with me; I should add that although I used to see him every day, I've not seen him since Easter, I was so annoyed that he'd not performed my sinfonia concertante; I often visited his house in order to see Mon‑sieur Raaff and each time had to pass his rooms - on each occasion the servants and maids saw me and on each occasion I asked them to give him my best wishes. - I think it's a shame that he didn't perform it, people would have liked it - but he no longer has any opportunity to do so. Where could he find 4 such people for it? One day, when I was planning to visit Raaff, he wasn't at home but I was assured that he'd soon be back. And so I waited - Monsieur Legros came into the room - it's a miracle that I've finally had the pleasure of seeing you again - yes, I've got so much to do - are you staying for lunch? - I'm sorry, but I've a prior engagement. - Monsieur Mozart, we must spend more time together; - it'll be a pleasure. - Long silence - finally:by the way, won't you write a grand symphony for me for Corpus Christi? - Why not? - But can I rely on it? - Oh yes, as long as I can rely on its being performed - and that it doesn't suffer the same fate as the sinfonia concertante - then the dance began - he apolo‑gized as best he could - but there wasn't much he could say - in a word, the symphony was universally liked - and Legros is so pleased that he says it's his best symphony - only the andante hasn't had the good fortune to win his approval - he says it contains too many modulations and that it's too long - but this is because the audience forgot to clap as loudly and make as much noise as they did for the first and final movements - but the andante won the greatest approval from me and from all the connoisseurs and music lovers and most other listeners - it's exactly the opposite of what Legros says - it's entirely natural - and short. - But in order to satisfy him - and, as he claims, several others - I've written another one - each is fitting in its own way - for each has a different character - but I like the last one even more - when I have a moment, I'll send you the symphony, together with the violin tutor, some keyboard pieces and Vogler's Tonwissenschaft und Tonsezkunst - and I shall then want to know what you think about them - the symphony will be performed for the second time - with the new andante - on 15 August - the Feast of the Assumption - the symphony is in re and the andante in sol - you're not supposed to say D or G here. - Well, Legros is now right behind me. - It's time to start thinking about ending this letter - if you write to me, I think it would be better if you were to do so chez Monsieur Le Baron de Grimm, Chaus‑sée d'Antin près le Boulevard - Monsieur Grimm will be writing to you himself very shortly. He and Madame d'Épinay both ask to be remembered to you and send you their heartfelt condolences - but they hope that you will be able to remain composed in the face of a matter that can't be changed - take comfort - and pray fervently, this is the only expedient that is left to us - I was going to ask you to have Holy Masses said at Maria Plain and Loreto - I've also done so here. As for the letter of rec‑ommendation for Herr Beer, I don't think it'll be necessary to send it to me - I still haven't met him; I know only that he's a good clarinettist but a dissolute companion - I don't like associating with such people - it does one no credit; and I've no wish to give him a letter of recommendation - I'd be truly ashamed to do so - even if he could do something for me! - But he's by no means respected - many people haven't even heard of him - Of the 2 Stamitzes, only the younger one is here - the older (the real composer à la Hafeneder) is in London - they're 2 wretched scribblers - and gamblers - drunkards - and whoremongers - not the kind of people for me - the one who's here has scarcely a decent coat to his back - by the way, if things don't work out with Brunetti, I'd very much like to recommend a good friend of mine to the arch‑bishop as first violin, a decent, honest, upstanding man - a stolid individual; - I'd put him at around 40 - a widower - he's called Rothfischer - he's concert master to the princess of Nassau‑Weilburg at Kirchheimbolanden - between ourselves, he's dissatisfied as the prince doesn't like him - or rather he doesn't like his music - he's com‑mended himself to me and it would give me real pleasure to help him - he's the best of men. - Adieu. I kiss your hands 100, 000 times and embrace my sister with all my heart. I am your most obedient son.

Wolfgang Amadè Mozart

Leopold Mozart to his wife and son, 13 July 1778, Salzburg

My Dear Wife and Son,

In order not to miss your name day, my dear wife, I'm writing to you today, even though the letter will no doubt arrive a few days early. I wish you a million joys in being able to celebrate it once more and ask Almighty God to keep you well on this day and for many years to come and allow you to live as contented a life as is possible in this inconstant world theatre. I'm absolutely convinced that for you to be truly happy you need your husband and daughter. God in His unfathomable decree and most holy providence will do what is best for us. Would you have thought a year ago that you'd be spending your next name day in Paris? - - However incredible this would have seemed to many people then, although not to our‑selves, it is possible that with God's help we may be reunited even before we expect it:for my one concern is that I am separated from you and living so far away, so very far away from you; otherwise we're well, God be praised! We both kiss you and Wolfgang a million times and beg you above all to take great care of your health. - The theatre of war has finally opened! In Paris you'll already know that on the 5th of this month the king of Prussia entered Bohemia from Glatz and that he's passed through Nachod and penetrated as far as Königgrätz. War was bound to break out as neither power could withdraw its armies without losing face. For several weeks Austria, with its marches and countermarches, has provided the king with occasional opportunities to make an incursion and launch an attack:but the king didn't think it advisable to undertake such an attack; now the emperor has estab‑lished a very powerful false arsenal at Nachod, and this persuaded the king to attack. But the arsenal was a feint and contained only a semblance of the real thing. They had to take this risk, whatever the outcome, as Austria was neither able nor willing to be the aggressor, while the Croats were merely an advance guard (the only position in which they can really be used) and could barely be restrained any longer, as these people always hope to win booty, which is why they're so keen to go to war. The Saxon troops have formed an alliance with Prussia, and it's presumably true that they've joined forces with Prince Heinrich and will no doubt attack Eger and the Upper Palatinate. More news will no doubt arrive with the next post:this came with the Austrian post on the 11th. This war will be one of the bloodiest, the king wants to die a glorious death, and the emperor wants to start his army life on an equally glorious note.

I wrote the foregoing yesterday, the 12th. This morning, the 13th, shortly before 10 o'clock, I received your distressing letter of 3 July. You can well imagine how we are both feeling. We wept so much that we could scarcely read your letter. - And your sister! - Great God in your mercy! May your most hallowed will be done! My dear son! For all that I am resigned as far as possible to God's will, you'll none the less find it entirely human and natural that I'm almost unable to write for weeping. What am I to con‑clude from all this-? Only that even as I write these lines, she is presumably already dead - or that she has recov‑ered, for you wrote on the 3rd and today is already the 13th. You say that after being bled she felt well, but that a few days later she complained of shivering and feverish‑ness. The last letter from the two of you was dated 12 June, and in it she wrote-I was bled yesterday:so that was the 11th - and why was it done on a Saturday - a fast day? - - I expect she ate some meat. She waited too long to be bled. Knowing her very well, I remember that she likes to put things off, especially in a foreign place, where she'd first have to enquire after a surgeon. Well, so the matter stands - it can't be helped any longer - I have complete confidence in your filial love and know that you have taken all possible care of your mother, who is undoubt‑edly good, and that if God restores her to us, you will always continue to do so - your good mother, who always saw you as the apple of her eye and whose love for you was exceptional, who was exceedingly proud of you and who - I know this better than you - lived for you alone. But if all our hopes are in vain! Could we really have lost her! - Good God! You need friends, honest friends! Other‑wise you'll lose everything, what with the funeral expenses etc. My God! There are many expenses about which you know nothing and where strangers are cheated - taken for a ride - tricked - put to unnecessary expense and exploited if they don't have honest friends:you can have no conception of this. If this misfortune has befallen you, ask Baron Grimm if you can store your mother's effects at his house, so that you don't have to keep an eye on so many things:or lock everything up, because if you're often away for whole days at a time, people could break into your room and rob you. God grant that all my pre‑cautions are unnecessary:but you will recognize your father in this. My dear wife! My dear son! - as she fell ill a few days after being bled, she must have been ill since 16 or 17 June. But you waited too long - she thought she'd get better through bed rest - by dieting - by her own devices, I know how it is, one hopes for the best and puts things off:but, my dear Wolfgang, diarrhoea when one has a fever requires a doctor to know if the fever should be reduced or allowed to run its course as medicines designed to reduce the temperature cause an increase in diarrhoea:and if the diarrhoea is stopped at the wrong time, the materia peccans leads to gangrene. - God! We are in your hands.

Congratulations on the success of your symphony at the Concert Spirituel. I can imagine how anxious you must have been. - Your determination to rush out into the orchestra if things hadn't gone well was presumably just a wild idea. God forbid! You must put this and all such notions out of your head; they're ill considered, such a step would cost you your life, which no man in his right senses risks for a symphony. - Such an affront - and a public affront to boot - would inevitably be avenged by the sword not just by a Frenchman but by all who value their honour. An Italian would say nothing but would lie in wait at a street corner and shoot you dead. - From Munich I've received reliable reports that Count Seeau has been confirmed as intendant of music for Munich and Mannheim; that a list of all the orchestral players has been sent to Mannheim; that the two orchestras will be combined and the worst players weeded out; Herr Wotschitka and the other valets de chambre have been pen‑sioned off on a pension of 400 florins, which surprises me; Dr Sänfftel had the effrontery to demand 3000 florins for his treatment, whereupon he was stripped of his title and salary; finally, it is hoped in Munich that the elector and his wife, the electress, will be back in Munich with their entire court by 10 August. - I began this letter with my congratulations, - and Nannerl was planning to end it with her own. But, as you can imagine, she's incapable of writing a single word, now that she has to write - each letter that she's supposed to write down brings a flood of tears to her eyes. You, her dear brother, must take her place, if - as we hope and desire - you can still do so.

But no! You can no longer do so - she has passed away - you are trying too hard to console me, no one is as eager as that unless driven to it quite naturally by the loss of all human hope or by the event itself. I'm now going to have some lunch, though I don't suppose I'll have much of an appetite.

I'm writing this at half past 3 in the afternoon. I now know that my dear wife is in heaven. I'm writing this with tears in my eyes but in total submission to God's will! Yesterday was the annual celebration of the dedication of the Holy Trinity, so our usual target practice was post‑poned till today. I was unable to cancel it at such a late hour and didn't want to either, in spite of your sad letter. We ate little, but Nannerl, who had cried a lot before lunch, was violently sick and had a terrible headache, so she went to lie down on her bed. Herr Bullinger and the rest of them found us in this deeply distressing situation. Without saying a word, I gave him your letter to read, and he acted his part very well and asked me what I thought of it. I told him that I was firmly convinced that my dear wife was already dead:he said that he was indeed inclined to suspect as much himself; and he then com‑forted me and as a true friend told me all that I had already told myself. I made an effort to cheer up and to remain so, while submitting to God's most holy will, we finished our target practice and everyone left, feeling very saddened, Herr Bullinger remained with me and, without appearing to do so, asked me if I thought that there was any hope in the condition that had been described to us. I replied that I thought that not only was she now dead but that she was already dead on the day you wrote your letter; that I had submitted to the will of God and had to remember that I still had 2 children who I hoped would continue to love me inasmuch as I lived only for them; that I was so firmly convinced that she was dead that I'd even written to you, reminding you to take care of her succes‑sion etc. To this he said, yes, she's dead. At that moment the scales fell from my eyes, scales that had been put in place by this sudden and unexpected turn of events, pre‑venting me from seeing what had happened, for otherwise I'd have quickly suspected that you'd secretly written the truth to Herr Bullinger as soon as I'd read your letter. But your letter had really stunned me - at first I was too dumbfounded to be able to think properly. Even now I still don't know what to write! You don't need to worry about me; I shall play the man. But just think of your mother's tender love for you and you'll realize how much she cared for you - just as when you reach maturity you'll love me more and more after my death - if you love me-as I do not doubt - you should take care of your health, -my life depends on yours, as does the future support of your sister, who honestly loves you with all her heart. It is unbelievably diffcult when death severs a good and happy marriage, but you have to experience that for your‑self to know it. - Write and tell me all the details; perhaps she wasn't bled enough? - - The only thing that's certain is that she trusted too much in herself and called in the doctor too late; meanwhile the inflammation of her intes‑tines gained the upper hand.Take good care of your health! Don't make us all unhappy! Nannerl doesn't yet know about Bullinger's letter, but I've already prepared her to believe that her dear mother is dead. - Write to me soon - tell me everything - when she was buried - and where. - - Good God! To think that I'll have to go to Paris in search of my dear wife's grave! - We kiss you both with all our heart. I must close as the post is leaving. Your honest and utterly distraught father

Mozart

Make sure that none of your things are lost.

维洛那二士

[II,iii，1-30][1]跟随其主人普洛丢斯外出旅行之前，小男仆朗斯向他的家人告别，所有人对他的离开都表达了足够多的悲伤和不舍，除了“人类最好的朋友”。

哎哟，我到现在才哭好呢，咱们朗斯一族里的人都有这个心肠太软的毛病。我像《圣经》上的浪子一样，派到了我的一份家产，现在要跟着普洛丢斯少爷上京城里去。我想我的狗克来勃是最狠心的一条狗。我的妈眼泪直流，我的爸涕泗横流，我的妹妹放声大哭，我家的丫头也号啕喊叫，就是我们养的猫儿也悲伤得乱搓两手，整个家弄得七零八乱，可是这条狠心的恶狗却不流一点儿泪。他是一块石头，像一条狗一样没有心肝；就是犹太人，看见我们分别的情形，也会禁不住流泪的；看我的老祖母吧，她眼睛早已盲了，可是因为我要离家远行，也把她的眼睛都哭瞎了呢。我可以把我们分别的情形扮给你们看。这只鞋子算是我的父亲；不，这只左脚的鞋子是我的父亲；不，不，这只左脚的鞋子是我的母亲；不，那也不对。-哦，不错，对了，这只鞋子底已经破了，它已经穿了一个洞，它就算是我的母亲；这一只是我的父亲。他妈的！就是这样。这一根棒是我的妹妹，因为她就像百合花一样的白，像一根棒那样的瘦小。这一顶帽子是我家的丫头阿南。我就算是狗；不，狗是他自己，我是狗-哦，狗是我，我是我自己。对了，就是这样。现在我走到我父亲跟前：“爸爸，请你祝福我。”现在这只鞋子就要哭得说不出一句话来；然后我就要吻我的父亲，他还是哭个不停。现在我再走到我的母亲跟前；唉！我希望她现在能够像一个木头人一样开起口来！我就是这么吻了她，她的一口气这么喘上喘下的。现在我要到我妹妹跟前，你瞧她哭得多么伤心！可是这条狗站在旁边瞧着我一把一把眼泪挥在地上，却始终不流一点儿泪也不说一句话。

[II,iv，190-212]普洛丢斯本来爱的是裘丽亚，但现在又被他密友的恋人雪尔薇亚迷得神魂颠倒。他既无法理解自己的感情为何如此易变，也不知如何为之辩护。

正像一阵更大的热烙压盖住原来的热焰，一枚大钉敲落了小钉，我的旧日的恋情，也因为一个新的对象而完全冷却了。是我的眼睛在作祟吗？还是因为伐伦泰因把她说得天花乱坠？还是她的真正的完美使我心醉？或者是我的见异思迁的罪恶，使我全然失去了理智？她是美丽的，我所爱的裘丽亚也是美丽的；可是我对于裘丽亚的爱已经成为过去了，那一段恋情就像投入火中的蜡像，已经全然熔解，不留一点儿原来的痕迹。好像我对于伐伦泰因的友谊已经突然冷淡，我不再像从前那样喜爱他了；啊，这是因为我太过于爱他的爱人了，所以我才对他毫无好感。我这样不假思索地爱上了她，如果跟她相知渐深之后，更将怎样为她倾倒？我现在看见的只是她的外相，可是那已经使我的理智的灵光晕眩不定，那么当我在看到她内心的美好时，我一定要变成盲目了。我要尽力克制我的罪恶的恋情；否则就得设计赢取她的芳心。

[II,vi，1-38]随着他的爱情越发炽烈，困境也变得越深。普洛丢斯试图平衡爱意和对友人的忠诚两方面的要求，却发现自己早已被种种繁复纠缠的情感束缚住了。

舍弃我的裘丽亚，我就要违背了盟誓；恋爱美丽的雪尔薇亚，我也要违背了盟誓；中伤我的朋友，尤其违背了盟誓。爱情的力量当初使我信誓旦旦，现在却又诱令我干犯三重的寒盟大罪。动人灵机的爱情啊！你已经引诱我犯罪，现在教我怎样为自己辩解吧。我最初爱慕的是一颗闪烁的星星，如今崇拜的是一个中天的太阳；无心中许可的誓愿，可以有意把它毁弃不顾；只有没有智慧的人，才会迟疑于善恶二者间的选择。呸，呸，不敬的唇舌！她是你从前用两万遍以灵魂做证的盟言，甘心供她驱使的，现在怎么好把她加上恶名！我不能朝三暮四转爱他人，可是我已经变了心了；可是我现在所爱的，才是真正值得我爱的。我失去了裘丽亚，失去了伐伦泰因；要是我继续对他们忠实，我必须失去我自己。我失去了伐伦泰因，换来了我自己；失去了裘丽亚换来了雪尔薇亚：爱情永远是自私的，我自己当然比一个朋友更为宝贵，裘丽亚在天生丽质的雪尔薇亚相形之下，不过是一个黝黑的丑妇。我要忘记裘丽亚尚在人间，记着我对她的爱情已经死去；我要把伐伦泰因当作敌人，努力取得雪尔薇亚更甜蜜的友情。要是我不用些诡计破坏伐伦泰因，我就无法贯彻自己的心愿。

[V,iv，1-12]以为自己情场失意的伐伦泰因，在孤独中找到了慰藉。

习惯是多么能够变化人的生活！在这座浓荫密布人迹罕至的荒林里，我觉得要比人烟繁杂的市镇里舒服得多。我可以在这里一人独坐，和着夜莺的悲歌调子，泄吐我的怨恨忧伤。唉，我那心坎儿里的人儿呀，不要长久抛弃你的殿堂吧，否则它会荒芜而颓圮，不留下一点儿可以供人凭吊的痕迹的！我这破碎的心，是要等着你来修补呢，雪尔薇亚！你这温柔的女神，快来安慰你的寂寞孤零的恋人呀！

[1]此处标识为原书节选篇目所在章节和位置。（后同）-编者注

罗密欧与朱丽叶

[II,ii，2-25]罗密欧望见他眼中的明星在夜空中出现，于是开始滔滔不绝地发表天文学感想——对于冷冰冰的月神黛安娜，处女童贞的卫护者，他说了些很是不客气的话。

轻声！那边窗子里亮起来的是什么光？那就是东方，朱丽叶就是太阳！起来吧，美丽的太阳！赶走那妒忌的月亮，她因为她的女弟子比她美得多，已经气得面色惨白了。既然她这样妒忌着你，你不要皈依她吧；脱下她给你的这一身惨绿色的贞女的道服，它是只配给愚人穿着的。那是我的意中人，啊，那是我的爱！唉，但愿她知道我在爱着她！她欲言又止，可是她的眼睛已经道出了她的心事。待我去回答她吧；不，我不要太鲁莽，她不是对我说话。天上两颗最灿烂的星，因为有事离去，请求她的眼睛替代它们在空中闪耀。要是她的眼睛变成了天上的星，天上的星变成了她的眼睛，那便怎样呢？她脸上的光辉会掩盖了星星的明亮，正像灯光在朝阳下黯然失色一样；在天上的她的眼睛，会在太空中大放光明，使鸟儿们误认为黑夜已经过去而展开它们的歌声。瞧！她用纤手托住了脸庞，那姿态是多么美妙！啊，但愿我是那一只手上的手套，好让我亲一亲她脸上的香泽！

[II,ii，33-49]完全没意识到有人在偷听自己讲话，朱丽叶对着夜空倾吐恋慕心意，自以为只是在独白。但她的话却已经被自己所钟情的对象听去了。

罗密欧啊，罗密欧！为什么你偏偏是罗密欧呢？否认你的父亲，抛弃你的姓名吧；也许你不愿意这样做，那么只要你宣誓做我的爱人，我也不愿再姓凯普莱脱了。

罗　（旁白）我是继续听下去呢，还是现在就对她说话？

朱　只有你的名字才是我的仇敌，你即使不姓蒙太玖，仍然是这样的一个你。姓不姓蒙太玖又有什么关系呢？它又不是手，又不是脚，又不是手臂，又不是脸孔，又不是身体上任何其他的部分。啊！换一个姓名吧！姓名本来是没有意义的；我们叫作玫瑰的这一种花，要是换了个名字，它的香味还是同样的芬芳；罗密欧要是换了别的名字，他的可爱的完美也绝不会有丝毫改变。罗密欧，抛弃了你的名字吧；我愿意把我整个的心魂，赔偿你这一个身外的空名。

[III,ii，1-31]等待情郎前来约会的朱丽叶一心只盼夜晚快点来临，催促为太阳神驾车穿越天穹的骏马快点奔跑。

朱　快快跑过去吧，踏着火云的骏马，把太阳拖回到它的安息的所在；但愿驾车的腓通[3]鞭策你们飞驰到西方，让阴沉的暮夜赶快降临。展开你密密的帷幕吧，成全恋爱的黑夜！遮住夜行人的眼睛，让罗密欧悄悄地投入我的怀里，不被人家看见也不被人家谈论！恋人们可以在他们自身美貌的光辉里互相缱绻；即使恋爱是盲目的，那也正好和黑夜相称。来吧，温文的夜，你朴素的黑衣妇人，教会我怎样在一场全胜的赌博中失败，把各人纯洁的童贞互为赌注。用你黑色的罩巾遮住我脸上羞怯的红潮，等我深藏内心的爱情慢慢儿胆大起来，不再因为在行动上流露真情而惭愧，来吧，黑夜！来吧，罗密欧！来吧，你黑夜中的白昼！因为你将要睡在黑夜的翼上，比乌鸦背上的新雪还要皎白。来吧，柔和的黑夜！来吧，可爱的黑颜的夜，把我的罗密欧给我，等他死了以后，你再把他带去，分散成无数的星星，把天空装饰得如此美丽，使全世界都恋爱着黑夜，不再崇拜炫目的太阳。啊！我已经买下了一所恋爱的华厦，可是它还不曾属我所有；虽然我已经把自己出卖，可是还没有被买主领去。这日子长得真叫人厌烦，正像一个做好了新衣服的小孩，在节日的前夜焦躁地等着天明一样。

[3]腓通是希腊日神赫里俄斯的儿子，与其父驾驭日车。

该撒遇弑记

[II,i，10-34]因其情怀高绝、目标宏大而变得不择手段的勃鲁脱斯说，该撒必须要死。无论该撒的个人品质如何，只要他活着，就是对自由的威胁。

勃　只有叫他死这一个办法；我自己对他并没有私怨，只是为了大众的利益。他将要戴上王冠；那会不会改变他的性格是一个问题；蝮蛇是在光天化日之下出现的，所以步行的人必须刻刻提防。让他戴上王冠？-不！那等于我们把一个毒刺给了他，使他可以随意加害于人。把不忍之心和威权分开，那威权就会被人误用；讲到该撒这个人，说一句公平话，我还不知道他什么时候曾经受他的感情的支配甚于他的理智。可是微贱往往是少年的野心的阶梯，凭借着它一步步爬上了高处；当他一旦登上了最高的一级之后，他便不再回顾那梯子，他的眼光仰望着云霄，瞧不起他从前所恃为凭借的低下的阶段。该撒何尝不会这样？所以，为了恐怕他有这一天，必须早一点儿防备。既然我们反对他的理由，不是因为他现在有什么可以指责的地方，所以就得这样说：他在现在的地位之上，要是再扩大了他的权力，一定会引起这样这样的后患；我们应当把它当作一颗蛇蛋，与其让它孵出以后害人，不如趁它还在壳里的时候就把它杀死。

[II,i，61-9]勃鲁脱斯称，凯歇斯暗中怂恿的话语，在他自己心中掀起了一场战争。

自从凯歇斯怂恿我反对该撒那一刻起，我一直没有睡过。在计划一件危险的行动和开始行动之间的一段时间里，一个人就好像置身于一场可怖的噩梦之中，遍历种种的幻象；他的精神和身体上的各部分正在彼此磋商；整个的身心像一个小小的国家，临到了叛变突发的前夕。

[II,i，77-85]心情忐忑的勃鲁脱斯问道，如果我们的事业是正义的，为什么谋划时如此见不得人？

阴谋啊！你在百鬼横行的夜里，还觉得不好意思显露你的险恶的容貌吗？啊！那么你在白天什么地方可以找到一处幽暗的巢窟，遮掩你的奇丑的脸相呢？不要找寻吧，阴谋，还是把它隐藏在和颜悦色的后面；因为要是您用本来面目招摇过市，即使幽冥的地府也不能把你遮掩过人家的眼睛的。

[III,i，254-75]在声言要与该撒的谋杀者和解后，玛格斯·安东尼话锋一转，开始用全然不同的语言形容他被害的朋友的尸身。

啊！你这一块流血的泥土，有史以来一个最高贵的英雄的遗体，恕我跟这些屠夫们曲意周旋。愿灾祸降于溅泼这样宝贵的血的凶手！你的一处处的伤口，好像许多无言的嘴，张开了它们殷红的嘴唇，要求我的舌头替它们向世人申诉；我现在就在这些伤口上预言：一个咒诅将要降临在人们的肢体上，残暴惨酷的内乱将要使意大利到处陷于混乱；流血和破坏将要成为一时的风尚，恐怖的景象将要每天被人们亲眼所见，以至于做母亲的人看见她们的婴孩被战争的魔手所肢解，也会毫不在乎地付之一笑；人们因为习惯于残杀，一切怜悯之心将要完全灭绝；该撒的冤魂借着从地狱的烈火中出来的哀提[4]的协助，将要用一个君王的口气，向罗马的全境发出屠杀的号令，让战争的猛犬四处蹂躏，为了这一个万恶的罪行，大地上将要弥漫着呻吟求葬的肉体的腐臭。

[4]哀提（Ate），现通常译作阿忒，是希腊神话中引诱人或神失去理智而发狂的女神。-编者注

汉姆莱脱[7]

[I,ii，129-59]发现自己的父亲被害，而且母亲没出几星期就改嫁他人，汉姆莱脱王子对生命感到无助的狂怒，对他而言，生命中除了绝望已经一无所有。

啊，但愿这一个太坚实的肉体会融解，消散，化成一堆露水！或者那永生的真神不会制定禁止自杀的律法！上帝啊！上帝啊！人世间的一切在我看来是多么可厌陈腐，乏味而无聊！哼！哼！那是一个荒芜不治的花园，长满了恶毒的莠草。想不到居然会有这种事情！刚死了两个月！不，两个月还不满！这样好的一个国王，比起这一个来，简直是天神和丑怪；这样爱我的母亲，甚至于不愿让天风吹痛了她的脸庞。天上和地下！我必须记着吗？嘿，她会偎依在他的身旁，好像吃了美味的食物，格外促进了食欲一般；可是，只有一个月的时间，我不能再想下去了！脆弱啊，你的名字就是女人！短短的一个月以前她哭得像个泪人儿似的，送我那可怜的父亲下葬；她在送葬的时候所穿的那双鞋子现在还没有破旧，她就，她就，-上帝啊！一头没有理性的畜生也要悲伤得长久一些，-她就嫁给我的叔父，我的父亲的弟弟。可是他一点儿不像我的父亲，正像我一点儿不像赫邱利斯一样。只有一个月的时间，她那流着虚伪之泪的眼睛还没有消去它们的红肿，她就嫁了人了。啊，罪恶的匆促，这样迫不及待地钻进了乱伦的衾被！那不是好事，也不会有好结果；可是碎了吧，我的心，因为我必须噤住我的嘴！

[I,v，92-112]得到父亲的鬼魂“记着我”的命令后，汉姆莱脱向所有的神灵和魔鬼发誓永远不忘。

天上的神明啊！地啊！再有什么呢？我还要向地狱呼喊吗？啊，呸！忍着吧，忍着吧，我的心！我的全身的筋骨，不要一下子就变得衰老，支持着我的身体呀！记着你！是的，你可怜的亡魂，当记忆不曾从我这混乱的头脑里消失的时候，我会记着你的。记着你！是的，我要从我的记忆的碑板上，拭去一切琐碎愚蠢的记录，一切书本上的格言，一切陈言套语，一切过去的印象，我的少年的阅历所留下的痕迹，只让你的命令留在我的脑筋的书卷里，不掺杂一丝下贱的废料；是的，上天为我做证！啊，最恶毒的妇人！啊，奸贼，奸贼，脸上堆着笑的万恶的奸贼！我的写字板呢？我必须把它记下来：一个人尽管满面都是笑，骨子里却是杀人的奸贼；至少我相信在丹麦是这样的。（写字）好，叔父，我把你写下来了。现在我要记下我的话，那是，“再会，再会！记着我”。我已经发过誓了。

[II,ii，547-603]伶人投入的表演让汉姆莱脱为自己无法在现实中采取行动，为父亲报仇而深感羞惭，但同时他也看到了一个机会，可以让戏剧表演为自己的计谋服务。

啊，我是一个多么不中用的蠢材！这一个伶人不过在一本虚构的故事、一场激昂的幻梦之中，却能够使他的灵魂融化在他的意象里，在它的影响之下，他的整个的脸色变得惨白，他的眼中洋溢着热泪，他的神情流露着仓皇，他的声音是这么呜咽凄凉，他的全部动作都表现得和他的意象一致，这不是很不可思议的吗？而且一点儿也不为了什么！为了赫邱琶！赫邱琶对他有什么相干，他对赫邱琶又有什么相干，他却要为她流泪？要是他也有了像我所有的那样使人痛心的理由，他将要怎样呢？他一定会让眼泪淹没了舞台，用可怖的字句震裂了听众的耳朵，使有罪的人发狂，使无罪的人骇愕，使愚昧无知的人惊惶失措，使所有的耳目迷乱了它们的功能。可是我，一个糊涂颟顸的家伙，垂头丧气，一天到晚像在做梦似的，忘记了杀父的大仇；虽然一个国王给人家用万恶的手段掠夺了他的权位，杀害了他的最宝贵的生命，我却始终哼不出一句话来。我是一个懦夫吗？谁骂我恶人？谁敲破我的脑壳？谁拔去我的胡子，把它吹在我的脸上？谁扭我的鼻子？谁当面指斥我胡说？谁对我做这种事？吓！我应该忍受这样的侮辱，因为我是一个没有心肝，逆来顺受的怯汉，否则我早已用这奴才的尸肉，喂肥了四境之内的乌鸢了。嗜血的，荒淫的恶贼！狠心的，奸诈的，淫邪的，悖逆的恶贼！啊！复仇！-嗨，我真是个蠢材！我的亲爱的父亲被人谋杀了，鬼神都在鞭策我复仇，我这做儿子的却像一个下流女人似的，只会用空言发发牢骚，学起泼妇骂街的样子来，真是了不得的勇敢！呸！呸！活动起来吧，我的脑筋！我听人家说，犯罪的人在看戏的时候，因为台上表演的巧妙，有时会激动天良，当场供认他们的罪恶；因为暗杀的事情无论干得怎样秘密，总会借着神奇的喉舌泄露出来。我要叫这班伶人在我的叔父面前表演一本跟我的父亲的惨死情节相仿的戏剧，我就在一旁窥察他的神色；我要探视到他的灵魂的深处，要是他稍露惊骇不安之态，我就知道我应该怎么办。我所看见的幽灵也许是魔鬼的化身，借着一个美好的形状出现，魔鬼是有这一种本领的；对于柔弱忧郁的灵魂，他最容易发挥他的力量；也许他看准了我的柔弱和忧郁，才来向我作祟，要把我引诱到沉沦的路上。我要先得到一些比这更切实的证据；凭着这一本戏，我可以发掘国王内心的隐秘。

[III,i，56-88]汉姆莱脱思考自杀。

生存还是毁灭，这是一个值得考虑的问题；默然忍受命运的暴虐的毒箭，或是挺身反抗人世的无涯的苦难，在奋斗中结束了一切，这两种行为，哪一种是更勇敢的？死了，睡去了-什么都完了-要是在这一种睡眠之中，我们心头的创痛，以及其他无数血肉之躯所不能避免的打击，都可以从此消失，那正是我们求之不得的结局。死了，睡去了；睡去了也许还会做梦。嗯，阻碍就在这儿：因为当我们摆脱了这一具朽腐的皮囊以后，在那死的睡眠里，究竟将要做些什么梦，那不能不使我们踌躇顾虑。人们甘心久困于患难之中，也就是为了这一个缘故；谁愿意忍受人世的鞭挞和讥嘲，压迫者的凌辱，傲慢者的冷眼，被轻蔑的爱情的惨痛，法律的迁延，官吏的横暴和微贱者费尽辛勤所换来的鄙视，要是他只要用一柄小小的刀子，就可以清算他自己的一生？谁愿意负着这样的重担，在烦劳的生命的迫压下呻吟流汗，倘不是因为惧怕不可知的死后，那从来不曾有一个旅人回来过的神秘之国，是它迷惑了我们的意志，使我们宁愿忍受目前的磨折，不敢向我们所不知道的痛苦飞去？这样理智使我们全变成了懦夫，决心的炽热的光彩，被审慎的思维盖上了一层灰色，伟大的事业在这一种考虑之下，也会逆流而退，失去了行动的意义。

[III,ii，395-406]为了让自己进入利于行动的心理状态，汉姆莱脱准备先去正面申斥他母亲对父亲犯下的罪行。

现在是一夜之中最阴森的时候，鬼魂都在此刻从坟墓里出来，地狱也要向人世吐放戾气；现在我可以痛饮热腾腾的鲜血，干那白昼所不敢正视的残忍的行为。且慢！我还要到我的母亲那儿去一趟。心啊！不要失去你的天性之情，永远不要让尼罗[8]的灵魂潜入我这样坚定的胸怀；让我做一个凶徒，可是不要做一个逆子。我要用利剑一样的话刺痛她的心，可是绝不伤害她身体上一根毛发；我的舌头和灵魂要在这一次学学伪善者的样子，无论在言语上给她多么严厉的谴责，在行动上却要做得丝毫不让人家指摘。

[III,iii，36-72]篡位者（同时也是汉姆莱脱的继父）克劳迪斯在祈祷时承认了自己可怖的罪行，同时也承认自己无法为之忏悔。

我的罪恶的戾气已经上达于天；我的灵魂上负着一个元始以来最初的咒诅，杀害兄弟的暴行！我不能祈祷，虽然我的愿望像决心一样强烈；我的更坚强的罪恶击败了我的坚强的意愿。像一个人同时要做两件事情，我因为不知道应该先从什么地方下手而徘徊歧途，结果反弄得一事无成。要是这一只可咒诅的手上染满了一层比它本身还厚的兄弟的血，难道天上所有的甘霖，都不能把它洗涤得像雪一样洁白吗？慈悲的使命，不就是宽宥罪恶吗？祈祷的目的，不是一方面预防我们的堕落，一方面救拔我们于已堕落之后吗？那么我要仰望上天；我的过失已经消灭了。可是唉！哪一种祈祷才是我所适用的呢？“求上帝赦免我的杀人重罪”吗？那不能，因为我现在还占有着那些引起我的犯罪动机的目的物，我的王冠，我的野心，我的王后。非分攫取的利益还在手里，就可以幸邀宽恕吗？在这贪污的人世，罪恶的镀金的手也许可以把公道推开不顾，暴徒的赃物往往就是枉法的贿赂；可是天上却不是这样的，在那边一切都无可遁避，任何行动都要显现它的真相，我们必须当面为我们自己的罪恶做证。那么怎么办呢？还有什么法子好想呢？试一试忏悔的力量吧。什么事情是忏悔所不能做到的？可是对于一个不能忏悔的人，它又有什么用呢？啊，不幸的处境！啊，像死亡一样黑暗的心胸！越是挣扎，越是不能脱身的胶住了的灵魂！救救我，天使们！试一试吧：弯下来，顽强的膝盖；钢丝一样的心弦，变得像新生之婴的筋肉一样柔嫩吧！但愿一切转祸为福！

[III,iii，73-95]汉姆莱脱遇见独自祈祷，无人在旁保护的克劳迪斯，意识到这是个刺杀他的绝好时机。但他停下了，害怕他会因此将一个本该下地狱受罚的灵魂送进天堂。

他现在正在祈祷，我正好动手；我决定现在就干，让他上天堂去，我也算报了仇了。不，那还要考虑一下：一个恶人杀死我的父亲；我，他的独生子，却把这个恶人送上天堂。啊，这简直是以恩报怨了。他用卑鄙的手段，在我父亲罪孽深重的时候乘其不备地把他杀死；虽然谁也不知道在上帝面前，他的生前的善恶如何相抵，可是照我们一般的推想，他的业债多半是很重的。现在他正在洗涤他的灵魂，要是我在这时候结果了他的性命，那么天国的路是为他开放着，这样还算是复仇吗？不，收起来，我的剑，等候一个更惨酷的机会吧；当他在酒醉以后，在愤怒之中，或是在荒淫纵欲的时候，在赌博，咒骂，或是其他邪恶的行为的中间，我就要叫他颠踬在我的脚下，让他幽深黑暗不见天日的灵魂永堕地狱。

[IV,iv，32-66]听闻别人为了争夺一块小小的土地要发动战争，汉姆莱脱又为自己连最重的欺辱都无法为之复仇而感到羞惭不安。

我所见到听到的一切，都好像在对我谴责，鞭策我赶快进行我的蹉跎未就的复仇大愿！一个人要是在他生命的盛年，只知道吃吃睡睡，他还算是个什么东西？简直不过是一头畜生！上帝造下我们来，使我们能够这样高谈阔论，瞻前顾后，当然要我们利用他所赋予我们的这一种能力和灵明的理智，不让它们白白废掉。现在我明明有理由，有决心，有力量，有方法，可以动手干我所要干的事，可是我还是在说一些空话，“我要怎么怎么干”，而始终不曾在行动上表现出来；我不知道这是为了鹿豕一般的健忘呢，还是为了三分懦怯一分智慧的过于审慎顾虑。像大地一样显明的榜样都在鼓励我；瞧这一支勇猛的大军，领队的是一个娇养的少年王子，勃勃的雄心振起了他的精神，使他蔑视不可知的结果，为了区区弹丸大小的一块不毛之地，拼着血肉之躯，去向命运、死亡和危险挑战。真正的伟大不是轻举妄动，而是在荣誉遭遇危险的时候，即使为了一根稻秆之微，也要慷慨力争。可是我的父亲给人惨杀，我的母亲给人污辱，我的理智和感情都被这种不共戴天的大仇所激动，我却因循隐忍，一切听其自然，看着这两万人为了博取一个空虚的名声，视死如归地走下他们的坟墓里去，目的只是争夺一方还不够作为他们埋骨之所的土地，相形之下，我将何地自容呢？从这一刻起，让我摒除一切的疑虑妄念，把流血的思想充满在我的脑际！

[7]汉姆莱脱，现多译作“哈姆雷特”，与《奥赛罗》（本书译作《奥瑟罗》）、《李尔王》、《麦克白》（本书译作《麦克佩斯》）并称为莎士比亚“四大悲剧”。-编者注

[8]尼罗（Nero），现通常译作尼䘵，古罗马暴君。

特洛埃围城记

（原名：特洛埃勒斯与克蕾雪达）

[I,i，91-106]尽管他的城邦正在与希腊人交战，特洛埃王子特洛埃勒斯认为，一切纷争都无法将他的注意力从爱人克蕾雪达身上引开——他的怒气只会留给为他传情达意的难对付的信使潘达勒斯。

别闹，你们这些聒耳的喧哗！别闹，粗暴的声音！两方面都是些傻瓜！无怪海伦是美丽的，因为你们每天用鲜血涂着她的红颜。我不能为了这一个理由去和人家作战；它对于我的剑是一个太贫乏的题目。可是潘达勒斯-天啊！你是多么作弄着我！我要向克蕾雪达传达我的情愫，只有靠着潘达勒斯的力量；可是央他去说情，他自己就是这么难说话，克蕾雪达又是那么凛若冰霜，把一切哀求置之不闻。爱坡罗[9]，为了你的达芬[10]的爱，告诉我，克蕾雪达是什么，潘达勒斯是什么，我们都是些什么？她的眠床就是印度；她睡在上面，是一颗无价的明珠；一道汹涌的波涛隔开在我们的中间；我是个采宝的商人，这个潘达勒斯便是我的不可靠的希望，我的载登彼岸的渡航。

[I,ii，281-95]克蕾雪达也觉得必须要通过一个中间人来传达情意不太方便，但她足够精明，不会屈服于特洛埃勒斯的追求，轻易委身于他。她发觉，爱情和任何战争一样，是一场力量的博弈。

言语，盟誓，礼物，眼泪，以及恋爱的全部祭礼，他都借着别人的手向我呈献过了；然而我从特洛埃勒斯本身所看到的，比之从潘达勒斯的谀辞的镜子里所看到的，还要清楚千倍。可是我却还不能就答应他。女人在被人追求的时候是个天使；无论什么东西，一到了人家手里，便一切都完了；无论什么事情，也只有在正在进行的时候兴趣最为浓厚。一个被人恋着的女子，要是不知道男人重视未获得的事物，甚于既得的事物，她就等于一无所知；一个女人要是以为恋爱在达到目的以后，还是像热情未获满足以前一样的甜蜜，那么她一定从来不曾有过恋爱的经验。所以我从恋爱中间归纳出这一句箴言：既得之后是命令，未得之前是请求。虽然我的心里装满了爱情，我却不让我的眼睛泄露我的秘密。

[III,ii，16-27]特洛埃勒斯已然被预期中将要到来的爱情冲昏了头脑，他确信自己在爱情真的来临时一定会经受不住它的强烈冲击——实际上，他会被快乐摧毁，就像死在战场上一样。

我觉得眼前迷迷糊糊的，期望使我的头脑打着回旋。想象中的美味是这样甘芳，它迷醉了我的神经。要是我的生津的齿颊果然尝到了经过三次提炼的爱情的旨酒，那就该怎样呢？我怕我会死去，昏昏沉沉地倒下去不再醒来；我怕那种太微妙渊深的快乐，调和在太芳洌的甘美里，不是我的粗俗的感官所能经受；我怕，我更怕在无边的幸福之中，我会失去一切的知觉，正像大军冲锋，敌人披靡的时候，每个人都忘记了自己一样。

[9]爱坡罗（Apollo），现通常译作阿波罗，光明与预言之神，因被邱必特之箭射中，疯狂爱着达芙尼。-编者注

[10]达芬（Daphne），现通常译作达芙尼，河神拉冬的女儿，为躲避阿波罗的追求，变成了一棵月桂树，成为月桂女神。-编者注

量罪记

[II,ii，162-87]所有官员中最虔信，最道貌岸然的安哲鲁声称自己抗拒了所有女性的诱惑，但唯独不可抗拒地被贞洁的依莎贝拉吸引。

什么？这是哪里说起？是她的错处？还是我的错处？诱惑的人和受诱惑的人，哪一个更有罪？嘿！她没有错，她也没有引诱我。像芝兰旁边的一块臭肉，在阳光下蒸发腐烂的是我，芝兰却不曾因为枯萎而失去了芬芳，难道一个贞淑的女子，比那些狂花浪柳更能引动我们的情欲吗？难道我们因为缺少荒芜的旷地，必须把圣殿拆毁，种植我们的罪恶吗？呸！呸！呸！安哲鲁，你在干些什么？你是个什么人？你因为她的纯洁而对她爱慕，因为爱慕她而必须玷污她的纯洁？啊，让她的弟弟活命吧！要是法官自己也偷窃人家的东西，那么盗贼是可以振振有词的。啊！我竟是这样爱她，所以才想再听见她说话，饱餐她的美色吗？我在做些什么梦？狡恶的魔鬼为了引诱圣徒，会把圣徒做他钩上的美饵；因为爱慕纯洁的事物而驱令我们犯罪的诱惑，才是最危险的。娼妓用尽她天生的魅力，人工的狐媚，都不能使我的心中略起微波，可是这位贞淑的女郎却把我完全征服了。我从前看见人家为了女人发痴，总是讥笑他们，想不到我自己也会有这么一天！

[II,iv，1-17]安哲鲁惧怕，自己对依莎贝拉不被准许的感情，会使他的宗教信仰顷刻间成为笑柄。

我每次要祈祷沉思的时候，我的心思总是纷乱无主：上天所听到的只是我的口不应心的空言，我的精神却贯注在依莎贝拉身上；上帝的名字挂在我的嘴边咀嚼，心头的欲念，兀自在那里奔腾。我已经厌倦于我所矜持的尊严，正像一篇大好的文章一样，在久读之后也会使人掩耳；现在我宁愿把我这岸然道貌，去换一根因风飘荡的羽毛。什么地位！什么面子！多少愚人为了你还虚伪的外表而凛然生畏，多少聪明人为了它而俯首帖服！可是人孰无情，不一定出角的才是魔鬼呢。

奥瑟罗

[III,iii，255-74]奥瑟罗被埃古包藏祸心的欺骗性暗示与自己的嫉妒心蒙蔽了双眼，他此时已经在信里准备将他的爱人苔丝德梦娜视为背叛了自己的人——不是真正忠诚的猎鹰，而是一只“没有被驯服的野鹰”。

这是一个非常诚实的家伙，对于人情世故实在是熟悉不过的了。要是我能证明她是一只没有被驯服的野鹰，虽然我用自己的心弦把她系住，我也要放她随风远去，追寻她自己的命运。也许因为我生得黑丑，缺少绅士们温柔风雅的谈吐，也许因为我年纪老了点儿-虽然还不算顶老-所以她才会背叛我，我已经自取其辱，只好割断对她这一段痴情。啊，结婚的烦恼！我们可以在名义上把这些可爱的人儿称为我们所有，却不能支配她们的爱憎喜恶。我宁愿做一只虾蟆，呼吸牢室中的浊气，也不愿占住了自己心爱之物的一角，让别人把它享用。可是就算是权贵也不能幸免灾祸，他们并不比贫贱者享有更多的特权。那是像死一样不可逃避的命运，我们一生下来就已经冥冥中注定了的。

[V,ii，1-22]只因着自己疯狂的嫉妒心，在没有确凿证据的情况下，奥瑟罗就确信自己的妻子不忠。于是他决心要杀死苔丝德梦娜。

只是为了这一个原因，只是为了这一个原因，我的灵魂！纯洁的星星啊，让我不要向你们说出它的名字！只是为了这一个原因……可是我不愿溅她的血，也不愿毁伤她那比白云更皎洁、比石膏更腻滑的肌肤。可是她不能不死，否则她将要陷害更多的男子。让我熄灭了这一盏灯，然后我就熄灭你的生命的火焰。融融的灯光啊，我把你吹熄以后，要是我心生后悔，仍旧可以把你重新点亮；可是你，造化最精美的粉本啊，你的火焰一旦熄灭，我不知道什么地方有那天上的神火，能够燃起你的原来的光彩！我摘下了蔷薇，就不能再给它已失的生机，只好让它枯萎凋谢；当它还在枝头的时候，我要嗅一嗅它的芳香。（吻苔）啊，甘美的气息！你几乎诱动公道的心。使她折断她的利剑了！再一个吻，再一个吻。愿你到死都是这样；我要杀死你，然后再爱你。再一个吻，这是最后的一吻了；这样销魂，却又是这样无比的惨痛！我必须哭泣，然而这些是无情的眼泪。她醒来了。

黄金梦

[IV,i，1-41]在将一笔巨大的财富全部花在款待宾客和赠送礼物上之后，因慷慨而变得一贫如洗的泰门发现昔日所谓的“朋友”们全都离弃了自己。他对人类的世界彻底失望了，跑到城外郊野的树林里生活。在他进入林中之前，最后望了一眼家乡雅典，并对那里的人们发出这样的咒诅。

让我回头瞧瞧你。城啊，你包藏着如许的豺狼，快快陆沉吧，不要再替雅典做藩篱！已婚的妇人们，淫荡起来吧！子女们不要听父母的话！奴才们和傻瓜们，把那些年高德劭的元老们拉下来，你们自己坐上他们的位置吧！娇嫩的处女变成人尽可夫的娼妓，在你们父母的眼前跟别人奸通吧！破产的人，不要偿还你们的欠款，用刀子割破你们债主的咽喉吧！仆人们，放手偷窃吧！你们庄严的主人都是借着法律的名义杀人越货的大盗。婢女们，睡到你们主人的床上去吧；你们的主妇已经做卖淫妇去了！十六岁的儿子，夺下你步履龙钟的老父手里的拐杖，把他的脑浆敲了出来吧！孝亲敬神的美德，和平公义的正道，齐家睦邻的要义，教育，礼仪，百工的技巧，尊卑的品秩，风俗，习惯，一起陷于混乱吧！加害于人身的各种瘟疫，向雅典伸展你们的毒手，播散你们猖獗传染的热病！让风湿钻进我们那些元老的骨髓，使他们手脚瘫痪！让淫欲放荡占领我们那些少年人的心，使他们反抗道德，沉溺在狂乱之中！在每一个雅典人身上播下疥癣疮毒的种子，让他们一个个害起了癞病！让他们的呼吸中都含着毒素，谁和他们来往做朋友的都会中毒而死！除了我这赤裸裸的一身以外，我什么也不要带走，你这可憎的城市！我给你的只有无穷的咒诅！泰门要到树林里去，和最凶恶的野兽做伴侣，比起无情的人类来，它们是要善良得多了。天上一切神明听着我，把那城墙内外的雅典人一起毁灭了吧！求你们让泰门把他的仇恨扩展到全体人类，不分贵贱高低！阿门。

[IV,iii，1-45]在人类的世界中，决定地位高低的是财富而非真正的价值。泰门一边抨击着世界的丑恶不公，一边挖取地里的树根来填饱肚子，却意外地挖出了金子。此时，他对这“最卑下的金属”“人尽可夫的娼妇”充满了怨恨和冷嘲。

神圣的化育万物的太阳啊！把地上的瘴雾吸起，让天空中弥漫着毒气吧！同生同长，同居同宿的孪生兄弟，也让他们各人去接受不同的命运，让那贫贱的被富贵的所轻蔑吧。重视伦常天性的，必须遍受各种颠沛困苦的凌虐，灭伦悖义的才会安享荣华。让乞儿跃登高位，大臣退处贱职吧；元老必须世世代代受人贱视，乞儿必须享受世袭的光荣。有了丰美的牧草，牛儿自然肥胖；缺少了饲料它就会瘦瘠下来。谁敢秉着光明磊落的胸襟挺身而起，说，“这人是一个谄媚之徒”？要是有一个人是谄媚之徒，那么谁都是谄媚之徒；因为每一个按照财产多寡区分的阶级，都要被次一阶级所奉承；博学的才人必须向多金的愚夫鞠躬致敬。在我们万恶的天性之中，一切都是歪曲偏斜的，一切都是奸邪淫恶。所以，让我永远厌弃人类的社会吧！泰门憎恨形状像人一样的东西，他也憎恨他自己；愿毁灭吞噬了整个人类！泥土，给我一些树根充饥吧！（掘地）谁要是希望你给他一些更好的东西，你就用你最猛烈的毒物餍足他的口味吧！咦，这是什么？金子！黄黄的，发光的，宝贵的金子！不，天神们啊，我不是一个游手好闲的信徒；我只要你们给我一些树根！这东西，只这一点点儿，就可以使黑的变成白的，丑的变成美的，错的变成对的，卑贱变成尊贵，老人变成少年，懦夫变成勇士。吓！你们这些天神们啊，为什么要给我这东西呢？嘿，这东西会把你们的祭司和仆人从你们的身旁拉走，把健汉头颅底下的枕垫抽去；这黄色的奴隶可以使异教联盟，同宗分裂；它可以使受咒诅的人得福，使害着灰白色癞病的人为众人所敬爱；它可以使窃贼得到高爵显位，和元老们分庭抗礼；它可以使鸡皮黄脸的寡妇重做新娘，即使她的尊容可以使身染恶疮的人见了呕吐，有了这东西也会恢复三春的娇艳。来，该死的土块，你这人尽可夫的娼妇，你惯会在乱七八糟的列国之间挑起纷争，我倒要让你去施展一下你的神通。

李尔王

[I,ii，1-22]私生子凭什么比合法的儿子卑贱？葛罗斯脱的私生子爱特门决定，自己在行为上绝不会尊重合法嫡子埃特加先天优越的权利。

大自然，你是我的女神，我愿意在你的法律之前俯首听命。为什么我要受世俗的排挤，让世人的歧视剥夺我的应享的权利，只因为我比一个哥哥迟生了一年或是十四个月？为什么他们要叫我私生子？为什么我比人家卑贱？我的壮健的体格，我的慷慨的精神，我的端正的容貌，哪一点比不上正夫人的公子？为什么他们要给我加上庶出，贱种，私生子的恶名？贱种，贱种；贱种？难道在热烈兴奋的奸情里生下的孩子，倒不及拥着一个毫无欢趣的老婆，在半睡半醒之间制造出来的那一批蠢货？好，合法的埃特加，我一定要得到你的土地；我们的父亲欢喜他的私生子爱特门，正像他欢喜他的合法的嫡子一样。好听的名词，“合法”好；我的合法的哥哥，要是这封信发生效力，我的计策能够成功，瞧着吧，庶出的爱特门将要把合法的嫡子盖罩在他的下面-那时候我可要扬眉吐气啦，帮助帮助私生子吧！

[II,iii，1-21]父亲因受了私生子弟弟爱特门的欺骗，下令逮捕埃特加，于是埃特加被迫伪装逃命。他觉得自己身边发生的一切如此疯狂，以至于他想不到什么伪装能比一个四处流浪的疯乞丐更合适的了。

听说他们已经发出告示捉我，幸亏我躲在一株空心的树干里，没有给他们找到。没有一处城门可以出入无阻：没有一个地方不是警卫森严，准备把我捉住！为了保全自己的生命起见，我想还不如改扮作一个最卑贱穷苦，最为世人所轻视，和禽兽相去无几的家伙；我要把污泥涂在脸上。一块毡布裹住我的腰，把满头的头发打了许多乱结，赤身裸体抵抗着风雨的侵没。这地方本来有许多疯乞丐，他们高声叫喊，用针哪，木槌哪，钉子哪，迷迭香的树枝哪，刺在他们麻木而僵硬的手臂上，用这种可怕的形状，到那些穷苦的农场，乡村，羊棚和磨坊里去，有时候发出一些疯狂的咒诅，有时候向人哀求祈祷，乞讨一些布施。我现在学着他们的样子一定不会引起人家的疑心。可怜的疯叫花！可怜的汤姆！倒有几分像；我现在不再是埃特加了。

[IV,i，1-9]仍然处于疯乞丐伪装下的埃特加，对自己稳居社会底层地位这个事实感到欣慰。

与其被人在表面上恭维而背地里鄙弃，那么还是像这样自己知道为举世所不容的好。一个最困苦最微贱最为命运所屈辱的人，可以永远抱着希冀而无所恐惧；从最高的地位上跌落下来，那变化是可悲的，对于穷困的人，命运的转机却能使他欢笑！

[III,iv，28-36]因着自己的落难，李尔开始思考他的国家里穷人的悲惨境遇。

衣不蔽体的不幸的人们，无论你们在什么地方忍受着这样无情的暴风雨的袭击，你们的头上没有片瓦遮身，你们的腹中饥肠雷动，你们的衣服千疮百孔，怎么抵挡得了这样的气候呢？啊！我一向太不关心这种事情了。安享荣华的人们啊，睁开你们的眼睛来，替这些不幸的人们设身处地想一想，分一些你们享用不了的福泽给他们，让上天知道你们不是全无心肝的人吧！

麦克佩斯

[I,v，36-52]麦克佩斯夫人意识到，只需一场谋杀就能让自己的丈夫坐上苏格兰的王位——而刚好国王邓根今晚要来他们的城堡做客。

报告邓根走进我这堡门来送死的乌鸦，它的叫声是嘶哑的。来，注视着人类恶念的魔鬼们！解除我的女性的柔弱，用最凶恶的残忍自顶至踵贯注在我的全身；凝结我的血液，不要让悔恨通过我的心头，不要让天性中的恻隐摇动我的狠毒的决意！来，你们这些杀人的助手，你们无形的躯体散满在空间，到处找寻为非作恶的机会，进入我的妇人的胸中，把我的乳水当作胆汁吧！来，阴沉的黑夜，用最昏暗的地狱中的浓烟罩住你自己，让我的锐利的刀瞧不见它自己切下的伤口，让青天不能从黑暗的重衾里探出头来，高喊着：“住手，住手！”

[I,vii，1-28]在妻子将谋杀邓根的念头放进他的脑海中之后，麦克佩斯思考自己将要犯下的罪行，并为其之巨大和不可饶恕而感到惊骇。

要是干了以后就完了，那么还是快一点儿干；要是凭着暗杀的手段，可以攫取美满的结果；要是这一刀砍下去，就可以完成一切，终结一切；要是我们就可以在这里跳过时间的浅濑，展开生命的新页……可是在这种事情上，我们往往可以看见冥冥中的裁判；教唆杀人的人，结果反而自己被人所杀；把毒药投入酒杯里的人，结果也会自己饮鸩而死。他到这儿来是有两重的信任：第一，我是他的亲戚，又是他的臣子，按照名分绝对不能干这样的事；第二，我是他的主人，应当保障他的身体的安全，怎么可以自己持刀行刺？而且这个邓根秉性仁慈，处理国政，从来没有过失，要是把他杀死了，他的生前的美德将要像天使一般发出喇叭一样清澈的声音，向世人昭告我的弑君重罪；怜悯像一个御气而行的天婴，将要把这可憎的行为揭露在每一个人的眼中，使眼泪淹没了天风。没有一种力量可以鞭策我前进，可是我的跃跃欲试的野心，却不顾一切地驱着我去冒颠踬的危险。

[II,i，33-64]麦克佩斯试图坚定自己杀邓根的决心时几近谵妄，谋杀想象和实际谋杀行为之间的区别在他的头脑里渐渐模糊。

在我面前摇晃着，它的柄对着我的手的，不是一把刀子吗？来，让我抓住你。我抓不到你，可是仍旧看见你。不祥的幻象，你只是一件可视不可触的东西吗？或者你不过是一把想象中的刀子，从谵热的脑筋里发出来的虚妄的意匠？我仍旧看见你，你的形状正像我现在拔出的这一把刀子一样明显。你指示着我所要去的方向，告诉我应当用什么利器。我的眼睛倘不是受了其他知觉的愚弄，就是兼领了一切感官的机能。我仍旧看见你；你的刃上和柄上还流着一滴一滴刚才所没有的血。没有这样的事；杀人的恶念使我看见这种异象。现在在半个世界上，大自然似乎已经死去，罪恶的梦景扰乱着平和的睡眠，作法的巫觋在向惨白的赫凯娣献祭；形容枯瘦的杀人犯，听到了替他巡风的豺狼的嗥声，像一个鬼似的向他的目的地蹑足跨步前进。坚固结实的大地啊，不要听见我的脚步声音，知道它们是到什么地方去的，我怕路上的砖石会泄露了我的行踪。我正在这儿威胁他的生命，他却在那儿活得好好的；在紧张的行动中间，言语是多么软弱无力。（钟声）我去，就是这么干；钟声在招引我。不要听见它，邓根，这是召唤你上天堂或者下地狱的丧钟。

[V,v，17-28]听闻妻子的死讯，麦克佩斯缩进了自己的内心世界中，悲叹自己为之战斗和杀戮过的一切终究都是徒劳，毫无意义。

她应该迟一点儿再死；现在不是应该让我听见这个消息的时候。明天，明天，再一个明天，一天接着一天地蹑步前进，直到最后一秒钟的时间；我们所有的昨天，不过替傻子们照亮了到死亡的土壤中去的路。熄灭了吧，熄灭了吧，短促的烛光！人生不过是一个行走的影子，一个在舞台上指手画脚的拙劣的伶人，登场了片刻，就在无声无息中悄然退下；它是一个愚人所讲的故事，充满着喧哗和骚动，找不到一点儿意义。

沉珠记

（原名：泰尔亲王配力克尔斯）

[I,i，122-43]配力克尔斯惊骇而恐惧地意识到他的求婚对象与其父亲——伟大的安替奥克斯国王有着乱伦关系。

殷勤的礼貌把罪恶掩盖得多么巧妙！正像一个伪君子一样，除了一副仁义的假面具以外，便没有一毫可取的地方。要是我果然理解错了，那么你当然不会是那样的坏人，因为淫邪的欲念而出卖你的灵魂；可是现在你是父亲又是儿子，因为你非礼拥抱了你的女儿，那种快乐是应该让一个丈夫享受，不应该让一个父亲享受的；她是吃她母亲血肉的人，因为她玷污了她母亲的枕席；两人都像毒蛇一样，虽然吃的是芬芳的花草，它们的身体内却藏着毒液。安替奥克斯，再会吧！因为智慧告诉我，凡是能够动手干那些比黑夜更幽暗的行为而不知惭愧的人，一定会不惜采取任何的手段，把它竭力遮掩。一件罪恶往往引起第二件，奸淫和杀人正像火焰和烟气一样互相联系。毒药和阴谋是罪恶的双手，犯罪者遮羞的武器；为了免得我的生命遭人暗算，我要赶快逃出这危险的陷阱。

[II,i，1-11]配力克尔斯痛斥毁坏其船只的风暴，风暴已经充分展示了威力，现在他只希望它可以给自己一个安静的死亡。

天上的星辰啊，停止你们的愤怒吧！风雨雷电的神灵，请你们记着，尘世的凡民在你们的神威之下是无能为力的，我这脆弱的身心唯有对你们俯首降服。唉！海水曾经把我冲在岩石上，从一处海岸卷到另一处海岸，留下我这仅余残喘的一身，除了一死而外，再没有其他的想望。你们已经使一个君王失去他所有的一切，这就足够表现你们力量的伟大了；你们既然不让他葬身鱼腹，他的唯一的要求，只是让他在这儿得到一个安静的死。

还璧记

（原名：辛白林）

[II,ii，12-51]埃契摩吹嘘自己能够引诱任何他想引诱的女人，于是普修默斯就与他打赌自己贞洁的妻子伊慕琴一定品行端正无瑕。伊慕琴抵御住了埃契摩的进攻。发现自己作为风流浪子的名声和财富都即将毁于一旦，埃契摩只好铤而走险，偷偷躲在箱子里潜入伊慕琴的卧房，这样他就能够得到足够的信息来向普修默斯证明自己已经得手。他在黑夜中现身，开始记录伊慕琴房间里的陈设和她本人的身体细节：虽然他不会动她的身体，但要强暴她的好名声。

蟋蟀们在歌唱，人们都在休息之中恢复他们疲劳的精神。我们的达昆正是像这样蹑手蹑脚地，轻轻走到那被他毁坏了贞操的女郎的床前。赛西莉霞，你睡在床上的姿态是多么优美！鲜嫩的百合花，比你的被褥更洁白！要是我能够接触一下她的肌肤！但是一个吻，仅仅一个吻！无比美艳的红玉，它们被安放得多么可爱！散布在室内的异香，是她樱唇中透露出来的气息。蜡烛的火焰向她的脸上低俯，想要从她紧闭的眼睫之下，窥视那收藏了的光辉，虽然它们现在被窗户所遮掩，还可以依稀想见那净澈的纯白和空虚的蔚蓝，那正是太空本身的颜色。可是我的计划是要记录这室内的陈设；我要把一切写下来：这样这样的图画；那边是窗子；她的床上有这样的装饰；织锦的褂帏，上面织着这样这样的人物和故事。啊！可是关于她肉体上的一些活生生的记录，才是比一万种琐屑的家具更有力的证明，更可以充实我此行的收获。睡眠啊！你死亡的模仿者，沉重地压在她的身上，让她的知觉像教堂里的墓碑一般漠无所感吧。下来，下来；（自伊慕琴臂上取下手镯）一点儿不费力地，它就滑落下来了！它是我的；有了这样外表上的证据，一定可以格外加强内心的扰乱，把她的丈夫激怒得发起疯来。在她的左胸还有一颗梅花形的痣，就像莲香花花心里的红点一般：这是一个确证，比任何法律所能造成的证据更有力；这一个秘密将使他不能不相信我已经打开链锁，把她宝贵的贞操偷走了。够了。我好傻！为什么我要把这也记了下来，它不是已经牢牢地钉住在我的记忆里了吗？她读了一个晚上的书，原来看的是替吕厄斯的故事；这儿折下的一页，正是菲萝美儿被迫失身的地方。够了；回到箱子里去，把弹簧关上了。黑夜的巨龙，走快一些吧，让黎明拨开乌鸦的眼睛！恐惧包围着我的全身；虽然这是一位天上的神仙，我却像置身在地狱之中。（钟鸣）一，二，三；赶快，赶快！

[II,v，1-35]听到埃契摩的胜利故事后，普修默斯的世界和信念完全崩塌了，进入了一种极度厌女的情绪状态之中。

难道男人们生到这世上来，一定要靠女人的合作的吗？我们都是私生子，全都是。被我称为父亲的那位最可尊敬的人，当我的母亲怀我的时候，谁也不知道他在什么地方；不知道哪一个人造下了我这冒牌的赝品；可是我的母亲在当时却是像黛安娜一般圣洁的，正像现在我的妻子担着无双美誉一样。啊，报复！报复！她不让我享受我的合法的欢娱，常常劝诫我忍耐自制，她的神情是那样的贞静幽娴，带着满脸的羞涩，那楚楚可怜的样子，便是铁石心肠的人，也不能不见了心软；我以为她是像没有被太阳照临的白雪一般皎洁的。啊，一切的魔鬼们！这卑鄙的埃契摩在一小时之内-也许还不到一小时的工夫？-也许他没有说什么话，只是像一头日耳曼的野猪似的，一声叫喊，一头就扑了上去，除了照例的半推半就以外，并没有遭遇任何的反抗。但愿我能够在我自己的一身之内找到哪一部分是女人给我的！因为我断定男人的罪恶的行动，全都是女人遗留给他的性质所造成的：说诳是女人的天性；谄媚也是她的；欺骗也是她的；淫邪和猥亵的思想，都是她的，她的；报复也是她的本能；野心，贪欲，好胜，傲慢，虚荣，诽谤，反复，凡是一切男人所能列举，地狱中所知道的罪恶，或者一部分或者全部分，都是属于她的；不，简直是全部分；因为她们即使对于罪恶也没有恒心，每一分钟都要更换一种新的花样。我要写文章痛骂她们，厌恶她们，咒诅她们。可是这还不是表示真正的痛恨的最好的办法，我应该祈祷她们如愿以偿，因为她们自己招来的痛苦，是远胜于魔鬼所能给予她们的灾祸的。

[III,vi，1-27]伊慕琴满怀欣喜地去见丈夫，却发现他在计划着杀掉自己——因为她所谓的“不贞”而嫉妒到发狂了。现在，身穿男子服色的伊慕琴坚持前往密尔福特港，希望在那里找到丈夫，并让他相信自己的忠诚不变。

我现在明白了做一个男人是很麻烦的；我已经筋疲力尽，连续两夜把大地当作我的眠床；倘不是我的决心支持着我，我早就病倒了。密尔福特啊，当毕散尼奥在山顶上把你指点给我看的时候，你仿佛就在我的眼底。天哪！难道一个不幸的人，连一块安身之地都不能得到吗？我想他所到之处，就是地面也会从他的脚下逃走的。两个乞丐告诉我我不会迷失我的路径；难道这些可怜的苦人儿，他们自己受着痛苦，明知这是上天对他们的惩罚和磨难，还会向人扯诳吗？是的，富人们也难得讲半句真话，怎么怪得他们？被锦衣玉食汩没了本性，是比因穷困而扯诳更坏的；国王们的诈欺，是比乞丐的假话更可鄙的。我的亲爱的夫啊！你也是一个欺心之辈。现在我一想到你，我的饥饿也忘了，可是就在片刻之前，我已经饿得快要站不起来。咦！这是什么？这儿还有一条路通到洞口；它大概是野人的巢窟。我还是不要叫喊，我不敢叫喊；可是饥饿在没有使人完全失去知觉以前是会提起人的勇气的。升平富足的盛世徒然养成一批懦夫，困苦永远是坚强之母。喂！有人吗？要是里面住着文明的人类，回答我吧；假如是野人的话，我也要向他们夺取或是告借一些食物。喂！没有回答吗？那么我就进去。最好还是拔出我的剑；万一我的敌人也像我一样见了剑就害怕，他会瞧都不敢瞧它的。好天啊，但愿我所遇到的是这样一个敌人！

[IV,ii，293-334]此时她仍然在向西方走的路上。悲伤得快要疯掉的伊慕琴从不安的睡眠中醒来，竟发现身边躺着的似乎是自己丈夫的无头尸体。

是的，先生，到密尔福特港是怎么走的？谢谢您啦。打那边的林子里过去吗？请问还有多少路？哎哟！还有六里吗？我已经走了整整一夜了。真的，我要躺下来睡一会儿。（见克尸[11]）可是且慢！我可不要跟人家睡在一起！天上的男女神明啊！这些花就像是人世的欢乐，这个流血的汉子是忧愁烦恼的象征。我希望我在做梦；因为我自己仿佛是一个看守山洞的人，替一些诚实的人们烹煮食物。可是不会有这样的事，这不过是脑筋里虚构出来的无中生有的幻象；我们的眼睛有时也像我们的判断一般靠不住。真的，我还是在害怕得发抖。要是天上还剩留着仅仅像麻雀眼睛一般大小的一点点儿的慈悲，敬畏的神明啊，求你们赐给我一部分吧！这梦仍然在这儿；虽然在我醒来的时候，它还是围绕在我的周遭，盘踞在我的心头；并不是想象却是有实感的。一个没有头的男子！普修默斯的衣服！我知道他的两腿的肥瘦，这是他的手他的迈邱利一般敏捷的脚，他的马斯一般威武的股肉，赫邱利斯一般雄壮的筋骨，可是他的乔武一般神圣的脸呢？天上也有谋杀案了吗？怎么！

[V,iv，1-26]监狱中的普修默斯回想起自己对挚爱的妻子伊慕琴犯下的多重罪恶，感到监狱正是他最该在的地方。

欢迎，拘囚的生活！因为我想你是到自由去的路。可是我还比一个害痛风病的人好一些，因为他宁愿永远生活在痛苦呻吟之中，不愿让死亡这一个手到病除的良药治愈他的疾病；只有死才是打开这些铁锁的钥匙。我的良心上负着比我的足胫和手腕上更重的镣铐；仁慈的神明啊，赐给我忏悔的利剑，让我劈开这黑暗的牢门，得到永久的自由吧！我已经衷心悔恨，这还不够吗？儿女们是这样使他们尘世的父亲回嗔作喜；天上的神明是更充满了慈悲的。我必须忏悔吗？还有什么比拖镣戴铐更好的方式，出于自愿而不是被迫的？为了祓除我的罪孽，我愿意呈献我整个的生命。我知道你们比万恶的世人仁慈得多，他们从破产的负债人手里拿去三分之一，六分之一，或是十分之一的财产，让这些债户留着有余不尽的残资，供他们继续地剥削：那却不是我的愿望。把我的生命拿去，抵偿伊慕琴的宝贵的生命吧；虽然它们的价值并不相等，可是那总是一条生命，为你们所亲手铸下的。在人与人之间，他们并不戥量着每一枚货币，即使略有轻重，也瞧着上面的花纹而收受下来；你们应该把我收受，因为我是你们的。伟大的神明啊，要是你们愿意做这一次清算，就请拿去我的生命，勾销这些无情的债务。啊，伊慕琴！我要在沉默中向你抒陈我的心曲。（睡）

[11]此处指克洛登。-编者注

暴风雨

[II,ii，1-17]野人卡列班诅咒普洛士丕罗，因为他觉得对方篡夺了自己在岛上王国的合法统治，并设各种各样的酷刑来折磨自己，以让自己顺服于他。

愿太阳从一切沼泽平原上吸起来的瘴气都降在普洛士丕罗身上，让他的全身没有一处不生恶病！他的精灵会听见我的话，但我非把他咒一下不可。他们要是没有他的吩咐是不会捻掏我，显出各种的怪相吓我，把我推到烂泥里或是在黑暗中化作一团磷火诱我迷失了路的；但是他们要想出种种的恶作剧来摆布我：有时变成猴子，向我咧着牙齿扮嘴脸，然后再咬我；一下子又变成刺猬在路上滚作一团，我的赤脚一踏上去便把针刺竖了起来；有时我的四面围绕着毒蛇，吐出分叉的舌头来，那咝咝的声音吓得我发了狂。

（屈林鸠罗上。）

卡　瞧！瞧！又有一个他的精灵来了！因为我柴捡得慢，要来给我吃苦头。让我把身体横躺下来；也许他会注意不到我。

[18-40]屈林鸠罗不是轻盈的精灵，而只是一个被暴风雨吹到岸边的水手。当他遇到卡列班时，不知该如何看待这个形状奇异的卧姿生物。

这儿没有丛林也没有灌木可以抵御任何风雨。又有一阵大雷雨要起来啦，我听见风在呼啸，那边那堆大的乌云像是一只臭水袋，就要把水倒下来的样子。要是这回再像不久以前响着那么大的雷，我不晓得我该把我的头藏到什么地方去好；那块云准要整桶整桶地倒下水来。咦！这是什么东西？是一个人还是一条鱼？死的还是活的？一定是一条鱼；他的气味像一条鱼，有些隔宿的发霉了的鱼腥气，不是新腌的鱼。奇怪的鱼！我从前曾经到过英国；要是我现在还在英国，只要把这条鱼染上一些颜色，包管那边无论哪一个假期里没事做的傻瓜都会掏出整块的银洋来：在那边很可以靠这条鱼发一笔财；随便什么稀奇古怪的畜生在那边都可以做成一桩好生意。他们不愿意丢一个铜子给跛脚的叫花子，却愿意拿出一角钱来看一个死了的印第安红人。嘿，他像人一样生着腿呢！他的翼鳍多么像是一对臂膀！他的身体还是暖的！我说我弄错了，这不是鱼，是一个岛上的土人，才刚被天雷轰的那样子。（雷声）唉！雷雨又来了；我只得躲到他的衫子底下去，别的再没有躲避的地方了：一个人倒运起来就要跟妖怪一起睡觉。让我躲在这儿直到云消雨散。

[V,i，33-57]岛屿的主宰普洛士丕罗成功报复了曾经错待他的人，他所有的工作即告结束。于是他念出了最后一个咒语，意在让魔法力量从这个世界上消失。

你们山河林沼的小妖们；踏沙无痕，追逐着退潮时的海神，而他一转身来，便又倏然逃去的精灵们；在月下的草地上留下了环舞的圈迹，使羊群不敢走近的小神仙们；以及在半夜中以制造菌蕈为乐事，一听见肃穆的晚钟便雀跃起来的你们：虽然你们不过是些弱小的孩儿，但我借着你们的帮助，才能遮暗了中天的太阳，唤起了作乱的狂风，在青天碧海之间激起了浩荡的战争；我把火给予震雷，用乔武大神的霹雳劈碎了他自己那株粗干的橡树；我使稳固的海岬震动，连根拔起了松树和杉柏；因着我的法力无边的命令，坟墓中的长眠者也被惊醒，打开了墓门而出来。但现在我要捐弃这种狂暴的魔术，仅仅再要求一些微妙的天乐化导他们的心性，使我能得到我所希望的结果；以后我便将折断我的魔杖，把它埋在幽深的地底，把我的书投向深不可测的海心。

Two Gentlemen of Verona

[II, iii, 1– 30] Off on his travels with his master Proteus,Launce the servant- boy has had to say his fond farewells: all have been gratifyingly sad to see him go except for ‘man’s best friend’:

Nay, ’twill be this hour ere I have done weeping; all the kind of the Launces have this very fault. I have received my proportion, like the prodigious son, and am going with Sir Proteus to the Imperial’s court. I think Crab my dog be the sourest- natured dog that lives. My mother weeping, my father wailing, my sister crying, our maid howling, our cat wringing her hands, and all our house in a great perplexity; yet did not this cruelhearted cur shed one tear. He is a stone, a very pebblestone, and has no more pity in him than a dog. A Jew would have wept to have seen our parting. Why, my grandam, having no eyes, look you, wept herself blind at my parting. Nay, I’ll show you the manner of it. This shoe is my father. No, this left shoe is my father. No, no, left shoe is my mother. Nay, that cannot be so neither. Yes, it is so, it is so, it hath the worser sole. This shoe with the hole in it is my mother, and this my father. A vengeance on’t, there ’tis. Now, sir, this staff is my sister; for, look you, she is as white as a lily and as small as a wand. This hat is Nan our maid. I am the dog. No, the dog is himself, and I am the dog. O, the dog is me, and I am myself. Ay, so, so. Now come I to my father: ‘Father, your blessing.’ Now should not the shoe speak a word for weeping. Now should I kiss my father; well, he weeps on. Now come I to my mother. O, that she could speak now like an old woman! Well, I kiss her. Why, there ’tis; here’s my mother’s breath up and down. Now come I to my sister. Mark the moan she makes. Now the dog all this while sheds not a tear, nor speaks a word; but see how I lay the dust with my tears.

[II, iv, 190– 212] Previously in love with Julia, but now newly smitten with Silvia, his best friend’s girl, Proteus finds it as hard to comprehend his fickle feelings as he does to justify them:

Even as one heat another heat expels,

Or as one nail by strength drives out another,

So the remembrance of my former love

Is by a newer object quite forgotten.

Is it my mind, or Valentine’s praise,

Her true perfection, or my false transgression,

That makes me reasonless to reason thus?

She is fair; and so is Julia that I love –

That I did love, for now my love is thawed;

Which, like a waxen image ’gainst a fire,

Bears no impression of the thing it was.

Methinks my zeal to Valentine is cold,

And that I love him not as I was wont.

O, but I love his lady too too much,

And that’s the reason I love him so little.

How shall I dote on her with more advice

That thus without advice begin to love her!

’Tis but her picture I have yet beheld,

And that hath dazzlèd my reason’s light;

But when I look on her perfections,

There is no reason but I shall be blind.

If I can check my erring love, I will;

If not, to compass her I’ll use my skill.

[II, vi, 1– 38] His dilemma deepening with his passion, Proteus ties himself up into emotional knots, as he seeks to square the demands of love and loyalty:

To leave my Julia, shall I be forsworn;

To love fair Silvia, shall I be forsworn;

To wrong my friend, I shall be much forsworn.

And e’en that power which gave me first my oath

Provokes me to this threefold perjury:

Love bade me swear, and Love bids me forswear.

O sweet- suggesting Love, if thou hast sinn’d,

Teach me, thy tempted subject, to excuse it!

At first I did adore a twinkling star,

But now I worship a celestial sun.

Unheedful vows may heedfully be broken;

And he wants wit that wants resolvèd will

To learn his wit t’exchange the bad for better.

Fie, fie, unreverend tongue, to call her bad

Whose sovereignty so oft thou hast preferred

With twenty thousand soul- confirming oaths!

I cannot leave to love, and yet I do;

But there I leave to love where I should love.

Julia I lose, and Valentine I lose;

If I keep them, I needs must lose myself;

If I lose them, thus find I by their loss:

For Valentine, myself; for Julia, Silvia.

I to myself am dearer than a friend,

For love is still most precious in itself;

And Silvia – witness heaven, that made her fair! –

Shows Julia but a swarthy Ethiope.

I will forget that Julia is alive,

Remembering that my love to her is dead;

And Valentine I’ll hold an enemy,

Aiming at Silvia as a sweeter friend.

I cannot now prove constant to myself

Without some treachery used to Valentine.

[V, iv, 1– 12] A loser, it seems, in love, Valentine finds solace in solitude:

How use doth breed a habit in a man!

This shadowy desert, unfrequented woods,

I better brook than flourishing peopled towns.

Here can I sit alone, unseen of any,

And to the nightingale’s complaining notes

Tune my distresses, and record my woes.

O thou that dost inhabit in my breast,

Leave not the mansion so long tenantless,

Lest, growing ruinous, the building fall

And leave no memory of what it was!

Repair me with thy presence, Silvia:

Thou gentle nymph, cherish thy forlorn swain.

The Taming of the Shrew

[IV, i, 174– 97] Petruchio unfolds his masterplan for breaking the ungovernable Katherine to his will – he’ll treat the ‘shrew’ as a haggard or hawk and tame her that way:

Thus have I politicly begun my reign,

And ’tis my hope to end successfully.

My falcon now is sharp and passing empty,

And till she stoop she must not be full- gorged,

For then she never looks upon her lure.

Another way I have to man my haggard,

To make her come, and know her keeper’s call,

That is, to watch her, as we watch these kites

That bate and beat and will not be obedient.

She eat no meat to- day, nor none shall eat.

Last night she slept not, nor tonight she shall not.

As with the meat, some undeservèd fault

I’ll find about the making of the bed,

And here I’ll fling the pillow, there the bolster,

This way the coverlet, another way the sheets.

Ay, and amid this hurly I intend

That all is done in reverend care of her.

And, in conclusion, she shall watch all night,

And if she chance to nod I’ll rail and brawl,

And with the clamour keep her still awake.

This is a way to kill a wife with kindness,

And thus I’ll curb her mad and headstrong humour.

He that knows better how to tame a shrew,

Now let him speak –’tis charity to show.

Love’s Labour’s Lost

[III, i, 170– 202] A wit and self- conscious cynic, Berowne has always scoffed at the idea of love, yet now he finds he too has been struck by an arrow from the bow of Dan (Lord) Cupid:

And I, forsooth, in love!

I, that have been love’s whip,

A very beadle to a humorous sigh;

A critic, nay, a night- watch constable,

A domineering pedant o’er the boy,

Than whom no mortal so magnificent!

This wimpled, whining, purblind, wayward boy,

This Signor Junior, giant- dwarf, Dan Cupid,

Regent of love- rhymes, lord of folded arms,

Th’ anointed sovereign of sighs and groans,

Liege of all loiterers and malcontents,

Dread prince of plackets, king of codpieces,

Sole imperator and great general

Of trotting paritors – O my little heart!

And I to be a corporal of his field,

And wear his colours like a tumbler’s hoop!

What? I love? I sue? I seek a wife?

A woman, that is like a German clock,

Still a- repairing, ever out of frame,

And never going aright, being a watch,

But being watched that it may still go right!

Nay, to be perjured, which is worst of all;

And, among three, to love the worst of all –

A whitely wanton with a velvet brow,

With two pitch- balls stuck in her face for eyes;

Ay, and, by heaven, one that will do the deed,

Though Argus were her eunuch and her guard!

And I to sigh for her, to watch for her,

To pray for her! Go to, it is a plague

That Cupid will impose for my neglect

Of his almighty dreadful little might.

Well, I will love, write, sigh, pray, sue, and groan;

Some men must love my lady, and some Joan.

A Midsummer Night’s Dream

[I, i, 226– 45] Her own beauties once adored, but now despised by a sweetheart who has transferred his affections to her best friend Hermia, Helena is forced to reflect upon the utter, unjust arbitrariness of love:

How happy some o’er other some can be!

Through Athens I am thought as fair as she.

But what of that? Demetrius thinks not so;

He will not know what all but he do know.

And as he errs, doting on Hermia’s eyes,

So I, admiring of his qualities.

Things base and vile, holding no quantity,

Love can transpose to form and dignity.

Love looks not with the eyes, but with the mind,

And therefore is winged Cupid painted blind.

Nor hath love’s mind of any judgement taste;

Wings and no eyes figure unheedy haste.

And therefore is love said to be a child

Because in choice he is so oft beguiled.

As waggish boys in game themselves forswear,

So the boy love is perjured everywhere;

For ere Demetrius looked on Hermia’s eyne,

He hailed down oaths that he was only mine,

And when this hail some heat from Hermia felt,

So he dissolved, and showers of oaths did melt.

Much Ado About Nothing

[II, iii, 8– 33] His own armour of scorn so far proof against Cupid’s arrows, Benedick muses on the mysterious miracles worked by love, even on those who, like his friend Claudio, should know better:

I do much wonder that one man, seeing how much another man is a fool when he dedicates his behaviours to love, will, after he hath laughed at such shallow follies in others, become the argument of his own scorn by falling in love; and such a man is Claudio. I have known when there was no music with him but the drum and the fife, and now had he rather hear the tabor and the pipe. I have known when he would have walked ten mile afoot to see a good armour, and now will he lie ten nights awake carving the fashion of a new doublet. He was wont to speak plain and to the purpose, like an honest man and a soldier, and now is he turned orthography; his words are a very fantastical banquet, just so many strange dishes. May I be so converted and see with these eyes? I cannot tell; I think not. I will not be sworn but love may transform me to an oyster; but I’ll take my oath on it, till he have made an oyster of me he shall never make me such a fool. One woman is fair, yet I am well; another is wise, yet I am well; another virtuous, yet I am well; but till all graces be in one woman, one woman shall not come in my grace. Rich she shall be, that’s certain; wise, or I’ll none; virtuous, or I’ll never cheapen her; fair, or I’ll never look on her; mild, or come not near me; noble, or not I for an angel; of good discourse, an excellent musician,and her hairshall be of what colour it please God.

Julius Caesar

[II, i, 10– 34] Ruthless in his high- mindedness, Brutus says that Caesar simply has to die. Alive, he is a threat to freedom, whatever his personal qualities may be:

It must be by his death; and, for my part,

I know no personal cause to spurn at him,

But for the general. – He would be crowned.

How that might change his nature, there’s the question.

It is the bright day that brings forth the adder,

And that craves wary walking. Crown him! – that!

And then, I grant, we put a sting in him

That at his will he may do danger with.

Th’abuse of greatness is when it disjoins

Remorse from power; and, to speak truth of Caesar,

I have not known when his affections swayed

More than his reason. But ’tis a common proof

That lowliness is young ambition’s ladder,

Whereto the climber- upward turns his face;

But when he once attains the upmost round,

He then unto the ladder turns his back,

Looks in the clouds, scorning the base degrees

By which he did ascend: so Caesar may;

Then, lest he may, prevent. And, since the quarrel

Will bear no colour for the thing he is,

Fashion it thus: that what he is, augmented,

Would run to these and these extremities;

And therefore think him as a serpent’s egg

Which, hatched, would as his kind grow mischievous,

And kill him in the shell.

[II, i, 61– 9 ] Cassius’ whisperings, says Brutus, have set off acivil war in his very nature:

Since Cassius first did whet me against Caesar

I have not slept.

Between the acting of a dreadful thing

And the first motion, all the interim is

Like a phantasma or a hideous dream:

The genius and the mortal instruments

Are then in council; and the state of man,

Like to a little kingdom, suffers then

The nature of an insurrection.

[II, i, 77– 85] If our cause is so just, says an uneasy Brutus, why such need for secrecy?

O conspiracy,

Sham’st thou to show thy dangerous brow by night,

When evils are most free? O then, by day

Where wilt thou find a cavern dark enough

To mask thy monstrous visage? Seek none, conspiracy;

Hide it in smiles and affability;

For if thou path, thy native semblance on,

Not Erebus itself were dim enough

To hide thee from prevention.

[III, i, 254– 75] After conciliatory words with Caesar’s killers, Mark Antony uses very different language over the body of his murdered friend:

O, pardon me, thou bleeding piece of earth,

That I am meek and gentle with these butchers!

Thou art the ruins of the noblest man

That ever livèd in the tide of times.

Woe to the hand that shed this costly blood!

Over thy wounds now do I prophesy –

Which like dumb mouths do ope their ruby lips

To beg the voice and utterance of my tongue –

A curse shall light upon the limbs of men;

Domestic fury and fierce civil strife

Shall cumber all the parts of Italy;

Blood and destruction shall be so in use,

And dreadful objects so familiar,

That mothers shall but smile when they behold

Their infants quartered with the hands of war,

All pity choked with custom of fell deeds;

And Caesar’s spirit, ranging for revenge,

With Ate by his side come hot from hell,

Shall in these confines with a monarch’s voice

Cry havoc and let slip the dogs of war,

That this foul deed shall smell above the earth

With carrion men, groaning for burial.

Hamlet

[I, ii, 129– 59] His father murdered, his mother remarried within weeks, Prince Hamlet rages helplessly against a life which for him holds nothing but disappointment:

O that this too too sullied flesh would melt,

Thaw, and resolve itself into a dew;

Or that the Everlasting had not fixed

His canon ’gainst self- slaughter. O God, God,

How weary, stale, flat, and unprofitable

Seem to me all the uses of this world!

Fie on’t! ah, fie, ’tis an unweeded garden

That grows to seed. Things rank and gross in nature

Possess it merely. That it should come to this –

But two months dead, nay, not so much, not two!

So excellent a king, that was to this

Hyperion to a satyr; so loving to my mother

That he might not beteem the winds of heaven

Visit her face too roughly. Heaven and earth,

Must I remember? Why, she would hang on him

As if increase of appetite had grown

By what it fed on. And yet, within a month –

Let me not think on’t. Frailty, thy name is woman.

A little month, or e’er those shoes were old

With which she followed my poor father’s body

Like Niobe, all tears, why she, even she –

O God! a beast that wants discourse of reason

Would have mourned longer – married with my uncle,

My father’s brother, but no more like my father

Than I to Hercules. Within a month,

Ere yet the salt of most unrighteous tears

Had left the flushing in her gallèd eyes,

She married. O, most wicked speed, to post

With such dexterity to incestuous sheets!

It is not, nor it cannot come to good.

But break, my heart, for I must hold my tongue.

[I, v, 92– 112] Conjured by his father’s ghost to ‘Remember’,Hamlet swears by every power imaginable never to forget:

O all you host of heaven! O earth! What else?

And shall I couple hell? O, fie! Hold, hold, my heart.

And you, my sinews, grow not instant old,

But bear me stiffly up. Remember thee?

Ay, thou poor ghost, while memory holds a seat

In this distracted globe. Remember thee?

Yea, from the table of my memory

I’ll wipe away all trivial fond records,

All saws of books, all forms, all pressures past

That youth and observation copied there,

And thy commandment all alone shall live

Within the book and volume of my brain,

Unmixed with baser matter. Yes, by heaven!

O most pernicious woman!

O villain, villain, smiling, damnèd villain!

My tables – meet it is I set it down

That one may smile, and smile, and be a villain.

At least I am sure it may be so in Denmark.

(He writes )

So, uncle, there you are. Now to my word:

It is ‘Adieu, adieu, remember me’.

I have sworn’t.

[II, ii, 547– 603] An actor’s performance having brought humiliatingly home to him his own inability to take real- life action in avenging his father, Hamlet nevertheless sees an opportunity to use the theatre as a means to advance his own personal plot:

O what a rogue and peasant slave am I!

Is it not monstrous that this player here,

But in a fiction, in a dream of passion,

Could force his soul so to his own conceit

That, from her working, all his visage wanned,

Tears in his eyes, distraction in his aspect,

A broken voice, and his whole function suiting

With forms to his conceit? And all for nothing.

For Hecuba!

What’s Hecuba to him, or he to Hecuba,

That he should weep for her? What would he do

Had he the motive and the cue for passion

That I have? He would drown the stage with tears

And cleave the general ear with horrid speech,

Make mad the guilty and appal the free,

Confound the ignorant, and amaze indeed

The very faculties of eyes and ears. Yet I,

A dull and muddy- mettled rascal, peak

Like John- a- dreams, unpregnant of my cause,

And can say nothing, no, not for a king

Upon whose property and most dear life

A damned defeat was made. Am I a coward?

Who calls me villain? Breaks my pate across?

Plucks off my beard and blows it in my face?

Tweaks me by the nose? Gives me the lie i’th’ throat

As deep as to the lungs? Who does me this?

Ha, ’swounds, I should take it. For it cannot be

But I am pigeon- livered and lack gall

To make oppression bitter, or ere this

I should ha’ fatted all the region kites

With this slave’s offal. Bloody bawdy villain!

Remorseless, treacherous, lecherous, kindless villain!

O, vengeance!

Why, what an ass am I! This is most brave,

That I, the son of a dear father murdered,

Prompted to my revenge by heaven and hell,

Must like a whore unpack my heart with words

And fall a- cursing like a very drab,

A stallion! Fie upon’t, foh!

About, my brain! Hum – I have heard

That guilty creatures sitting at a play

Have by the very cunning of the scene

Been struck so to the soul that presently

They have proclaimed their malefactions.

For murder, though it have no tongue, will speak

With most miraculous organ, I’ll have these players

Play something like the murder of my father

Before mine uncle. I’ll observe his looks.

I’ll tent him to the quick. If he do blench,

I know my course. The spirit that I have seen

May be a devil, and the devil hath power

T’ assume a pleasing shape, yea, and perhaps

Out of my weakness and my melancholy,

As he is very potent with such spirits,

Abuses me to damn me. I’ll have grounds

More relative than this. The play’s the thing

Wherein I’ll catch the conscience of the King.

[III, i, 56– 88] Hamlet contemplates suicide:

To be, or not to be – that is the question;

Whether ’tis nobler in the mind to suffer

The slings and arrows of outrageous fortune

Or to take arms against a sea of troubles

And by opposing end them. To die, to sleep –

No more – and by a sleep to say we end

The heartache, and the thousand natural shocks

That flesh is heir to. ’Tis a consummation

Devoutly to be wished. To die – to sleep –

To sleep – perchance to dream. Ay, there’s the rub.

For in that sleep of death what dreams may come

When we have shuffled off this mortal coil

Must give us pause. There’s the respect

That makes calamity of so long life.

For who would bear the whips and scorns of time,

Th’ oppressor’s wrong, the proud man’s contumely,

The pangs of despised love, the law’s delay,

The insolence of office, and the spurns

That patient merit of th’ unworthy takes,

When he himself might his quietus make

With a bare bodkin? Who would these fardels bear,

To grunt and sweat under a weary life,

But that the dread of something after death,

The undiscovered country, from whose bourn

No traveller returns, puzzles the will,

And makes us rather bear those ills we have

Than fly to others that we know not of?

Thus conscience does make cowards of us all;

And thus the native hue of resolution

Is sicklied o’er with the pale cast of thought,

And enterprises of great pith and moment

With this regard their currents turn awry

And lose the name of action.

[III, ii, 395– 406] Trying to get into the right frame of mind for action, Hamlet prepares to confront his mother with the wrongs she has committed against his father’s memory:

’Tis now the very witching time of night,

When churchyards yawn, and hell itself breathes out

Contagion to this world. Now could I drink hot blood

And do such bitter business as the day

Would quake to look on. Soft! now to my mother.

O heart, lose not thy nature; let not ever

The soul of Nero enter this firm bosom.

Let me be cruel, not unnatural.

I will speak daggers to her, but use none.

My tongue and soul in this be hypocrites.

How in my words somever she be shent,

To give them seals never, my soul, consent!

[III, iii, 36– 72] King Claudius, the usurper (and Hamlet’s stepfather), at prayer, acknowledges his heinous crime, but acknowledges too that he cannot find it in himself to repent it:

O, my offence is rank. It smells to heaven.

It hath the primal eldest curse upon’t,

A brother’s murder! Pray can I not,

Though inclination be as sharp as will.

My stronger guilt defeats my strong intent,

And like a man to double business bound

I stand in pause where I shall first begin,

And both neglect. What if this cursèd hand

Were thicker than itself with brother’s blood,

Is there not rain enough in the sweet heavens

To wash it white as snow? Whereto serves mercy

But to confront the visage of offence?

And what’s in prayer but this twofold force,

To be forestallèd ere we come to fall

Or pardoned being down? Then I’ll look up.

My fault is past. But, O, what form of prayer

Can serve my turn? ‘Forgive me my foul murder’?

That cannot be, since I am still possessed

Of those effects for which I did the murder,

My crown, mine own ambition, and my queen.

May one be pardoned and retain th’ offence?

In the corrupted currents of this world

Offence’s gilded hand may shove by justice;

And oft ’tis seen the wicked prize itself

Buys out the law; but ’tis not so above.

There is no shuffling. There the action lies

In his true nature, and we ourselves compelled,

Even to the teeth and forehead of our faults,

To give in evidence. What then? What rests?

Try what repentance can. What can it not?

Yet what can it when one cannot repent?

O, wretched state! O, bosom black as death!

O limèd soul, that, struggling to be free

Art more engaged! Help, angels! Make assay.

Bow, stubborn knees, and heart with strings of steel,

Be soft as sinews of the new- born babe.

All may be well.

[III, iii, 73– 95] Hamlet, finding Claudius at prayer and vulnerable, senses a golden opportunity to kill him, but pauses, fearing he might thus save a soul whom he thinks deserves damnation:

Now might I do it pat, now ’a is a- praying.

And now I’ll do’t. And so ’a goes to heaven.

And so am I revenged. That would be scanned.

A villain kills my father, and for that,

I, his sole son, do this same villain send

To heaven.

Why, this is hire and salary, not revenge.

’A took my father grossly, full of bread,

With all his crimes broad blown, as flush as May;

And how his audit stands, who knows save heaven?

But in our circumstance and course of thought,

’Tis heavy with him! And am I then revenged,

To take him in the purging of his soul,

When he is fit and seasoned for his passage?

No.

Up, sword, and know thou a more horrid hent.

When he is drunk asleep; or in his rage,

Or in th’incestuous pleasure of his bed,

At game, a- swearing, or about some act

That has no relish of salvation in’t –

Then trip him, that his heels may kick at heaven,

And that his soul may be as damned and black

As hell, whereto it goes.

[IV, iv, 32– 66] The news of a war to be fought over ownership of a tiny piece of territory sparks thoughts in Hamlet of his own failure to avenge even the most grievous of wrongs:

How all occasions do inform against me

And spur my dull revenge! What is a man,

If his chief good and market of his time

Be but to sleep and feed? A beast, no more.

Sure He that made us with such large discourse,

Looking before and after, gave us not

That capability and godlike reason

To fust in us unused. Now, whether it be

Bestial oblivion, or some craven scruple

Of thinking too precisely on th’ event –

A thought which, quartered, hath but one part wisdom

And ever three parts coward – I do not know

Why yet I live to say ‘This thing’s to do’,

Sith I have cause, and will, and strength, and means

To do’t. Examples gross as earth exhort me.

Witness this army of such mass and charge,

Led by a delicate and tender prince,

Whose spirit, with divine ambition puffed,

Makes mouths at the invisible event,

Exposing what is mortal and unsure

To all that fortune, death, and danger dare,

Even for an eggshell. Rightly to be great

Is not to stir without great argument,

But greatly to find quarrel in a straw

When honour’s at the stake. How stand I then,

That have a father killed, a mother stained,

Excitements of my reason and my blood,

And let all sleep, while to my shame I see

The imminent death of twenty thousand men

That for a fantasy and trick of fame

Go to their graves like beds, fight for a plot

Whereon the numbers cannot try the cause,

Which is not tomb enough and continent

To hide the slain? O, from this time forth,

My thoughts be bloody, or be nothing worth!

Twelfth Night

[II, ii, 17– 41] When Viola, disguised as a boy, is sent a love token by the beautiful Olivia – who claims to be ‘returning’ it – she is struck by the power of a handsome form over female sensibilities:

I left no ring with her; what means this lady?

Fortune forbid my outside have not charmed her!

She made good view of me; indeed, so much

That – methought – her eyes had lost her tongue,

For she did speak in starts, distractedly.

She loves me, sure, the cunning of her passion

Invites me in this churlish messenger.

None of my lord’s ring! Why, he sent her none.

I am the man! If it be so – as ’tis –

Poor lady, she were better love a dream.

Disguise, I see thou art a wickedness

Wherein the pregnant enemy does much.

How easy is it for the proper false

In women’s waxen hearts to set their forms.

Alas, our frailty is the cause, not we,

For such as we are made of, such we be.

How will this fadge? My master loves her dearly;

And I, poor monster, fond as much on him;

And she, mistaken, seems to dote on me.

What will become of this? As I am man,

My state is desperate for my master’s love.

As I am woman – now alas the day,

What thriftless sighs shall poor Olivia breathe!

O time, thou must untangle this, not I!

It is too hard a knot for me t’ untie.

Troilus and Cressida

[I, i, 91– 106] Though his city, Troy, is at war, Prince Troilus deems no dispute worthy of his Cressida- engrossed attention – his anger is saved for the difficult intermediary who is running his love affair, Lord Pandarus:

Peace, you ungracious clamours! Peace, rude sounds!

Fools on both sides! Helen must needs be fair,

When with your blood you daily paint her thus.

I cannot fight upon this argument;

It is too starved a subject for my sword.

But Pandarus – O gods, how do you plague me!

I cannot come to Cressid but by Pandar,

And he’s as tetchy to be wooed to woo

As she is stubborn- chaste against all suit.

Tell me, Apollo, for thy Daphne’s love,

What Cressid is, what Pandar, and what we –

Her bed is India; there she lies, a pearl:

Between our Ilium and where she resides,

Let it be called the wild and wandering flood,

Ourself the merchant, and this sailing Pandar

Our doubtful hope, our convoy, and our bark.

[I, ii, 281– 95] Cressida too finds romance conducted through a go- between hard, but knows enough not to surrender any ground. Love, she senses, is as much a power- struggle as any war:

Words, vows, gifts, tears, and love’s full sacrifice

He offers in another’s enterprise;

But more in Troilus thousandfold I see

Than in the glass of Pandar’s praise may be.

Yet hold I off. Women are angels, wooing;

Things won are done; joy’s soul lies in the doing.

That she beloved knows naught that knows not this:

Men prize the thing ungained more than it is.

That she was never yet that ever knew

Love got so sweet as when desire did sue;

Therefore this maxim out of love I teach:

‘Achievement is command; ungained, beseech.’

Then, though my heart’s content firm love doth bear,

Nothing of that shall from mine eyes appear.

[III, ii, 16– 27] All but overcome already by the anticipation of love, Troilus is sure he will be overwhelmed by love in fact – annihilated as effectively by pleasure, perhaps, as he might be by death in battle:

I am giddy; expectation whirls me round.

Th’ imaginary relish is so sweet

That it enchants my sense. What will it be,

When that the watery palate tastes indeed

Love’s thrice- repurèd nectar? – death, I fear me,

Swooning destruction, or some joy too fine,

Too subtle- potent, tuned too sharp in sweetness,

For the capacity of my ruder powers.

I fear it much; and I do fear besides

That I shall lose distinction in my joys,

As doth a battle, when they charge on heaps

The enemy flying.

Measure for Measure

[II, ii, 162– 87] Angelo, most pious of officials, claims he has resisted every other feminine temptation without difficulty, but is attracted despite himself to the chaste Isabella:

What’s this? What’s this? Is this her fault or mine?

The tempter or the tempted, who sins most?

Ha?

Not she, nor doth she tempt; but it is I

That, lying by the violet in the sun,

Do as the carrion does, not as the flower,

Corrupt with virtuous season. Can it be

That modesty may more betray our sense

Than woman’s lightness? Having waste ground enough,

Shall we desire to raze the sanctuary,

And pitch our evils there? O, fie, fie, fie!

What dost thou? Or what art thou, Angelo?

Dost thou desire her foully for those things

That make her good? O, let her brother live:

Thieves for their robbery have authority

When judges steal themselves. What, do I love her,

That I desire to hear her speak again,

And feast upon her eyes? What is’t I dream on?

O cunning enemy, that, to catch a saint,

With saints dost bait thy hook. Most dangerous

Is that temptation that doth goad us on

To sin in loving virtue. Never could the strumpet,

With all her double vigour, art and nature,

Once stir my temper; but this virtuous maid

Subdues me quite. Ever till now,

When men were fond, I smiled and wondered how.

[II, iv, 1– 17] His unlicensed feelings for Isabella, fears Angelo, make a mockery of his religious faith:

When I would pray and think, I think and pray

To several subjects: heaven hath my empty words,

Whilst my invention, hearing not my tongue,

Anchors on Isabel: God in my mouth,

As if I did but only chew His name,

And in my heart the strong and swelling evil

Of my conception. The state, whereon I studied,

Is like a good thing being often read,

Grown seared and tedious; yea, my gravity,

Wherein, let no man hear me, I take pride,

Could I with boot change for an idle plume

Which the air beats for vain. O place, O form,

How often dost thou with thy case, thy habit,

Wrench awe from fools, and tie the wiser souls

To thy false seeming! Blood, thou art blood;

Let’s write ‘good Angel’ on the devil’s horn;

’Tis not the devil’s crest.

Othello

[III, iii, 255– 74] Taken in as much by his own jealousy as by the lying insinuations of his malevolent ensign, Iago, the moor Othello is tragically ready to see his beloved Desdemona as his betrayer – no true falcon but an unruly ‘haggard’ hawk:

This fellow’s of exceeding honesty,

And knows all qualities, with a learnèd spirit

Of human dealings. If I do prove her haggard,

Though that her jesses were my dear heart- strings,

I’d whistle her off and let her down the wind

To prey at fortune. Haply, for I am black

And have not those soft parts of conversation

That chamberers have; or for I am declined

Into the vale of years – yet that’s not much –

She’s gone: I am abused, and my relief

Must be to loathe her. O, curse of marriage!

That we can call these delicate creatures ours

And not their appetites! I had rather be a toad

And live upon the vapour of a dungeon,

Than keep a corner in the thing I love

For others’ uses. Yet, ’tis the plague of great ones;

Prerogatived are they less than the base.

’Tis destiny unshunnable, like death:

Even then this forked plague is fated to us

When we do quicken:

[V, ii, 1– 22] Convinced of his wife’s infidelity by no more compelling cause than his own frantic jealousy, Othello resolves to murder Desdemona:

It is the cause, it is the cause, my soul:

Let me not name it to you, you chaste stars!

It is the cause. Yet I’ll not shed her blood,

Nor scar that whiter skin of hers than snow,

And smooth as monumental alabaster:

Yet she must die, else she’ll betray more men.

Put out the light, and then put out the light:

If I quench thee, thou flaming minister,

I can again thy former light restore,

Should I repent me; but once put out thy light,

Thou cunning’st pattern of excelling nature,

I know not where is that Promethean heat

That can thy light relume. When I have plucked thy rose,

I cannot give it vital growth again,

It must needs wither. I’ll smell it on the tree.

He kisses her

O, balmy breath, that dost almost persuade

Justice to break her sword! One more, one more.

Be thus when thou art dead and I will kill thee,

And love thee after. One more, and this the last.

So sweet was ne’er so fatal. I must weep.

But they are cruel tears; this sorrow’s heavenly –

It strikes where it doth love. She wakes.

All’s Well That Ends Well

[I, i, 78– 97] Helena should, she knows, reserve her sorrow forthe recent death of her beloved father – but she finds her overpowering love for Bertram displacing such filial feelings:

O, were that all! I think not on my father,

And these great tears grace his remembrance more

Than those I shed for him. What was he like?

I have forgot him; my imagination

Carries no favour in’t but Bertram’s.

I am undone: there is no living, none,

If Bertram be away. ’Twere all one

That I should love a bright particular star

And think to wed it, he is so above me.

In his bright radiance and collateral light

Must I be comforted, not in his sphere.

Th’ ambition in my love thus plagues itself:

The hind that would be mated by the lion

Must die for love. ’Twas pretty, though a plague,

To see him every hour; to sit and draw

His archèd brows, his hawking eye, his curls,

In our heart’s table – heart too capable

Of every line and trick of his sweet favour.

But now he’s gone, and my idolatrous fancy

Must sanctify his relics.

Timon of Athens

[IV, i, 1– 41] Having squandered a fortune in hospitality and gifts, Timon finds himself forgotten by his so- called ‘friends’ when, exhausted by generosity, his money runs out. Bitterly disenchanted with the world of men, he takes refuge in the wild woods outside the city, but allows himself a single backward glance at his hometown as he leaves:

Let me look back upon thee. O thou wall

That girdles in those wolves, dive in the earth

And fence not Athens. Matrons, turn incontinent.

Obedience, fail in children. Slaves and fools

Pluck the grave wrinkled Senate from the bench,

And minister in their steads. To general filths

Convert, o’th’instant, green virginity.

Do’t in your parents’ eyes. Bankrupts, hold fast;

Rather than render back, out with your knives

And cut your trusters’ throats. Bound servants, steal.

Large- handed robbers your grave masters are,

And pill by law. Maid, to thy master’s bed;

Thy mistress is o’th’brothel. Son of sixteen,

Pluck the lined crutch from thy old limping sire,

With it beat out his brains. Piety and fear,

Religion to the gods, peace, justice, truth,

Domestic awe, night- rest, and neighbourhood,

Instruction, manners, mysteries, and trades,

Degrees, observances, customs, and laws,

Decline to your confounding contraries

And let confusion live. Plagues incident to men,

Your potent and infectious fevers heap

On Athens, ripe for stroke. Thou cold sciatica,

Cripple our senators, that their limbs may halt

As lamely as their manners. Lust and liberty

Creep in the minds and marrows of our youth,

That ’gainst the stream of virtue they may strive,

And drown themselves in riot. Itches, blains,

Sow all th’ Athenian bosoms, and their crop

Be general leprosy. Breath infect breath,

That their society, as their friendship, may

Be merely poison. Nothing I’ll bear from thee

But nakedness, thou detestable town.

Take thou that too, with multiplying bans.

Timon will to the woods, where he shall find

Th’ unkindest beast more kinder than mankind.

The gods confound – hear me, you good gods all –

The Athenians both within and out that wall.

And grant, as Timon grows, his hate may grow

To the whole race of mankind, high and low!

Amen.

[IV, iii, 1– 45] Wealth, not worth, decides status in the world of men, inveighs an angry Timon as he digs in the woods for edible roots. When he finds gold instead he is filled with satirical scorn towards this basest of metals, the ‘common whore’ of all mankind:

O blessed breeding sun, draw from the earth

Rotten humidity. Below thy sister’s orb

Infect the air! Twinn’d brothers of one womb,

Whose procreation, residence, and birth,

Scarce is dividant – touch them with several fortunes,

The greater scorns the lesser. Not nature,

To whom all sores lay siege, can bear great fortune

But by contempt of nature.

Raise me this beggar and deject that lord –

The senator shall bear contempt hereditary,

The beggar native honour.

It is the pasture lards the wether’s sides,

The want that makes him lean. Who dares, who dares,

In purity of manhood stand upright,

And say ‘This man’s a flatterer’? If one be,

So are they all, for every grise of fortune

Is smoothed by that below. The learnèd pate

Ducks to the golden fool. All’s obliquy,

There’s nothing level in our cursèd natures

But direct villainy. Therefore be abhorred

All feasts, societies, and throngs of men.

His semblable, yea, himself, Timon disdains.

Destruction fang mankind. Earth, yield me roots.

He digs

44 Who seeks for better of thee, sauce his palate

With thy most operant poison. What is here?

Gold? Yellow, glittering, precious gold?

No, gods, I am no idle votarist.

Roots, you clear heavens! Thus much of this will make

Black white, foul fair, wrong right,

Base noble, old young, coward valiant.

Ha, you gods! Why this? What, this, you gods? Why, this

Will lug your priests and servants from your sides,

Pluck stout men’s pillows from below their heads.

This yellow slave

Will knit and break religions, bless th’ accursed,

Make the hoar leprosy adored, place thieves

And give them title, knee, and approbation,

With senators on the bench. This is it

That makes the wappened widow wed again –

She whom the spital- house and ulcerous sores

Would cast the gorge at, this embalms and spices

To th’ April day again. Come, damned earth,

Thou common whore of mankind, that puts odds

Among the rout of nations, I will make thee

Do thy right nature.

King Lear

[I, ii, 1– 22] What makes a bastard less worthy than his legitimate brother? Conceived on the wrong side of the blanket, Edmund, Gloucester’s bastard son, resolves that he will be no respecter of right in his own conduct:

Thou, Nature, art my goddess; to thy law

My services are bound. Wherefore should I

Stand in the plague of custom and permit

The curiosity of nations to deprive me,

For that I am some twelve or fourteen moonshines

Lag of a brother? Why bastard? Wherefore base?

When my dimensions are as well- compact,

My mind as generous, and my shape as true

As honest madam’s issue? Why brand they us

With ‘base’? with ‘baseness’? ‘bastardy’? ‘base, base’?

Who in the lusty stealth of nature take

More composition and fierce quality

Than doth, within a dull, stale, tired bed

Go to the creating a whole tribe of fops

Got ’tween asleep and wake? Well then,

Legitimate Edgar, I must have your land.

Our father’s love is to the bastard Edmund

As to the legitimate. Fine word ‘legitimate’!

Well, my ‘legitimate’, if this letter speed

And my invention thrive, Edmund the base

Shall top the legitimate. I grow. I prosper.

Now, gods, stand up for bastards!

[II, iii, 1– 21] His beloved father turned against him by his bastard brother’s machinations, Edgar must flee for his life in disguise. So crazy do things seem to be that he can think of no better shape to adopt for his flight than that of a wandering, ranting Bedlam beggar:

I heard myself proclaimed,

And by the happy hollow of a tree

Escaped the hunt. No port is free, no place

That guard and most unusual vigilance

Does not attend my taking. Whiles I may ’scape

I will preserve myself; and am bethought

To take the basest and most poorest shape

That ever penury, in contempt of man,

Brought near to beast. My face I’ll grime with filth,

Blanket my loins, elf all my hair in knots,

And with presented nakedness outface

The winds and persecutions of the sky,

The country gives me proof and precedent

Of Bedlam beggars, who, with roaring voices,

Strike in their numbed and mortified bare arms

Pins, wooden pricks, nails, sprigs of rosemary;

And with this horrible object, from low farms,

Poor pelting villages, sheepcotes, and mills

Sometime with lunatic bans, sometime with prayers,

Enforce their charity: ‘Poor Turlygod! Poor Tom!’

That’s something yet; Edgar I nothing am.

[IV, i, 1– 9 ] Still in his mad disguise, Edgar finds he can takeconsiderable comfort from the knowledge that he is firmly atthe bottom of the social heap:

Yet better thus, and known to be contemned

Than still contemned and flattered. To be worst,

The lowest and most dejected thing of fortune,

Stands still in esperance, lives not in fear.

The lamentable change is from the best;

The worst returns to laughter. Welcome then,

Thou unsubstantial air that I embrace!

The wretch that thou hast blown unto the worst

Owes nothing to thy blasts.

[III, iv, 28– 36] Brought low himself by circumstance, Learreflects on the plight of his country’s poor:

Poor naked wretches, wheresoe’er you are,

That bide the pelting of this pitiless storm,

How shall your houseless heads and unfed sides,

Your looped and windowed raggedness, defend you

From seasons such as these? O, I have ta’en

Too little care of this! Take physic, pomp;

Expose thyself to feel what wretches feel,

That thou mayst shake the superflux to them

And show the heavens more just.

Macbeth

[I, v, 36– 52] A single murder stands between her husband and the Scottish throne, realizes Lady Macbeth – and King Duncan is to be the guest of honour in her own home this very night:

The raven himself is hoarse

That croaks the fatal entrance of Duncan

Under my battlements. Come, you spirits

That tend on mortal thoughts, unsex me here

And fill me from the crown to the toe top- full

Of direst cruelty. Make thick my blood;

Stop up the access and passage to remorse,

That no compunctious visitings of nature

Shake my fell purpose nor keep peace between

The effect and it. Come to my woman’s breasts

And take my milk for gall, you murdering ministers,

Wherever, in your sightless substances,

You wait on nature’s mischief. Come, thick night,

And pall thee in the dunnest smoke of hell,

That my keen knife see not the wound it makes,

Nor heaven peep through the blanket of the dark

To cry, ‘Hold, hold!’

[I, vii, 1– 28] His wife having put the idea of murdering Duncan in his head, Macbeth is appalled at the enormity of the contemplated crime:

If it were done when ’tis done, then ’twere well

It were done quickly. If the assassination

Could trammel up the consequence, and catch,

With his surcease, success – that but this blow

Might be the be- all and the end- all! – here,

But here, upon this bank and shoal of time,

We’d jump the life to come. But in these cases

We still have judgement here – that we but teach

Bloody instructions, which being taught return

To plague the inventor. This even- handed justice

Commends the ingredients of our poisoned chalice

To our own lips. He’s here in double trust:

First, as I am his kinsman and his subject,

Strong both against the deed; then, as his host,

Who should against his murderer shut the door,

Not bear the knife myself. Besides, this Duncan

Hath borne his faculties so meek, hath been

So clear in his great office, that his virtues

Will plead like angels, trumpet- tongued against

The deep damnation of his taking- off;

And pity, like a naked new- born babe

Striding the blast, or heaven’s cherubin, horsed

Upon the sightless curriers of the air,

Shall blow the horrid deed in every eye,

That tears shall drown the wind. I have no spur

To prick the sides of my intent, but only

Vaulting ambition, which o’erleaps itself

And falls on the other.

[II, i, 33– 64] As he steels his nerves to kill the sleeping Duncan, an all but delirious Macbeth can hardly tell where his fantasies of power leave off and murderous fact takes up the story:

Is this a dagger which I see before me,

The handle toward my hand? Come, let me clutch thee –

I have thee not, and yet I see thee still!

Art thou not, fatal vision, sensible

To feeling as to sight? Or art thou but

A dagger of the mind, a false creation,

Proceeding from the heat- oppressèd brain?

I see thee yet, in form as palpable

As this which now I draw.

Thou marshall’st me the way that I was going,

And such an instrument I was to use. –

Mine eyes are made the fools o’ the other senses,

Or else worth all the rest. – I see thee still,

And on thy blade and dudgeon, gouts of blood,

Which was not so before. There’s no such thing:

It is the bloody business which informs

Thus to mine eyes. Now o’er the one half- world

Nature seems dead, and wicked dreams abuse

The curtained sleep. Witchcraft celebrates

Pale Hecat’s offerings; and withered Murder,

Alarumed by his sentinel the wolf,

Whose howl’s his watch, thus with his stealthy pace,

With Tarquin’s ravishing strides, towards his design

Moves like a ghost. Thou sure and firm- set earth,

Hear not my steps, which way they walk, for fear

Thy very stones prate of my whereabout

And take the present horror from the time

Which now suits with it. – Whiles I threat, he lives:

Words to the heat of deeds too cold breath gives.

(A bell rings.)

I go, and it is done; the bell invites me.

Hear it not, Duncan, for it is a knell

That summons thee to heaven, or to hell.

[V, v, 17– 28] On hearing the news of his lady’s death, Macbeth retreats into a world of his own to reflect upon the meaningless futility of all he has fought and killed for:

She should have died hereafter;

There would have been a time for such a word –

Tomorrow, and tomorrow, and tomorrow,

Creeps in this petty pace from day to day

To the last syllable of recorded time;

And all our yesterdays have lighted fools

The way to dusty death. Out, out, brief candle!

Life’s but a walking shadow, a poor player

That struts and frets his hour upon the stage

And then is heard no more. It is a tale

Told by an idiot, full of sound and fury,

Signifying nothing.

Antony and Cleopatra

[IV, xiv, 44– 54] Having parted at odds with his Egyptian lover, Antony is broken by the news of her death ( though it will turn out to be untrue). He will himself commit suicide, he resolves, and they will be reconciled in the next life, like the Carthaginian Queen Dido and the Trojan hero Aeneas:

I will o’ertake thee, Cleopatra, and

Weep for my pardon. So it must be, for now

All length is torture; since the torch is out,

Lie down, and stray no farther. Now all labour

Mars what it does; yea, very force entangles

Itself with strength. Seal then, and all is done.

Eros! – I come, my queen – Eros! Stay for me.

Where souls do couch on flowers, we’ll hand in hand,

And with our sprightly port make the ghosts gaze:

Dido and her Aeneas shall want troops,

And all the haunt be ours.

Pericles, Prince of Tyre

[I, i, 122– 43] Pericles is horror- struck – and terrified – when he realizes that his intended bride has been the incestuous lover of her father, the great king Antiochus:

How courtesy would seem to cover sin,

When what is done is like an hypocrite,

The which is good in nothing but in sight.

If it be true that I interpret false,

Then were it certain you were not so bad

As with foul incest to abuse your soul;

Where now you’re both a father and a son

By your untimely claspings with your child,

Which pleasures fits a husband, not a father,

And she, an eater of her mother’s flesh

By the defiling of her parents’ bed;

And both like serpents are, who though they feed

On sweetest flowers, yet they poison breed.

Antioch, farewell, for wisdom sees those men

Blush not in actions blacker than the night

Will shun no course to keep them from the light.

One sin, I know, another doth provoke.

Murder’s as near to lust as flame to smoke.

Poison and treason are the hands of sin,

Ay, and the targets to put off the shame.

Then, lest my life be cropped to keep you clear,

By flight I’ll shun the danger which I fear.

[II, i, 1– 11] Pericles harangues the storm that has wrecked his ship: it has shown its mastery, now he wishes it would leave him to die in peace:

Yet cease your ire, you angry stars of heaven!

Wind, rain, and thunder, remember earthly man

Is but a substance that must yield to you,

And I, as fits my nature, do obey you.

Alas, the seas hath cast me on the rocks,

Washed me from shore to shore, and left my breath

Nothing to think on but ensuing death.

Let it suffice the greatness of your powers

To have bereft a prince of all his fortunes,

And, having thrown him from your watery grave

Here to have death in peace is all he’ll crave.

Coriolanus

[IV, iv, 12– 26] Exiled from Rome himself as an enemy of the people, Coriolanus now finds himself in Antium, an ‘enemy’ state. ‘City, ’tis I who made thy widows,’ he wryly recalls, as he sets off in search of his old adversary, Aufidius:

O world, thy slippery turns! Friends now fast sworn,

Whose double bosoms seems to wear one heart,

Whose hours, whose bed, whose meal and exercise

Are still together, who twin, as ’twere, in love

Unseparable, shall within this hour,

On a dissension of a doit, break out

To bitterest enmity. So fellest foes,

Whose passions and whose plots have broke their sleep

To take the one the other, by some chance,

Some trick not worth an egg, shall grow dear friends

And interjoin their issues. So with me.

My birthplace hate I, and my love’s upon

This enemy town. I’ll enter. If he slay me,

He does fair justice: if he give me way,

I’ll do his country service.

The Winter’s Tale

[III, iii, 58– 76] King Leontes of Bohemia, having taken his head that his queen, Hermione, has been unfaithful, orders that their infant child – her bastard, he believes – be taken out and abandoned in the wilderness. Fortunately for the baby, an aged shepherd comes bumbling along, pondering as he goes the follies of youth:

I would there were no age between ten and three- andtwenty, or that youth would sleep out the rest: for there is nothing in the between but getting wenches with child, wronging the ancientry, stealing, fighting. Hark you now: would any but these boiled brains of nineteen and two- and- twenty hunt this weather? They have scared away two of my best sheep, which I fear the wolf will sooner find than the master. If anywhere I have them, ’tis by the sea- side, browsing of ivy. Good luck, an’t be thy will!

He sees the child

What have we here? Mercy on’s, a barne! A very pretty barne. A boy or a child, I wonder? A pretty one, a very pretty one. Sure, some scape. Though I am not bookish, yet I can read waiting gentlewoman in the scape: this has been some stair- work, some trunk- work, some behind- door- work. They were warmer that got this than the poor thing is here. I’ll take it up for pity – yet I’ll tarry till my son come: he hallowed but even now. Whoa- ho- hoa!

Cymbeline

[II, ii, 12– 51] Giacomo having bragged that he can seduce any woman he wants, Posthumus has made a bet on the chastity of his virtuous wife, Imogen. With not only his rakish pride but his fortune at stake, however, a desperate Giacomo has had himself carried into her chamber in a trunk so that he will be able to give Posthumus details suggestive of the closest intimacy. Emerging at dead of night, he begins to check off the features of her room and person: he may leave her body alone, but he will rape her reputation:

The crickets sing, and man’s o’ er- laboured sense

Repairs itself by rest. Our Tarquin thus

Did softly press the rushes ere he waken’d

The chastity he wounded. Cytherea,

How bravely thou becom’st thy bed! Fresh lily,

And whiter than the sheets! That I might touch!

But kiss; one kiss! Rubies unparagoned,

How dearly they do’t! ’Tis her breathing that

Perfumes the chamber thus. The flame o’ th ’taper

Bows toward her and would under- peep her lids

To see th’ enclosed lights, now canopied

Under these windows white and azure, lac’d

With blue of heaven’s own tinct. But my design

To note the chamber. I will write all down:

Such and such pictures; there the window; such

Th’ adornment of her bed; the arras, figures –

Why, such and such; and the contents o’ th’ story.

Ah, but some natural notes about her body

Above ten thousand meaner movables

Would testify, t’ enrich mine inventory.

O sleep, thou ape of death, lie dull upon her!

And be her sense but as a monument,

Thus in a chapel lying! Come off, come off;

(Taking off her bracelet )

As slippery as the Gordian knot was hard!

’Tis mine; and this will witness outwardly,

As strongly as the conscience does within,

To th’ madding of her lord. On her left breast

A mole cinque- spotted, like the crimson drops

I’ th’ bottom of a cowslip. Here’s a voucher

Stronger than ever law could make; this secret

Will force him think I have picked the lock and ta’en

The treasure of her honour. No more. To what end?

Why should I write this down that’s riveted,

Screw’d to my memory? She hath been reading late

The tale of Tereus; here the leaf’s turned down

Where Philomel gave up. I have enough.

To th’ trunk again, and shut the spring of it.

Swift, swift, you dragons of the night, that dawning

May bare the raven’s eye! I lodge in fear;

Though this a heavenly angel, hell is here.

(Clock strikes )

One, two, three. Time, time!

[II, v, 1– 35] His life in tatters, his faith destroyed, after hearing Giacomo’s tale of conquest, Posthumus is left in profoundly misogynistic mood:

Is there no way for men to be, but women

Must be half- workers? We are all bastards,

And that most venerable man which I

Did call my father was I know not where

When I was stamped. Some coiner with his tools

Made me a counterfeit; yet my mother seem’d

The Dian of that time. So doth my wife

The nonpareil of this. O, vengeance, vengeance!

Me of my lawful pleasure she restrained,

And prayed me oft forbearance; did it with

A pudency so rosy, the sweet view on’t

Might well have warmed old Saturn; that I thought her

As chaste as unsunned snow. O, all the devils!

This yellow Iachimo in an hour – was’t not?

Or less! – at first? Perchance he spoke not, but,

Like a full- acorned boar, a German one,

Cried ‘O!’ and mounted; found no opposition

But what he look’d for should oppose and she

Should from encounter guard. Could I find out

The woman’s part in me! For there’s no motion

That tends to vice in man but I affirm

It is the woman’s part. Be it lying, note it,

The woman’s; flattering, hers; deceiving, hers;

Lust and rank thoughts, hers, hers; revenges, hers;

Ambitions, covetings, change of prides, disdain,

Nice longing, slanders, mutability,

All faults that man may name, nay, that hell knows,

Why, hers, in part or all; but rather all;

For even to vice

They are not constant, but are changing still

One vice but of a minute old for one

Not half so old as that. I’ll write against them,

Detest them, curse them. Yet ’tis greater skill

In a true hate to pray they have their will:

The very devils cannot plague them better.

[III, vi, 1– 27] Imogen has set off in joy to meet her husband, only to discover that he has been plotting her death – driven to a frenzy of jealousy by news of her alleged adultery. Now, in man’s attire, she perseveres in her journey towards Milford Haven, hoping to find him there and convince him of her fidelity:

I see a man’s life is a tedious one.

I have tir’d myself, and for two nights together

Have made the ground my bed. I should be sick

But that my resolution helps me. Milford,

When from the mountain- top Pisanio showed thee,

Thou wast within a ken. O Jove! I think

Foundations fly the wretched; such, I mean,

Where they should be relieved. Two beggars told me

I could not miss my way. Will poor folks lie,

That have afflictions on them, knowing ’tis

A punishment or trial? Yes; no wonder,

When rich ones scarce tell true. To lapse in fullness

Is sorer than to lie for need; and falsehood

Is worse in kings than beggars. My dear lord!

Thou art one o’ th’ false ones. Now I think on thee

My hunger’s gone; but even before, I was

At point to sink for food. But what is this?

Here is a path to ’t; ’tis some savage hold.

I were best not call; I dare not call. Yet famine,

Ere clean it o’erthrow nature, makes it valiant.

Plenty and peace breeds cowards; hardness ever

Of hardiness is mother. Ho! Who’s here?

If anything that’s civil, speak; if savage,

Take or lend. Ho! No answer? Then I’ll enter.

Best draw my sword; and if mine enemy

But fear the sword, like me, he’ll scarcely look on’t.

Such a foe, good heavens!

[IV, ii, 293– 334] Still making her sad way westward, almost mad with grief, Imogen awakens from uneasy sleep to find herself lying by what appears to be the headless body of her husband:

Yes, sir, to Milford Haven. Which is the way?

I thank you. By yond bush? Pray, how far thither?

’Ods pittikins! Can it be six mile yet?

I have gone all night. Faith, I’ll lie down and sleep.

But, soft! no bedfellow. O gods and goddesses!

(Seeing the body )

These flow’rs are like the pleasures of the world;

This bloody man, the care on’t. I hope I dream;

For so I thought I was a cave- keeper,

And cook to honest creatures. But ’tis not so;

’Twas but a bolt of nothing, shot at nothing,

Which the brain makes of fumes. Our very eyes

Are sometimes, like our judgements, blind. Good faith,

I tremble still with fear; but if there be

Yet left in heaven as small a drop of pity

As a wren’s eye, feared gods, a part of it!

The dream’s here still. Even when I wake it is

Without me, as within me; not imagined, felt.

A headless man? The garments of Posthumus?

I know the shape of his leg; this is his hand,

His foot mercurial, his martial thigh,

The brawns of Hercules; but his jovial face –

Murder in heaven! How!

[V, v, 97– 123] Posthumus, in prison, feels he could be in no better place as he mulls over the manifold wrongs he has done his beloved Imogen:

Most welcome, bondage! For thou art a way,

I think, to liberty. Yet am I better

Than one that’s sick o’ th’ gout, since he had rather

Groan so in perpetuity than be cured

By th’ sure physician death, who is the key

T’ unbar these locks. My conscience, thou art fettered

More than my shanks and wrists; you good gods, give me

The penitent instrument to pick that bolt,

Then, free for ever! Is’t enough I am sorry?

So children temporal fathers do appease;

Gods are more full of mercy. Must I repent,

I cannot do it better than in gyves,

Desired more than constrained. To satisfy,

If of my freedom ’tis the main part, take

No stricter render of me than my all.

I know you are more clement than vile men,

Who of their broken debtors take a third,

A sixth, a tenth, letting them thrive again

On their abatement; that’s not my desire.

For Imogen’s dear life take mine; and though

’Tis not so dear, yet ’tis a life; you coined it.

’Tween man and man they weigh not every stamp;

Though light, take pieces for the figure’s sake;

You rather mine, being yours. And so, great pow’rs,

If you will take this audit, take this life,

And cancel these cold bonds. O Imogen!

I’ll speak to thee in silence.

(Sleeps )

The Tempest

[II, ii, 1– 17] The savage Caliban curses Prospero, who has, he feels, usurped his rightful rule in this island realm, contriving cruel torments of every kind to maintain his obedience:

All the infections that the sun sucks up

From bogs, fens, flats, on Prosper fall, and make him

By inch- meal a disease! His spirits hear me,

And yet I needs must curse. But they’ll nor pinch,

Fright me with urchin- shows, pitch me i’ th’ mire,

Nor lead me, like a firebrand, in the dark

Out of my way, unless he bid ’em; but

For every trifle are they set upon me;

Sometime like apes that mow and chatter at me,

And after bite me; then like hedgehogs which

Lie tumbling in my barefoot way, and mount

Their pricks at my footfall. Sometime am I

All wound with adders, who with cloven tongues

Do hiss me into madness.

Enter Trinculo

Lo, now, lo!

Here comes a spirit of his, and to torment me

For bringing wood in slowly. I’ll fall flat.

Perchance he will not mind me.

[18– 40] No airy spirit but a sailor, cast ashore in the recentstorm, Trinculo finds it hard to know what to make ofCaliban’s recumbent form:

Here’s neither bush nor shrub to bear off any weather at all, and another storm brewing. I hear it sing i’ th’ wind. Yond same black cloud, yond huge one, looks like a foul bombard that would shed his liquor. If it should thunder as it did before, I know not where to hide my head. Yond same cloud cannot choose but fall by pailfuls. What have we here? A man or a fish? Dead or alive? A fish! He smells like a fish; a very ancient and fish- like smell; kind of not- of- the- newest poor- John. A strange fish! Were I in England now, as once I was, and had but this fish painted, not a holiday fool there but would give a piece of silver. There would this monster make a man. Any strange beast there makes a man. When they will not give a doit to relieve a lame beggar, they will lay out ten to see a dead Indian. Legged like a man! And his fins like arms! Warm, o’ my troth! I do now let loose my opinion, hold it no longer: this is no fish, but an islander, that hath lately suffered by thunderbolt.

(Thunder )

Alas, the storm is come again! My best way is to creep under his gaberdine. There is no other shelter hereabout. Misery acquaints a man with strange bed- fellows. I will here shroud till the dregs of the storm be past.

[V, i, 33– 57] Prospero, the island’s ruler, his work done, the wrongs once done to him put right, weaves the final spell by which he intends to forsake the world of magic:

Ye elves of hills, brooks, standing lakes, and groves,

And ye that on the sands with printless foot

Do chase the ebbing Neptune, and do fly him

When he comes back; you demi- puppets that

By moonshine do the green sour ringlets make,

Whereof the ewe not bites; and you whose pastime

Is to make midnight mushrumps, that rejoice

To hear the solemn curfew; by whose aid –

Weak masters though ye be – I have bedimmed

The noontide sun, called forth the mutinous winds,

And ’twixt the green sea and the azured vault

Set roaring war; to the dread rattling thunder

Have I given fire, and rifted Jove’s stout oak

With his own bolt; the strong- based promontory

Have I made shake, and by the spurs plucked up

The pine and cedar; graves at my command

Have waked their sleepers, oped, and let ’em forth

By my so potent art. But this rough magic

I here abjure; and, when I have required

Some heavenly music – which even now I do –

To work mine end upon their senses that

This airy charm is for, I’ll break my staff,

Bury it certain fathoms in the earth,

And deeper than did ever plummet sound

I’ll drown my book.

苏格拉底的申辩

一、真理与修辞

[17a][1]雅典的人们，我不知道，你们到底是不是被我的控告者们说服了。至于我，我自己也快被他们说得不知道自己是谁了，他们可真是雄辩！可他们简直一句真话也没说。他们信口雌黄，其中有句话[a5]特别让我惊讶，即，你们必须小心被我欺骗，[17b]因为我伶牙俐齿。他们真不害羞，不怕会被我用事实马上驳倒（ἐξελεγχθήσονται）：我无论如何不像伶牙俐齿的——在我看来这是他们做的最可耻的事——除非是，他们把说真话叫作[b5]伶牙俐齿。而如果他们这么说，我会承认我是个演说者，但不是他们那种。可我得说，这些人说的话里，很少有真话，或根本没有真话，但你们听我说的都是真话。宙斯在上，雅典的人们，你们听到我说的并不像他们精心编造的词句那样，不是刻意修饰的[17c]辞令和名目，都是我临场口占的字句——我相信我说的是实事求是（δίκαια）的——你们中谁也不要期待别的说话方式。当然，诸位，在我这[c5]个年纪，是不该像孩子一样到你们这里来胡扯了。雅典的人们，我热切地求你们、恳请你们，如果你们听到我申辩的这些话，觉得和我在市场上的钱庄柜台边或别的地方常说的一样（你们中很多人在那里听到过），你们不要[17d]因此而惊讶或喧哗（θορυβεῖν）。因为事实是，现在我第一次到法庭上来，已经是七十高龄的老人。我完全不懂这里的说话方式。比如，要是我在这儿真的是一个外邦人，你们一定[d5]同意我用从小习惯了的[18a]口音和方式说话。那么，同样，我现在向你们提出这个正当请求——至少在我看来，它是正当的——你们不要管我的说话方式（这方式也许更糟，也许更好），只需了解我用这个方式表达出的想法，看我说的是[a5]不是对的。这是法官们的美德，而演说者的美德就是说真话。

二、案情的真相

那么，雅典的人们，我认为正确的申辩方式是，首先针对那些最初的虚假控告和那些最初的控告者做申辩；其次，针对后面的控告和后面的[18b]控告者申辩。而很久之前（有些年头了），在你们面前就出现了很多控告我的人，说的根本不是真话。比起阿努图斯周围的人，我更怕他们，虽然阿努图斯他们也可怕。诸位，那些人更可怕，你们中[b5]很多人从孩童时代就被他们说服了，听他们控告我。其中同样没有真话，他们说，有个苏格拉底，是个智慧的人，是关心天上的事的学究，还考察地下万物，把弱的说法变强。[18c]雅典的人们，他们散布这谣言，真是我可怕的控告者。听到这些话的人就认为，考察这些东西，就是不信神的。再者，这些控告者数量多，而且在很久以前[c5]就在告我了，他们在你们最易轻信的年龄里（你们是儿童或少年时）对你们讲的那些控告，都被想当然地接受了，根本无人申辩。在这一切当中，最没道理的是，我根本不[18d]知道，也无法说出他们的名字——除了其中一个正好是喜剧诗人。很多人出于嫉妒而诬蔑中伤我，说服了你们——或是先说服自己，再说服别人。所有这些人都是极难相处的。也不可能[d5]让他们中哪一个来此当面对质，那我就简直要像空拳练习[2]一般申辩，在无人回答时质疑他们。但你们要把我所说的当真，我有两拨[18e]控告者。其中一拨刚刚控告我，另外一拨就是我所说的很久之前控告我的那些。你们知道，我应该首先针对后者申辩，因为你们最先听到了后者的控告，听得比前者的多得多。

好了。雅典的人们，我是要申辩的，要试着[19a]在这么短的时间里，打消你们中间那么长时间以来持有的恶意。如果能对你们和我都好，我能圆满完成申辩，我当然愿意。但我认为这[a5]是很难的，这点根本不会逃过我的眼睛。一方面，神愿意怎样，就怎样发生吧；另一方面，我们要遵守法律来做申辩。

三、哲学生活的根据：针对第一拨控告者的辩护

A.智者之知

那么，是什么引起了对我的诬蔑？还是让我们从头讲起。莫勒图斯[19b]在写下现在这份诉状时，他信的就是这些诬蔑。好了。那些诬蔑者，究竟进行了怎样的诬蔑？他们若来控告，那他们起誓后的状辞一定是：“苏格拉底行了不义，忙忙碌碌，[b5]寻求地上和天上之事，把弱的说法变强，[19c]并把这些教给别人。”大体如此。而你们自己在阿里斯托芬的喜剧里看到了这些：有个苏格拉底被搬到那里，吹嘘说他在空气里走路，还胡说好些别的胡话。但对于这类事，我闻所未闻，无论[c5]大小。但我不是说，如果谁是擅长这些的智者，我就看不起这些学问——但愿莫勒图斯不会告我有这么重大的罪，让我辩护！但是，雅典的人们，这些事情和我都没有关系。[19d]并且，我可以让你们中的很多人做证，我觉得你们应该相互告知和展示，你们那些听到过我怎么说的人——你们中有很多人听我说过的——相互展示，无论听多听少，[d5]你们中是否有谁听我对此说过什么，因此你们就知道，很多人给我编造的其他罪名，也是这样莫须有的。

可这些都不是真的。如果你们听到，我试图教育人，然后从中牟利，[19e]那也根本不是真的。而在我看来，谁要是能教育人们，这还是很高贵的，就像雷昂提尼人（Λεοντῖνος）高尔吉亚（Γοργίας）、西欧斯人（Κεῖος）普罗迪科斯（Πρόδικος）、埃利斯人（Ἠλεῖος）希琵阿斯（Ἡιππίας）那样。诸位，他们当中的每一个，都走[e5]到每个城邦中的年轻人中去——本来，这些年轻人只要愿意，他们可以免费和城邦里的任何人交往，并且能说服他们，不和自己城邦中的那些人在一起。[20a]而和他们在一起，得给他们财物，还要为此感激他们。

这里还有另外一个智者，是巴洛斯人（Πάριος），听说他还在这里。我正好遇到了这么一个人，他在智者们身上花的钱[a5]比别的人都多，就是希波尼科（Ἱππόνικος）的儿子卡利亚（Καλλίας）[3]，卡利亚有两个儿子。我问他：

“卡利亚，如果你的两个儿子是马驹或牛犊，我们会给它们找个教习，雇用他，只要他愿意让它们按照自己[20b]的美德（ἀρετή）变得美好和善好，这个人就是一个马术师或者农夫；而今，你的儿子们是人，那么，你心里想给他们找什么人来做教习呢？是一个精通这样的美德，即关于做人和做公民[b5]的美德的教习吗？而我想，你既然有两个儿子，应该已经考量过这点了。是这样，”我说，“还是不是？”

“当然。”他说。

“他是谁？”我说，“从哪里来，要多少学费？”

“是欧埃诺斯（Εὔηνος），苏格拉底，他是巴洛斯人，五个米纳。”

如果欧埃诺斯真有这技艺，并且会循循善诱，那我祝福他。[20c]如果我懂这些，我就会美滋滋的，自我膨胀。但是我并不懂，雅典的人们。

B.无知之知

那么，也许你们当中有人会插话说：

“那么，苏格拉底，[c5]你到底是怎么回事呢？对你的诬蔑都从何而起呢？也许你没有做多少出格的事，但如果你所做的真的和大多数人没有不同，就不会出现这些流言和说法。那么告诉我们你出了什么事吧，[20d]以免我们武断地对待你。”

我看说这话的人说得很对，我会试着向你们揭示出来，是什么给我带来了这名声和诬蔑。听清楚了。也许在你们中的一些人看来，[d5]我是在说笑话。但你们要明白，我要告诉你们的都是真的。

雅典的人们，我得到这个名声，不因为别的，正是因为智慧。这到底是什么样的智慧？也许就是凡人的智慧。也许我确实善于这种智慧。而我刚刚提到的人，[20e]要么确实有比人更高的智慧，因而是智慧的，要么我说不出那是什么。因为我不懂这些，而谁说我懂，都是在说谎，制造对我的诬蔑。雅典的人们，不要对我喧哗，哪怕我好像在对[e5]你们说大话。我说的这话并不是我自己说的，我是借用你们认为值得信赖的（ἀξίοχρεων）一个人说的话。我的这些，究竟是不是真的智慧，是什么样的智慧，我要向你们举出的证人，就是德尔斐（Δελφοί）的神。你们该知道凯瑞丰（Χαιρεφῶν）的。他和我从年轻时就是伙伴，[21a]他也是你们大家（πλήθει）的伙伴，一起在新近的逃亡中出逃，又和你们一起回来[4]。你们知道凯瑞丰是怎样一种人[5]，知道他无论做什么事，都是那么莽撞。有一次他到了德尔斐，竟敢提出这[a5]个问题——我说过了，诸位，你们不要喧哗——他问，是否有人比我更智慧。于是皮提亚女祭司[6]拿起签（ἀνεῖλειν）说，没有人更智慧。这个人已经死了，但他的弟弟在你们中间，可以做证。

[21b]你们看我为什么说这些。我想要告诉你们，对我的诬蔑是从何而起的。听到这话，我就自己寻思：“神说的究竟是什么，这到底是什么哑谜？我自己知道，我没有大智慧，也没有小[b5]智慧。那么他说我最智慧，到底是什么意思呢？神可不会说假话，因为这不是神的做法。”在好长时间里，我都不明白他说的到底是什么。随后，我很不情愿地转向下面这样的探讨。我去拜访一个据说很智慧的人，[21c]好像在那里就可以证明（ἐλέγζων）这说法是错的，回应神谕说：

“你说我是最智慧的，但这个人比我更智慧。”于是我仔细审视了他——他的名字我不必说，雅典的人们，那是一个政治家[c5]——我观察了他，并且和他对话之后，得到这么个印象：我看到，虽然很多别的人觉得他很智慧，特别是他自己，但其实不然。随后，我试着告诉他，虽然他认为自己是智慧的，其实他不智慧。[21d]结果，我遭到他和在场很多人的忌恨。我离开那里，寻思，我比这个人更智慧。也许我俩都不知道美好（καλóν）和善好（ἀγαθóν）是什么，但是那个人[d5]认为他知道自己不知道的事，而我既然不知道，也就不认为我知道。我觉得好像在这件事上总比他智慧一点儿，即我不知道的事，我就不认为我知道。我离开那儿，到另外一个看起来更智慧的人那里去，[21e]结果在我看来也是这样，于是我就遭到那人和别的很多人的忌恨。

在这之后，我拜访了一个又一个人，痛苦而恐惧地看到，我被人们忌恨。可是在我看来，[e5]完成神给的任务一定先于所有别的事——为了考察他说的神谕，就要去找所有[22a]好像有知识的人。天狗在上[7]，雅典的人们——而我必须对你们说真话——我经历的就是这类的事。我按照神的说法考察之后，那些声名显赫的人在我看来是最无能的；而[a5]另外那些看上去更一般的人，却好像更明智些（φρονίμως）。我必须告诉你们，我的奔波真是干苦活，我这才觉得那个神谕变得不可驳斥了。在这些政治家之后，我去拜访了一些诗人，包括悲剧诗人、[22b]酒神的赞美诗人，还有别的诗人，自以为我在那里就可以当场发现，我比他们无知。我拿起在我看来他们最用心写的诗，细细询问他们说了什么，[b5]也看我能从他们那里学到什么。诸位，我简直羞于说出真相。可我必须讲出来。当时在场的人谈到他们花心血写的诗歌，没有几个人不比诗人自己说得好。于是，很快我就也明白诗歌是怎么回事了，作诗不是靠智慧[22c]作的，而是靠某种自然，被灵感激发，就像先知和灵媒一样：他们是说了很多很美的话，但是他们并不理解自己所说的。我明白了，诗人所感到的，也是他们的这种感觉。[c5]同时，我也看到，他们因为诗歌，就认为自己在别的事情上也是最智慧的人，其实并不是。于是我离开了他们，结果认为自己更高明，就像我比政治家高明一样。

最后我走到匠人们当中。[22d]我知道，我是所谓的什么也不知道，而我也知道，我会发现他们知道很多美好的事情。这一点我没弄错，他们知道我所不知道的，在这一点上比我智慧。但是，雅典的人们，[d5]在我看来，这些能工巧匠和诗人有一样的毛病——因为能漂亮地完成自己的技艺，他们一个个就自以为在别的事情上，哪怕天下大事上（τὰμέγιστα），也是最智慧的。他们的这种自以为是遮蔽了他们的智慧。[22e]于是我从那个神谕的角度问我自己，我究竟是愿意这样是我所是，既不像他们的智慧那样智慧，也不像他们的愚蠢那样愚蠢，还是像他们那样，兼有二者。我对我自己[e5]和神谕回答说：“‘是我所是’对我更好些。”

由于这种省察，雅典的人们，[23a]我遭到了很多人的忌恨，是最苛刻和最沉重的忌恨，因而他们对我也就有了很多诬蔑，于是人们用这么个名儿来说我：“智慧的。”每一次，在场的人都认为，我在什么问题上驳斥别人，我在那个问题上就[a5]是智慧的。而其实，诸位，神才是真正智慧的，他在那个神谕里表明的是这个：人的智慧价值很小，几乎什么也不是。他好像是在这样说：“这个苏格拉底，其实是假借[23b]我的名字，用我做个例子，如同在说‘你们中最智慧的，人类啊，就是像苏格拉底那样，知道就智慧而言，他真是毫无价值’。”正是因此，我现在[b5]还在按照神的意愿，四处寻求和追问每一个我以为智慧的公民及外邦人。每当我发现他并不智慧，我就替神证明，指出此人不智慧。因为忙于这些，我没有空闲从事城邦里那些值得一提的事务，也无暇顾及家里的事，而是[23c]因为服务于神而陷入赤贫。

C.诬蔑的形成

除此之外，有些青年自愿追随我——他们最有闲工夫，出身豪富。他们乐于听我省察人们，自己[c5]经常模仿我，还试着省察别人。于是，我想他们发现无数的人是自以为知道一些，其实知道得很少，甚至什么也不知道。于是，那些被他们省察的人对我生气了，却不对他们自己生气，[23d]说什么，苏格拉底是最有害的人，把青年都败坏了。有人问他们我做了什么，教了什么，他们什么也说不出，根本不知道，但又不愿表现得毫无根据，于是就说出了所有那些为爱知[d5]者们（φιλοσοφούντων）预备的控诉，说什么“天上地下的事”，什么“不信神”，什么“把弱的说法变强”。我认为他们并不想说出事实，非常明显，他们假装知道，其实不知道。同时，我认为他们是爱名者（φιλότιμοι）[23e]，很使劲，人数也多，异口同声（ξυντεταγμένως）、言之凿凿地说我的坏话，灌满了你们的耳朵，长期以来，一直使劲地诬蔑我。靠了这些，莫勒图斯伙同阿努图斯和卢孔攻击我。其中，莫勒图斯[e5]为诗人们不平，阿努图斯为那些匠人和[24a]政治家不平，卢孔为演说家不平。就像我开头说的，我要是能在这么短的时间里消除在你们当中已根深蒂固的诬蔑，那就怪了。雅[a5]典人，这就是你们要知道的真相，无论大事小事，我都说出来，都不隐瞒你们，一点儿也不保留。而且我清楚地知道，我也会因为这些而招致忌恨。这也证明我说的是真相，这就是对我的诬蔑，这就是诬蔑我的原因[24b]。无论你们现在还是以后考察这一点，你们都会发现是这样的。

四、在哲学与政治之间：针对第二拨控告者的辩护

A.诉状

那么，针对那些最先对我提出控告的控告者，向你们做这些申辩，就该够了。至于那所谓的好人和[b5]爱城者莫勒图斯，以及后来的控告者，我说过，我随后就要来申辩。既然这些人看来是另外一群控告者，我们就再来看他们宣誓所写的诉状[8]。上面是这样说的：苏格拉底行了不义，因为他败坏青年，不信城邦[24c]信的神，而是信新的精灵之事（δαιμόνιακαινά）。那控告就是这样的。我们来一条一条地省察这份控告。

他说我因败坏青年行了不义。而我[c5]，雅典的人们啊，说莫勒图斯行了不义，因为他把正事当玩笑，轻易地把人陷进官司（ἀγῶνα），对他从未关心过（ἐμέλησεν）的事情假装正经，无事生非。事情是不是这样的，我且来摆给你们看。

B.败坏青年

来吧，莫勒图斯，回答我。把[24d]青年们变得尽可能最好，不是顶重要的事吗？

我同意。

现在，告诉诸位，谁把他们变得更好了？显然你知道，因为你关心这事。像你说的，[d5]因为你发现了败坏青年的人，也就是我，所以把我带到诸位面前，提出控告。那么说说是谁把他们变好的，披露给大家。你看，莫勒图斯，你不说话，没什么可说的？这不可耻吗？这不是我所说的话的足够证据吗：你从未关心过此事！但是，[d10]说吧，来吧，是谁把他们变得更好的？

法律。

[24e]但这不是我所问的，最好的人啊。我问的是，最先知道这些——法律——的人，是谁呢？

他们，苏格拉底，法官们。

你怎么讲，莫勒图斯？他们能够教育[e5]年轻人成为更好的人？

当然是。

他们都能，还是有些人能，别的人不能？

都能。

赫拉在上，你说得好，青年的帮助者真是[e10]人才济济了。那怎样呢？这些听众会把他们变得更好，[25a]还是不会？

他们会。

怎样，议员们呢？

议员们也会。

[a5]那么，莫勒图斯，在公民大会上呢，参加大会的那些人，是不会败坏青年的？或者他们也都会把青年变得更好？

他们也会。

看来，除我之外，雅典人都会把年轻人变得[a10]高贵和好，只有我败坏他们。你是这么说的吧？

这正是我说的意思。

你可让我倒大霉了。回答我。你是否认为马也是这样的？所有[25b]人都可以把它们变得更好，只有一人是败坏者？或者是完全相反，只有特定的一人或很少的人，精于驯马，能把马变得更好，大多数人如果和马在一起，使用它们，就会败坏它们？无论是马，还是别的牲畜，[b5]难道不都是这样吗，莫勒图斯？一定是的，不论你和阿努图斯承认不承认。如果只有一人败坏，别人都帮助，那青年们可是太[25c]幸运了。但是，莫勒图斯，你已足以表明，你从未挂念过青年，还清楚地表现出了你的这种漠不关心。虽然你因此把我带上了法庭，但你自己从未关心过此事。

[c5]当着宙斯的面，你对我们说，莫勒图斯，是在善良的公民中过日子（οἰκεῖν）好，还是在邪恶的公民中过日子好？伙计（τᾶν），回答啊！我问的可不是个难题。难道不是恶人总是对身边的人做坏事，好人做好事吗？

[c10]当然是。

[25d]那么，是否有人更愿遭到身边的人的伤害，而不是得到帮助呢？回答呀，好人。因为法律命令你回答呢。有人愿意被伤害吗？

当然没有。

[d5]来吧，你带我到这儿来，说我败坏青年，把他们变得更坏，我是有意的还是无意的？

我认为是有意的。

那怎样，莫勒图斯？难道你小小年纪，比我这么大把年纪更有智慧，知道坏[d10]人总是对和自己最接近的人做坏事，好人做好事？[25e]难道我反而那么无知，根本不知道，如果我要给身边的人带来痛苦，我就会冒着被他伤害的危险，所以我还是像你所说的那样，有意做了这些坏事？[e5]我可不信你这一套，莫勒图斯，我认为别人也不相信。[26a]我要么没败坏他们，要么败坏了他们，但不是有意的；在这两种情况下，你都在撒谎。如果我无意败坏了他们，法律就不该因为这种（无意的）过错，让人带我来这里，而应该让人私下教育和警告我。显然，如果我得到了教诲，我就会停止我无意做的事。[a5]而你却回避，不愿意与我交往，不愿意教育我，反而把我带到这里来，而法律只要求把需要惩罚的人带到这里，不是需要教育的人。

C.不敬之罪

然而，雅典的人们，我说得很清楚，[26b]莫勒图斯从未或多或少地关心过这事。可你要告诉我们，莫勒图斯，你说，我怎么败坏青年？不过很明显，按照你写的这份诉状，我是通过教给他们不信[b5]城邦信的神，而是信新的精灵之事。你说的是不是这个：我用教育败坏他们？

我说的的确是这个。

现在谈的这些神，当着他们的面，莫勒图斯，你说得更清楚些，对我，[26c]也对这些人。我还不能明白，你是不是说我教育人们信（νομίζειν）有神存在——我自己信有神存在，并不完全是无神论，不因为这行不义——但不是城邦信的神，而是信别的神，这就是[c5]你状告我的原因，说我信别的神？或者你说我根本不信神，并把这教给别人？

我说的是后者，你根本不信神。

[26d]奇怪的莫勒图斯呀，你怎么这么说呢？难道我竟不像别的人那样，相信日月是神吗？

宙斯在上，法官们，他说太阳[d5]是石头，月亮是泥土。

你以为你控告的是阿那克萨哥拉（ἀναξαγόρης）吗，亲爱的莫勒图斯？你还如此看不起在场的人们，认为他们不通文墨，以至于不知道，这是充斥克拉佐梅纽（Κλαζομένιος）的阿那克萨哥拉的著作的说法？哪怕价格很高的时候，青年们也可以花一个德拉克马，[d10]从乐队[9]那里得到，难道竟然要从我这里学这些？如果苏格拉底自称这是他的说法，[26e]他们会笑话苏格拉底，特别是这么一个奇特的说法。宙斯面前的人啊，我在你看来是这样的吗？我不信有神存在吗？

[e5]不信，宙斯在上，从来都不信。

莫勒图斯，你让人无法相信，在我看来，连你自己都无法相信自己。这个人，雅典的人们啊，看来是太自负、太放肆了，他就是因为如此自负和放肆，年轻气盛，才如此控告。[27a]他就像编造了谜语来审查我：“智慧的苏格拉底是不是知道，我在开玩笑，说得自相矛盾，还是我会欺骗他和别的听众？”因为在我看来，他[a5]在自己的诉状里就说得自相矛盾，他如同在说：“苏格拉底因为不信神而行了不义，而他信神。”这真是开玩笑。

诸位，一起来看，为什么在我看来他是这么说的。你要回答我们，莫勒图斯。而你们，就像我[27b]一开始就请求你们的，如果我按照我习惯的方式讲话，记住不要喧哗。

莫勒图斯，是否会有一个人，相信有人事存在，但又不相信有人存在？让他回答，诸[b5]位，不要让他一次一次地喧哗。是否有人相信没有马，而有马之事？是否有人不相信有吹笛者，而有笛子之事？没有吧，最好的人？如果你不想回答，我替你和别的这些人说出来。回答这个问题：[27c]是否有人信有精灵之事，而不信有精灵？

没有。

太好了，你终于回答了，虽然是吞吞吐吐，在这些人的逼迫下[c5]回答的。那么，你说我信仰和教授精灵之事，且不论新旧，但按照你的说法，我相信精灵之事，你在诉状中已经就此发誓。而如果我相信精灵之事，那么我一定信精灵？不是这样吗？是这样的。[c10]既然你不回答，我就认为你同意了。而我们认为，[27d]精灵（δαίμων）当然就是神或神的孩子，不是吗？你说是还是不是？

当然是。

那么，倘若如你所说，我认为有精灵，而如果精灵们[d5]又是某种神，这就是我说的你出的谜和玩笑：说我不认为有神，又说我认为有神，因为我认为有精灵。如果精灵们是神的某种庶子，是仙女所生的，或是无论人们所说的别的什么所生，什么人[d10]会认为，有神的孩子存在，但没有神存在？这太奇怪了，[27e]就如同说认为马和驴的孩子（παῖδας），即骡子，存在，而马不存在，驴也不存在。但是，莫勒图斯，你做出这样的控告，难道不是要么为了用这个考我们，要么因为不知道[e5]该告我行了什么真的不义？哪怕那些心灵闭塞的人，你也没办法说服他们，一个信精灵之事又信神之事的人，却不信[28a]有精灵、神、英雄。

五、为哲学而死的理由

A.苏格拉底与阿喀琉斯

然而，雅典的人们啊，我并不像莫勒图斯的诉状上所说的那样行了不义，我认为不必再为此做更多申辩，这些也就够了。而我先前[a5]说的，即，在很多人当中，对我产生了很多忌恨，你们要清楚地知道，这是真的。就是这一点把我拿下的。如果有什么把我拿下了，那不是莫勒图斯，也不是阿努图斯，而是众人的诬蔑与嫉妒。这曾经拿下了很多其他的好[28b]人，我想还会拿下更多人。不必担心，这不会到我为止。

也许有人会说：“你难道不羞愧吗，苏格拉底，为了忙于这些事务（ἐπιτήδευμα ἐπιτηδεύσας），现在招来了杀[b5]身之祸？”

我义正词严地回应他：

“这位，如果你认为有点儿人格的人应该计较生死的危险，而不是在做事时仅仅关心这个——做的究竟是正义还是不义，是好人做的还是坏人做的，那你说得真不美。而依着[28c]你的说法，在特洛伊死去的半神们，包括忒提斯之子[10]，都是微不足道的了。忒提斯之子不愿在耻辱中苟活，藐视危险，所以，当他急切地要杀死赫克托耳的时候，他的女神[c5]母亲对他说了一番话，我记得是这么说的：‘孩子，如果你为你的朋友帕特罗克洛斯之死报仇，杀死赫克托耳，你的死期将至——因为，在赫克托耳死后，马上就是你了，轮到你了。’他听了这话，根本就蔑视死亡和危险。[28d]他更害怕过坏的生活，害怕朋友们得不到复仇。‘那就马上死吧，’他说，‘我让那行不义者得到惩罚后，不必留在这弓船旁边让人嘲笑，成为大地上的负担。’你不认为他考虑死亡和[d5]危险了吧？”

这样就是依循了真理，雅典的人们。人无论是自己认为这样最好，从而让自己站在一个岗位上，还是被长官安排在岗位上，在我看来，都应该在危险中坚守，不把死亡或别的什么看得比[d10]耻辱还重。雅典的人们，当你们选举来指挥我的长官[28e]来安排我在某个岗位上时，无论是在波底代亚（Ποδειδαία）[11]、安菲玻里（Ἀμφιπόλις）[12]，还是在德利昂（Δελίον）附近[13]，我就像别的任何人一样，冒着死的危险待在被安排的岗位上。而我在这里，我[e5]认为并意识到，是神安排我以爱知为生，省察自己和别人。我如果反而怕死，[29a]或因为别的什么原因，而脱离岗位，从这里逃走，那我可真是做了可怕之事了。而如果我不服从（ἀπειθῶν）神谕，怕死，以不智慧为智慧，那才是可怕之事，人们就可以正当地把我带上法庭，说我不信有神存在。所谓[a5]的怕死，诸位，不过是不智慧而自以为智慧，因为这就是自以为知道自己不知道的事。没人知道，死没准儿是人的所有好处中最大的一个，人们都害怕，好像明确知道[29b]，它是坏事中最大的。认为知道自己不知道的事，这不是极为可耻的无知吗？诸位，我和多数人不同或许也是因为这个。如果我要说我是更智慧的，就是因为这一点：[b5]我既然不足以知道冥界里的事，我就认为我不知道。但我知道，对比自己好的神和人行不义或不服从，是坏的和可耻的。相对于这些我知道是坏的坏事情，我从来不会害怕，也不会逃避那些我不知道没准儿是好的事情。

B.苏格拉底的哲学使命

而如果[29c]你们不听阿努图斯的话（他说，要么一开始就不该把我带到这里来；要么，既然我被带来了，就不能不处死我。他对你们说，我要是给放了，你们的孩子就都会[c5]按照苏格拉底教的去做，就全都败坏了），如果你们就此跟我说：

“苏格拉底，现在我们不听阿努图斯的话，而是放了你，但有一个条件，即，你不要再花时间研究了，不再爱知了。而如果[29d]我们逮着你还在做这些，你就要死。”

如果你们就是在我说的这些条件下放我，我要告诉你们：

“雅典的人们，我向你们致敬，爱你们，但是我更要听神的话，而不是你们的。只要我还有一口气，能够做，我就根本不能[d5]停止爱知，要激励你们，告诉你们中每个我遇到的人，说我习惯说的话：‘最好的人，你是雅典人，是这个最伟大、最以智慧（σοφία）和力量著称的城邦的人，你只想着聚敛尽可能多的钱财[29e]，追求名声和荣誉，却不关心，也不求知（φροντίζω）智慧（φρόννησις）和真理，以及怎样使灵魂变成最好的，你不为这些事而羞愧吗？’如果你们中有人反驳，说他关心，我不会轻易放他走，自己也不走，而是询问他，省察他。如果我发现他并没有美德，[e5]他反而说自己有，就羞辱（ἐλέγξω）他，责备他[30a]把最大价值的当成最不重要的，把更微小的当成更大的。只要我遇上了，无论年轻人还是老人，无论外邦人还是本城的人，我都会对他这么做，尤其是本城的人，因为你们是离我最近的同胞。[a5]你们要清楚，是神命令我这么做的。我认为，比起我对神的服务，你们在这城里还没有过什么更大的好处。我在城中转悠，所做的不过就是劝说你们当中的青年和老人，不要这么关心身体或金钱，[30b]而要使劲让灵魂变得尽可能最好，对你们说：‘美德不来自金钱，相反，金钱和人类所有别的好处，无论个体的还是城邦的，之所以好，都是因为美德。’[b5]那么，如果我就是用说这些来败坏青年，那么这就是有害的。但，如果谁说我说的不是这些，他说得不对。对此，我会说：‘雅典的人们，不论你们是否被阿努图斯说服了，不论你们是否放我，我都会[30c]这么做，虽九死而不悔。’”

不要喧哗，雅典的人们，请按照我请求你们的做，在我说话时不对我喧哗，而是听我说。因为，我认为，听我说话也对你们有益。我要对[c5]你们说一些话，也许这会让你们叫（βοήσεσθε）起来。但是永远不要这么做。而要清楚地知道，如果你们杀了我，而我是我所说的这样的人，那么，你们对我的伤害，并不比对你们自己的伤害大。没人会伤害我，无论是莫勒图斯还是阿努图斯——他们没有能力——因为我想，让[30d]更好的人被更坏的人伤害，是渎神违法的。也许有人能杀死、放逐或羞辱我。此人和别人一定都认为，这是很大的坏事，但是我不这么想，而是认为，现在做这事（即[d5]试图不义地杀人）的人对自己带来了大得多的伤害。而现在，雅典的人们，我远不是常人想象的那样，在为自己申辩，而是为你们申辩，以免你们判了我罪，从而对神给你们的赐予犯了错误。[30e]而如果你们杀死我，你们将不容易找到别的这类赐予了，即——打个不恰当的比方——像我这样，受命于神，献身城邦的一个。这城邦就如同一匹高头大马，因为大，就会[e5]慵懒，需要一只牛虻来惊醒。在我看来，神就派我到城邦里来当这样的一个，惊醒、[31a]劝说、责备你们每一个，我整天不停地在各处安顿你们。诸位，另外一个这样的人不容易出现在你们中间了，而如果你们听了我的话，你们就放了我。也许你们立即会遭到烦扰，就像打盹儿的人被惊醒；如果你们要打[a5]我，听信了阿努图斯的话，很容易就能杀我。如果神不再操心，派另外一个来烦你们，随后你们就要在沉睡中度完余生。

而我恰巧就是神派给城邦的这样一个，你们[31b]由下面的事会明白的：我不关心我自己的任何事，简直不像是人所能为。多年来，家里的事都得不到关心，而我总是为你们做事，亲自走到你们每个人那里，像父亲或长兄一样，[b5]劝你们关心美德。如果我从中得到什么，或靠叫你们做这些挣薪水，那还有些道理。现在，你们自己看，他们，那些控告者，虽然如此无耻地在别的所有事情上控告我，却不能厚着脸皮[31c]提供证人，证明我拿过或乞求过薪水。而我认为，我可以提供足够的证据，证明我说的是真的，那就是我的贫困。

C.哲学作为政治

这看起来也许有点儿不合常理：我私下为[c5]人们出主意，奔走忙碌。在公共场合，却不肯走到你们众人当中，为城邦出主意。此事的原因，就是你们多次听我在很多地方说的，会出现一个神性的[31d]精灵的声音，而莫勒图斯在写诉状时，嘲讽的也许就是这一点。这从我小时候就开始了，就出现了某种声音，每当它出现时，它总是阻止我做事，却从不鼓励我做什么。[d5]就是它反对我参与政事，而且我认为反对得漂亮（παγκάλως）。可你们要清楚地知道，雅典的人们，如果我很早以前就试图参与政事，我早就死了，那么我[31e]对你们和我自己都会毫无益处。不要因为我说出真话而对我动怒。凡是坦诚地反对你们或别的大众，阻止在城邦里发生不义或犯法的事的人，都活不了。事实[32a]上，谁若一定要为正义而战，并且想多活一段，他必须私下干，而不是参与政事。

对这些，我会给你们举出有力的证据，不用[a5]语言，而是用你们看重的事实。请你们听我的经历，你们就会知道，我不会因为怕死而向一个违背正义的人屈服，哪怕不屈服就会灭亡。我要告诉你们的，虽然像是讼师的陈词滥调，却都是真的。而我，雅典的人们，从来没有在城邦里担任过[32b]别的职务，只当过议员[14]。那时正该我们的部族安提俄克斯（᾿Αντιοχίς）当主席（πρυτανεύω）[15]，而你们通过决议[16]，要集体审判十个将军，因为他们从海战班师时，很多阵亡将士的尸体没有被运回——后来，[b5]你们都认为这是不合法的。但在那时的主席（πρύτανις）当中，只有我反对你们做违法的事，投了反对票。虽然那些演说家准备弹劾我，要逮捕我，你们发号施令、大喊大叫，但我认为我掌握了法[32c]律和正义，认为自己应该冒风险，而不是因为害怕被捕或死亡，就赞同你们提不义的建议。那是城邦里还是民主制的时候。等到成了寡头制，三十僭主[17][c5]召我们五个人到圆宫[18]，命我们把撒拉密斯的赖翁（ΣαλαμῖνοςΛέοντα）[19]从撒拉密斯带走处死，他们也给了别的很多人很多这类命令，希望让尽可能多的人承担责任。对此我[32d]又用行动（而非言辞）指出，我宁愿死（如果这不是一个很粗鲁的说法），也不愿意做这个，这不义或不虔诚（ἀνόσιον）的事。这是我的全部关心所在。因为那个政府虽然强硬，却不能逼我[d5]去行不义，于是，我们走出圆宫后，另外四个人到撒拉密斯去带赖翁，我却回家去了。也许，如果这个政府不很快被推翻，我会因此而死。[32e]关于这，很多人可以向你们做证。

那么，如果我以公事为业，做一个好人应该做的事，扶助正义，公事公办地把这当作最重要的事来做，你们认为我还能活这么大岁数吗？[e5]根本不能，雅典的人们。谁也不能。[33a]在我的整个一生中，我若是从事公共事务，就都是这样的，在私下的活动中，也是如此。我从来没有屈服于任何违背正义的事，不论是对诬蔑我的人、称为我的学生的人，[a5]还是别人。我从来都不是老师。如果有谁想听我说话，听我完成我的任务，不论老少，我都从不拒绝。我不会收了钱[33b]才讲，不收钱就不讲。不论贫富，我都会向他们问问题。谁要想听我说什么，就要回答我的问题。不论这些人变好没有，都不该由我[b5]负责，因为我对他们从未许诺什么，也没教给他们什么。如果有人说，曾经从我处私下学过或听到过什么，而别人都没有，你们一定要知道，他说的不是真的。

但是，为什么有人那么喜欢和我来往[33c]这么长时间？你们听到了，雅典的人们，我对你们说的是全部真相。这是因为，他们喜欢听我省察那些自以为智慧其实不智慧的人。这不是不愉快的事。正如我说的，这是神[c5]派我干的，通过神谕，通过托梦，通过凡是神分派让人完成任务时，所采用的别的各种方式。

这些，雅典的人们，都是真的，很容易检验。而如果我败坏[33d]青年，我就已经败坏了一些，他们中一些人应该已经长大了，就会认识到，他们在年轻的时候，我曾经给他们出过坏主意，现在就会走上来控告我，报复我。如果他们[d5]自己不愿意，他们的那些亲戚中也会有人来，父亲、兄弟，以及别的亲戚都会。如果这些人的一些亲戚曾经从我这里遭遇了坏事，他们现在就会记起来，报复我。我看到，这里有他们中的很多人，首先是这个克力同（Κρίτων），[33e]和我是同龄人，出身也相同，是这个克力同布鲁斯（Κριτοβούλυς）的父亲；然后是斯菲图斯（Σφήττιος）人吕萨尼亚（Λυσανίας），这个埃斯奇涅（Αισχίνης）的父亲；还有这个凯菲西欧（Κηφισιεὺς）人安提丰（Αντιφῶν），埃匹格涅斯（Επιγένης）的父亲。还有别的一些人，他们的兄弟都和我来往。还有西奥佐提多斯（Θεοζοτίδος）的儿子[e5]尼克斯特拉托斯（Νικόστρατος），是西奥多托斯（Θεόδοτος）的兄弟，现在西奥多托斯死了，他不能阻止尼克斯特拉托斯告我了。还有[34a]德谟多克斯（Δημοδόκος）的儿子，那个帕拉鲁斯（Πάραλος），已故的忒阿格斯（Θεάγης）是他的兄弟。还有阿里斯图诺斯（᾿Αρίστωνος）的儿子，那个阿德曼托斯（᾿Αδείμαντος），柏拉图是他的兄弟。还有艾安托多罗斯（Αἰαντόδωρος），那个阿波罗多罗斯（᾿Απολλόδωρος）是他的兄弟。

我还可以说出好多人来，莫勒图斯真应该在他的演说中把其中一些当成证人。如果[a5]他忘了，现在他可以举出来——我可以让步——让他说，他可有一个这种证人？但是你们会发现，事实是完全相反的，诸位，他们都会帮助我这个莫勒图斯和阿努图斯认为的所谓败坏了他们的亲戚、对他们[34b]作恶的人。那些被败坏的人自己帮助我还有道理。而那些未被败坏的亲戚，已在耄耋之年，都会来帮我。如果不是他们有正当和正义的原因，[b5]知道莫勒图斯是在说谎，我说的是真的，那还有什么原因来帮我？

D.爱智者的荣耀

诸位，这些，也许还有别的更多此类的话，就是我所要申辩的。你们中也许有人[34c]想起自己的申辩来，会受刺激，也许他在为比这个官司（ἀγῶνα）还小的官司角逐（ἀγονιζέμενος）时，泪流满面地向法官们恳求，还带孩子上来，以便能得到最大的同情，甚至还带上来很多别的[c5]亲戚朋友。我可不做这些事，宁愿冒着好像是最大的危险。那么，这样想的人也许会对我的态度更固执，就因为这而生气，冲动地投[34d]我的反对票。如果你们中有人是这样——我认为没有，但如果有，我这么对他说就很好：

“最好的人，我也有家庭。因为就像荷马说的，我不是‘[d5]出生于岩石或古老的橡树’。我是父母生的，也有家庭，还有儿子，雅典的人们，有三个呢，一个已经是小伙子，其余两个还是小孩儿。我不需要带他们中的哪个上来，求你们投票放过我。”

那么，我到底为什么不这样做？不是因为我太固执，雅典[34e]的人们，也不是我看不起你们；究竟我是否敢于面对死亡，是另外一个问题（λόγος）；但对声望而言，无论是我的、你们的，还是整个城邦的，我这样年纪和名声的人这么做，都是不大[e5]高贵的。不论真假，人们[35a]认为，苏格拉底与大多数人有些不同。那么，如果你们当中有什么人，无论因为智慧、勇敢，还是别的这类美德，看起来和别人不同，要这样做就太可耻了。我经常看到，本来[a5]很体面的人，在受审时做出非常奇怪的事，以为死就是遭受很可怕的事，好像你们如果不杀他们，他们就不会死（ἀθανάτος）。在我看来，他们真是给城邦带来（περιάπτω）耻辱，让一个外邦人[35b]以为，在雅典人中，那些本来靠美德与别人不同，从而让人们选出授予职位和别的荣誉的，和女人没什么不同。雅典的人们，你们中凡是有体面的，[b5]不管在哪方面有体面，都不该这么做；我们若是这么做了，你们也不该允许。而你们要由此表明，谁要把这种可怜的表演带上台来，把城邦变得滑稽可笑，你们就更应该投他的反对票，而不是给那保持安静的投反对票。

除去名声，诸位，我认为，哀求法官[35c]是不对的，靠乞求逃脱也是不应该的，而应该教育和说服。因为法官占据那席位，不是为了施舍正义，而是要裁判正义。他们发誓并不是要按照自己的喜好施舍，而是根据[c5]法律裁判。所以，我们不能让你们习惯于发假誓，你们也不该习惯于此。否则我们双方就都不虔敬（εὐσεβοῖεν）了。所以，雅典的人们，你们不能认为我应该对你们做这些我觉得不高贵、不[35d]正义、不虔诚（ὅσιον）的事，特别是，宙斯在上，不虔敬又是莫勒图斯给我加的罪名。显然，既然你们已经发了誓，如果我劝说和以乞求逼迫，我就是在教给你们，不要认为神存在，我这申辩简[d5]直就成了控告自己不信神。但是远不是这样。我信神，雅典的人们，我的控告者们无人比得上我，我请你们和神抉择，怎样才是对我对你们都最好的。

六、惩罚与荣耀

[35e]雅典的人们，你们投我的反对票[20]，我[36a]对这结果并不生气。这有很多原因，其中一个是，这样的结果并不出乎我的意料，但我反而更惊讶于双方所投石子的数目。因为我觉得反对票不会只[a5]多一点儿，而要多出更多。但现在看起来，只要有三十个石子不这么投，我就会被放了。要是只有莫勒图斯，看来我现在就已经被放了；不仅放了，而且每个人都清楚，如果阿努图斯不和卢孔上来告我，那他就要付一千[36b]德拉克马，因为他得不到五分之一的石子。[21]

他对我提出（τιμάω）死刑。好吧。雅典的人们，我应向你们提出什么替代[22]的呢？不是显然要按[b5]照我的品行（ἄξιός）吗？那该是什么呢？按我这品行该遭受或付出什么呢？要知道，我一生没有庸庸碌碌地过，我不关心众人所关心的金钱、家业、军阶，不做公众演说，也不做别的当权者，不想参加城里的朋党和帮派，我认为自己真是[36c]太忠厚了，要参与这些就难以保命。我没有去那儿做这些事，如果去了，我认为我对你们和我自己都没有什么助益。但正如我说的，我私下到你们每个人那里，做有最大益处（εὐεργετεῖν）的益事（εὐεργεσία）。我[c5]尝试着劝你们中的每个人，不要先关心“自己的”，而要先关心自己，让自己尽可能变得最好和最智慧；不要关心“城邦的”，而要关心城邦自身，对其他事情也要按同样的方式关心——我既然是这样，[36d]那么按这品行应该得到什么呢？应该是好的——雅典的人们，如果真正要按照我的品行提出我应得的。而且是我该得到的那种好事。我这样一个需要闲暇来劝勉你们的贫穷的恩人（εὐεγρέτης），[d5]应得到什么样的好处呢？雅典的人们，给我这种人最合适不过的，就是在政府大厅（πρυτανεῖον）里用膳[23]。你们中有谁在奥林匹亚运动会中用一匹马、两匹马或四匹马的马车赢了比赛，我比他都更适合在那里吃。因为，他好像在给你们造福，我就是在造福；而他[36e]不需要这供养，我需要。那么，如果按照正义，根据我的品行提出，我就要提出这个：[37a]在政府大厅用膳。

也许，就像我谈乞怜和妥协时一样，你们觉得我说这些是大放厥词。雅典的人们，不是那样的，而应该是[a5]下面这样。我认为，我从不曾对谁行不义，至少不曾有意行不义，但是我不能说服你们这样认为。因为我们相互交谈的时间太短。我就认为，如果你们有一项法律，就像别人有一样[24]，并不选[37b]某一天来判死刑，而是多等几天，你们会被说服的。而今，在这么短的时间里，从这么大的诬蔑中解脱出来，是不容易了。我相信，我没有对任何人行不义，我也不会对自己行不义，不会说我自己的品行该得恶报，[b5]给自己提出这样一种惩罚方式。我怕什么？怕遭到莫勒图斯给我提的惩罚吗？我说了，我不知道那是好还是坏。难道我不这样，而是从我明知道是坏的事情中，另找一种，提出来罚我？难道要监禁？我为什么[37c]要在监狱里生活，给每届（ἀεί）选出来的惯例者当奴隶，给十一人[25]当奴隶？难道要在付清罚款前先收监吗？但对于我来说，罚款和我刚说的监禁是一样的。因为我从哪儿也找不到钱来付清。但是我可以提出[c5]流放吗？也许，你们将会给我这个惩罚。我也太贪生怕死（φιλοψυχία）了，雅典的人们，才会这么不合情理，以至于不能明白，你们，我的同胞公民，都不能忍受我的行事[37d]和言辞，觉得这些是那么难以承受，惹人忌恨，以至你们要寻求除掉这些；难道别人会容易忍受这类东西吗？雅典的人们，根本不可能。对于我这年纪的人，此时被流放，[d5]轮番跑到一个又一个别的城邦去，又被赶出来，这可真是高贵的生活。因为我清楚地知道，我无论到哪里去，青年人都会像在这里一样倾听我说话。如果我赶他们走，他们会说服自己的长辈，赶我走；但如果[37e]我不赶他们走，他们的父辈和家人会为了他们赶我走。

也许有人会说：

“苏格拉底，你要是沉默不语，在流放后，不就可以过日子了吗？”

要在这方面说服你们[e5]中那些人，是最难的。因为，如果我说那是不遵从神的，因此我不能[38a]保持沉默，你们不会被说服，好像我在出言讥讽（εἰρωνευομένω）。如果我又说，每天谈论美德，谈论别的你们听我说的事——听我对自己[a5]和别的人做省察，听我说，未经省察的生活是不值得过的生活——这对人而言恰恰是最大的好，你们就更不可能被我说服了。事情就是我说的这样；但诸位，要说服你们可不容易。同时，我不习惯认为我的品行该遭什么恶罚。如果我有钱，我就会[38b]按我能够付的那么多提出罚我的钱，因为那不会伤害我。但现在不是这样，除非你们同意我提出我付得起的钱数。也许，我能付[b5]一个米纳的银子。那我就提这么多。

雅典的人们，柏拉图、克力同、克力同布鲁斯和阿波罗多罗斯叫我付三十个米纳的罚款，他们做担保。那么我就提出这些。他们可以向你们做这银子的可信赖的担保。

七、临别告白

[38c]雅典的人们[26]，不必多长时间，那些想毁掉城邦的人就可以加给你们杀害智慧者苏格拉底的罪名和责任——虽然我不智慧，那些想责怪你们的人会说我智慧——[c5]但只要你们等一小段时间，你们期待的自然就发生了。看我这把年纪，活了很久，离死很近了。我不是对你们全体说这话的，而是对那些[38d]投票处死我的人说的。我对这些人还说下面的话：雅典的人们，你们也许认为，我很难用语言说服你们，来赢得你们——好像我认为需要[d5]用尽各种言行来逃出这个案子。根本不是。我很难赢得你们，不是因为缺少语言，而是因为缺乏勇气和无耻，我不愿对你们说那些你们最喜欢听的话，我不哀悼，不悲恸，不做也不[38e]说别的很多我认为不合我的品行（如我所说的）而你们习惯从别人那里听到的那些。我认为，我不该因为危险而做自由人不该做的事，而且我现在也不后悔做了这样的申辩，我宁愿[e5]选择这样申辩而死，也不选择那样活着。因为，不论是在法庭上，还是在战斗中，无论是我还是别人，都不该[39a]蓄意做什么事来逃脱死亡。因为在很多战争中都很明显，有人丢盔弃甲，对追击者摇尾乞怜，从而逃脱死亡；还有很多别的办法，[a5]如果有勇气做任何事、说任何话，在任何危险中都有办法逃脱死亡。但是各位，逃离死亡并不难，可逃离邪恶（πονηρία）却难得多。因为邪恶比死亡跑得更快。而[39b]今我迟缓年迈，那慢一些的会赢我，那些控诉我的又聪明又敏捷，却被快一些的赢了，那就是恶（κακίας）。而今我要走了，接受你们判的死刑；他们却要接受真理所判的罪恶[b5]和不义。那就让我服从这个惩罚，他们也要服从他们的。也许就该是这样了，我认为他们也该得到所应得的。

然后，[39c]投票判我罪的人们，我愿对你们预言。因为我所在的处境，是人们大多要预言的处境：就是临死之前。而我说，杀我的人们，宙斯在上，[c5]我死之后，你们的报应（τιμωρία）也会很快来临，那可比你们给我的这惩罚——杀我——残酷多了。现在你们这么做了，以为就可以摆脱对生活做出检验（ἔλεγχον），但是，如我所说，结果会完全相反。会有更多的人检验你们，现在我一直阻拦他们，而你们[39d]看不到。他们会更严厉，也更年轻，会让你们更加恼怒。你们靠杀人来阻止人们责备你们活[d5]得不正确，这念头可不美。因为这种解脱既全无可能，也不美。而那最美和最容易的解脱，不是阻止别人，而是把自己培养成最好的。对你们中那些投我反对票的人，我如此预言，[39e]然后我就走了。

至于那些投票认为我无罪的人，我们可以愉快地谈谈所发生的这事，趁着当官的还忙着，我还没有到就死之地去。诸位，和我待一会儿吧。只要还能，我们不[e5]妨互相聊聊天（διαμυθολογέω）。我想把你们当[40a]朋友，告诉你们，刚刚所发生的对我究竟意味着什么。各位法官（ἄνδρεςδικασταί）——我叫你们法官（δικασταῖς），才叫得对了——我这里发生了奇妙的事。在以前的时候，那个和我相伴的[a5]精灵的声音，总会不断出来反对——只要我想做不对的事，哪怕是小事。而刚才，你们看到，我这儿发生的，人们总是以为，并且确实都相信，是最大的坏事。但是，从早晨[40b]离家开始，这个神就没有给出信号反对，即使到了法庭这里，也没有，在我说话的过程中，也没有反对我要说的话。而别的时候在我说话时，它却不断在讲话的中途阻拦。现在，针对我[b5]做的这件事，它从来没有反对我的言行。在我看来，这事的原因是什么呢？我要告诉你们：或许，我的这次遭遇变成了好事，我们要认为死是坏的，[40c]都是不对的。我认为，这里有一个巨大征兆发生了：如果我要做的不是件好事，那么，我所熟悉的信号就不会不反对我。

让我们这么来想，这为什么很有希望（ἐλπίς）成为[c5]好事。因为死是下面的两者之一。要么死就是什么也不存在，死者没有任何感觉；要么，根据一些人的说法，死就是发生一种变化，就是灵魂从这里迁移到别的地方。如果就是没有感觉，那就[40d]如同睡觉，而且睡着的人还不做梦，那死可真是很奇妙的好事。我认为，如果让人选出一个他沉睡而没有梦境的夜晚，把他一生中别的夜晚和[d5]白天同这个夜晚相比，让他仔细想后，说出，在他一生所经历的当中，有多少日夜，比这个夜晚更好、更舒服，我想，且不说一个老百姓，就是波斯大王[27][40e]也会发现，和别的日夜比起来，像这样好的屈指可数。而如果死是这样的，我说它是好事。那时候，永恒好像也不比一夜更长。

另外，如果死就是从这里[e5]迁移到另外一个地方，而且人们所说的是真的，即，所有的死人都在那里，法官们，还有什么比这更好的？如果一个到了冥府的人，从这些[41a]所谓的法官中得到解脱，他会发现那些真正的法官，他们据说在那里审判，有米诺斯（Μίνως）[28]、拉达马索斯（Ῥαδάμανθυς）[29]、埃亚库斯（Αἰακός）[30]、特里普托勒摩斯（Τριπτόλεμος）[31]和别的很多活着[a5]时公正（δίκαιοι）的半神。那这趟旅行岂可小看？还有，要是能和俄耳甫斯（Ὀρφεύς）、穆塞欧（Μουσαῖος）、赫西俄德（σίοδος）、荷马（Ὁμήρος）[32]在一起，你们中谁不宁愿付出高额代价？如果这是真的，我愿意死很多次。当我[41b]遇到帕拉梅德（Παλαμήδης）[33]、特拉蒙（Τελαμών）的埃阿斯（Αἴας）[34]，还有别的死于不义的冤狱的古人时，我会把我自己的遭遇和他们的相比，对我而言，在那里这样过日子是尤其奇妙的——我认为，[b5]这没有什么不快乐的——而最大的好事是，在那里省察和询问他们，就像在这里做的那样，看他们当中谁有智慧，谁自以为有智慧，而其实没有。法官们，人们愿付出多大代价，来省察带领大军攻打特洛伊的人[35]、奥德修斯（Ὀδυσσεύς）、[41c]西西弗斯（Σίσυφος）[36]，或人们能提到的其他无数男人、女人？在那里和他们谈论、交往，省察他们，会是无比幸福。当然，那里的人根本不会因此[c5]杀人。如果所说的是真的，那里的人不仅在别的方面比这里的人幸福，而且在余下的时间里都是不朽的。

法官们啊，你们也应该对死抱有良好的希望，把这当成真的：[41d]好人不会有恶报，无论生前还是死后，诸神不会不关心他的事。我出的这事不是偶然的，而是明白显示给我的——死去，从杂事[d5]中解脱，这对我更好。因此，那征兆不让我转向任何地方，我也并不抱怨那些投我反对票和控告我的人。但他们并不是因为想到了这，才投我的反对票和控告我的；他们是要伤害我。为此[41e]他们该受谴责。

但我对他们提个请求。我的儿子们长大以后，诸位，如果他们在你们看来关心钱财或别的东西[e5]胜过了关心美德，你们就惩罚（τιμωρέω）他们，像我烦扰你们一样烦扰他们；如果他们实际不是什么而自以为是，你们就要谴责他们，就像我谴责你们一样，告诉他们没有关心应该关心的，他们的认知配不上自己的品行。如果你们这么做，我和[42a]我的儿子从你们这里得到的就是正义的。不过，是该走的时候了，我去死，你们去生。我们所去做的究竟哪个更好，谁也不知道——除了[a5]神。

[1] 柏拉图著作中的数字和字母标号即“斯特方页码”，来自1578年斯特方在巴黎出版的柏拉图希腊文著作的页码标注，是柏拉图著作的标准页码标号。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2] 即拳击手在没有对手时所做的练习。在现代拳击中，仍有“空拳练习”（shadow-boxing）。

[3] 卡利亚是雅典的巨富。在《普罗塔戈拉》中，他同时款待普罗塔戈拉、西庇亚和普罗迪科斯。色诺芬的《会饮》所记述的场景就发生在卡利亚家中。此外，还有很多雅典作家提到过他。

[4] 这次出逃发生在公元前404年，也就是苏格拉底审判的五年前，他们八个月后回到雅典。当时，雅典在伯罗奔尼撒战争中战败，斯巴达人为雅典建立了寡头制，而这些寡头为自己攫取了绝对权力，因此被称为“三十僭主”。于是，很多民主派逃离雅典。苏格拉底反对民主制，但也不支持寡头制，不过苏格拉底一直留在了雅典城。

[5] 苏格拉底的早年同伴凯瑞丰举止怪异，是雅典人所熟知的。他不仅出现在柏拉图的对话中，还出现在很多喜剧当中，阿里斯托芬的《云》《鸟》《蛙》等作品都讽刺了他。

[6] 阿波罗杀死了德尔斐看守神殿的龙皮图（πύθω），于是得到了皮提亚的徽标。他的祭司都被称为皮提亚。

[7] 苏格拉底多次以天狗发誓，比如在《高尔吉亚》[482b5]中。他在那里还明确讲，这是埃及的一个神。早在希罗多德的时候，希腊人已经知道了埃及人对狗的崇拜。

[8] 第欧根尼・拉尔修在《名哲言行录》第二卷的“苏格拉底”部分提到，这份诉状在罗马皇帝哈德良时期还保存在雅典的档案里，其中写道：“皮特索斯的莫勒图斯的儿子莫勒图斯盟誓，状告阿罗匹克的索夫罗尼斯克的儿子苏格拉底，说：‘苏格拉底行了不义，因为他不信城邦信的神，而是带进新的精灵之事。他还因为败坏青年而行了不义。判死刑。’”

[9] 有关“乐队”的说法，通常有两种解释。一是指通过悲剧了解阿那克萨哥拉的说法；二是雅典广场中卖书的地方通常在乐队旁边。

[10] 即阿喀琉斯，这里不说“阿喀琉斯”而说“忒提斯之子”，是为了突出阿喀琉斯的半神身份。在希腊散文中，以某人的父母指代某人是很常见的，不过一般是用父名，而不是母名。

[11] 这一战役发生在公元前432年（修昔底德《伯罗奔尼撒战争史》卷一），当时苏格拉底37岁。在《会饮》[219e5]以下，阿尔喀比亚德详细描述了苏格拉底在这次战役中的表现。在这一战里，苏格拉底连续站了24小时，救了阿尔喀比亚德的性命。

[12] 这可能指的是公元前422年的一场著名战役，但并没有充足的证据（修昔底德《伯罗奔尼撒战争史》卷二）。当时苏格拉底已经47岁，不太可能参加这样的远征。另外一种可能是，这指的是在公元前437年至公元前436年之间建造安菲玻里时的战斗。那时候苏格拉底32岁。

[13] 德利昂不是城镇名，而是阿波罗一个神殿的名字，那次战役发生在这“附近”（参见色诺芬《回忆苏格拉底》）。在德利昂之战中，雅典人被忒拜人打败（参见修昔底德《伯罗奔尼撒战争史》卷四）。在《会饮》[221a2]中，阿尔喀比亚德描述到，苏格拉底从战场上撤退时极为沉着和勇敢，超出了将军拉克斯，他的表现比在波底代亚之战中更加突出。

[14] 苏格拉底说自己只当过议员，并不意味着他只当过一次议员。亚里士多德在《政治学》62：3里谈到，一个人可以当两次议员。我们会在[32b6]看到，这很可能是苏格拉底第二次当议员。另外，苏格拉底当议员，也并不违背他不从政的原则。当议员和当兵一样，是公民的义务，不算从政。

[15] 雅典的议会一般由十个部落分别出五十人组成。每个部落的五十个人，通过抽签，组成议会为城邦工作三十五或三十六天。议会决定把什么事情提交公民大会讨论。这五十个人被称为“主席”。

[16] 在雅典和斯巴达的战争结束前两年，也就是公元前406年，雅典和斯巴达在爱琴岛附近有一场海战，雅典取得了胜利。战斗结束后，海上起了风暴，很多被打坏的战船和雅典将士（包括阵亡的和活着的）还在战场上，无法营救。公民大会举行了两次集会，要集体判处十个将军中的六人死刑，但苏格拉底认为这是不合法的，应该分别审判。他的反对没有起到作用。

[17] 伯罗奔尼撒战争结束后，斯巴达取胜，在雅典扶植了三十僭主。三十僭主起初只是处死一些人们不喜欢的煽动家和政治人物，后来就发展到诛杀了很多民主制的支持者，以及富有的公民和外邦人。很多同情民主制的人逃离了雅典。公元前403年，三十僭主的统治只有八个月，就被这些逃亡者推翻了。寡头党的余部从雅典退到附近的一个小镇上，到公元前401年才被彻底消灭，当时距苏格拉底的审判只有两年。苏格拉底不是民主派，所以在三十僭主时期没有离开雅典。

[18] 圆宫（θολός），又称“伞宫”（σκιάς），是一个圆形建筑，在民主制时期的雅典，当主席的五十个议员在那里集会、献祭、吃饭。三十僭主把这里当成他们主要的政府建筑之一。

[19] 赖翁据说是一个很正直的人。处死他是三十僭主犯下的一大罪行。三十僭主处死的无辜的人很多，但赖翁之死尤其引起人们的愤恨。

[20] 这是在陪审团投票之后的演说。雅典人用石子投票。这次一共有500人，投票结果应该是280（反对票）：220（赞成票）。

[21] 苏格拉底的算法，是认为三个人分别得了280票中的三分之一，这个数字不到500票的五分之一。按照雅典的法律，如果原告得票不到总数的五分之一，就会因为诬告的罪名而被判处一千德拉克马的罚金。

[22] 按照雅典的法律，有些案件按照固有的规定处罚，有些则不必。苏格拉底的这个案子就是没有固定处罚的。在这样的案子中，法律要求法官从两者之中选择一个处罚方式，即，原告在诉讼书最后提出的惩罚，以及被告在判罪之后提出的惩罚。而法官不准提出第三种处罚。

[23] 在古典时代，在政府大厅用膳的人是享有特权的极少数人，贵宾一般只包括奥林匹亚运动会的得胜者、雅典民主制的建立者哈摩狄阿斯（Ἁρμόδιος）和阿利斯托斋吞（Ἀριστογείτων）的直系后裔中的长子。有时候，也会有大使、经选举获得此荣耀的官员、得胜的将军等被邀请去用膳。

[24] 斯巴达的法律就是这样规定的。

[25] 雅典管理监狱和刑罚的官员共有十一人，是抽签选定的。

[26] 在苏格拉底正式提出了一种惩罚方式后，陪审团再次投票，结果是大多数人支持死刑。

[27] 因为波斯国王拥有巨大的财富和庞大的帝国，希腊人一般认为他是最快乐的人。

[28] 米诺斯是古代克里特的国王，扫清了附近的海盗。据说他制定了克里特的法律，生时是一个正义的人。传说他让雅典每年送七个童男和七个童女到克里特，给怪兽做牺牲。忒修斯杀死了怪兽，解救了童男童女。此后，雅典每年有纪念忒修斯的仪式。苏格拉底之所以没有很快被处死，就是因为这个仪式正在进行。在《奥德赛》卷十一：568-571，奥德修斯曾游冥府，看到米诺斯在那里的各位法官之中。

[29] 拉达马索斯是米诺斯的兄弟，也有义人之名。品达曾说，他执掌幸福岛（好人死后去的地方）。

[30] 据品达说，埃亚库斯是爱琴海的立法者，甚至还审理诸神之间的争执，但没有说他审判死人。在《高尔吉亚》[523e-527a]中，苏格拉底谈到，米诺斯、拉达马索斯、埃亚库斯是冥府的法官。

[31] 特里普托勒摩斯是传说中阿提卡地区厄琉息斯的国王克琉斯的儿子。他从女神得墨忒尔处学到了让作物生长收获的方法。

[32] 这是希腊文化中最重要的四位诗人。俄耳甫斯和穆塞欧可能只是传说人物。在《普罗塔戈拉》[316d8]、《理想国》[364e3]中，按照俄耳甫斯神话传统，俄耳甫斯和穆塞欧并提。在阿里斯托芬的《蛙》[1032-1036]中，四位诗人按照和这里同样的顺序排列。

[33] 帕拉梅德参加了希腊人对特洛伊的战争。据说，因为某种原因（对此有各种说法），帕拉梅德和奥德修斯陷入争执，于是奥德修斯以背叛希腊、里通特洛伊的名义逮捕了帕拉梅德。帕拉梅德被希腊军队用石头砸死。埃斯库罗斯、欧里庇得斯、索福克勒斯都曾写过题为《帕拉梅德》的悲剧，但都没有流传下来。高尔吉亚曾写过《帕拉梅德的申辩》，没有佚失。在色诺芬的《申辩》[26]中，苏格拉底提到了帕拉梅德的申辩。第欧根尼・拉尔修说，欧里庇得斯在《帕拉梅德》中提到了苏格拉底的申辩，但这是不可能的，因为欧里庇得斯比苏格拉底早死十六年。

[34] 埃阿斯是特洛伊战争中著名的希腊勇士。在阿喀琉斯死后，他和奥德修斯争夺阿喀琉斯的盔甲。奥德修斯作弊取胜。埃阿斯为了报复，想杀死奥德修斯和阿伽门农。但雅典娜把他变疯癫了，疯了的埃阿斯杀死了一群羊。他清醒过来以后，羞愤自杀。

[35] 指希腊军队的统帅阿伽门农。

[36] 在《伊利亚特》卷五：153中，西西弗斯被称为“最巧的人”。

山魈

/

孙太白尝言：其曾祖肄业于南山柳沟寺。麦秋旋里[1]，经旬始返。启斋门，则案上尘生，窗间丝满。命仆粪除[2]，至晚始觉清爽可坐。乃拂榻陈卧具，扃扉[3]就枕，月色已满窗矣。

辗转移时，万籁俱寂。忽闻风声隆隆，山门忽然作响，窃谓寺僧失扃。注念间[4]，风声渐近居庐，俄而房门辟矣。大疑之。思未定，声已入屋；又有靴声铿铿然，渐傍寝门。心始怖。俄而寝门辟矣。忽视之，一大鬼鞠躬塞入，突立榻前，殆与梁齐。面似老鸦皮色；目光睒闪[5]，绕室四顾；张巨口如盆，齿疏疏长三寸许；舌动喉鸣，呵喇[6]之声，响连四壁。

公惧极；又念咫尺之地，势无所逃，不如因而刺之。乃阴抽枕下佩刀，遽[7]拔而斫之，中腹，作石缶声。鬼大怒，伸巨爪攫公。公少缩。鬼攫得衾，捽[8]之，忿忿而去。

公随衾堕，伏地号呼。家人持火奔集，则门闭如故，排窗入，见公状，大骇。扶曳登床，始言其故。共验之，则衾夹于寝门之隙。启扉检照，见有爪痕如箕，五指着处皆穿。

既明，不敢复留，负笈[9]而归。后问僧人，无复他异。

译文

孙太白曾经讲过这样一件事：他的曾祖父在南山柳沟寺读书，某一年的麦秋时节回故乡，在家待了十多天才返回寺里。他打开书房的门，只见书案上落满了灰尘，窗户上也布满了蜘蛛网。他叫来仆人打扫房间，一直到晚上才觉得屋子清爽了，可以坐下来了。于是，他掸掸床，铺好被褥，关上门躺下休息。这时，月光已满洒窗棂间。

他翻来覆去很久都无法入眠，四周静悄悄的，没有一点儿声音。忽然，他听到风声隆隆大作，山门也“砰”地发出巨响，他心道：一定是寺里的僧人忘记关门了。正在凝思驻想间，只听得风声离他住的屋子越来越近，不一会儿，房门自动打开了。他大为疑惑，但还没等想明白，风声已经进了屋。又听见穿着靴子的脚步声铿铿作响，逐渐靠近卧室的门。他开始感到恐怖。不一会儿，卧室的门也自动打开了，他猛然看过去，只见一个大鬼正弯腰挤进房里来。它耸立床前，几乎与房梁一样高；它的面孔是老瓜皮似的颜色，目光闪烁不定；它在房间里走来走去四下张望，张开如盆大口，稀疏的牙齿约有三寸长，舌头一动喉咙里就发出哗啦哗啦的声音，震得四面墙壁嗡嗡响。

孙公害怕极了，但想到卧室这样的方寸之地根本无处可逃，不如乘势刺杀它。于是，他偷偷从枕头下抽出佩刀，猛地拔出砍向大鬼，正好砍在大鬼的肚子上，发出撞击石缶似的声音。大鬼勃然大怒，伸出巨爪来抓他。孙公稍稍缩了缩身子，大鬼抓住被子揪扯着，气冲冲地离开了。

孙公随着被子掉在床下，趴在地上大声呼救。家人都拿着火把赶了过来，只见门和原先一样依然关着，就打开窗子跳了进去。见到孙公的样子，大家都吓了一大跳。家人将他搀扶到床上，他才将事情的原委说了一遍。大家一起查看，只见被子夹在卧室的门缝里。再打开门，就着火把查看，看到门上留有簸箕般大小的爪子印，五根手指抠着的地方将门板都穿透了。

等到天亮，孙公不敢再留下来，就背起书箱回去了。后来问僧人，他们说并没有再发生什么怪事。

[1] 旋里：返回故乡。

[2] 粪除：打扫，扫除。

[3] 扃（jiōng）扉：扃，原指关闭门户用的门闩，引申为关闭；扉，门扇。扃扉，指关门。

[4] 注念间：凝注思虑的时候。

[5] 睒（shǎn）闪：闪烁的样子。

[6] 呵喇：拟声词，形容喘气的声音。

[7] 遽：急速，匆忙。

[8] 捽（zuó）：揪扯。

[9] 笈：书箱。

偷桃

/

童时赴郡试，值春节。旧例，先一日，各行商贾，彩楼鼓吹赴藩司，名曰“演春”。余从友人戏瞩。

是日游人如堵。堂上四官，皆赤衣，东西相向坐。时方稚，亦不解其何官，但闻人语哜嘈[17]，鼓吹聒耳。忽有一人，率披发童，荷担而上，似有所白[18]；万声汹动，亦不闻其为何语，但视堂上作笑声。即有青衣人[19]大声命作剧。其人应命方兴，问：“作何剧？”堂上相顾数语。吏下宣问所长。答言：“能颠倒生物。”吏以白官。少顷复下，命取桃子。

术人应诺，解衣覆笥[20]上，故作怨状，曰：“官长殊不了了[21]！坚冰未解，安所得桃？不取，又恐为南面者怒。奈何！”其子曰：“父已诺之，又焉辞？”术人惆怅良久，乃曰：“我筹之烂熟。春初雪积，人间何处可觅？惟王母园中，四时常不凋谢，或有之。必窃之天上，乃可。”子曰：“嘻！天可阶而升乎？”曰：“有术在。”乃启笥，出绳一团，约数十丈，理其端，望空中掷去；绳即悬立空际，若有物以挂之。未几，愈掷愈高，渺入云中；手中绳亦尽。乃呼子曰：“儿来！余老惫，体重拙，不能行，得汝一往。”遂以绳授子，曰：“持此可登。”

子受绳，有难色，怨曰：“阿翁亦大愦愦[22]！如此一线之绳，欲我附之，以登万仞之高天。倘中道断绝，骸骨何存矣！”父又强呜拍之，曰：“我已失口，追悔无及，烦儿一行。儿勿苦，倘窃得来，必有百金赏，当为儿娶一美妇。”子乃持索，盘旋而上，手移足随，如蛛趁丝，渐入云霄，不可复见。

久之，坠一桃，如碗大。术人喜，持献公堂。堂上传示良久，亦不知其真伪。忽而绳落地上，术人惊曰：“殆矣！上有人断吾绳，儿将焉托！”移时，一物坠。视之，其子首也。捧而泣曰：“是必偷桃，为监者所觉。吾儿休矣！”又移时，一足落；无何[23]，肢体纷堕，无复存者。

术人大悲，一一拾置笥中而阖之，曰：“老夫止此儿，日从我南北游。今承严命，不意罹此奇惨！当负去瘗[24]之。”乃升堂而跪，曰：“为桃故，杀吾子矣！如怜小人而助之葬，当结草以图报耳。”坐官骇诧，各有赐金。术人受而缠诸腰，乃扣笥而呼曰：“八八儿，不出谢赏，将何待？”忽一蓬头童首抵笥盖而出，望北稽首，则其子也。

以其术奇，故至今犹记之。后闻白莲教能为此术，意此其苗裔耶？

译文

年少的时候，我曾去济南府参加府试。正好碰到春节，按照旧时风俗，春节的前一天，各行各业做生意的人要抬着彩楼，吹吹打打到藩司衙门去庆贺，这叫“演春”。我也跟着友人去看热闹。

这天游人众多，把四周围得像一堵堵墙。大堂上坐着四位官员，都穿着红色官袍，东西相对而坐。我当时年纪还小，也不知道他们是什么官，只听得人声嘈杂，鼓乐喧天，震耳欲聋。忽然，有一人领着一个披散着头发的小孩儿，挑着一副担子走了上来，好像说了几句话。当时人声鼎沸，也听不见他说了些什么，只看到堂上的人都在笑，随即有一名衙役大声吩咐他们进行表演。那人答应一声站起来，问道：“表演什么？”堂上的官员互相看看商量了几句，就有一名衙役走下堂来，问他们有什么拿手的表演。他回答说：“我能变出不按季节时令生长的植物。”衙役回到堂上禀告官员，过了一会儿又走下来，让他们表演取桃子。

变戏法的答应了，脱下衣服盖在竹箱上，故意装出一副埋怨的样子，说：“长官们太不明事理了，现在厚厚的冰还没有融化，到哪里能找到桃子呢？不去找的话，又怕当官的生气发怒，这可怎么办？”他儿子说：“父亲已经答应了，又怎能推托呢？”变戏法的人懊恼发愁了好一会儿，才说道：“我已想得很清楚，眼下还是初春时节，冰雪尚未融化，人间哪里能找到桃子？只有王母娘娘的桃园中四季如春，花木不会凋零，也许会有桃子。必须上天去偷才行。”儿子说：“嘻！天也能像爬台阶一样登上去吗？”变戏法的说：“我有办法。”于是打开竹箱，拿出一团有几十丈长的绳子。他理出绳子的一头，向空中抛去，绳子立刻立在了空中，好像挂在了什么东西上一样。不一会儿，绳子越升越高，隐约没入云彩中，他手中的绳子也放到了尽头。这时，变戏法的人叫来儿子，说：“孩子，你过来。我年老力衰，身体笨重，行动不灵便，爬不上去了，还得你上去一趟。”就将绳子头交给儿子，说：“抓着它可以爬上去。”

儿子接过绳子，面有难色，抱怨说：“父亲真是太糊涂了！这么一根细线似的绳子，想让我顺着它爬上万丈高空，如果半路上绳子断了，我岂非尸骨无存！”做父亲的又尽力哄劝，拍抚着他说：“我已经脱口答应了，后悔也来不及了，还是要麻烦你走一趟。你不要怕苦，万一能偷来桃子，定能得到上百两银子的赏赐，到时我一定给你娶个漂亮媳妇。”儿子这才抓着绳子，盘旋着向上攀爬，脚随着手向上移动，好像蜘蛛在丝网上爬行一样，渐渐没入云端看不见了。

过了好久，从天上掉下一个桃子，有碗口那么大。变戏法的人很高兴，拿着献到公堂上。堂上的官员传递着看了很久，也不知道桃子是真是假。忽然绳子掉落在地，变戏法的人大惊失色，说：“危险！天上有人弄断了我的绳子，我儿子靠什么下来啊？”过了一会儿，又有东西掉下来，一看，是他儿子的头。变戏法的人捧着儿子的头，哭着说：“这一定是偷桃子的时候被看守的人发现了，我儿子这回可完了。”又过了一会儿，掉下一只脚来；接着，四肢、躯干纷纷掉下来，再不可能活着了。

变戏法的人悲恸欲绝，一件一件捡起来放进竹箱里，并盖上盖子，说：“老汉只有这么一个儿子，每天跟着我走南闯北。今天因遵循长官们的命令去取桃，想不到遭遇这样的惨祸，我要将他背回去安葬。”于是，他走到堂上，跪下说道：“因为桃子的缘故，我儿子被杀了。大人们如果可怜小人，帮助我安葬了他，我即使死了也要报答各位大人的恩情。”堂上的官员惊骇不已，各自拿出银钱赏赐他。变戏法的人接过钱缠在腰上，然后拍了拍竹箱说：“八八儿，不出来谢各位大人的赏赐，还等什么呢？”忽然，一个披头散发的小孩用头顶开箱盖，从里面爬了出来，朝北面大堂上的官员们叩头。一看，正是变戏法老汉的儿子。

因为这个戏法太神奇了，所以直到现在我都记得。后来听说白莲教能表演这样的法术，这父子二人是白莲教的后人吧？

[17] 哜（jì）嘈：形容人声杂乱。

[18] 白：禀告，报告。

[19] 青衣人：指衙役，皂隶。

[20] 笥（sì）：盛饭或衣物的方形竹器。

[21] 了了：指心里明白，通达事理。

[22] 愦愦：糊涂。

[23] 无何：不久，很短时间之后。

[24] 瘗（yì）：掩埋，埋葬。

狐嫁女

/

历城殷天官，少贫，有胆略。邑有故家之第，广数十亩，楼宇连亘。常见怪异，以故废无居人；久之，蓬蒿渐满，白昼亦无敢入者。会公与诸生饮，或戏云：“有能寄此一宿者，共醵[31]为筵。”公跃起曰：“是亦何难！”携一席往。众送诸门，戏曰：“吾等暂候之，如有所见，当急号。”公笑云：“有鬼狐，当捉证耳。”

遂入，见长莎[32]蔽径，蒿艾如麻。时值上弦，幸月色昏黄，门户可辨。摩娑数进，始抵后楼。登月台，光洁可爱，遂止焉。西望月明，惟衔山一线耳。坐良久，更无少异，窃笑传言之讹。席地枕石，卧看牛女。

一更向尽，恍惚欲寐，楼下有履声，籍籍而上。假寐睨之，见一青衣人，挑莲灯，猝见公，惊而却退。语后人曰：“有生人在。”下问：“谁何？”答云：“不识。”俄一老翁上，就公谛视，曰：“此殷尚书，其睡已酣。但办吾事，相公倜傥，或不叱怪。”乃相率入楼，楼门尽辟。移时，往来者益众。楼上灯辉如昼。

公稍稍转侧，作嚏咳。翁闻公醒，乃出，跪而言曰：“小人有箕帚女[33]，今值于归。不意有触贵人，望勿深罪。”公起，曳之曰：“不知今夕嘉礼，惭无以贺。”翁曰：“贵人光临，压除凶煞，幸矣。即烦陪坐，倍益光宠。”公喜，应之。入视楼中，陈设绮丽。遂有妇人出拜，年可四十余。翁曰：“此拙荆。”公揖之。

俄闻笙乐聒耳，有奔而上者，曰：“至矣！”翁趋迎，公亦立俟。少间，笼纱[34]一簇，导新郎入。年可十七八，丰采韶秀。翁命先与贵客为礼。少年目公。公若为傧，执半主礼。次翁婿交拜，已，乃即席。少间，粉黛云从，酒胾雾霈[35]，玉碗金瓯，光映几案。酒数行，翁唤女奴请小姐来。女奴诺而入，良久不出。翁自起，搴[36]帏促之。俄婢媪辈拥新人出，环佩璆然[37]，麝兰散馥。翁命向上拜。起，即坐母侧。微目之，翠凤明珰，容华绝世。

既而酌以金爵，大容数斗。公思此物可以持验同人，阴内袖中。伪醉隐几[38]，颓然而寝。皆曰：“相公醉矣。”居无何，新郎告行，笙乐暴作，纷纷下楼而去。已而主人敛酒具，小一爵，冥搜不得。或窃议卧客；翁急戒勿语，惟恐公闻。

移时，内外俱寂，公始起。暗无灯火，惟脂香酒气，充溢四堵。视东方既白，乃从容出。探袖中，金爵犹在。及门，则诸生先候，疑其夜出而早入者。公出爵示之。众骇问，公以状告。共思此物非寒士所有，乃信之。

后公举进士，任肥丘。有世家朱姓宴公，命取巨觥，久之不至。有细奴掩口与主人语，主人有怒色。俄奉金爵劝客饮。谛视之，款式雕文，与狐物更无殊别。大疑，问所从制。答云：“爵凡八只，大人为京卿时，觅良工监制。此世传物，什袭[39]已久。缘明府辱临，适取诸箱簏，仅存其七，疑家人所窃取；而十年尘封如故，殊不可解。”公笑曰：“金杯羽化矣。然世守之珍不可失。仆有一具，颇近似之，当以奉赠。”终筵归署，拣爵持送之。主人审视，骇绝。亲诣谢公，诘所自来。公为历陈颠末。始知千里之物，狐能摄致，而不敢终留也。

译文

山东历城的殷尚书，年轻时家中贫寒，但他有胆量有见识。县里有一处世家大族的宅院，占地几十亩，里面的亭台楼阁连成一片。因为那里经常发生怪异的事，所以被荒废了，无人居住。时间长了，宅院里渐渐长满了蓬蒿，即使白天也没人敢进去。一天，殷公与一群生员在一起喝酒，有人开玩笑说：“如果有人能在那里住一宿，大家就一起凑钱请他吃桌酒席。”殷公一跃而起，说：“这有什么难的！”当晚就带着一张席子过去了。大家将他送到门口，开玩笑说：“我们暂且在这里等着，如果你见到什么鬼狐精怪，赶紧呼救。”殷公笑着说：“如果有鬼狐的话，我一定捉住它做个证明。”

于是殷公走进院子，只见高高的莎草掩隐了路径，蒿艾也长得密密麻麻。这时正是初七初八的样子，幸好有昏黄的月光，勉强可以分辨出门户。殷公摸索着走过几重院落，才到了后面的楼阁。登上月台，见上面光洁可爱，就停了下来。再看看西边的月亮，已落到山后，只留下一线余晖。殷公坐了好久，并无一点儿异常，心中暗笑传言的荒谬。他在地上铺上席子，枕着石头，仰面躺下观赏起天边的牛郎织女星。

一更将尽的时候，殷公迷迷糊糊快睡着了，楼下忽传来杂乱的脚步声，有人上楼来了。殷公假装睡着了，斜眼看去，是一个身穿青衣提着莲花灯的人。这人猛然看见殷公，吓了一跳往后退去，对后面的人说：“有个陌生人在上面。”下面的人问：“是谁？”他回答道：“不认识。”不一会儿，一老翁上来，靠近殷公仔细看了看，说：“这是殷尚书，他已睡熟了。只管办我们的事吧，殷相公洒脱不拘小节，或许不会责怪我们。”于是众人相继上了楼，将楼上的门都打开了。又过了一会儿，来来往往的人越来越多，楼上灯火辉煌，如同白昼。

殷公轻轻翻了个身，打了个喷嚏。老翁听到他醒了，赶快走出来并跪下说道：“小人有个女儿，今晚出嫁。想不到冒犯了贵人，还望不要怪罪。”殷公起身，将他扶起来，说：“不知道贵府今晚有喜事，很抱歉没有奉上贺礼。”老翁说：“贵人大驾光临，能压除凶神恶煞，我们已经很荣幸。如果能麻烦您入座陪客，那更是加倍的荣光。”殷公很高兴，就答应了。进楼一看，屋内陈设很华丽。又有妇人出来拜见，年纪四十几岁。老翁说：“这是我妻子。”殷公也拱手还礼。

一会儿，听到笙管鼓乐震耳欲聋，有人跑上来说：“来了！”老翁急忙快步上前迎接，殷公也站起来等候。不一会儿，好多灯笼引导着新郎走了进来。他年纪十七八岁，相貌俊雅，风度翩翩。老翁让他先给殷公行礼。新郎看着殷公，殷公像代主人迎接宾客的傧相一样，还了半主礼。接着翁婿互拜，拜完后才入席。又过了一会儿，年轻美貌的丫鬟侍女们一个接一个送上热气蒸腾的美酒佳肴，玉碗金杯，光芒映照在酒桌上。酒过数巡，老翁让侍女请小姐过来。侍女应声而去，但过了好久也没出来。老翁亲自起身，掀起帏幔进去催促。一会儿，几个丫鬟仆妇簇拥着新娘走了出来，新娘身上的环佩叮当作响，兰麝之香四溢。老翁让女儿向上座贵客行礼，新娘礼毕起身后就坐在了母亲身边。殷公稍微看了一眼，只见她髻插翡翠凤钗，耳戴明珠耳坠，容颜艳丽，举世无双。

随后用金爵斟酒，金爵大得能装下好几斗的酒。殷公心想这个东西可以拿回去向同窗们做证，就偷偷藏在了袖子中。他假装醉酒倚靠在几案上，好像萎靡不振地睡着了。众人都说：“殷相公醉了。”没过多久，听见新郎辞行，笙管鼓乐猛然间又响了起来，大家纷纷离席下楼而去。过后主人收拾酒具，发现少了一个金爵，四处寻找也没找到。有人私下议论可能为醉卧的殷公所拿，老翁急忙告诫大家不要乱说，唯恐殷公听见。

又过了一阵，内外都已寂静无声，殷公这才起来。周围一片黑暗，没有一点儿灯火，只有脂粉的芳香、浓郁的酒气弥漫在室内。看东方已发白，殷公才不慌不忙走出来，伸手摸摸袖子，金爵还在。殷公到了门口，众生员已经先等候在那里，都怀疑他是夜里出来早晨又进去的。殷公拿出金爵给大家看，众人惊讶地询问，殷公就将自己的所见所闻告诉他们。大家都认为金爵这么贵重的东西非贫寒的读书人所能拥有，于是都相信了他的话。

后来殷公中了进士，在肥丘任职。当地的世家大族朱氏宴请殷公，让家人去取大酒杯，过了好久也没拿来。有个小童捂着嘴与主人说了几句话，主人面有怒色。不一会儿捧来金爵劝殷公饮酒。殷公仔细一看，金爵的款式及上面雕刻的图案，与狐狸的金爵毫无差别。他心中十分疑惑，就问主人金爵是什么地方制造的。朱氏回答说：“金爵一共八个，是我祖上做京官时找能工巧匠打造的。这是家传宝物，已珍藏很久。因为大人大驾光临，刚才从竹箱里取出来，仅剩下七只，怀疑是家里人偷走了。但十年间灰尘厚积，与原来一样，实在无法解释。”殷公笑着说：“你那只金爵羽化成仙了，但家传的珍宝不能丢失了。我也有一只，与您的金爵很相似，我要赠送与您。”散席后，殷公回到官署，找出金爵并派人送了过去。朱氏拿着金爵反复查看，非常震惊，亲自到官署感谢殷公，并询问金爵的来历。殷公就将事情的原委一一讲给他听。这才知道千里以外的东西，狐狸也能取来，但终究不敢留下。

[31] 醵（jù）：凑钱。

[32] 莎（suō）：指莎草，多年生草本植物，地下的块根称“香附子”，可入药，此处泛指野草。

[33] 箕帚女：旧时谦称自己的女儿缺乏才貌，只能胜任家务粗活。箕帚，泛指家中洒扫之事。

[34] 笼纱：用绢纱做外罩的灯笼。

[35] 酒胾（zì）雾霈：美酒佳肴，热气蒸腾。酒胾，酒与肉，泛指酒肴。雾霈，热气蒸腾的样子。

[36] 搴（qiān）：撩起。

[37] 璆（qiú）然：形容佩玉相击之声。

[38] 隐（yìn）几：倚靠着几案。

[39] 什袭：原指将物品一层层地包裹起来，后形容珍重地收藏。

鬼哭

/

谢迁之变[40]，宦第皆为贼窟。王学使七襄之宅，盗聚尤众。城破兵入，扫荡群丑，尸填墀[41]，血至充门而流。公入城，扛尸涤血而居。往往白昼见鬼；夜则床下磷飞，墙角鬼哭。

一日，王生皞迪，寄宿公家，闻床底小声连呼：“皞迪！皞迪！”已而声渐大，曰：“我死得苦！”因哭，满庭皆哭。公闻，仗剑而入，大言曰：“汝不识我王学院耶？”但闻百声嗤嗤，笑之以鼻。公于是设水陆道场，命释道忏度之。夜抛鬼饭，则见磷火荧荧，随地皆出。

先是，阍人[42]王姓疾笃[43]，昏不知人事者数日矣。是夕，忽欠伸若醒。妇以食进。王曰：“适主人不知何事施饭于庭，我亦随众啖噉[44]。食已方归，故不饥耳。”由此鬼怪遂绝。岂钹铙钟鼓[45]，焰口瑜伽[46]，果有益耶？

译文

谢迁起义时，官宦之家都被贼寇占据，学使王七襄家里聚集的盗贼尤其多。官兵破城后，扫荡搜杀叛乱的人，死尸躺满了台阶，血一直流到大门口。王学使进城回到家里，扛出尸体，洗净血污，这才住了下来。但常常大白天也能看到鬼，一到夜晚，床下鬼火乱飞，墙角鬼哭之声不断。

一天，有个叫王皞迪的书生借住在王公家，听到床底有细小的声音连连呼喊他：“皞迪！皞迪！”随即声音越来越大，并且说道：“我死得好苦啊！”又哭起来，于是满院子都是啼哭声。王公听见后，拿着宝剑冲入王生屋里，大声说：“你们不认识我王学院吗？”却只听见众鬼哧哧冷笑。王公没有办法，只好设了水陆道场，让和尚、道士念经超度这些亡魂。夜里又将饭抛撒在院子里让群鬼吃，只见磷火飞来飞去，到处都是。

此前，王公家的一个王姓看门人病情严重，已昏迷数天不省人事。这天晚上，他忽然伸了伸懒腰，好像刚睡醒的样子。他妻子给他端来食物，他说：“刚才主人不知道为什么在院子里施饭，我也跟着大家一起吃了。吃完才回来的，所以现在不觉得饿。”从此以后鬼怪就绝迹了。难道和尚道士们奏乐作法、放焰口念经超度亡魂，果然有效果吗？

[40] 谢迁之变：指顺治初年谢迁领导的一次农民起义。

[41] 墀（chí）：台阶上的空地，亦指台阶。

[42] 阍人：守门人。

[43] 疾笃：病情严重。

[44] 噉（dàn）：同“啖”，吃或给人吃。

[45] 钹铙钟鼓：法会上僧众所使用的四种法器。钹、铙，圆形的铜质打击乐器，为两个圆铜片，中心鼓起呈半球形，正中有孔，可以穿绸条等用以持握，两片相击作声。小的叫钹，大的叫铙。

[46] 焰口瑜伽（qié）：指招僧众做佛事以超度亡魂。焰口，佛经中饿鬼名。密宗对饿鬼施食超度的仪式，称为“放焰口”。瑜伽，指瑜伽僧，即密宗僧侣。

焦螟

/

董侍读默庵家，为狐所扰，瓦砾砖石，忽如雹落，家人相率奔匿，待其间歇，乃敢出操作。公患之，假[47]怍庭孙司马[48]第移避之。而狐扰犹故。

一日，朝中待漏[49]，适言其异。大臣或言：关东道士焦螟，居内城，总持敕勒之术[50]，颇有效。公造庐而请之。道士朱书符，使归粘壁上。狐竟不惧，抛掷有加焉。公复告道士。道士怒，亲诣公家，筑坛作法。俄见一巨狐，伏坛下。家人受虐已久，衔恨綦[51]甚，一婢近击之。婢忽仆地气绝。

道士曰：“此物猖獗，我尚不能遽服之，女子何轻犯尔尔。”既而曰：“可借鞫[52]狐词亦得。”戟指[53]咒移时，婢忽起，长跪。道士诘其里居。婢作狐言：“我西域产，入都者十八辈。”道士曰：“辇毂下[54]，何容尔辈久居？可速去！”狐不答。

道士击案怒曰：“汝欲梗吾令耶？再若迁延，法不汝宥[55]！”狐乃蹙怖作色，愿谨奉教。道士又速之。婢又仆绝，良久始苏。俄见白块四五团，滚滚如毬，附檐际而行，次第追逐，顷刻俱去。由是遂安。

译文

翰林院侍读学士董默庵家中被狐狸骚扰，砖瓦沙石经常忽然间像下冰雹一样落下来，一家人只好纷纷奔跑躲藏，等到狐狸停下来才敢出来干活。董公深感忧虑，借了司马孙祚庭的宅子搬过去躲避，但狐狸仍像以前一样来骚扰。

一天，董公在朝房等候上朝时，与同僚们谈起这件怪事。有位大臣说，关东道士焦螟，现在居住在内城，他会道教画符降妖的法术，非常灵验。董公于是登门拜访焦螟，请他帮忙降妖。道士用朱砂画了一道符，让董公回去后贴在墙上。狐狸竟然不害怕，还变本加厉地抛掷砖石。没有办法，董公只好又去告诉道士。道士大怒，亲自来到董公家，筑起神坛，施展法术。不一会儿，只见一只大狐狸趴在了神坛下。董家人受害很久，对狐狸恨之入骨，一个丫鬟上前击打它，却忽然倒在地上没有了呼吸。

道士说：“这个狐狸非常猖獗，我都不能一下子降伏它，一个女子怎么敢轻易冒犯它呢？”接着又说道：“正好我可以借这个丫鬟之口来审问狐狸，也是个办法。”于是，他伸出食指与中指，念起咒语。过了一会儿，丫鬟忽然从地上爬起来，直身跪在坛前。道士问它住在哪里，丫鬟发出狐狸的声音说：“我出生在西域，来京城已经十八辈子了。”道士说：“京城里，哪里容得下你们长久居住？赶快离开吧。”狐狸没有回答。

道士大怒，拍着桌子说：“你还想违抗我的命令吗？如果再拖延，道法绝不饶恕你！”狐狸这才面露恐惧之色，表示愿意遵守教令。道士又催它快走。丫鬟这时又倒地没了呼吸，过了很久才苏醒过来。又过了一会儿，只见四五个白色团块，圆滚滚的像球一样，贴着屋檐边儿，一个挨着一个依次相随，转眼间都离开了。从此董公家就安宁下来了。

[47] 假：借。

[48] 怍庭孙司马：指孙光祀，字溯玉，号祚庭，平阴人。顺治乙未进士，历任礼科给事中、兵部右侍郎等职。怍，当作“祚”。

[49] 待漏：指官员们五更前到朝房等待上朝的时刻。漏指铜壶滴漏，古代计时器，此处代指时间。

[50] 敕勒之术：道士画符咒驱鬼怪的法术。因画符咒时，上书“时令”“敕勒”字样，因此被用来代称符咒。

[51] 綦（qí）：极，很。

[52] 鞫（jū）：审问犯人。

[53] 戟指：伸出或竖起食指和中指。

[54] 辇毂（niǎn gǔ）下：天子的车驾之下，代指京城。辇毂，天子的车驾，用以指天子。

[55] 宥：宽恕，原谅。

张老相公

/

张老相公，晋人。适将嫁女，携眷至江南，躬市奁妆。舟抵金山，张先渡江，嘱家人在舟，勿煿[56]膻腥。盖江中有鼋怪，闻香辄出，坏舟吞行人，为害已久。

张去，家人忘之，炙肉舟中。忽巨浪覆舟，妻女皆没。张回棹，悼恨欲死。因登金山，谒寺僧，询鼋之异，将以仇鼋。僧闻之，骇言：“吾侪日与习近，惧为祸殃，惟神明奉之，祈勿怒；时斩牲牢，投以半体，则跃吞而去。谁复能相仇哉！”

张闻，顿思得计。便招铁工，起炉山半，冶赤铁，重百余斤。审知所常伏处，使二三健男子，以大钳举投之。鼋跃出，疾吞而下。少时，波涌如山。顷之浪息，则鼋死已浮水上矣。

行旅寺僧并快之，建张老相公祠，肖像其中，以为水神，祷之辄应。

译文

张老相公是山西人，因为女儿将要出嫁，就携带家眷到江南一带，亲自为女儿置办嫁妆。船到镇江金山时，张老相公准备先过江，就嘱咐家里人在船上不要烹饪有腥膻气味的食物。因为江中有大鼋作怪，它闻到香味就会出来，毁坏船只、吞食行人，在此已为害很久。

张老相公离开后，家里人忘记了他的嘱咐，在船上烤肉。忽然滔天巨浪将船打翻，张老相公的妻子女儿都落水沉没。等张老相公驾船返回得知消息，他悲伤痛恨，几不欲独活。他登上金山，拜见金山寺的和尚，打听大鼋的怪异之事，准备找大鼋报仇。僧人们听了非常害怕，说：“我们每天与它相邻，担心被它祸害，只好将它当神仙一样供奉着，祈祷它不要发怒。经常屠宰牲畜，半只半只地扔到江中，大鼋就会跳出水面吞食。谁还敢跟它作对啊？”

张老相公听后，立刻想出了报仇的办法。他找来几个铁匠，在金山的半山腰建起冶炼炉，炼成一块百余斤重的大铁块。问清大鼋经常出没的地方，让两三位身强力壮的男子，用大铁钳举起铁块投入江中。大鼋跳出水面，快速将铁块吞下又沉入水底。不一会儿，江面波涛汹涌，浪高如山。又过了一会儿，波平浪息，大鼋的尸体浮上水面。

过往的旅客、寺中的僧人都很高兴，修建了张相公祠，并在祠内塑了他的像。人们将他当作水神供奉，向他祈愿都很灵验。

[56] 煿（bó）：煎炒或烘烤食物。

翩翩

/

罗子浮，邠人。父母俱早世。八九岁，依叔大业。业为国子左厢[75]，富有金缯而无子，爱罗若己出。

十四岁，为匪人诱去作狭邪游[76]。会有金陵娼，侨寓郡中，生悦而惑之。娼返金陵，生窃从遁去。居娼家半年，床头金尽，大为姊妹行齿冷。然犹未遽绝之。无何，广疮[77]溃臭，沾染床席，逐而出。丐于市，市人见辄遥避。自恐死异域，乞食西行；日三四十里，渐至邠界。又念败絮脓秽，无颜入里门，尚趑趄[78]近邑间。

日就暮，欲趋山寺宿。遇一女子，容貌若仙。近问：“何适？”生以实告。女曰：“我出家人，居有山洞，可以下榻，颇不畏虎狼。”生喜，从去。入深山中，见一洞府。入则门横溪水，石梁驾之。又数武[79]，有石室二，光明彻照，无须灯烛。命生解悬鹑[80]，浴于溪流，曰：“濯之，疮当愈。”又开幛拂褥促寝，曰：“请即眠，当为郎作裤。”乃取大叶类芭蕉，剪缀作衣。生卧视之。制无几时，折迭床头，曰：“晓取着之。”乃与对榻寝。

生浴后，觉疮疡无苦。既醒，摸之，则痂厚结矣。诘旦，将兴，心疑蕉叶不可着。取而审视，则绿锦滑绝。少间，具餐。女取山叶呼作饼，食之，果饼；又剪作鸡、鱼烹之，皆如真者。室隅一罂，贮佳酝，辄复取饮；少减，则以溪水灌益之。数日，疮痂尽脱，就女求宿。女曰：“轻薄儿！甫能安身，便生妄想！”生云：“聊以报德。”遂同卧处，大相欢爱。

一日，有少妇笑入曰：“翩翩小鬼头快活死！薛姑子好梦，几时做得？”女迎笑曰：“花城娘子，贵趾久弗涉，今日西南风紧，吹送来也！小哥子抱得未？”曰：“又一小婢子。”女笑曰：“花娘子瓦窑[81]哉！那弗将来？”曰：“方呜之，睡却矣。”于是坐以款饮。又顾生曰：“小郎君焚好香也。”生视之，年二十有三四，绰有余妍。心好之。剥果误落案下，俯地假拾果，阴捻翘凤。花城他顾而笑，若不知者。生方恍然神夺，顿觉袍裤无温；自顾所服，悉成秋叶。几骇绝。危坐移时，渐变如故。窃幸二女之弗见也。

少顷，酬酢[82]间，又以指搔纤掌。花城坦然笑谑，殊不觉知。突突[83]怔忡间，衣已化叶，移时始复变。由是惭颜息虑，不敢妄想。花城笑曰：“而家小郎子，大不端好！若弗是醋葫芦娘子，恐跳迹入云霄去。”女亦哂曰：“薄幸儿，便值得寒冻杀！”相与鼓掌。花城离席曰：“小婢醒，恐啼肠断矣。”女亦起曰：“贪引他家男儿，不忆得小江城啼绝矣。”花城既去，惧贻诮责；女卒晤对如平时。居无何，秋老风寒，霜零木脱，女乃收落叶，蓄旨御冬。顾生肃缩，乃持襆[84]掇拾洞口白云为絮复衣，着之温暖如襦，且轻松常如新绵。

逾年，生一子，极惠美。日在洞中弄儿为乐。然每念故里，乞与同归。女曰：“妾不能从；不然，君自去。”因循二三年，儿渐长，遂与花城订为姻好。生每以叔老为念。女曰：“阿叔腊[85]故大高，幸复强健，无劳悬耿。待保儿婚后，去住由君。”女在洞中，辄取叶写书，教儿读，儿过目即了。女曰：“此儿福相，放教入尘寰，无忧至台阁。”

未几，儿年十四，花城亲诣送女。女华妆至，容光照人。夫妻大悦，举家宴集。翩翩扣钗而歌曰：“我有佳儿，不羡贵官。我有佳妇，不羡绮纨。今夕聚首，皆当喜欢。为君行酒，劝君加餐。”既而花城去，与儿夫妇对室居。新妇孝，依依膝下，宛如所生。

生又言归。女曰：“子有俗骨，终非仙品。儿亦富贵中人，可携去，我不误儿生平。”新妇思别其母，花城已至。儿女恋恋，涕各满眶。两母慰之曰：“暂去，可复来。”翩翩乃剪叶为驴，令三人跨之以归。

大业已归老林下，意侄已死，忽携佳孙美妇归，喜如获宝。入门，各视所衣，悉蕉叶；破之，絮蒸蒸腾去。乃并易之。

后生思翩翩，偕儿往探之，则黄叶满径，洞口路迷，零涕而返。

译文

罗子浮是邠州人，父母都早早去世了，八九岁时就由叔叔罗大业抚养。大业为国子监祭酒，家境富有但没有儿子，他很疼爱罗子浮，把他当作自己的亲生儿子一样。

罗子浮十四岁时，被坏人引诱着狎妓宿娼。当时有个从金陵来的妓女侨居本郡，子浮很喜欢她，被她迷住了。当妓女返回金陵时，罗子浮也偷偷跟着她逃离了家乡。他在妓院住了半年，钱财都用光了，被妓女们嘲笑、嫌弃，但他并没有被立即赶走。不久，罗子浮身上的梅毒疮溃烂发臭，弄脏了床褥席子，终于被妓院赶了出来。他只能在街市上乞讨，街上的人见到他都远远地躲开。罗子浮担心自己客死他乡，便一边讨饭一边西行，每天走三四十里，渐渐到了邠州地界。又想到自己衣衫褴褛，一身脓疮污秽不堪，实在没脸回家，就先滞留在邻近的县里。

一天傍晚，罗子浮打算去山中寺庙投宿，路上遇到一位女子，容颜美丽如仙女一般。女子上前问道：“你要去哪里？”罗子浮如实相告。女子说：“我是出家人，住的地方有山洞，你可以住下来，不用担心有虎狼相害。”罗子浮很高兴，跟着女子去了。进入深山中，看到一个洞府，进去后看到门前横淌着一条小溪，上面架着小石桥。又走了几步，有两间石室，室内非常光亮，不需要点灯烛。女子让罗子浮脱去破烂衣服在溪水中沐浴，说：“洗洗吧，身上的毒疮自然会痊愈。”又打开帷幛，铺好被褥，催促罗子浮去睡觉，说道：“你赶快睡吧，我要给你做套衣裤。”于是取来像芭蕉叶一样的大叶子，裁剪后缝起来做衣服，罗子浮躺在床上看着。过了一会儿，衣服便缝好了，女子将衣服折叠整齐放在他床头，说：“早上起床后穿上吧。”说完，便在对面的床上睡下了。

罗子浮洗浴后，感觉身上的烂疮不疼了。醒来后一摸，已经结了厚厚的痂。清晨准备起床时，他心里怀疑叶子做的衣服没法儿穿，取过来仔细一看，却是绿色锦缎，非常光滑。过了一会儿准备吃早餐，女子拿来山叶说是饼，一吃果然是饼；又将叶子剪成鸡、鱼的样子烹饪，都跟真的一样。室内一角存放着一坛好酒，女子一次次取来饮用，坛中美酒稍微少一些，她就将溪水灌进去补充。过了几天，罗子浮身上的疮痂都脱落了，他靠近女子恳请同宿。女子说：“你这个轻薄的人，刚能安身，就开始胡思乱想。”罗子浮说：“我只是想以此报答你的恩德。”于是二人同床而眠，非常愉悦开心。

一天，有一少妇笑着进来，说：“翩翩小鬼头快活死了，你们俩何时做成的好事啊？”翩翩迎上去笑着说：“原来是花城娘子。你这贵客可是好久没有光临此地了，今天定是西南风吹得紧，将你吹过来了。抱上儿子没有？”花城说：“又是个小丫头。”翩翩笑着说：“花城娘子真是个瓦窑啊。怎么没有将孩子带来啊？”花城说：“刚刚哄了她一会儿，已经睡下了。”于是三人一齐落座，慢慢饮酒。花城又看着罗子浮说：“小郎君烧高香了。”罗子浮见她二十三四岁，风姿绰约、容貌秀美，心里很喜欢。剥果实时不小心将果子掉到桌子底下，他俯身假装拾果子，偷偷捏了一下花城的小脚。花城看着别处笑笑，好像什么都不知道。罗子浮正在神魂颠倒间，忽然觉得身上的衣服裤子都不暖和了，低头一看，自己穿的衣服已都变成了秋叶。他差点吓死，赶紧坐端正，过了一会儿，身上的衣服才慢慢变回原来的样子，他暗自庆幸两位女子没看见。

又过了一会儿，罗子浮在给花城敬酒时，又用手指挠她的掌心。花城坦然地说笑戏谑，好像完全没有感觉。正在罗子浮心神不宁、心怦怦乱跳时，身上的衣服又已变成了叶子。过了一会儿才又变回来。罗子浮满面羞惭，这才打消杂念，再不敢胡思乱想。花城笑着说：“你家小郎君太不正经了。如果不是醋葫芦娘子拘管得严，他大概早跳到云端逍遥快活了。”翩翩也讥笑说：“这个轻薄的人，就应该活活被冻死。”两人拍掌大笑。花城离席说：“小丫头醒来，恐怕要哭断肠子了。”翩翩也起身说：“你只顾勾引别人的男人，就想不起小江城会哭死了。”花城走后，罗子浮害怕翩翩嘲笑责骂他，但翩翩仍像平时一样对待他。

住了不久，已到深秋季节，寒风阵阵，霜降叶落，翩翩就捡拾起落叶，储存食物准备过冬。她看到罗子浮冻得瑟瑟发抖，就拿着个包袱，收集起洞口的白云，铺在衣服里做成棉衣。罗子浮穿在身上，暖和得像穿了短袄一样，并且轻软蓬松，就跟新棉衣一样。

过了一年，翩翩生了个儿子，非常聪明漂亮，罗子浮每天的乐趣就是在山洞里逗弄儿子。但他常常想念家乡，恳请翩翩跟他一起回去。翩翩说：“我不能跟你回去，要不你就自己回去吧。”这样拖延了两三年，儿子渐渐长大，翩翩就与花城结成了亲家。罗子浮常常牵挂年迈的叔叔，翩翩说：“叔叔虽然年纪大了，但身体还很强健，用不着你挂念。等保儿结婚后，是走是留，你自己决定。”翩翩在山洞用树叶写字，教儿子读书，儿子一看就明白了。翩翩说：“这孩子有福相，让他到人世间，不愁做不到台阁大臣这样的高官。”

又过了几年，他们的儿子十四岁了，花城亲自将女儿送来完婚。只见花城之女衣着华美，容貌艳丽，夫妻二人都很高兴，合家团聚设宴庆贺。翩翩敲着钗环唱道：“我有好儿郎，不羡做高官。我有好儿媳，不羡穿绣锦。今晚聚一起，大家都喜欢。为君斟满酒，劝君多进餐。”酒后，花城离去，翩翩夫妇与儿子儿媳对门住着。新媳妇很孝顺，依恋在翩翩膝下，犹如亲生女儿一样。

罗子浮又说要回去，翩翩说：“你有俗骨，终究不能成仙。儿子也是富贵中人，你可将他带回去，我不耽误他的前程。”新媳妇正想着要与母亲告别，花城已经来了。小儿女对他们的母亲恋恋不舍，眼泪盈眶。翩翩与花城都安慰说：“你们暂时离开，以后还可以回来。”翩翩就将树叶剪成毛驴，让三人骑上回家去。

罗大业此时已告老还乡，他以为侄子早已死了，忽见罗子浮带着英俊的孙子、美貌的孙媳回来，欢喜得像得到了宝贝。罗子浮三人入门后，再看看自己所穿的衣服，都已变成了蕉叶。扯破蕉叶，里面充作棉絮的白云也升到了天空。于是，三人都换了衣服。

后来罗子浮思念翩翩，带着儿子回去探望，只见路上落满了黄叶，再也找不到通往洞口的路，父子二人只能流着泪回了家。

[75] 国子左厢：明清时国子监祭酒的别称。

[76] 狭邪游：冶游，狎妓。

[77] 广疮：即梅毒。据说此病最先由粤广通商口岸传入，因称“广疮”。

[78] 趑趄：滞留，徘徊不前。

[79] 武：半步，泛指脚步。

[80] 悬鹑：鹌鹑毛斑尾秃，似披敝衣，因以“悬鹑”比喻衣服破烂。

[81] 瓦窑：烧制砖瓦的窑，用以戏称生女不生男的妇女，因称生女为“弄瓦”，故云。

[82] 酬酢：主客相互敬酒，主敬客称酬，客还敬称酢。

[83] 突突：形容心跳剧烈。

[84] 襆：同“袱”，包袱。

[85] 腊：古代在农历十二月合祭众神叫作腊，因以纪年，此指年岁。

余德

/

武昌尹图南，有别第，尝为一秀才税居[87]。半年来，亦未尝过问。一日，遇诸其门，年最少，而容仪裘马，翩翩甚都[88]。趋与语，却又蕴藉[89]可爱。异之。归语妻。妻遣婢托遗问以窥其室。室有丽姝，美艳逾于仙人；一切花石服玩，俱非耳目所经。

尹不测其何人，诣门投谒，适值他出。翼日，却来拜答，展其刺呼[90]，始知余姓德名。语次，细审官阀，言殊隐约。固诘之，则曰：“欲相还往，仆不敢自绝。应知非寇窃逋逃者，何须必知来历。”尹谢之。命酒款宴，言笑甚欢。向暮，有昆仑[91]捉马挑灯，迎导以去。

明日，折简报主人。尹至其家，见屋壁俱用明光纸裱，洁如镜。金狻猊[92]爇[93]异香。一碧玉瓶，插凤尾孔雀羽各二，各长二尺余。一水晶瓶，浸粉花一树，不知何名，亦高二尺许，垂枝覆几外；叶疏花密，含苞未吐；花状似湿蝶敛翼；蒂即如须。

筵间不过八簋，丰美异常。即命童子击鼓催花为令。鼓声既动，则瓶中花颤颤欲折；俄而蝶翅渐张；既而鼓歇，渊然[94]一声，蒂须顿落，即为一蝶，飞落尹衣。余笑起，飞一巨觥；酒方引满，蝶亦飏去。顷之，鼓又作，两蝶飞集余冠。余笑云：“作法自毙矣。”亦引二觥。三鼓既终，花乱堕，翩翩而下，惹袖沾衿。鼓童笑来指数：尹得九筹，余得四筹。尹已薄醉，不能尽筹，强引三爵，离席亡去。由是益奇之。

然其为人寡交与，每阖门居，不与国人通吊庆[95]。尹逢人辄宣；闻其异者，争交欢余，门外冠盖相望。余颇不耐，忽辞主人去。去后，尹入其家，空庭洒扫无纤尘；烛泪堆掷青阶下；窗间零帛断绵，指印宛然。惟舍后遗一小白石缸，可受石许。尹携归，贮水养朱鱼。经年，水清如初贮。后为佣保移石，误碎之。水蓄并不倾泻。视之，缸宛在，扪之虚耎。手入其中，水随手泄；出其手，则复合。冬月不冰。一夜，忽结为晶，鱼游如故。

尹畏人知，常置密室，非子婿不以示也。久之渐播，索玩者纷错于门。腊月，忽解为水，阴湿满地，鱼亦渺然。其旧缸残石犹存。忽有道士踵门求之。尹出以示。道士曰：“此龙宫蓄水器也。”尹述其破而不泄之异。道士曰：“此缸之魂也。”殷殷然乞得少许。问其何用，曰：“以屑合药，可得永寿。”予一片，欢谢而去。

译文

武昌尹图南有一处宅院，曾租给一个秀才居住，半年多也没过问过此事。一天，尹图南在宅子门口遇到秀才，只见他非常年轻，容仪俊美，衣着华丽，风度翩翩。尹图南上前与他交谈，又觉得他谈吐优雅，令人喜爱。尹图南认为此人很特别，回去后告诉妻子。妻子便让丫鬟以送礼为名，暗地里查看秀才的家庭情况。发现他妻子也是美女，比天仙还美艳，家里所有的奇花异石、衣饰珍玩，都是从来没有看见过、没有听说过的。

尹图南猜测不出秀才是什么人，就递上名帖，登门拜访。秀才正好外出了。第二天，秀才来回拜。尹图南打开他的名帖，才知道他姓余名德。两人交谈之间，尹图南细细询问他的家族门第，余德的回答非常含糊。尹图南反复追问，余德说：“您如想与我交往，我也不敢拒绝。您应该知道我并不是逃亡在外的窃贼盗匪，何必一定要知道我的来历呢？”尹图南连忙道歉，命家人上酒款待他。二人相谈愉快，一直到傍晚，才有两个奴仆牵着马提着灯过来将余德接了回去。

第二天，余德写便笺给尹图南要回请他。尹图南来到余德家，见室内墙壁都用明光纸装裱，光洁如镜子。金狻猊香炉里燃烧着特别的香料，一只碧玉瓶里插着凤尾与孔雀翎各两支，每支二尺多长。一只水晶瓶里浸着一树粉花，叫不出名字，也是二尺多高。垂下的枝条覆盖到了几案之外，树叶稀疏，花朵繁密，含苞待放。花朵的形状像沾水的蝴蝶收拢着翅膀，花蒂像蝴蝶的触须。

酒席上不过摆了八个盘子的菜肴，但异常丰盛精美。余德命童子击鼓催花行酒令。鼓声一响，水晶瓶中的花就微微颤动起来，好像要折断一样。不一会儿，“蝴蝶”的翅膀慢慢张开。接着停止击鼓，随着一声闷响，蝶须样的花蒂立刻凋落，当即变成一只蝴蝶飞落在尹图南的衣服上。余德笑着起身，递上一个大酒杯，斟上酒让尹图南喝。酒刚斟满，蝴蝶便飞走了。一会儿，鼓声又响起，两只蝴蝶飞来落在余德的帽子上，余德笑着说：“我这是自作自受了。”也喝了两大杯。第三次鼓声响过，花纷纷飘落，化作蝴蝶翩翩飞舞，落在二人的袖子上、衣襟上。击鼓的童子笑着过来，指点计数二人身上各落了多少，结果尹图南应喝九杯，余德应喝四杯。这时尹图南已有些醉意，不敢多喝，勉强喝了三杯便离席逃遁。从此，尹图南越发觉得余德是个奇人。

然而余德很少与人打交道，总是关着门待在家里，不与周围的人有婚丧庆吊的往来。尹图南逢人就为余德宣扬，听说他逸事的人都争相与他结交，常常是贵客盈门、络绎不绝。余德很不耐烦，忽然辞别尹图南离开了。余德走后，尹图南来到他家，只见空空的庭院打扫得一尘不染，烛油堆放在青石阶下，窗户上只剩些残布断线，上面还印着清晰的指痕。只有屋后留下一个小小的白色石缸，可以盛一石水左右。尹图南将缸带回去，盛上水养了几条红鱼，过了一年，缸里的水仍然清澈如初。后来，仆人在搬石块时不小心打碎了石缸，但缸里的水仍凝聚着没流出来。再一看，缸好像还在，用手一摸却空空的、软软的。将手伸进去，水就随着手流出来，手拿开，水又合拢过来，到了冬天也不结冰。一天夜里，缸里的水忽然结成冰晶，而鱼仍在里面游动。

尹图南怕别人知道这件事，一直将它放在密室里，除了儿子、女婿这样的至亲之人，从不给别人看。但时间长了，消息逐渐传开，要求观看赏玩的人纷纷登门。腊月里，冰晶忽然化为水，流了一地，里面的鱼也不见了，只剩下原来旧缸的碎石。忽然有一道士登门索看，尹图南拿出残石给他看，道士说：“这是龙宫中盛水的器皿。”尹图南又跟他讲述了缸破后水不流的奇特之处，道士说：“这是缸的魂魄。”又很殷切地向尹图南求取一点儿碎石，问他有什么用处，道士说：“用石缸的碎屑合药，吃了能够长寿。”尹图南给了他一片，道士高兴地道谢而去。

[87] 税居：租赁居住。

[88] 都：美好。

[89] 蕴藉：宽厚而有涵养。

[90] 刺呼：名帖上所写的姓名。

[91] 昆仑：昆仑奴的省称，泛指奴仆。

[92] 金狻猊：一种金属香炉，上铸有狻猊，有口可通烟火。

[93] 爇（ruò）：点燃，焚烧。

[94] 渊然：形容鼓声低沉。

[95] 吊庆：吊唁与庆贺。

Te Troll

Sun Taibo told me this story.

His great- grandfather, also named Sun, had been studying at Willow Gully Temple on South Mountain, and came home for the autumn wheat harvest. He only stayed at home for ten days, but when he returned to the temple and opened the door of his lodgings, he saw that the table was thick with dust and the windows laced with cobwebs. He ordered his servant to clean the place, and by evening it was in sufficiently good order for him to be able to install himself comfortably again. He dusted off the bed, spread out his quilt, closed the door and lay his head down on the pillow. Moonlight came flooding in at the window.

He tossed and turned a long while, as silence descended on the temple. Then suddenly a wind got up and he heard the main temple door flapping noisily. Thinking to himself that one of the monks must have forgotten to close it, he lay there a while in some anxiety. The wind seemed to be coming closer and closer in the direction of his quarters, and the next thing he knew the door leading into his room blew open. He was now seriously alarmed, and quite unable to compose himself. His room filled with the roaring of the wind, and he heard the sound of clomping boots gradually approaching the alcove in which his bed was situated. By now he was utterly terrified. Then the door of the alcove itself flew open, and there it was, a great troll, stooping down at first as it approached, then suddenly looming up over his bed, its head grazing the ceiling, its face dark and blotchy like an old melon rind. Its blazing eyes scanned the room, and its cavernous mouth lolled open, revealing great shining fangs more than three inches long. Its tongue flickered from side to side, and from its throat there issued a terrible rasping sound that reverberated through the room.

Sun quaked in sheer terror. Thinking quickly to himself that the beast was already too close for him to have any chance of escape and that his only hope now lay in trying to kill it, he secretly drew his dagger from beneath his pillow, concealed it in his sleeve, then swiftly drew it out and stabbed the creature in the belly. The blade made a dull thud on impact, as if it had struck a stone mortar. The enraged troll flailed out at him with its huge claws, but Sun shrank back from it. The troll only succeeded in tearing at the bedcover, and pulled it down on to the ground as it stormed out.

Sun had been dragged to the ground with the bedcover, and he lay there howling. His servant came running with a lantern, and, finding the door locked, as it usually was during the night, he broke open the window and climbed in. Appalled at the state his master was in, he helped him back to bed and heard his tale. Afterwards they examined the room together and saw that the bedcover was still caught tight between the door and the door frame. As soon as they opened the door and the cover fell free, they saw great holes in the fabric, where the beast’s claws had torn at it.

When dawn broke the next morning, they dared not stay there a moment longer but packed their things and returned home. On a subsequent occasion they questioned the resident monks, but there had been no further apparition.

The Monster in the Buckwheat

An old gentleman of Changshan County, by the name of An, enjoyed working on his land. One autumn, when his buckwheat was ripe, he went to supervise the harvest, cutting it and laying it out in stacks along the sides of the fields. At that time, someone was stealing the crops in the neighbouring village, so the old gentleman asked his men to load the cut buckwheat on to a cart that very night and push it to the threshing ground by the light of the moon. He himself stayed behind to keep watch over his remaining crops, lying in the open field with spear at hand as he waited for them to return. He had just begun to doze off, when he heard the sound of feet trampling on the buckwheat stalks, making a terrific crunching noise, and suspected that it might be the thief. But when he looked up, he saw a huge monster bearing down upon him, more than ten feet tall, with red hair and a big bushy beard. Leaping up in terror, he struck out at it with all his might, and the monster gave a great howl of pain and fled into the night.

Afraid that it might reappear at any moment, An shouldered his spear and headed home, telling his labourers, when he met them on the road, what he had seen, and warning them not to proceed any further. They were reluctant to believe him.

The next day, they were spreading out the buckwheat in the sun when suddenly they heard a strange sound in the air.

‘It’s the monster again!’ cried old An in terror, and fled, as did all the others.

A little later that day, they gathered together again and An told them to arm themselves with bows and lie in wait. The following morning, sure enough, the monster returned a third time. They each shot several arrows at it, and it fled in fear. Then for two or three days it did not return. By now all the threshed buckwheat was safely stored in the granary, but the stalks of straw still lay higgledy- piggledy on the threshing floor. Old An gave orders for the straw to be bound together and piled into a rick, then he himself climbed up on to the rick, which was several feet high. He was treading it down firmly when suddenly he saw something in the distance.

‘The monster is coming again!’ he cried aghast.

Before his men could get to their bows, the creature had already jumped at him, and knocked him back on to the rick. It took a bite out of his forehead and went away again. The men climbed up and saw that a whole chunk of the old man’s forehead, a piece the size of a man’s palm, had been bitten off, bone and all. He had already lost consciousness, and they carried him home, where he died.

The monster was never seen again. Nobody could even agree on what sort of creature it was.

Stealing a Peach

When I was a boy, I went up to the prefectural city of Ji’nan to take an examination. It was the time of the Spring Festival, and, according to custom, on the day before the festival all the merchants of the place processed with decorated banners and drums to the provincial yamen. This procession was called Bringing in the Spring. I went with a friend to watch the fun. There was a huge crowd milling about, and ahead of us, facing each other to the right and left of the raised hall, sat four mandarins in their crimson robes. I was too young at the time to know who they were. All I was aware of was the hum of voices and the crashing noise of the drums and other instruments.

In the middle of it all, a man led a boy with long unplaited hair into the space in front of the dais and knelt on the ground. The man had two baskets suspended from a carrying pole on his shoulders and seemed to be saying something, which I could not distinguish for the din of the crowd. I only saw the mandarins smile, and immediately afterwards an attendant came down and in a loud voice ordered the man to give his performance.

‘What shall I perform?’ said the man, rising to his feet.

The mandarins on the dais consulted among themselves, and then the attendant inquired of the man what he could do best.

‘I can make the seasons go backwards, and turn the order of nature upside down.’

The attendant reported back to the mandarins, and after a moment returned and ordered the man to produce a peach. The man assented, taking off his coat and laying it on one of his baskets, at the same time complaining loudly that they had set him a very hard task.

‘The winter frost has not melted – how can I possibly produce a peach? But if I fail, their worships will surely be angry with me. Alas! Woe is me!’

The boy, who was evidently his son, reminded him that he had already agreed to perform and was under an obligation to continue. After fretting and grumbling a while, the father cried out, ‘I know what we must do! Here it is still early spring and there is snow on the ground – we shall never get a peach here. But up in heaven, in the garden of the Queen Mother of the West, they have peaches all the year round. There it is eternal summer! It is there we must try!’

‘But how are we to get up there?’ asked the boy.

‘I have the means,’ replied his father, and immediately proceeded to take from one of his baskets a cord some dozens of feet in length. He coiled it carefully and then threw one end of it high up into the air, where it remained suspended, as if somehow caught. He continued to pay out the rope, which kept rising higher and higher until the top end of it disappeared altogether into the clouds, while the other end remained in his hands.

‘Come here, boy!’ he called to his son. ‘I am getting too old for this sort of thing, and anyway I am too heavy, I wouldn’t be able to do it. It will have to be you.’

He handed the rope to the boy.

‘Climb up on this.’

The boy took the rope, but as he did so he pulled a face. ‘Father, have you gone mad?’ he protested. ‘You want me to climb all the way up into the sky on this flimsy thing? Suppose it breaks and I fall – I’ll be killed!’

‘I have given these gentlemen my word,’ his father pleaded, ‘and there’s no backing out now. Please do this, I beg of you. Bring me a peach, and I am sure we will be rewarded with a hundred taels of silver. Then I promise to get you a pretty wife.’

So his son took hold of the rope and went scrambling up it, hand over foot, like a spider running up a thread, finally disappearing out of sight and into the clouds.

There was a long interval, and then down fell a large peach, the size of a soup bowl. The delighted father presented it to the gentlemen on the dais, who passed it around and studied it carefully, unable to tell at first glance whether it was genuine or a fake. Then suddenly the rope came tumbling to the ground.

‘The poor boy!’ cried the father in alarm. ‘He is done for! Someone up there must have cut my rope!’

The next moment something else fell to the ground, an object which was found on closer examination to be the boy’s head. ‘Ah me!’ cried the father, weeping bitterly and holding the head up in both his hands. ‘The heavenly watchman caught him stealing the peach! My son is no more!’

After that, one by one, the boy’s feet, his arms and legs, and every single remaining part of his anatomy came tumbling down in a similar manner. The distraught father gathered all the pieces up and put them in one of his baskets, saying, ‘This was my only son! He went with me everywhere I went. And now, at his own father’s orders, he has met with this cruel fate. I must away and bury him.’

He approached the dais.

‘Your peach, gentlemen,’ he said, falling to his knees, ‘was obtained at the cost of my boy’s life. Help me, I beg you, to pay for his funeral expenses, and I will be ever grateful to you for your kindness.’

The mandarins, who had been watching the scene in utter horror and amazement, immediately collected a good purse for him. When the father had received the money and put it in his belt, he rapped on the basket.

‘Babar! ’ he called out. ‘Out you come now and thank the gentlemen! What are you waiting for?’

He had no sooner said this than there was a knock from within and a tousled head emerged from the basket. Out jumped the boy, and bowed to the dais. It was his son.

To this very day I have never forgotten this extraordinary performance. I later learned that this ‘rope trick’ was a speciality of the White Lotus sect. Surely this man must have learned it from them.

The Golden Goblet

Yin Shidan, who rose to be President of the Board of Civil Office, was a native of Licheng who grew up in circumstances of great poverty and had shown himself to be a young man of courage and resourcefulness.

In his home town there was a large estate that had once belonged to a long- established family, a rambling property consisting of a series of pavilions and other buildings that extended over several acres. Strange apparitions had often been witnessed on the estate, with the result that it had been abandoned and allowed to go to ruin. No one was willing to live there. With time the place grew so overgrown and desolate that no one would so much as enter it even in broad daylight.

One day, Yin was drinking with some young friends of his when one of them had a bright idea.

‘If one of us dares to spend a night in that haunted place,’ he proposed jokingly, ‘let’s all stand him a dinner!’

Yin leaped up at once. ‘Why, what could be easier!’

And so saying he took his sleeping mat with him and went to the place, the others accompanying him as far as the entrance.

‘We will wait here outside,’ they said, smiling nervously. ‘If you see anything out of the ordinary, be sure to raise the alarm.’

Yin laughed. ‘If I find any ghosts or foxes, I’ll catch one to show you.’ And in he went.

The paths were overgrown with long grass and tangled weeds. It was the first quarter of the month, and the crescent moon gave off just enough light for him to make out the gateways and doors. He groped his way forwards until he found himself standing before the building that stood at the rear of the main compound. He climbed on to the terrace and thought it seemed a delightful place to take a little nap. The slender arc of the moon shining in the western sky seemed to hold the hills in its mouth. He sat there a long while without observing anything unusual, and began to smile to himself at the foolish rumours about the place being haunted. Spreading his mat, and choosing a stone for a pillow, he lay there gazing up at the constellations of the Cowherd and the Spinning Maid in the night sky.

By the end of the first watch, he was just beginning to doze off when he heard the patter of footsteps from below, and a servant- girl appeared, carrying a lotus- shaped lantern. The sight of Yin seemed to startle her and she made as if to flee, calling out to someone behind her, ‘There’s a strange- looking man here!’

‘Who is it?’ replied a voice.

‘I don’t know.’

Presently an old gentleman appeared and, approaching Yin, scrutinized him.

‘Why, that is the future President Yin! He is fast asleep. We can carry on as planned. He is a broad- minded fellow and will not take offence.’

The old man led the maid on into the building, where they threw open all the doors. After a while a great many guests started arriving, and the upper rooms were as brightly lit as if it had been broad daylight.

Yin tossed and turned on the terrace where he lay. Then he sneezed. The old man, hearing that he was awake, came out and knelt down by his side.

‘My daughter, sir, is being given in marriage tonight. I had no idea that Your Excellency would be here, and crave your indulgence.’

Yin rose to his feet and made the old man do likewise. ‘I was not aware that a wedding was taking place tonight. I regret I have brought no gift with me.’

‘Your very presence is gift enough,’ replied the old man graciously, ‘and will help to ward off noxious influences. Would you be so kind as to honour us further with your company now?’

Yin assented. Entering the building, he looked around him at the splendid feast that had been prepared. A woman of about forty, whom the old gentleman introduced as his wife, came out to welcome him, and Yin made her a bow. Then the sound of festive pipes was heard, and someone came rushing in, crying, ‘He has arrived!’

The old man hurried out to receive his future son- in- law, and Yin remained standing where he was in expectation. After a little while, a bevy of servants bearing gauze lanterns ushered in the groom, a handsome young man of seventeen or eighteen, of a most distinguished appearance and prepossessing bearing. The old gentleman bade him pay his respects to the guest of honour, and the young man turned to Yin, whom he took to be some sort of Master of Ceremonies, and bowed to him in the appropriate fashion. Then the old man and the groom exchanged formal courtesies, and when these were completed, they took their seats. Presently a throng of finely attired serving- maids came forward, with choice wines and steaming dishes of meat. Jade bowls and golden goblets glistened on the tables. When the wine had been round several times, the old gentleman dispatched one of the maids to summon the bride. The maid departed on her errand, but when she had been gone a long while and still there was no sign of his daughter, the old man himself eventually rose from his seat and, lifting the portière, went into the inner apartments to chivvy her along. At last several maids and serving- women ushered in the bride, to the sound of tinkling jade pendants, and the scent of musk and orchid wafted through the room. Obedient to her father’s instructions, she curtseyed to the senior guests and then took her seat by her mother’s side. Yin could see from a glance that beneath the kingfisher- feather ornaments she was a young woman of extraordinary beauty.

They were drinking from large goblets of solid gold, each of which held well over a pint, and Yin thought to himself that one of these would be an ideal proof of his adventure that night. So he hid one in his sleeve, to show his friends on his return, then slumped across the table, pretending to have been over powered by the wine.

‘His Excellency is drunk,’ they remarked.

A little later, Yin heard the groom take his leave, and as the pipes started up again, all the guests began trooping downstairs.

The old gentleman came to gather up his golden goblets, and noticed that one of them was missing. He searched for it to no avail. Someone suggested their sleeping guest as the culprit, but the old gentleman promptly bid him be silent, for fear that Yin might hear.

After a while, when all was still within and without, Yin rose from the table. The lamps had all been extinguished and it was dark, but the aroma of the food and the fumes of wine still lingered in the hall. As he made his way slowly out of the building, and felt inside his sleeve for the golden goblet, which was still safely hidden, the first light of dawn glimmered in the eastern sky.

He reached the entrance of the estate to find his friends still waiting outside. They had stayed there all night, in case he should try to trick them by coming out and going back in again early in the morning. He took the goblet from his sleeve and showed it to them. In utter amazement they asked him how he had come by it, whereupon he told them the whole story. They knew how poor he was, and that he was most unlikely to have owned such a valuable object himself, and so were obliged to believe him.

Some years later, Yin passed his final examination and ob tained the degree of Doctor or jinshi, after which he was appointed to a post in Feiqiu. A wealthy gentleman of the district by the name of Zhu gave a banquet in his honour, and ordered his large golden goblets to be brought out for the occasion. They were a long time coming, and as the company waited a young servant came up and whispered something to the master of the household, who instantly flew into a rage. Presently the goblets were brought in, and Zhu urged his guests to drink. To his astonishment, Yin at once recognized the shape and pattern of the goblets as being identical with the one he had ‘kept’ from the fox wedding. He asked his host where they had been made.

‘I had eight of them,’ was the reply. ‘An ancestor of mine was a high- ranking mandarin in Peking and had them made by a master goldsmith of the time. They have been in my family for generations, but it is a long while since I last had them taken out of storage. When I knew we would have the honour of your company today, I told my man to open the box, and it turns out there are only seven left! I would have suspected one of my household of stealing it, but apparently there was ten years’ dust on the seals and the box was untampered with. It baffles me how this can have happened.’

‘The thing must have grown wings and flown away of its own accord!’ quipped Yin with a laugh. ‘But seeing that you have lost an heirloom, I feel I must help you replace it. I myself have a goblet, sir, very similar to this set of yours. Allow me to make you a present of it.’

When the meal was over, he returned to his official residence, and taking out his own goblet, sent it round straightaway to Zhu’s house. When he inspected it, Zhu was absolutely amazed. He went to thank Yin in person, and when he asked him where he had acquired the goblet, Yin told him the whole story.

Which all goes to show that although foxes may be capable of getting hold of objects from a very long way away, they do not hold on to them for ever.

Wailing Ghosts

At the time of the Xie Qian troubles in Shandong, the great residences of the nobility were all commandeered by the rebels. The mansion of Education Commissioner Wang Qixiang accommodated a particularly large number of them. When the government troops eventually retook the town and massacred the rebels, every porch was strewn with corpses. Blood flowed from every doorway.

When Commissioner Wang returned, he gave orders that all the corpses were to be removed from his home and the blood washed away, so that he could once more take up residence. In the days that followed, he frequently saw ghosts in broad day light, and during the night ghostly will- o’- the- wisp flickerings of light beneath his bed. He heard the voices of ghosts wailing in various corners of the house.

One day, a young gentleman by the name of Wang Gaodi who had come to stay with the Commissioner heard a little voice crying beneath his bed, ‘Gaodi! Gaodi!’

Then the voice grew louder. ‘I died a cruel death!’

The voice began sobbing, and was soon joined by ghosts throughout the house.

The Commissioner himself heard it and came with his sword.

‘Do you not know who I am?’ he declared loudly. ‘I am Education Commissioner Wang.’

The ghostly voices merely sneered at this and laughed through their noses, whereupon the Commissioner gave orders for a lengthy ritual to be immediately performed for all departed souls on land and sea, in the course of which Buddhist bonzes and Taoist priests prayed for the liberation of his supernatural tenants from their torments. That night they put out food for the ghosts, and will- o’- the- wisp lights could be seen flickering across the ground.

Now before any of these events, a gate- man, also named Wang, had fallen gravely ill, and had been lying unconscious for several days. The night of the ritual he suddenly seemed to regain consciousness, and stretched his limbs. When his wife brought him some food, he said to her, ‘The Master put some food out in the courtyard – I’ve no idea why! Anyway I was out there eating with the others, and I’ve only just finished, so I’m not that hungry.’

From that day, the hauntings ceased.

Does this mean that the banging of cymbals and gongs, the beating of bells and drums, and other esoteric practices for the release of wandering souls are necessarily efficacious?

Scorched Moth the Taoist

The household of Hanlin Academician Dong was troubled by fox- spirits. Tiles, pebbles and brick shards were liable to fly around the house like hailstones at any moment, and his family and household were forever having to take shelter and wait for the disturbances to abate before they dared carry on with their daily duties. Dong himself was so affected by this state of affairs that he rented a residence belonging to Under- Secretary Sun, and moved there to avoid his troubles. But the fox- spirits merely followed him.

One day when he was on duty at court and described this strange phenomenon to his colleagues, a senior minister mentioned a certain Taoist master from the north- east by the name of Jiao Ming – Scorched Moth – who lived in the Inner Manchu City and issued exorcist spells and talismans reputed for their efficacy. Dong paid the man a personal call and requested his aid, whereupon the Master wrote out some charms in cinnabar- red ink and told Dong to paste them on his wall. The foxes were unperturbed by these measures, however, and continued to hurl things around with greater vigour than ever. Dong reported back to the Taoist, who was angered by this apparent failure of his charms and came in person to Dong’s house, where he set up an altar and performed a full rite of exorcism. Suddenly they beheld a huge fox crouching on the ground before the altar. Dong’s household had suffered long from this creature’s antics, and the servants felt a deep- seated sense of grievance towards it. One of the maids went up to it to deal it a blow, only to fall dead to the ground.

‘This is a vicious beast!’ exclaimed the Taoist. ‘Even I could not subdue it! This girl was very foolish to provoke it.’ He continued, ‘Nonetheless, we can now use her to question the fox.’

Pointing his index finger and middle finger at the maid, he pronounced certain spells, and suddenly she rose from the ground and knelt before him. The Taoist asked her where she hailed from.

‘I come from the Western Regions,’ replied the maid, in a voice that was clearly not her own but that of the fox. ‘We have been here in the capital for eighteen generations.’

‘How dare creatures such as you dwell in the proximity of His Imperial Majesty? Off with you at once!’

The fox- voice was silent, and the Taoist thumped the altar- table angrily. ‘How dare you disobey my orders? Delay a moment longer, and my magic powers will work on you harshly!’

The fox shrank back fearfully, indicating his submission, and the Taoist urged him once more to be gone. Meanwhile the maid had fallen to the ground again, dead to the world. It was a long while before she regained consciousness.

All of a sudden they saw four or five white lumps of some strange substance go bouncing like balls one after the other along the eaves of the building, until they were all gone. Then peace finally reigned in the Dong household.

The Giant Turtle

An elderly gentleman called Zhang, a native of the western region of Jin, was about to give away his daughter in marriage, and took his family with him by boat on a trip to the South, having decided to purchase there all that was necessary for her trousseau. When the boat arrived at Gold Mountain, he went ahead across the river, leaving his family on board and warning them not to fry any strong- smelling meat during his absence, for fear of provoking the turtle- demon that lurked in the river. This vicious creature would be sure to come out if it smelled meat cooking, and would destroy the boat and eat alive anyone on board. It had been wreaking havoc in the area for a long while.

Once the old man had left, his family quite forgot his words of caution, lit a fire on deck and began to cook meat on it. All of a sudden a great wave arose, overturning their boat and drowning both Zhang’s wife and daughter. When Zhang returned, he was grief- stricken at their deaths. He climbed up to the monastery on Gold Mountain and called on the monks there, asking them for information about the turtle’s strange ways, so that he could plan his revenge. The monks were appalled at his intentions.

‘We live with the turtle every day, in constant fear of the devastation it is capable of causing. All we can do is worship it and pray to it not to fly into a rage. From time to time we slaughter animals, cut them in half and throw them into the river. The turtle jumps out of the water, gulps them down and disappears. No one would be so crazy as to try to seek revenge!’

As he listened to the monks’ words, Zhang was already forming his plan. He recruited a local blacksmith, who set up a furnace on the hillside above the river and smelted a large lump of iron, over a hundred catties in weight. Zhang then ascertained the turtle’s exact hiding place and hired a number of strong men to lift up the red- hot molten iron with a great pair of tongs and hurl it into the river. True to form, the turtle leaped out of the water, gulped down the molten metal and plunged back into the river. Minutes later, mountainous waves came boiling to the water’s surface. Then, in an instant, the river became calm and the turtle could be seen floating dead on the water.

Travellers and monks alike rejoiced at the turtle’s death. They built a temple to old man Zhang, erected a statue of him inside it and worshipped him as a water god. When they prayed to him, their wishes were always fulfilled.

A Fatal Joke

The schoolmaster Sun Jingxia once told this story.

A certain fellow of the locality, let us call him ‘X’, was killed by bandits during one of their raids. His head flopped down on to his chest. When the bandits had gone and the family came to recover the corpse for burial, they detected the faintest trace of breathing, and on closer examination saw that the man’s windpipe was not quite severed. A finger’s breadth remained. So they carried him home, supporting the head carefully, and after a day and a night, he began to make a moaning noise. They fed him minute quantities of food with a spoon and chopsticks, and after six months he was fully recovered.

Ten years later, he was sitting talking with two or three of his friends when one of them cracked a hilarious joke and they all burst out laughing. ‘X’ was rocking backwards and forwards in a fit of hysterical laughter, when suddenly the old sword- wound burst open and his head fell to the ground in a pool of blood. His friends examined him, and this time he was well and truly dead.

His father decided to bring charges against the man who had told the joke. But the joker’s friends collected some money together and succeeded in buying him off. The father buried his son and dropped the charges.

A Prank

A certain fellow of my home district, a well- known prankster and libertine, was out one day strolling in the countryside when he saw a young girl approaching on a pony.

‘I’ll get a laugh out of her, see if I don’t!’ he called out to his companions.

They were sceptical of his chances of success and wagered a banquet on it, even as he hurried forward in front of the girl’s pony and cried out loudly, ‘I want to die! I want to die ...’

He took hold of a tall millet stalk that was growing over a nearby wall and, bending it so that it projected a foot into the road, untied the sash of his gown and threw it over the stalk, making a noose in it and slipping it round his neck, as if to hang himself. As she came closer, the girl laughed at him, and by now his friends were also in fits. The girl then rode on into the distance, but the man still did not move, which caused his friends to laugh all the more. Presently they went up and looked at him: his tongue was protruding from his mouth, his eyes were closed. He was quite lifeless.

Strange that a man could succeed in hanging himself from a millet stalk. Let this be a warning to libertines and pranksters.

Butterfly

Luo Zifu was born in Bin County, and lost both his parents at an early age. When he was eight or nine years old he went to live with his Uncle Daye, a high official in the Imperial College and an immensely wealthy man. Daye had no sons of his own and came to love Luo as if he were his own child.

When the boy was fourteen, he fell in with bad company and became a regular frequenter of the local pleasure- houses. A famous Nanking courtesan happened to be in Bin County at the time, and the young Luo became hopelessly infatuated with her. When she returned to Nanking, he ran away with her and lived with her there in her establishment for a good six months – by which time his money was all gone and the other girls had begun to mock him mercilessly, though they still tolerated his presence.

Then he contracted syphilis and broke out in suppurating sores, which left stains on the bedding, and they finally drove him from the house. He took to begging in the streets, where the passers- by shunned him. He began to dread the thought of dying so far from home, and one day set off begging his way back to Shaanxi, covering ten or so miles a day, until eventually he came to the borders of Bin County. His filthy rags and foul, pus- covered body made him too ashamed to go any further into his old neighbourhood, and instead he hobbled about on the outskirts of town.

Towards evening, he was stumbling towards a temple in the hills, seeking shelter for the night, when he encountered a young woman of a quite unearthly beauty, who came up to him and asked him where he was going. He told her his whole story.

‘I myself have renounced the world,’ was her response. ‘I live here in a cave in the hills. You are welcome to stay with me. Here at least you will be safe from tigers and wolves.’

Luo followed her joyfully, and together they walked deeper into the hills. Presently he found himself at the entrance to a grotto, inside which flowed a stream, with a stone bridge leading over it. A few steps further and they came to two chambers hollowed out of the rock, both of them brightly lit, but with no sign anywhere of either candle or lamp. The girl bid Luo remove his rags and bathe in the waters of the stream.

‘Wash,’ she said, ‘and your sores will all be healed.’

She drew apart the bed- curtains and made up a bed for him, dusting off the quilt.

‘Sleep now,’ she said, ‘and I will make you a pair of trousers.’

She brought in what looked like a large plantain leaf and began cutting it to shape. He lay there watching her, and in a very short while the trousers were made and placed folded on the bed.

‘You can wear these in the morning.’

She lay down on a couch opposite.

After bathing in the stream, Luo felt all the pain go out of his sores, and when he awoke during the night and touched them, they had already dried and hardened into thick scabs. In the morning he rose, wondering if he would truly be able to wear the plantain- leaf trousers. When he took them in his hands, he found that they were wonderfully smooth, like green satin.

In a little while, breakfast was prepared. The young woman brought more leaves from the mountainside. She said that they were pancakes, and they ate them, and sure enough they were pancakes. She cut the shapes of poultry and fish from the leaves and cooked them, and they made a delicious meal. In the corner of the room stood a vat filled with fine wine, from which they drank, and when the supply ran out she merely replenished it with water from the stream.

In a few days, when all his sores and scabs were gone, he went up to her and begged her to share his bed.

‘Silly boy!’ she cried. ‘No sooner cured than you go losing your head again!’

‘I only want to repay your kindness ...’

They had much pleasure together that night.

Time passed, and one day another young woman came into the grotto and greeted them with a broad grin.

‘Why, my dear wicked little Butterfly!’ (for such was the girl’s name). ‘You do seem to be having a good time! And when did this cosy little idyll of yours begin, pray?’

‘It’s been such an age since you last visited, dearest Sister Flower!’ returned Butterfly, with a teasing smile. ‘What Fair Wind of Love blows you here today? And have you had your little baby boy yet?’

‘Actually I had a girl ...’

‘What a doll factory you are!’ quipped Butterfly. ‘Didn’t you bring her with you?’

‘She’s only just this minute stopped crying and fallen asleep.’

Flower sat down with them and drank her fill of wine.

‘This young man must have burned some very special incense to be so lucky,’ she remarked, looking at Luo. He in turn studied her. She was a beautiful young woman in her early twenties, and the susceptible young man was instantly smitten. He peeled a fruit and ‘accidentally’ dropped it under the table. Bending down to retrieve it, he gave the tip of one of her tiny embroidered slippers a little pinch. She turned away and smiled, pretending not to have noticed. Luo, who was now totally entranced and more than a little aroused, noticed all of a sudden that his gown and trousers were growing cold, and when he looked down at them they had turned into withered leaves. Horrified, he sat primly upright for a moment, and slowly they reverted to their former soft, silken appearance. He was secretly relieved that neither of the girls seemed to have noticed anything.

A little later, they were still drinking together when he let his finger stray to the palm of Flower’s dainty little hand. Flower carried on laughing and smiling, as if nothing had happened. And then suddenly, to his horror, it happened a second time: silk was transformed to leaf, and leaf back to silk. He had learned his lesson this time, and resolved to behave himself.

‘Your young man is rather naughty!’ said Flower, with a smile. ‘If you weren’t such a jealous jar of vinegar, he’d be roaming all over the place!’

‘You faithless boy!’ quipped Butterfly. ‘You deserve to freeze to death!’

She and Flower both laughed and clapped their hands.

‘My little girl’s awake again,’ said Flower, rising from her seat. ‘She’ll hurt herself crying like that.’

‘Hark at you,’ said Butterfly, ‘leading strange men astray and neglecting your own child!’ Flower left them, and Luo was afraid he would be subjected to mockery and recrimination from Butterfly. But she was as delightful as ever.

The days passed, and, as autumn turned to winter, the cold wind and frost stripped the trees bare. Butterfly gathered the fallen leaves and began storing them for food to see them through the winter. She noticed Luo shivering, and went to the entrance of the grotto, where she gathered white clouds with which to line a padded gown for him. When it was made, it was warm as silk, and the padding was light and soft as fresh cotton floss.

A year later, she gave birth to a son, a clever, handsome child with whom Luo loved to pass the days playing in the grotto. But, as time went by, he began to pine for home and begged Butterfly to return with him.

‘I cannot go,’ she told him. ‘But you go if you must.’

A further two or three years went by. The boy grew, and they betrothed him to Flower’s little daughter. Luo was now constantly thinking of his old uncle, Daye.

‘The old man is strong and well,’ Butterfly assured him. ‘You do not need to worry on his behalf. Wait until your boy is married. Then you can go.’

She would sit in the grotto and write lessons on leaves for their son, who mastered them at a single glance.

‘Our son has a happy destiny,’ she said to Luo. ‘If he goes into the human world, he will certainly rise to great heights.’

When the boy was fourteen, Flower came with her daughter, dressed in all her finery. She had grown into a radiantly beautiful young woman. She and Butterfly’s son were very happy to be married, and the whole family held a feast to celebrate their union. Butterfly sang a song, tapping out the rhythm with her hairpin:

A fine son have I,

Why should I yearn

For pomp and splendour?

A fine daughter is mine,

Why should I long

For silken luxury?

Tonight we are gathered

To sing and be merry.

For you, dear lad, a parting cup!

For you, a plate of food!

Flower took her leave. The young couple made their home in the stone chamber opposite, and the young bride waited dutifully on Butterfly as if she were her own mother.

It was not long before Luo started talking again of returning home.

‘You will always be a mortal,’ said Butterfly. ‘It is in your bones, and in our son’s. He, too, belongs in the world of men. Take him with you. I do not wish to blight his days.’

The young bride wanted to say a last farewell to her mother, and Flower came to visit them. Both she and her husband were loth to leave their mothers, and their eyes brimmed with tears.

‘Go for a while,’ said the women, by way of comforting them. ‘You can always come back later.’

Butterfly cut out a leaf and made a donkey, and the three of them, Luo and the young couple, climbed on to the beast and rode away upon it.

Luo’s uncle, Daye, was by now an old man and retired from public life. He thought that his adopted son had died. And now, out of the blue, there he was, with a son of his own and a beautiful daughter- in- law! He rejoiced as if he had come upon some precious treasure. The moment they entered his house, their silken clothes all turned once more into crumbling plantain leaves, while the ‘cotton padding’ drifted up into the sky. They dressed themselves in new, more ordinary clothes.

As time went by, Luo pined for Butterfly, and he went in search of her with his son. But the path through the hills was strewn with yellow leaves, and the entrance to the grotto was lost in the mist. The two of them returned weeping from their quest.

The Stone Bowl

A certain gentleman by the name of Yin Tu’nan, of Wuchang, possessed a villa that he rented out to a young scholar. Half a year passed and he never once had occasion to call on this young tenant of his. Then one day he chanced to see him outside the entrance to the compound, and observing that, despite the tenant’s evident youth, he had the fastidious manner and elegant accoutrements of a person of refinement, Yin approached him and engaged him in conversation. He found him indeed to be a most charming and cultivated person. Clearly this was no ordinary lodger.

Returning home, Yin mentioned the encounter to his wife, who sent over one of her own maids to spy out the land, on the pretext of delivering a gift. The maid discovered a young lady in the young man’s apartment, of a breathtaking beauty that surpassed (as she put it) that of a fairy, while the living quarters, she observed to her mistress, were furnished with an extraordinary variety of plants, ornamental stones, rare clothes and assorted curios, things such as she had never before set eyes on.

Yin was intrigued to find out exactly what sort of person this young man could be, and went himself to the villa to pay him a visit. It so happened the man was out, but the following day he returned Yin’s visit and presented his name card. Yin read on the card that his name was Yu De, but when Yin pressed Yu De for further details of his background, he became extremely vague.

‘I am happy to make your acquaintance, sir. Trust me, I am no robber, nor am I a fugitive from justice. But beyond that, I am surely not obliged to divulge further particulars of my identity.’

Yin apologized for his incivility and set wine and food before his guest, whereupon they dined together in a most convivial manner until late in the evening, when two dark- skinned servants came with horses and lanterns to fetch their young master home.

The following day, he sent Yin a note inviting him over to the villa for a return visit. When Yin arrived, he observed that the walls of the room in which he was received were lined with a glossy paper that shone like the surface of a mirror, while fumes of some exotic incense smouldered from a golden censer fashioned in the shape of a lion. Beside the censer stood a vase of dark- green jade containing four feathers – two phoenix feathers, two peacock – each of them over two feet in length. In another vase, made of pure crystal, was a branch of some flowering tree which he could not identify, also about two feet long, covered with pink blossoms and trailing down over the edge of the little table on which it stood. The densely clustered flowers, still in bud, were admirably set off by the sparsity of leaves. They resembled butterflies moistened by the morning dew, resting with closed wings on the branch, to which they were attached by delicate antenna- like tendrils.

The dinner served consisted of eight dishes, each one a gastronomic delicacy. After dinner, the host ordered his servant to ‘sound the drum for the flowers’ and to commence the drinking game. The drum duly sounded, and as it did so the flowers on the branch began to open tremulously, spreading their ‘butterfly wings’ very slowly one by one. And then as the drumming ceased, on the final solemn beat, the tendrils of one flower detached themselves from the branch and became a butterfly, fluttering through the air and alighting on Yin’s gown. With a laugh, Yu poured his guest a large goblet of wine, and when Yin had drained the goblet dry, the butterfly flew away. An instant later the drumming recommenced, and this time when it ceased two butterflies flew up into the air and settled on Yu’s cap. He laughed again.

‘Serves me right! I must drink a double sconce myself!’

And he downed two goblets. At the third drumming, a veritable shower of butterfly- flowers began to fall through the air, fluttering here and there and eventually settling in large numbers on the gowns of both men. The pageboy drummer smiled and thrust out his fingers twice, in the manner of drinking games: once for Yin, and it came to nine fingers; once for Yu, and it came to four. Yin was already somewhat the worse for drink and was unable to down his quota. He managed to knock back three goblets, and then got down from the table, excused himself and stumbled home. His evening’s entertainment had only served to intensify his curiosity. There was indeed something very unusual about his lodger.

Yu seldom socialized, and spent most of his time shut up at home in the villa, never going out into society even for occasions such as funerals or weddings. Yin told his friends of his own strange experience and word soon got around, with the result that many of them competed to make Yu’s acquaintance, and the carriages of the local nobility were often to be seen at the doors of the villa. Yu found this attention more and more irksome, and one day he suddenly took his leave of Yin and went away altogether. After his departure, Yin inspected the villa and found the interior of the building quite empty. It had been left spotlessly clean and tidy. Outside, at the foot of the stone steps leading up to the terrace, was a pile of ‘candle tears’, the waxen accumulation, no doubt, of the revels of many evenings. Tattered curtains still hung in the windows, and there seemed to be the marks of fingers still visible on the fabric. Behind the villa, Yin found a white stone bowl, about a gallon in capacity, which he took home with him, filled with water and used for his goldfish. A year later, he was surprised to see that the water in the bowl was still as clear as it had been on the very first day. Then, one day, a servant was moving a rock and accidentally broke a piece out of the rim of the bowl. But somehow, despite the break, the water stayed intact within the bowl, and when Yin examined it, it seemed to all intents and purposes whole. He passed his hand along the edge of the break, which felt strangely soft. When he put his hand inside the bowl, water came trickling out along the crack, but when he withdrew his hand, water filled the bowl as before.

Throughout the winter months, the water in the bowl never froze. And then one night it turned into a solid block of crystal. But the fish could still be seen swimming around inside it.

Yin was afraid that others might get to know of this strange bowl, and he kept it in a secret room, telling only his own children and their husbands and wives. But, with time, word got out and everyone was at his door wanting to see and touch this marvel.

The night before the festival of the winter solstice, the crystal block suddenly melted and water leaked from the bowl, leaving a large dark stain on the floor. Of the goldfish there was no sign whatsoever. Only the fragments of the broken bowl remained.

One day, a Taoist came knocking at the door and asked to see the bowl. Yin brought out the broken pieces to show him.

‘This,’ said the Taoist, ‘was once a water vessel from the Dragon King’s Underwater Palace.’

Yin told him how it had been broken, and how it had continued to hold water.

‘That is the spirit of the bowl at work,’ commented the Taoist, entreating Yin to give him a piece of it. Yin asked him why he wanted it.

‘By pounding such a fragment into a powder,’ he replied, ‘I can make a drug that will give everlasting life.’

Yin gave him a piece, and the Taoist thanked him and went on his way.

黄色墙纸

/

像约翰和我这样的普通人居然会租一处祖传老宅来消夏，这是很不寻常的事情。

一幢殖民风格的别墅，一座世袭的房产，我愿称之为闹鬼的房子，由此获得一种浪漫主义的至喜体验——然而我又怎能对命运要求太多！

不过，我还是要骄傲地说这座房子确有古怪之处。

否则，它的租金为何如此便宜？又为何会空置如此之久？

当然，约翰会嘲笑我，这是婚姻中可以预料到的事情。

约翰极其现实。他对信仰毫无耐心，对迷信避之不及，并且公开嘲笑一切看不见摸不着且没有具体形象的东西。

约翰是一位医生，也许（当然我不会对任何一个活人这么说，但这是一张没有生命的纸，我用它来放松精神）——也许这就是我无法快速康复的原因之一。

你看，他不相信我病了！

那我又能做什么呢？

当一位权威的医生，同时也是你的丈夫，向亲朋好友保证你并没有什么严重的疾病，只不过是暂时性的精神抑郁——轻微情绪激动的倾向——你又能怎么做呢？

我的哥哥也是一名医生，同样很权威，他给出了一样的说辞。

所以我服用磷酸盐或亚磷酸盐——管它是哪一种呢——吃补药，进行康复旅行，呼吸新鲜空气，进行适当锻炼，而“工作”在康复之前是被绝对禁止的。

我并不同意他们的理念。

而我相信适宜的工作会带来兴奋和变化，将对我有益。

然而我又能做些什么呢？

我确实无视他们的意见，写作过一段时间。可这件事确实极大地消耗了我——我需要精心隐藏，否则就要面对他们的强烈反对。

有时候我会想，像我这种状况如果能少一些反对，多一些社交和激励……可是约翰说，对我来讲最坏的事情就是去琢磨自己的状况，我也承认这总让我心绪不佳。

所以先不去管它，我来聊聊这幢房子吧。

这地方的确漂亮！房子孤零零的，远离大路，离村庄有三英里之遥。它令我想起了曾经读到过的英伦建筑，有篱笆，有高墙，有上锁的大门，还有很多为园丁和其他仆人准备的独栋小屋。

还有个宜人的花园！我从未见过这样的花园——巨大而阴凉，里面处处是树篱环绕的小径，小径两旁是长长的葡萄藤架，架下有一些座椅。

也有几处温室，只是完全毁坏了。

我想，这里可能存在着某种法律纠纷，继承人和共同继承人的问题。总之，出于某种原因，这个地方已经空置多年。

恐怕，这助长了我身上的幽灵之气。我有些害怕，但并不困扰——这幢房子有某种异样，我能感觉到。

一个月光朗照的夜晚，我甚至对约翰也说过这样的话，但他说我感觉到的只不过是一阵气流而已，旋即便关上了窗子。

我时而会对约翰产生无名火。我确信自己过去从未如此敏感。我想这是我的精神状况所致。

但是约翰说，如果我放任自己这样感觉，我就是疏于恰当的自制。所以我很辛苦地控制自己——至少在他面前。而这让我感到疲惫至极。

我一点儿都不喜欢我们的房间。我想住楼下的那间，它对着走廊，窗户镶满玫瑰花，还挂着那么美丽的老式印花棉布帘子！可是约翰不愿意。

他说那个房间只有一个窗户，而且放不下两张床；假如他想分屋睡，隔壁也没有房间。

他非常细致体贴，除非有特别的指令，他也几乎不让我走动。

我有一份精确到小时的日常作息时间表。他照顾好我的一切，如果我不加倍珍惜，真会觉得自己是卑鄙的忘恩负义之人。

约翰说，来这里纯粹是为了我，我应该好好休息，尽力多呼吸新鲜空气。“亲爱的，你的运动量取决于你的体力，”他说，“你的进食量也多多少少取决于你的胃口，而新鲜空气你随时都能呼吸到。”所以我们住进了顶层的那间育婴室。

那是一间通风很好的大房间，几乎占据了整个楼层，四面都是窗子，空气和阳光十分充沛。我判断，它最初是一间育婴室，后来变成了游戏室和健身房，因为窗子装有保护小孩的栏杆，墙上还有一些圆环和类似的东西。

看墙漆和墙纸，这里像是办过男童学校。墙纸已经剥落——我床头伸手可及之处的墙纸被撕成一大块一大块的，对面墙脚有一大片也是如此。我此生从未见过比这更糟糕的墙纸了。

其中那蔓生开来华丽杂乱的纹饰，简直犯了艺术里的每一项大忌。

当你的目光追随它时，它沉闷得足以迷惑你的视线，又鲜明得不断激起你去一探究竟的欲望。当你追随那些蹩脚而飘忽的曲线看上一小段后，却发现它们突然无疾而终、自断前程——从一个极反常的角度跌落，在闻所未闻的矛盾中自我毁灭。

那色彩实在令人不快，几乎令人作呕；一种不洁净的焦黄色，在缓缓变化的日照中褪成了奇怪的颜色。

有些地方，呈现出一种乏味而又耀眼的橘黄色，其他地方则是一种惨淡的硫黄色。

难怪孩子们讨厌它！假如我不得不久居此地，我也会嫌弃它。

约翰来了，我要把这张纸放到一边去——我哪怕写下一个字，他都会厌恶。

我们来此地已经两个星期了，自从第一天起，我就没有写作的欲望。

此刻我坐在窗边，就在顶层这间恶劣的育婴室里。只要我愿意，没有什么能够阻止我写作，除非我体力不支。

约翰整个白天都不在，病人病情严重时，他晚上都要出诊。

我很欣慰我的病情并不严重！

可这些精神问题令人极其消沉。

约翰并不知道我有多么痛苦。在他的认知里，我没有痛苦的理由，而这足以让他感到满意。

当然我只是神经质而已。我没有尽到我在任何一方面的职责，这真的令我心情沉重！

我本想对约翰有所帮助，让他安心、感到宽慰，可到了今天这个地步，我已然成了他的累赘。

没有人会相信，我付出了多大的努力，却连最简单的事情——穿衣、招待客人，以及订购物品——都力不从心。

幸亏玛丽很擅长照看宝宝。多可爱的一个宝贝！

但是我不能和他在一起，这也让我非常紧张。

我想约翰从来没觉得紧张不安。他狠狠嘲笑了我对墙纸的反应！

他原本想要给这个房间贴上新墙纸，后来他却说我是在放纵自己被情绪左右——对一位神经质患者来说，最坏的事情就是让这种幻想肆意生长。

约翰说，墙纸换过之后，便轮到笨重的床架，接着是带栏杆的窗户，然后是楼梯口的那扇门，如此等等。

“你知道这个地方对你的健康有益，”约翰说，“而且说真的，亲爱的，我可不想为了只租三个月的房屋大动干戈。”

“那我们搬到楼下吧，”我说，“楼下有那么漂亮的房间。”

他拥我入怀，唤我为幸运的小可爱，说如果我想的话，他愿搬去地下室，还会请人将它粉刷一新。

关于床、窗户，以及其他，他倒是说对了。

这是一间人人都会心仪的房间，通风又舒适，当然我也不会傻到为了一时的念头而为难约翰。

我确实喜欢上这个大房间了，除了那可怕的墙纸。

从一扇窗子望出去，我能看见花园，那里有被浓荫遮蔽的神秘的藤架凉亭，有怒放的老气的花朵，还有灌木丛和长满疙瘩的树木。

透过另一扇窗子，我可以看见迷人的海湾，还有一处隶属于这套房子的私人小码头。一条美丽的林荫小径从房子向下延伸至码头。我总是幻想路人在这些数不清的小路上和凉亭下散步，但是约翰已经警告我绝对不要沉溺于幻想。他说我的想象力以及虚构故事的习惯，会使得像我这样神经衰弱的病人产生各种活跃的幻想，我应该运用我的意念和理智去遏制这种倾向。于是我听从了他的建议。

有时候我想，要是我可以恢复到能写一点儿东西，我就能放下思想重负，得到休息。

可我发现，只要我一开始尝试，就会感觉非常疲惫。

在没有任何建议和陪伴的情况下写作，是一件十分令人气馁的事。约翰说，当我真正康复后，他愿邀请表亲亨利和朱莉娅前来长住；但随后补充道，以我现在的状况，他宁可在我的枕头里放烟花，也不愿意让这些会令我情绪激动的人环绕在我周围。

我希望自己能快点儿康复。

不过我不能去思考这件事。那墙纸仿佛对自己的恶劣影响全然自知。

墙纸上有一种反复出现的斑点，那图案就像一只被拧断的脖子从那里耷拉下来，两只凸出的眼睛倒着瞪着你。

我对这图案的粗俗感到愤怒，而它们似乎还永无止境。它们上下左右匍匐而行，那些荒诞可笑、死鱼一样的眼睛则到处都是。有一个地方两边的宽度没有对上，竖直的衔接线两侧上上下下都是眼睛的图案，一侧比另一侧略高。

我从未在无生命体上见过如此丰富的表情，现在我们知道它们可以有多么丰富的表情了！小时候我经常睡不着，便躺在床上盯着空白的墙壁和简单的家具看，从中得到的乐趣和恐惧比大多数孩子在玩具店里得到的还要多。

我犹记得我们家那个巨大的老式衣柜，它的球形把手曾多么温和地闪烁着光泽；还有一把椅子，就像是一位坚定有力的朋友。

我曾觉得，如果其他任何一样东西露出狰狞的表情，我一定会跳入那把椅子，寻求安全。

这间房子里的家具，虽然和其他部分搭配不甚和谐，但鉴于它们都是临时从楼下搬来的，这一点也可以接受。我猜测当这间房被用作游戏室时，那些育婴用品也不得不搬出去。难怪房间的剩余部分被孩子们野蛮地破坏到面目全非。

正如我之前所说，一处处的墙纸都被撕破了，而它们和墙面曾像亲兄弟一样紧紧贴在一起——孩子们一定不乏毅力和怨恨才能把它们撕下来。

地板被划得沟壑纵横、坑坑洼洼，时不时扎出一根木刺，灰泥也被挖了出来，遍地都是。而这张笨重的大床，是我们在房间里找到的唯一的家具，它看上去似乎经历过战争的浩劫。

但对于这些，我丝毫不在乎——我眼里只有那墙纸。

约翰的妹妹来了。一个如此可爱的姑娘，对我又关心体贴！我绝不能让她发现我在写作。

她是一个完美又热情的管家，对这份工作也心满意足。我确信，她认为正是写作害得我生了病。

她出门后我就是能写作的，透过这些窗户，我目送她一路远去。

有一扇窗可以俯瞰那条路，一条林荫遮蔽的可爱的蜿蜒曲径。还有一扇窗正好眺望远处的乡村，那也是一处可爱的乡村，遍布着高大的榆树和丝绒般的草地。

墙纸还有一种不同色调的隐藏图案，特别令人不适，因为你只能在特定光线下才能看见它，而且还看不清楚。

但是在墙纸没有褪色的地方，在阳光正好的地方，我能看见一个奇怪的、讨厌的，而且形状不明的图案，仿佛躲在那愚蠢又显眼的表层图案后面，鬼鬼祟祟地走动。

约翰的妹妹上楼来了！

哎呀，七月四日[1]终于过去了！人们都走了，我累极了。约翰认为稍微见一见人，对我或许有益处，所以妈妈、内莉和孩子们刚刚来这里住了一个星期。

我自然一件事也没有做。现在是詹妮负责一切家务。

但我还是感到一样的疲劳。

约翰说，如果我不能尽快康复，今年秋天他就要把我送到威尔·米切尔[2]那里。

然而我根本不想去。我有一个朋友曾是他的病人，她说米切尔就跟约翰和我哥哥一样，甚至更过分！

况且，去那里路途遥远，于我是难以承受的。

我觉得任何事情都不值得我动一动手指，我变得异常不安，十分易怒。

我无缘无故地哭泣，大多数时候都在哭泣。

当然，约翰或别人在场时，我不会哭，我独自一人时才哭。

最近很多时候我都是一个人，约翰经常因为要照顾重症患者而留在镇上。而当我需要独处时，詹妮总是给我自由。

我会在花园里或是沿着那条可爱的小径散散步，在玫瑰花荫下的门廊里坐一坐，或者在这里躺上一会儿。

我真的喜欢上这个房间了，虽然那墙纸还在。也许正是因为这墙纸。

墙纸就这样占据了我的心！

我躺在这张无法移动的大床上——我确信，它是被钉子牢牢固定在地面上的——视线追踪着那个图案，一小时又一小时。我向你保证，这就像做体操一样有益。这样说吧，我从底部开始，视线落在那边角落下面还没有被触碰过的地方；我下了一千次决心，一定要追随那无意义的图案，直到得出某种结论。

我对设计原则略知一二，我知道这图案并非根据辐射、变换、重复或对称等法则（或是任何我听说过的设计逻辑）排布的。

当然，图案在每个幅宽上都是重复的，但在别的方向上并无规律可循。

从一个角度看，每个幅宽都是独立的，臃肿的曲线和花饰——一种蹩脚的罗马花纹——带着癫狂在愚昧的竖列里上下摇摆。

但从另一个角度看，它们又对角式地衔接在一起，蔓生的轮廓线越出边界，形成倾斜的巨大波纹，就像一群舞动的海藻在全力追逐，看起来很恐怖。

整个图案也在水平方向延展，至少表面如此，我费尽心力想辨认出它在那个方向上的排列次序。

他们贴上了一条宽幅的水平腰线，这又加剧了混乱。

在房间一侧，墙纸几乎完好无损。当交错的光线暗淡下来，斜阳直射那里时，我几乎可以幻想到辐射线——漫无止境的怪影仿佛环绕着一个共同的中心而成形，又以同样的离心力向前突然跌落出去。

追随墙纸的图案令我感到疲倦。我想我要小睡片刻。

我不明白为什么我要写这个。

我并不想写。

我觉得很无力。

而且我知道约翰会认为它很可笑。但我必须用某种方式说出我的感觉和想法——它对我真是很大的安慰！

但是要付出的努力比获得的安慰还要大。

我有一半时间慵懒至极，总是躺在床上。

约翰说我不能丧失体力，他让我吃鳕鱼鱼肝油和大量的补品、补药，麦芽酒、葡萄酒和嫩肉则更为常见。

亲爱的约翰！他深爱我，痛恨我生病。几天前，我跟他真诚又理性地聊过一次，我告诉他我多希望他能允许我离开此地，去我的表亲亨利和朱莉娅那儿小住。

他却说我既承受不了离开此地，也无法忍受那边的生活。我也没能为自己据理力争，因为我话还没说完就哭了起来。

对我来说，正常思考变得愈发艰难。我想这正是我的神经衰弱造成的。

亲爱的约翰将我抱起，径直抱到楼上，然后把我放在床上。他坐在我身边念书给我听，直到我困倦。

他说我是他心爱的人，是他的安慰，是他的一切，我必须为了他照顾好我自己，我得保持健康。

他说，除了我自己，没有人能帮我走出困境，我必须依靠自我意志和自控力，不可以再任凭愚蠢的幻想蔓延。

毕竟还有一丝慰藉，那就是我的宝宝健康又快乐，不必住进这间贴着可怖墙纸的育婴室里。

如果不是我们占用了这个房间，我那有福的孩子肯定要住进来！多么幸运地逃过一劫啊！唉，无论如何我都不能让我的孩子，一个柔弱的小东西，住在这样一个房间里。

我之前从未想过这个问题，好在约翰把我留在了这里，你瞧，婴儿可没有我这样的忍耐力。

当然我再也没有对他们提起墙纸的事——我太明智了——但我仍然在观察它。

墙纸上有些东西，除了我，没人知道，以后也不会有人知道。

隐匿在表层图案背后的那些暗淡的图形，一天天地清晰起来了。

它的形状保持不变，只是数量越来越多。

那图形就像是一个女人弯下身子，在表层图案后缓慢地爬行。我一点儿也不喜欢它。我思考——我开始想——我盼望约翰能把我带离此地！

跟约翰谈论我的病情太困难了，因他如此智慧，又因他如此爱我。

但是昨晚我尝试了一次。

那是一个月夜。月色从四周注入房间，和白天的太阳光无异。

有时，我讨厌见到月光，它悄无声息地爬行，如此缓慢，总是透过这扇或那扇窗户进入房间。

约翰睡了，我不愿吵醒他，所以静静地注视着月光照在起伏的墙纸上，直到它令我感到害怕。

后面那个模糊的人影仿佛在摇动图案，好像想要挣脱而出。

我轻轻地起身，走过去触摸墙纸，看它是否真的在动。我回到床上时，约翰醒了。

“怎么了，小姑娘？”他说，“别那样起来走动——你会感冒的。”

我想这正是谈话的良机。我告诉他，实情是我在这里并没有好转，希望他能带我离开。

“哎呀，亲爱的！”他说，“我们的租期还有三个星期，我不知道那之前怎么走。

“家里的维修还没有完工，而且我现在也不太可能离开城镇。如果你有任何危险，我肯定能，当然也会带你走。但你真的好多了，亲爱的，不管你自己是否意识到了。我是医生，亲爱的，我知道。你恢复了些体重，脸上有血色了，胃口也好多了，真的，你让我放心多了。”

“我一点儿都没有长胖，”我说，“体重还轻了一些。晚上你在时我的胃口或许好些，但早上你一离开我的胃口就差了！”

“上帝保佑她的小心脏！”约翰使劲地抱了我一下，“她想生病就生病吧！但现在我们要争分夺秒地睡觉，明天早上再谈！”

“那你不打算走啦？”我郁闷地问道。

“哎呀，亲爱的，我怎么能呢？只有三个星期了，然后趁詹妮收拾房子时，我们走几天，好好享受一次短途旅行。真的，亲爱的，你好多了！”

“或许身体是好多了——”我刚一开口便咽了回去，因为约翰坐直了身子，严厉而责备地看着我，我无法再继续。

“亲爱的，”他说，“我请求你，为了我，为了我们的孩子，也为你自己，你一刻也不要让那个念头再进入你的头脑！对你这种性情的人来说，没有比这种幻想更危险、更魅惑的了，这是错误和愚蠢的幻想。我作为一名内科医生这样对你说，难道你还不能信任我吗？”

关于此事我便不再提及，很快我们就睡了。他以为我先睡着了，但我没有。我躺在床上有好几小时，试图确认墙纸的表层和背后的图案是一起移动，还是分开移动。

在白天看来，这样的图案缺乏连贯性，毫无规则可言，让正常人都感到愤怒。

墙纸的颜色本就丑陋至极、变化多端，令人恼火，而墙纸的图案更是极大的折磨。

你以为你已经看透了它，但正当你顺利地追随它时，它却向后翻了个筋斗，躲开你的追逐。它打了你一记耳光，把你撞翻在地，然后践踏你。这就像是一场噩梦。

墙纸的表层图案是华丽的阿拉伯式花纹，令人联想到一种菌类。如果你能想象一串串伞菌的样子，无穷无尽的伞菌在发育抽芽，绵延卷绕着——噢，就是那样的东西。

有时候，它就是那样！

墙纸有一个显著的特征，只有我一个人注意到了，那就是它会随着光线变化。

阳光从东边的窗子照进时——我总是会观察第一束长直的光线——图案在这光线里变化得如此之快，让人难以相信。

所以我总是观察它。

在月光下——如果有月亮的话，房间整晚都会月光朗照——我简直认不出那是同一张墙纸了。

晚上，在任何一种光线下——在暮色下，在烛光下，或是在灯光下，而最可怖的是在月光下，墙纸都变成了栏杆！我是指表层图案，而图案后面的那个女人真是清晰可见。

很长一段时间，我都没有意识到墙纸后面那模糊的图案是什么，而现在我非常确定它是一个女人。

日光下，她温顺、安静。我想，正是那图案使她一动不动。这真令人困惑，也让我长时间地默不作声。

我现在总是躺着。约翰说这对我的身体有好处，而且我要尽量多睡。

他确实形成了一个习惯，每餐过后都让我躺一小时。

我相信这是个很坏的习惯，因为你瞧，我并没有睡着。

而且那是欺骗的温床，因为我没有告诉他们我醒着——噢，不！

事实上我有点儿害怕约翰了。

他有时显得很奇怪，甚至詹妮的神情也令人费解。

偶尔我闪过一个念头，可以说是一种科学假设吧——或许就是因为墙纸！

我曾经在约翰不经意的时候观察过他。我以最若无其事的借口突然走进房间，有好几次发现他正盯着墙纸！詹妮也是如此。有一次我发现詹妮把手放在墙纸上。

她不知道我在房间里，而我极力克制自己，用一种平静得不能再平静的声调问她，她在对墙纸做什么。而她转过身来，好像窃贼被人捉住一样，看上去有点儿恼羞成怒——质问我为什么这样吓唬她！

她说，任何东西碰到墙纸都会沾上污色，她发现我所有的衣物和约翰的衣服上都有黄色污渍，希望我们更小心些！

听起来是不是很合情合理？其实我知道她正在研究那图案，可我坚信除了我没有人能发现它的秘密！

* * *

与以往相比，目前的生活令人兴奋许多。你瞧，我有更多值得期盼和观察的东西。我的胃口确实变好了，人也比从前更安静了。

约翰见我状况改善，高兴极了！前几天，他甚至笑了笑，说我看上去活力四射，尽管房间里的墙纸还在。

我笑着转移了话题。我无意告知他正是因为墙纸——他会取笑我的，甚至有可能把我带走。

在解开墙纸的秘密之前，我还不想离开。租约还剩一个星期，我想时间是够用了。

我感觉好多了！晚上我睡眠不多，观察图案的发展实在有趣；但是白天我睡眠充足。

白天，墙纸显得无聊又令人困惑。

伞菌总是吐出新芽，到处都是新的黄色。尽管我认真地数过它们的数量，却永远也数不清。

那墙纸有着最奇怪的黄色！它使我想起见过的所有的黄色东西——不是毛茛那种黄花，而是污秽的、恶劣的黄色东西。

而且那墙纸还有一个特点——它的气味！我们一走进房间我就闻到了，但由于通风和阳光充足，那气味不算难闻。现在一个星期里都是雾雨天气，不管窗户是关还是开，气味总是经久不散。

这气味缓缓地爬满了整幢房子。

我发现这气味盘旋在餐厅里，悄悄潜入起居室，隐藏在大厅，埋伏在楼梯上等待我。

它渗入了我的头发。

甚至我出门骑马时，如果我趁其不备突然回头——也会闻到那个气味！

而且它还是如此奇特的味道！我花了几小时分析它，想弄清它闻起来像什么。

一开始，它并不浓郁，并且非常柔和，却是我遇到过的最微妙和最持久的味道。

现在天气潮湿，它就变得强烈，晚上我醒过来时发现它正悬在我上方。

起初，这气味总困扰我。我曾认真地想过烧掉房子——为了捕捉到这气味。

不过现在我习惯它了。我能想到的唯一与之相似的就是那墙纸的颜色！一种黄色的气味。

墙上有一个非常滑稽的痕迹，在下面很低的地方，靠近踢脚板。那是一道沿墙延展、环绕整个房间的条纹。它从除了床以外的家具后面绕过，长直而平坦，似乎被摩擦过一次又一次。

我好奇它是如何形成的，又是谁干的，他们为什么这样做。一圈，一圈，又一圈；一圈，一圈，又一圈——看得我头晕目眩！

终于，我还是发现了什么。

通过夜晚的长时间观察，在墙纸图案的诸多变化中，我终于发现了它的秘密。

表层图案果然在动——难怪！是图案后面的女人在摇动它！

有时候我觉得图案后面有很多很多女人；有时候又觉得只有一个，她飞快地来回匍匐而行，动作震动了整个图案。

遇到墙上的明处，她就安静不动；遇到暗处，她就抓住栏杆，使劲地摇动。

她一直努力想爬出来。然而没有人能从那图案里爬出来——图案勒死了她们，我想这就是墙纸上有那么多头颅的原因。

她们穿过来了，然而图案扼杀了她们，将她们倒吊起来，勒得她们眼珠上翻！

如果把那些头颅盖住或截掉，图案就远远没有那么可怕了。

我猜，那个女人在白天爬了出去！

我会告诉你为什么——悄悄告诉你——我见过她！

透过我房间的每一扇窗，我都能看见她！

这是同一个女人，我知道，因为她总是爬行，而其他被困住的女人不在白天爬行。

我看见她在那条长长的林荫小径里，来来回回地爬行。我看见她在暗处的葡萄藤架下，环绕整个花园爬行。

我看见她沿着树下那条长道一直爬行，一有马车过来，她就躲入黑莓藤下。

我丝毫不想责怪她。被人发现大白天的在爬行，她必定感到非常羞耻！

我在白天爬行时总是锁上门。晚上我不能这样做，因为我知道约翰会立刻起疑心。

约翰最近也很反常，我不想去激怒他。我真希望他能搬到另一个房间！另外，我不想让任何除了我以外的人在晚上把那个女人放出来。

我时常好奇自己能否同时透过所有窗户看见她。

但是无论我转身有多快，只能在一个时刻观察一扇窗户。

而且尽管我总能看见她，她却可能爬得更快，超过我转身的速度！

有时候我看着她爬到空旷的乡间，速度快得像被强风吹动的云影。

要是能把表层的图案同下面的剥离出来，那多好啊！我打算尝试一下，一点点地剥。

我还发现了另一件有趣的事情，但现在我不想说！轻信他人是不好的。

我只有两天时间来剥掉这墙纸了，而且我相信约翰已经有所察觉了。我不喜欢他的眼神。

我听到他问詹妮许多关于我的专业性问题。詹妮也给他做了很详细的汇报。

她说我白天睡得很多。

约翰知道我晚上睡眠很不好，尽管我是那么安静！

他也问了我本人各种各样的问题，还假装充满爱意与柔情。

好像我无法看穿他似的！

不过他这样做我也不奇怪，毕竟在这墙纸下睡了三个月。

尽管只有我对墙纸产生了兴趣，但我确信，不知不觉中约翰和詹妮也被墙纸影响到了。

太好啦！这是最后一天，不过时间够用了。约翰今晚将待在镇上，并且要到晚上才出发。

詹妮想与我一起睡——狡猾的东西！但我告诉她，我独自一人睡肯定会休息得好一些。

这是聪明的借口，因为我根本不是一个人！月夜初始，那可怜的东西就开始匍匐而行、摇动图案，我便立即起来跑过去帮她。

我拉她摇，我摇她拉，天亮之前我们剥掉了好几码墙纸。

一长条墙纸，有我本人那么高，绕房半圈那么长。

太阳升起了，那讨厌的图案开始嘲笑我，我宣布我今天就要把它结束！

我们明天就要离开了，他们正把我房间里所有的家具搬回楼下，恢复到出租前的状态。

詹妮惊讶地看着墙壁，但我欢快地告诉她，我这么做纯粹是出于对那邪恶墙纸的厌恶。

她笑着说她乐意自己来做，而我绝不能累倒。

她那样说是多么违心啊！

但我就在这里，除了我，没有人能触摸这墙纸——任何人都不行！

她想让我离开房间——她的用意太明显了！但我说现在房间这样安静、空荡和干净，我想要躺下来，尽可能再睡一会儿，晚餐时也不要叫醒我——我醒来后会叫她的。

她只好走了，所有的用人都走了，东西也都搬走了，除了那个被钉住的大床架，以及床架上那张原本就有的帆布床垫。

今晚我们将睡在楼下，明天乘船回家。

我很喜欢这个房间，现在它又空了。

这个床架磨损得很厉害！

想想那些孩子曾在这里怎样嬉闹过！

但是我必须着手工作了。

我锁上门，把钥匙扔到了楼下的门前小路上。

我不想出去，约翰回来之前我也不想让任何人进来。

我要让他大吃一惊。

我拿了一根绳子上楼，詹妮并没有发觉。假如那个女人真的从墙纸里出来了，试图逃离，我可以绑住她！

但是我忘记了，如果不站在什么东西上，我伸手够不到那么高！

这张床动不了！

我试图把床抬起来，推过去，直到累得一瘸一拐，我气急败坏地咬下一小块床角，却弄伤了自己的牙齿。

我站在地板上把够得着的墙纸全撕了下来。墙纸黏得吓人，而图案也享受着这种胶着！那些被勒下的头颅，凸起的眼睛，以及摇摆着滋生的伞菌，正发出嘲讽的尖叫声！

我愤怒得无以复加，要尝试些疯狂的举动。跳窗将是英勇之举，可是栏杆实在太坚固了，根本没必要去尝试。

而我也不会这么做。当然不会。我非常清楚，走出这一步是不恰当的，还可能被人误解。

我甚至都不想往窗外看——外面有那么多女人在爬行，而且她们爬得飞快。

我不知道她们是否像我一样，也是从那墙纸里爬出来的。

但是我现在已经被我悄悄藏匿的那根绳子牢牢地捆住了——你休想把我拉到那条路上！

我觉得到了晚上我应该回到那图案后面去，但这可不容易做到！

从墙纸里走出来，待在这个大房间里，我可以随意爬行，可真是件乐事！

我不想出去。即使詹妮叫我，我也不出去。

出去后你只能在地面上爬行，而且一切都是绿色而不是黄色的。

然而，在这里我可以在地板上顺畅地爬行，环绕墙壁的那条长长的污渍与我齐肩，所以我不会迷失方向。

哎呀，约翰在门口！

没有用的，年轻人，你打不开门！

他嚷叫，砸门，好大声！

他在大叫着让人拿一把斧头来。

砸烂那扇美丽的门将是一件可耻的事！

“约翰，亲爱的！”我用最温柔的声音说，“钥匙在楼下门前的台阶旁，在芭蕉叶下面！”

这让他沉默了片刻。

然后他轻声细语地说：“开门，我亲爱的！”

“我打不开门，”我说，“钥匙在楼下门前的芭蕉叶下面！”

我又说了一遍，非常温柔和缓地重复了好几遍。我反反复复地说，他只好下楼去看。当然他找到了钥匙，走了进来。他却突然止步在门口。

“怎么回事？”约翰大叫，“天哪，你在干什么？”

我一边不动声色地爬行着，一边扭头去看他。

“我终于出来了，”我说，“不管你和詹妮怎么反对！我已经把大部分墙纸撕下来了，你们无法把我放回去！”

那个男人为什么就昏倒了呢？他确实昏过去了，正好倒在了墙边，挡住了我的爬行之路，所以每次我都只能从他身上爬过去！

[1]7月4日，美国国庆节。（书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2]塞拉斯·威尔·米切尔（1829-1914），美国哈佛大学医学博士、法学博士，提出了著名的“休息疗法”，用以治疗神经衰弱。休息疗法包括6-8周的禁闭，在此期间女性被禁止写作和进行社交活动，要求卧床休息，严重时会被进行电击治疗。相反，威尔·米切尔提出的治疗男性神经衰弱的方法则是去西部，进行大量的体力和脑力劳动，例如写作。本书作者夏洛特·珀金斯·吉尔曼曾接受过威尔·米切尔的治疗，但强烈谴责休息疗法给女性带来的伤害。

摇椅

/

一处摇曳的太阳光点，一个信号光源，在一片普通杂乱的房屋中间，在一条城市窄巷所有的沉闷昏暗之中，立刻吸引了我们的视线。

低矮的屋檐自水泥墙中伸出，落日发出一道明亮的光线，水平地穿越其下，落在窗边女孩的金色头发上。

她坐在一把高背摇椅上慢慢地前后摇晃，黄铜底座随着晃动闪闪发光。她的头始终没有抬起来，但她头发上的点点光芒却把街道点亮了。

我们两人停了下来，盯着这幅画面，这时就看见了楼下窗户上有一个小标牌——“房屋出租，配有家具”。怀着共同的憧憬，我们穿过马路，敲了敲暗淡的大门。

缓慢均匀的脚步声从里面传来，门开了，一阵少女柔和的笑声戛然而止——我们看到的是一位老妇人，面容呆滞，毫无表情，眼神无光。

是的，她有房间出租。是的，我们可以去看看。不，不提供服务。不，不提供餐食。她带着我们上了楼，一路这样单调地低语。这幢房子在一条穷街陋巷里，再普通不过，丝毫也不突出，跟其他的房子没什么不同。

她带我们看了两个紧挨着的房间，与大多数同类房间相比，既不好，也不坏。房间更没有什么引人注目之处，除了窗边那把还在轻轻摇晃的黄铜包边大椅子。

那个金发女孩却不见了。

我幻想着里屋传来了少女长袍的窸窣声——一阵浅笑——但是这个公寓房间的门是锁着的。我问那个老妇人，我们是否可以看看其他房间，她说，她没有其他房间可租。

我和哈尔在一旁商量了几句，便决定租下这两个房间，立刻搬进去。我们没有理由不这样做。我们正在寻找住处时，那道晃动的光线吸引了我们，住宿条件完全对得起我们出得起的价格。我们当场成交，又回到原来破旧的旅馆去拿了几样行李，当晚就重新安顿下来。

哈尔和我都是年轻的记者——“穷苦文人”，我们是一群奋斗的有志者中的一员，我们追求文学，就像从前扈从和侍卫向往骑士身份一样。我们正在赢得功名的路上。目前为止这仍是一项缓慢的事业，令人不快，报酬很低——我肯定这正像扈从和侍卫的工作：提供卑贱的服务，日复一日地保养骑士的盔甲；主人骑马的时候，他们长时间步行。然而扈从至少对他的主人和领主心怀敬意，而我们呢，唉！在我们这个行业里，我们有着充分的理由对位高者嗤之以鼻；并且坚信，当我们身处同样的职位后，我们的所作所为会高尚得多！

这或许纯粹是一种文学本能——当代用文字糊口的作家对“素材”的攫取，又或许是另一种——被无名美人莫名吸引的本能。反正不管是什么原因，这个地方吸引了我们，我们就来了。

从婴儿时期就开始的友谊把我们两人联系在一起，坚不可摧。哈尔是一个快乐、缺乏想象力而头脑清醒的人，我是一个敏感又浪漫的人，这也使得我们的关系更加亲密。

我们对彼此有着家庭生活般无所畏惧的坦诚，但也尊重彼此的私人空间，因此我们之间的关系也一直张弛有度。

我们兴致勃勃地研究了新住处。前面的房间是哈尔的，相当大，空荡荡的。后面的房间是我的，相当小，也空荡荡的。

我相信，他比较喜欢那个房间，是因为有窗户和摇椅。我喜欢另一个，是因为那扇锁着的门。我们两人都对这些偏好闭口不提。

“你确定你不想要这个房间吗？”哈尔问道。或许，他是意识到了自己的选择有一种隐秘的动机。

“不想，真的，”我带着同样的保留态度说道，“你房间里只看得到街道，而我的窗外有真正的‘风景’。我唯一嫉妒的是你那把椅子！”

“不管白天还是晚上，你随时都可以来啊，坐在椅子里摇吧，”他大度地说，“它舒服极了，虽然外表黑乎乎的。”

这是一把舒服的椅子，非常舒服的椅子，我们两人都经常用它。椅背很高，顶部略微向前弯曲，四个方角很重。这些方角、摇杆的两头、焊在扶手上的尖尖的巨大把手，以及其他每一个节点和包角，都用黄铜和椅身嵌合。

“可以用作攻城锤[3]！”哈尔说。

他坐在椅子里抽烟，在窗边缓慢而惬意地摇晃着。而我懒洋洋地躺在床脚边，看着一轮苍白的新月慢慢从西边的屋顶落下。

月亮终于落出了视线，房间变得越来越暗，我只能看见，在暗淡的天空下，哈尔英俊的脑袋和那弧形的椅背一起慢慢地来回移动。

“莫里斯，是什么把我们突然带到这里的？”他在黑暗中问道。

“三个原因，”我回答，“我们需要住处，这里条件合适，还有一个美丽的脑袋。”

“没错，”他说，“还有别的吗？”

“即使有，你也不会承认它的存在，我逻辑严谨的朋友。但我觉得在这件事上，还有某种冲动，或者至少是吸引力，并不完全来自那金色头发。”

“这次我同意你，”哈尔说，“我自己也有同样的感觉，即使我不轻易受这类冲动的影响。”

我们沉默了片刻。我可能闭上了眼睛——也许比我想象的要久，但似乎就在下一秒，有什么东西轻轻拂过我的胳膊，而我看到哈尔坐在他的大椅子上，在我身旁摇晃着。

“对不起，”看见我吃了一惊，他说，“这把椅子显然会‘走路’，我以前也见到过。”

我也是，我见过它移动到地毯上，但现在这儿没有地毯，我想我应该脱离梦境了。

他将那把沉重的椅子拉回窗边，然后我们准备就寝。

我们的门开着，可以隔空交谈。但很快我就睡着了，睡得很沉，一觉到天亮。我一定是做了一个相当逼真的梦，因为哈尔说我在他的椅子上摇晃了半夜，他说在星光下能清楚地看到我的轮廓。

“不，”我说，“是你在做梦。那把摇椅深深烙印在你脑子里啦。”

“那就当它是梦吧，”他快活地回答，“噩梦总比矛盾强，吸血鬼总比吵架好！好啦，我们去吃早餐吧！”

日子一天天过去，我们很奇怪那位迷人的金发女孩竟然踪影全无。但我们只是默默好奇着，谁也没有向对方提起此事。

有时我听见她在我隔壁的房间里轻轻地走动，或者在屋子里什么地方轻声笑着。相比之下，那母亲缓慢而均匀的脚步其实更加频繁，可就连她也不常露面。

据我所知，我们两人都只从街上看到过那女孩，因为她仍然会坐在窗边我们的椅子上。在理论上，这种行为是不被许可的，尤其是我们还在门上落了锁时，而她的出现则说明她还有一把钥匙。不，也可能是通过我房间的那扇门！我没有将这个想法说出来。每当我们从窗外看见她晃着摇椅时，我们都不会抱怨，而是偷偷飞快地跑上楼梯，希望吓她一跳。但我们从未成功过，只有那张椅子时不时地仍在摇晃，有时我也会想象有一股淡淡的甜蜜气味萦绕未散，一种令人悲伤又挑逗人的奇怪味道。但是有一天，我以为在房间里的是哈尔，便唐突地冲了进去。也就是在那时，我见到了她。那不过是惊鸿一瞥——身影迅疾、轻盈、无声地拂过——她消失在我自己的房间里。我跟着她，为自己的突然闯入致歉，但我没能追上她。那满怀妒意的门又锁上了。

每当被我们看到时，我们房东太太的漂亮女儿显然非常害羞。而奇怪的是，当我们不在时，她又显得十分自得。

我终究是看到了她，仅这一眼就会让我尽情地原谅她。她的美是一种奇特的美，无限迷人，又无限迷惑。我暗自赞叹，怀着痛苦的热盼，渴望再见她一面。但是我从没对哈尔说起我把她吓了一跳——这对那个女孩儿似乎不公平！她可能有充分的理由进到我们房间。也许我还能再见到她。

我开始找这样或那样的借口早早地回家，趁哈尔不在的时候，我又假借各种各样的理由进入他的房间。

不过，直到经历了无数次这样的突袭之后，我发现每每我以为他人在城里时，却能在他的房间里找到他。而他那些不必要的解释中，也多了一些牵强。直到那时我才开始怀疑，或许他和我一样，也在寻找着这同样一个身影。

不久我就确认了这个想法。一个日落时分，我正走到街角处——在打开的窗子的黑暗边框里，那个明亮的脑袋正有节奏地摆动。哈尔就在楼下的马路上。她向窗外看，笑了。他走进房子，上了楼。

我加快了脚步。我正好看到她停止晃动，那漂亮的脑袋转过去，哈尔站在她身后的阴影里。

我越过门，穿过街道，走了一小时、两小时——在某处吃完夜宵，到睡觉时间才回来。我心如刀绞，竭力想用理性说服自己，却失败了。或许哈尔和我有着同等的权利见她，但我依旧对他感到出奇的愤怒。

我回来的时候，灯光从白色的窗帘后面照过来，大椅子的影子矗立在那里一动不动，与另一个影子交错——是哈尔在抽烟。我走上楼去。

他热情洋溢地迎接我，问我为何回来这么晚，我在哪里吃的晚饭。他快活得不自然。我们之间忽然有了一种可怕的相互隐瞒。他什么也没说，我什么也没问，我们沉默地去睡觉了。

我责怪他对我们的神秘美人只字不提，但同样，我对自己那次见面也是守口如瓶。我左思右想，猜测他到底见过她几次面，她是否跟他说过话，她告诉了他什么，她待了有多久。

我整夜辗转反侧，哈尔也睡不着，我听见他在离我门很近的窗前和床边摇了好几个小时，我从来不知道有一把摇椅能像它一样“行走”。

快到早晨的时候，持续的嘎吱声和摇摆声令我神经崩溃，快要发作。

“看在上帝的分儿上，哈尔，停下来吧，去睡觉！”

“什么？”传来带着睡意的声音。

“别犯傻！”我说，“你摇个不停，我一夜都没合眼。快停下来，去睡觉吧。”

“去睡觉！我整晚都睡在床上，我希望你也是！你能别自己晃着椅子，还怪到我头上来吗？”

而在我们对话期间，我依旧听见他一直摇呀摇，摇呀摇，就在大厅门口！

我悄悄地站起身，走进房间，想给这不合时宜开玩笑的人一个惊吓，把他当场抓住。

两个房间都注满了月色映射下的暗淡粼光。在黑暗中我也了解这房间的模样，可是我刚进门就被绊了一下，重重地摔倒了。

哈尔立刻下床开灯。

“我亲爱的小男孩，你受伤了吗？”

我受伤了，这完全是他的错，因为椅子不在我以为的地方，而是紧临着我卧室的门。他一定是听见我进来的声音，便立即从摇椅跳回了床上。我生硬地拒绝了他的帮助，一瘸一拐地回到自己那无眠的枕头上。我的脚踝撞在一根焊了黄铜的摇杆上，疼得要命。我从未见过那样伤人的椅子——又大又重，十分不平衡，每一个连接处和边角都包裹着黄铜。哈尔和我以前都因为这个椅子受过罪，尤其是在黑暗中，我们忘了那把椅子究竟身处何处，但没有哪一次撞得像这次这么疼。哈尔不像是玩这种把戏的人，我带着受伤的心灵和脚踝爬上床，翻来覆去，昏昏欲睡，做着梦，时不时地惊醒，直到早晨。

尽管语气十分友善，但哈尔还是坚持说他睡着了，是我整晚都在摇。我真的开始生他的气了。

“这玩笑实在太过分了，”我终于说，“我不在意玩笑，即使很伤人，但总要有限度。”

“是的，我承认。”他意味深长地说。我们不再继续这个话题。

几天过去了。哈尔又与那个金发少女见了几次面，这是我从街上看见的。而除了痛苦地目睹这一切，我只是徒劳地等待。

这是难以忍受的，几乎比哈尔和我日益疏远的关系还要难以忍受，这深深地刺痛了我。我想，我们两人最终会十分乐意各奔东西，但谁也不愿意让另一个人独享这房间、这椅子、这未知的美丽。

一天早晨我偶然回到家，发现那个面容呆滞的房东太太正在整理房间。我尽力想讨好她，却是白费心思。

“你那把老式椅子真好看。”我说道。而她站在那里用围裙机械地擦拭黄铜包角。

她看着那在暗中闪闪发光的东西，几乎是带着一抹骄傲。

“是的，”她说，“一把好椅子！”

“有些年头了？”我追问道。

“是的，非常老了。”她简短地回答。

“但是我以为摇椅是现代美国的发明？”我说。

她冷漠地看着我。

“这是西班牙的，”她说，“西班牙橡木，西班牙皮革，西班牙黄铜，西班牙……”我没有听清最后一个词，她也不再多说，就离开了房间。

尽管坐起来很放松，很舒服，这把椅子本身却相当古怪，很不稳当。摇杆的后面又长又尖，总像是在伏击粗心大意的人；前端却骤然缩短。椅背那么高，顶上那么重，这重量和前面的短摇杆，让摇椅以令人吃惊的力度轻松却猛烈地向前倾斜。

这是我的经验之谈，每当我碰到这把摇椅，它就会突然倒在我身上。哈尔也深受其害。我们身上都伤痕累累，但两人谁也不愿把椅子搬走，只因为她会一晚又一晚地坐在椅子里，在夕阳的金色余晖中摇晃。

于是，每天晚上我们都早早地下班，各自匆匆赶回家，各走各的路，走到那条肮脏的街道，走到那扇神圣的窗下。

我不可能永远忍受下去。当哈尔先回家的时候，我在楼下的街道徘徊，透过我们的窗户可以看见那个可爱的脑袋和他的脑袋紧贴在一起。当我先回来的时候，却只能看到楼上的匆匆一瞥——一个令人迷惑的微笑——除此之外，再也没有别的。我走进房间时，她总是消失得无影无踪，徒留房间里牢牢锁着的内门。

有时我甚至捕捉到门闩的咔嗒声，听到另一边宽松长袍的沙沙声。有时，这种日复一日的失望，这种希望屡次落空的苦痛，驱使我跪在那扇门前，求她给我开门，用人类痛苦的心灵所能想到的每一种热烈的情话和劝告的言语对她哭诉。

哈尔现在既不跟我说话，也不看我一眼，只有刻意的礼貌和冷淡。既然他已经当着我的面说下谎言，我又怎能再坦诚相待？

一天晚上，我从街上看见他坐在那把椅子里，在宽阔平坦的太阳光影里，那个美丽的脑袋搭在他肩上。我忍无可忍了。假如他赢了，而且赢得如此彻底，我只要求跟她说一次话，然后跟他们两人从此永别。我重重地爬上楼梯，大声敲门，在哈尔的应和声中旋即进入房间，却发现他一个人坐着抽烟——是的，就在刚才搂着她的那把椅子上抽烟！

他刚刚才点燃那根雪茄，一个蒙蔽我眼睛的小动作。

“听着，哈尔，”我说，“我受不了了。我能否请求你一件事？让我看她一次，就一次，好让我跟她说一声再见，然后我就会从你们眼前消失！”

哈尔站起身，直视我的眼睛。他把整根雪茄扔出窗外，走到离我两英尺内的地方。

“你疯了吗？”他说，“我问她！我！我这辈子从来没有跟她说过话！而你——”他停住，转身而去。

“我什么？”我不顾一切地发问。

“你每天都见她，跟她说话，我不用把我亲眼所见全都重复一遍！”

“你不用，真的，”我说，“它甚至会让你更加无法自圆自说。在这个房间里我只见过她一次，转瞬即逝的一瞥——一句话也没有说。而我经常从街上看见她——跟你在一起！”

他脸色变得煞白，从我身边走到窗前，又转过身来。

“我从来没有在这个房间里见过她，哪怕是你所说的瞬间一瞥。我经常从街上看见她——跟你在一起！”

我们望着对方。

“你的意思是说，”我慢慢地问他，“我刚才并没有看见你坐在窗边的那把椅子上，还把她搂在怀里吗？”

“停！”他叫道，猛然挥手，却狠狠地打在了椅背的包角上。他机械地擦去手上三角伤口的血迹，目不转睛地盯着我。

“我看见你了。”我说。

“你没有！”他说。

我慢慢地转身走进我的房间。我不忍心告诉那个人，那个比兄弟还亲的人，他在撒谎。

我把头埋在手掌中，在床上坐了下来。不久我听见哈尔的门开了又关，我听见楼梯上他的脚步声，大门在他身后砰地关上了。他走了，我不知道他去了哪里。就算他正在走向死亡，就算我的一言一语能够拯救他，我也会保持沉默。我不知道自己在那里坐了多久，被无望的爱、嫉妒和仇恨所包围。

突然，从空房间的一片寂静中，传来了那把大椅子平稳摇动的嘎吱声。也许——一定是！我一跃而起，悄无声息地打开门。她坐在窗前，看向窗外，而且——是的——她给了窗下的某人一个飞吻。啊，她是多么美丽啊！多么美丽！我向她走近一步。我伸出手，我说了些自己都不知所以的话——突然，楼梯上传来了哈尔快步走来的声音。

她也听到了，她看了我一眼，微妙、神秘、胜利的一眼。而就在哈尔进门时，她从我身边溜了过去，溜进了我的房间。他看见她离开了。他径直朝我走来，我想他会原地把我打倒。

“别挡我的道，”他叫道，“我要跟她谈谈。难道我看见的还不够吗？（他用受伤的手朝窗户指了指）让我过去！”

“她不在那儿，”我回答，“她已经去另一个房间了。”

我们的身旁响起一阵低低的笑声，一阵微弱的、柔和的、银铃般的笑声，几乎近在我的耳边。

哈尔用力推开我，猛地打开门，走了进去——房间是空的。

“你把她藏在哪里了？”他反问道。我冷冷地指着另一扇门。

“这么说她的房间和你的房间是相通的，是吗？”他苦笑着嘀咕，“难怪你更喜欢‘风景’！也许我也能打开它？”他把手放在门闩上。

我微笑，因为痛苦的经验告诉我它总是锁着的，对我所有的祈祷和恳求都无动于衷。让他像曾经的我那样跪在那儿苦苦哀求吧！但是门闩在他的手下打开了！我跑到他身边，一起朝里面看——一个壁橱，小得可怜，又空又浅，像空棺材！

他转向我，脸色因愤怒而发白，就像我的脸因恐惧而发白。我脑子里想的不是他。

“你对她做了什么？”他叫道。然后轻蔑地说——“我竟然停下来质问一个骗子！”

我没有理他，而是走回另一个房间——那把大椅子在窗边摇晃着。

他跟在我后面，失望得发狂。他的手放在摇晃的椅背上，手指用力地紧紧抓住它，直到指甲都发白了。

“你要离开这个地方吗？”他说。

“不。”我说。

“我不会再跟一个骗子、一个叛徒一起生活下去了。”他说。

“那你只能自杀。”我说。

他低声咒骂了一句，扑向我，但脚被长摇杆绊了一下，重重地摔倒了。

我心中涌起一股巨大的仇恨，如此强烈，以至于几乎想在他躺倒的身上踩一脚，让他像狗一样死去——我极力克制才从他身边转身，离开了房间。

我回来的时候，天已经亮了。清早寂静，太阳还没有升起，屋顶、墙壁和路面上却铺满了明亮的强光。我在楼下驻足，找到房东太太，告诉她我即将离开。我敲了一扇又一扇门，试着打开；我进了一个又一个房间，彻底搜查了一番。在整幢房子里，从地窖到阁楼，除了我们的房间外，其他房间什么家具也没有，没有人住过的痕迹。处处都是灰尘，灰尘，遍布蜘蛛网。除此之外，别无他物。

我的心奇怪地一沉，回到我们自己的门口。

我清楚地听见了房间里房东太太缓慢而均匀的脚步声，还有那柔和的、低低的笑声。我冲了进去。

房间里毫无生命的痕迹，两个房间都是。

是的，什么生命都没有。因为，当我怀着心中对哈尔所有的情感冲到他在窗下的所躺之处时，我发现他已经死了。

死了，而且死得惨烈至极。三个重重的标记——拳头的击打形成了三个深深的三角形裂口。我站起来——连那把椅子也不见了！

又是那窃窃私语的笑声。我绝望地逃离了那恐怖的房子。

我从街上瞥了一眼那扇致命的窗户，我的目光战栗。

冉冉升起的太阳给所有的屋顶都镀上了金，水平的光线打在对面建筑物高高的玻璃窗格上。窗边那把大椅子，那甜美的面孔，那垂下的眼睛，还有那晃动的金色脑袋，都反射出一缕宁静的光辉。

[3]攻城锤，中世纪的一种武器，主体为一根重圆木，圆形或锥形的头部用金属制成，用以撞击围攻城镇和城堡的城墙或城门。

老水

/

那湖水，平滑如镜地躺在水平的金色光线里。树木覆盖的湖岸投下长长的阴影，铺满了水面，那里一片漆黑，深不可测。湖的东岸有一处尖耸的小悬崖，它那明亮的倒影顺着水面铺展开来。

一只平静的独木舟慢慢地划过开阔的金色水面，由一双熟练的手臂迅疾而平稳地向前推去。

“多么强壮！多么辉煌！啊！她就像一位女武神！”那位诗人说道。奥斯古德太太抬起头，用欣赏的目光望着那深色的高大身躯。

“你不知道你这样说我有多高兴！”她温柔地说，“我也有这样的感觉，却没有天赋把它们付诸文字。而埃伦又是如此现实。”

“是你的女儿就一定会有诗意的灵魂。”他回答道，沉静地笑着。

“我真希望是这样。但我对这一点从来都没有信心！她小时候，我总是给她读诗。可她对诗没有兴趣——除非是她所谓的‘故事诗’。一旦她可以自己拿主意了，她就选择了科学。”

“诗就在那里。”他一边说着，眼睛盯着那光滑的褐色手臂——它离他越来越近。“那种姿势！那种动作！它就是诗性本身——还有那身体！她的身体就是一首诗！”

奥斯古德太太注视着那精准的着陆，那强劲的拉力带动独木舟越过滚柱[4]，向上进入小船屋。“埃伦是如此现实！”她低声说道，“她甚至不承认自己的美丽。”

“她还没有觉醒，”诗人呢喃说，“还没有觉醒！”他的大眼睛似乎闪烁着希望的光芒。

“她也很勇敢，”母亲接着说，“她并不是真喜欢水，只是强迫自己到水面上去。我想她心里很害怕——但不愿承认。噢，埃伦！到这里来吧，亲爱的。这是潘达克斯特先生——那位诗人。”

埃伦伸出她褐色的手，手冰凉；她的手还有点儿湿，因为才在水边匆匆洗过。他热情地紧握了一下，对她划独木舟的技巧表示钦佩。

“哦，那没什么，”女孩儿说，“划独木舟非常容易。”

“你能教我吗？”他问，“我会是个最听话的学生。”

她狐疑地上下打量他那魁梧的身躯。他无疑是很健壮的，粗壮的四肢定然意味着力量，但他缺乏一种来自长期训练的平衡感以及一种自信的敏捷。

“你不会划桨吧？”她说。

“原谅我的无知吧——我从未坐上过那精巧纤细的小船。但我很乐意试试。”

“潘达克斯特先生主要在欧洲活动，比在美国待的时间多，”她母亲急忙插嘴道，“我亲爱的，不是所有人都喜爱这项运动。我相信如果你有兴趣，我女儿会非常乐意教你的，潘达克斯特先生。”

“当然，”埃伦说，“我可以尝试着教他一下。你想明天早晨开始吗？我通常很早就出发了。”

“我很愿意，”他说，“我们将一起向极光问好。”

“是曙光吧，亲爱的先生。”她母亲带着歉意，微笑地提示道。

“噢，是的，”女孩儿表示同意并对母亲说，“我还是认得出极光的，妈妈。晚饭做好了吗？”

“等你穿好衣服我们就可以用餐了，”母亲说，“穿上你的蓝色连衣裙，亲爱的——浅色的那件。”

“好啊。”埃伦说着轻快地跑上小径。

“多美呀！多美呀！”他喃喃地说，目光追寻着她飞逝的身影。“啊，夫人！你有这样一个女儿，这对你该多么有意义啊！看到你自己的青春——转瞬即逝——又重现在你眼前！”他说着，低头赞赏地瞥了一眼女主人的轮廓。

晚餐时分，奥斯古德夫人穿着一件有点儿古典的长裙出现在餐桌前，漂亮的头发上粗野地绑着些金饰。她满意地看着自己的女儿，在一片迷雾般的蓝色中，像年轻的朱诺[5]一样闪亮。埃伦兼具母亲的美貌和父亲的力量。她身材高大，流畅优雅的线条下藏着有力的肌肉。她的举止像一位王后，又带着一种健康女学生活泼烂漫的神情。一位健康的女学生，这确实就是埃伦。

她的食欲如此旺盛，她母亲几乎害怕这会令诗人有些不满，但很快发现诗人也正尽情享用着厨师准备的餐点。埃伦也观察他，她坦率地对诗人的用餐习惯表现出了些许异议，指出诗人糖果和奶油吃得太多，而且似乎过于喜欢喝咖啡和利口酒。

“埃伦从来不喝咖啡，”他们坐在豪华的起居室时，奥斯古德太太解释说，“我想是出于训练的考虑。”

“妈妈！我们还处在训练期！”女孩抗议道，“尽管不是正式的——因为没有比赛——但是我喜欢保持良好的状态。我在学校是尾桨手，品达克斯特先生，我在学校是尾桨手。”

“是潘达克斯特，亲爱的。”她母亲低声说。

这个魁梧的男人拿起了他的第二杯咖啡，坐在了女孩儿旁边。

“我的景仰之情无以言表，”他说着，身体前倾，“你像瑙西卡[6]，像阿塔兰忒[7]，像我梦中的那些女人！”

她对他公开的赞美并没有感到不快——即使是健美的女孩也会对恭维感到愉悦——尽管她接受得有些尴尬。

“我不相信梦。”她说。

“不，”他表示赞成，“不——人们也绝不该相信梦。可是——难道你从来没有反复做过一个梦吗？一个会重复的梦？”

“我做过噩梦，”她承认说，“恐怖的梦，但不是同样的梦。”

“在可怕的梦里，你梦到了什么？”

“野兽，”她立刻回答，“扑向我的巨兽！我跑啊跑啊——啊！”

奥斯古德太太抿了一口咖啡，看着他们。眼前这位是前途无量的诗人，他代表了她少女时代所渴望的一切，而这一切都是她那位极富有的工厂主丈夫身上所缺乏的。真希望她的女儿能弥补这个遗憾！

“他们说那些梦来自我们遥远的过去，”她说，“你相信吗，潘达克斯特先生？”

“是的，”他赞同地说，“来自我们这一物种演化早期的记忆，来自深藏已久的恐惧与痛苦的岁月。”

“那我们产生的‘似曾相识’的奇怪感觉，和反复的梦是同一种东西吗？”

“这人们还不知道，”他说，“有人说，这是由于一半大脑在思考中出现了片刻的延迟。我不知道，对我来说，把一个人突然产生的似曾相识的感觉解读为对前世生活的模糊记忆，会更加神秘，更加有趣。”他看着埃伦，仿佛她从他的前世中走出来。“你有过那种感觉吗，奥斯古德小姐？”

那个女孩儿有点儿羞怯地笑了。“在一件事上我有过，”她说，“那就是我怕水的原因。”

“居然怕水！你！一个水中女神！”

“哦，我当然没有放任这种恐惧。但这是我唯一感到紧张的事情。我从小就有这种感觉——那种恐怖的感觉！”

她打了个寒战，问他是否想听听音乐。

“啊！你还会弹奏吗？”

她欢快地笑了。“我只会用自动钢琴，或其他某种自动乐器。我可以开始了吗？”

“等一下，”他说，“马上。但是，你可否告诉我这个关于可怕东西的梦？我非常非常感兴趣。”

“噢，不算什么啊，”她说，“我没有梦见它，真的——它是在我醒着的时候出现的。只有两三次——有一次是在我十岁或十一岁的时候，那以后还有一两次。是水——漆黑、平静、光滑的水——在我身下。我无法摆脱它。我想要——然后什么东西抓住了我——啊！”

她决然地站起身，走到乐谱架前。“如果那是我过去的记忆，我一定是曾被一只愤怒的猩猩过早地了结了！总之我不喜欢水，除非是一片汪洋大海。我该演奏什么呢？”

他本想第二天早晨天一亮就起来，却没有醒。当他往外看时，那只独木舟已经轻快地往家划来，正好赶上吃早餐。

她嘲笑他的懒惰，却答应以后给他补上这一课，并且很高兴地发现他会打网球。他穿着白色法兰绒长裤，看上去很帅气。事实上他的外表比他的球艺更令人赞赏，他被女孩儿打得落花流水，直至近乎发怒。

奥斯古德太太在他们打得精彩的时候，会偶尔在一旁高兴地观看一阵；有时候为了能让他们俩单独多待一会儿，则会找各种借口离开。

他私下向她提出一个问题，担心对于独木舟来说，自己会不会太重了。但她让他放宽心。

“哦，不必担心，真的，潘达克斯特先生，这是一只特别宽的独木舟，里面还有气囊——它不会下沉的。”这是她父亲为她亲手做的。“我父亲也是一个大块头，他很喜欢划独木舟。”

于是这位健壮的诗人被缓缓地领到船的中央，女孩儿递给他一支船桨。

看不到漂亮的女导师让他沮丧，所以他提议两人换一下位置。

“不，真不行！”她说，“把另一支桨也给你？——还不到时候吧！”

他提议能否至少面对着她。听了这话，她顽皮地笑了，告诉他最好先学会划桨前进，然后再试着向后划。

“如果你想看我，你可以另找一只独木舟，试着跟上我吧。”她微笑着补充。直到听了这句话，他才宣布自己会对她的命令绝对服从。

他占满了那小小的藤制船椅，像她一样卷起袖子。她把桨交给他，给他演示应该怎样握着它。尽管她拼命地掌舵，他用力地划桨，小船仍左右摆动，引得她默默地笑了。

“别这么用力！”她说，“你比我有力，你的桨又伸得太远了，让我们的船晃来晃去的。”

他稍微用了一点儿耐心就掌握了这门艺术，足以成为一名合格的舵手，但她不相信他能驾驭船尾。平静湖面上的所有美景都无法平复他看不见她的懊恼。不过他又想，她能看见他。或许这就是她把他留在前面的原因！——想到这点，他就坐得更直了。

她确实挺喜欢他那匀称的身躯，可是她瞧不上他的笨拙，而且对他手臂和双手上浓密的黑色汗毛感到深深的厌恶。

他厌倦了独木舟。他不能转头深情地注视她，也不能说些甜蜜的话；换言之，相处的效果并不好。打网球时，她发挥很稳，总是赢得比赛，这也令他厌倦。她不喜欢高尔夫球；他不会骑马；她开车时，她的手、眼睛和所有的注意力都集中在汽车上。所以他只能提议，一起去散步。

“你一定要在这美妙的树林里散散步，”他说，“我在许多方面都技不如人，但我起码可以走路！”

“好吧。”她愉快地同意了，然后和他一起在乡间漫步，轻快而不知疲倦。

她母亲在一旁屏息观察。这个大眼睛男人有着天鹅绒般的声音，柔软胡须下是两片红唇，她是彻底为他倾倒了。她认为他的诗歌极为精妙动听，埃伦却认为它“毫无实际用途”。

“他究竟想把那些古老的传说改写成什么呢？”当母亲试图赢得她的某种赞赏时，埃伦这样说，“难道现在就没有足够的东西可写了吗——一定要回到那些从不存在的人身上，写别人故事里的人物？”

“它们是世界诗歌素材的一部分，我亲爱的。民间传说、种族神话，它们关乎我们的世界意象。”

“好吧，我不喜欢关于世界意象的诗歌，仅此而已。就像木乃伊一样，是陈腐的，精心打扮的！”

“我感到很遗憾！”她母亲有些恼怒地说，“我们在此荣幸地迎来了我们最伟大的诗人之一——或许就是最伟大的诗人。我的亲生孩子却没有能力欣赏他的美妙作品。你真像你父亲！”

“好吧，我也无能为力，”埃伦说，“我不喜欢那些愚蠢老套的故事，讲的都是那些不做实事，脑子里只有恋爱和谋杀的人！他们没有理智，没有勇气，毫不体面！”

她母亲设法使她承认诗人其他作品的价值。

“没有用的，妈妈！或许你心里有你的诗人，并从中得到所有审美的愉悦。我当然会对他以礼相待。但我不喜欢他写的东西。”

“亲爱的，你不喜欢他的《每日抒情诗》和《森林》吗？”

“不喜欢，妈妈，连那些也不行。我相信他从未真正看过日出——除非他是特意起床，像照相机一样站着记录！还有森林！哎呀，他都分不清这棵树和那棵树！”

她母亲几乎对她绝望了。但这位诗人并不气馁。

“啊！奥斯古德夫人！既然我有幸得到你的信任，我只有感谢你，并且试试我的运气。这个萌芽的灵魂是如此美丽——她的花苞还未开放，紧紧闭着，甚至还有些坚硬！但是当她的玫瑰花瓣绽开的时候……”

然而，他并没有把自己的秘密向奥斯古德太太和盘托出，只是用一种温柔、诗意的比喻来形容开花是为了什么。他没有告诉她自己内心正在酝酿的激情的风暴，这样沸腾的强度会使那个温和的灵魂极度惊恐，或许会使她怀疑自己的选择是否明智。

奥斯古德夫人仍然处于一种热切而克制的情感状态中，几乎对埃伦只字不提，生怕惊吓到她，却希望女孩儿能和这个伟大的灵魂一起找到幸福。

与此同时，那个伟大的灵魂继续在他的道路上前进着，运用他所了解的每一种艺术——对此他经验颇丰——去触碰身边那个拥有红褐色肌肤的仙女的心。

她天真又年轻。她深陷于自己的冷漠之中而无法真正欣赏他所付出的辛苦，更不用说同情了。而且她还以戏弄他为乐，伤害了他却毫无觉察，就像一个顽皮的孩子。她取笑他打网球、划桨和开车不行；她承认或许他高尔夫球打得不错，但她本人并不喜欢高尔夫球——这项运动太慢了；她甚至嘲笑他的林间散步。

“他并不想走路！”一天吃晚餐时，她兴高采烈地对她母亲说，“他只是想去一个地方，把自己优雅地安顿在一棵树下，给我读一些关于爱洛伊丝、阿拉明塔[8]或什么人的故事；都是苗条、白皙、金色鬈发的美人，还有她们是如何为爱而殉情的！”

她坦率地嘲笑他。他也和她一起笑，但他的内心深处炽热又黑暗。他越是追求，越是挫败，对她的欲望也就越强烈。这份爱持续的时间已经比平常要久了。他那势不可当的求爱，从来没有像现在这样被轻巧地回避和置之不理。

“今天吃过晚饭以后，你愿意和我一起去散步吗？”他提议说，“今晚有最圣洁的月亮——而我也无法看书，不能给你读诗。月光落在你的湖面上，一定会奇妙得可人，你说是吗，奥斯古德太太？”

“的确是这样。”奥斯古德太太热情地表示同意，不满地望着女孩——女孩仍沉浸在对金发的阿拉明塔的回忆里，小声地咯咯笑个不停——“带他去悬崖边散步吧，埃伦，一定要试着欣赏美啊！”

“好的，妈妈，”埃伦说，“我会乖乖的。”

她在月色下散步，是如此乖驯。她温柔，富有同情心，如此真诚地想与他达成一致。他的感情因此过于强烈，于是失去了判断力，他捉住她的手，吻了一下。她震惊得说不出话来，惊吓着把他推开。

“哎呀，潘达克斯特先生！你在想什么啊！”

然后他向她倾诉衷肠。他告诉她，他是多么爱她——疯狂地，热烈地，不可抗拒地。他恳求她听他诉说。

“啊！你这年轻的戴安娜！你不知道我有多痛苦！你这么年轻，这么冷淡！这么圣洁美丽！别那么残忍！听我说！说你愿意做我的妻子！给我一个吻！只一个！”

她年轻，冷淡，残忍，却不自知。她嘲笑他，无情地嘲笑，然后转身走了。

他跟着她，血脉偾张，声音因强烈的感情而颤抖。他抓住她的手，又把她拉了过来。她低低地叫了一声，挣脱了他，跑走了。他狂热地、发疯地跟在后面，冲向她，抓住她，紧紧抱住她。

“你会爱我的！你会的！”他叫道。他的手热得发烫，在颤抖。他紧紧地抱住她，把她的脸转向他。

“我才不会！”她挣扎着叫道，“让我走！我恨你！我告诉你，我恨你！你真——恶心！”她尽可能地把他推得很远。

他们已经到了房子对面的小悬崖顶上。巨大的黑松林悬在他们头上，宽大的树枝温柔地摇摆。

脚下的水面躺在阴影里，平滑，油黑。

女孩低头看了看水面，紧张的身体突然打了个寒战。她发出一声低低的悲叹，用双手捂住脸。

“啊！”他叫道，“这是你的命运！我们的命运！我们前世经历过！假如我们不能生活在一起，我们就要死在一起！”

他把她拉进怀里，疯狂地、热烈地吻她，然后一起纵身跃进了黑色的湖水中。

“幸好我会游泳，”埃伦一边说，一边匆匆赶回家，“可他不会。这个可怜的人！噢，这个可怜的人！他一定是疯了！”

[4]滚柱，用于将船只移到海里或船屋里。

[5]朱诺（Juno），罗马神话中的天后，朱庇特之妻，婚姻和母性之神，罗马十二主神之一，集美貌、温柔、慈爱于一身。

[6]瑙西卡（Nausicaa）是古希腊神话中法埃亚科安岛国王阿尔喀诺俄斯的女儿，长得美丽端庄。

[7]阿塔兰忒（Atalanta）是古希腊神话中一位善于疾走的女猎手，是阿特弥斯女神的伙伴。她在野外长大，身形健壮，性情开朗。

[8]均为传说中的人物，见于一些传奇和诗歌中的描写。

The Yellow Wall- Paper

It is very seldom that mere ordinary people like John and myself secure ancestral halls for the summer.

A colonial mansion, a hereditary estate, I would say a haunted house, and reach the height of romantic felicity – but that would be asking too much of fate!

Still I will proudly declare that there is something queer about it.

Else, why should it be let so cheaply? And why have stood so long untenanted?

John laughs at me, of course, but one expects that in marriage.

John is practical in the extreme. He has no patience with faith, an intense horror of superstition, and he scoffs openly at any talk of things not to be felt and seen and put down in figures.

John is a physician, and perhaps – (I would not say it to a living soul, of course, but this is dead paper and a great relief to my mind – ) perhaps that is one reason I do not get well faster.

You see he does not believe I am sick!

And what can one do?

If a physician of high standing, and one's own husband,assures friends and relatives that there is really nothing the matter with one but temporary nervous depression – a slight hysterical tendency – what is one to do?

My brother is also a physician, and also of high standing, and he says the same thing.

So I take phosphates or phosphites – whichever it is, and tonics, and journeys, and air, and exercise, and am absolutely forbidden to ‘work' until I am well again.

Personally, I disagree with their ideas

Personally, I believe that congenial work, with excitement and change, would do me good.

But what is one to do?

I did write for a while in spite of them; but it does exhaust me a good deal – having to be so sly about it, or else meet with heavy opposition.

I sometimes fancy that in my condition if I had less opposition and more society and stimulus – but John says the very worst thing I can do is to think about my condition, and I confess it always makes me feel bad.

So I will let it alone and talk about the house.

The most beautiful place! It is quite alone, standing well back from the road, quite three miles from the village. It makes me think of English places that you read about, for there are hedges and walls and gates that lock, and lots of separate little houses for the gardeners and people.

There is a delicious garden! I never saw such a garden – large and shady, full of box- bordered paths, and lined with long grape- covered arbors with seats under them.

There were greenhouses, too, but they are all broken now.

There was some legal trouble, I believe, something about the heirs and co- heirs; anyhow, the place has been empty for years.

That spoils my ghostliness, I am afraid, but I don't care – there is something strange about the house – I can feel it.

I even said so to John one moonlight evening, but he said what I felt was a draught, and shut the window.

I get unreasonably angry with John sometimes. I'm sure I never used to be so sensitive. I think it is due to this nervous condition.

But John says if I feel so, I shall neglect proper self- control; so I take pains to control myself – before him, at least, and that makes me very tired.

I don't like our room a bit. I wanted one downstairs that opened on the piazza and had roses all over the window, and such pretty old- fashioned chintz hangings! but John would not hear of it.

He said there was only one window and not room for two beds, and no near room for him if he took another.

He is very careful and loving, and hardly lets me stir without special direction.

I have a schedule prescription for each hour in the day; he takes all care from me, and so I feel basely ungrateful not to value it more.

He said we came here solely on my account, that I was to have perfect rest and all the air I could get. ‘Your exercise depends on your strength, my dear,' said he, ‘and your food somewhat on your appetite; but air you can absorb all the time.' So we took the nursery at the top of the house.

It is a big, airy room, the whole floor nearly, with windows that look all ways, and air and sunshine galore. It was nursery first and then playroom and gymnasium, I should judge; for the windows are barred for little children, and there are rings and things in the walls.

The paint and paper look as if a boys' school had used it. It is stripped off – the paper – in great patches all around the head of my bed, about as far as I can reach, and in a great place on the other side of the room low down. I never saw a worse paper in my life.

One of those sprawling flamboyant patterns committing every artistic sin.

It is dull enough to confuse the eye in following, pronounced enough to constantly irritate and provoke study, and when you follow the lame uncertain curves for a little distance they suddenly commit suicide – plunge off at outrageous angles, destroy themselves in unheard of contradictions.

The color is repellant, almost revolting; a smouldering unclean yellow, strangely faded by the slow- turning sunlight.

It is a dull yet lurid orange in some places, a sickly sulphur tint in others.

No wonder the children hated it! I should hate it myself if I had to live in this room long.

There comes John, and I must put this away, – he hates to have me write a word.

We have been here two weeks, and I haven't felt like writing before, since that first day.

I am sitting by the window now, up in this atrocious nursery, and there is nothing to hinder my writing as much as I please, save lack of strength.

John is away all day, and even some nights when his cases are serious.

I am glad my case is not serious!

But these nervous troubles are dreadfully depressing.

John does not know how much I really suffer. He knows there is no reason to suffer, and that satisfies him.

Of course it is only nervousness. It does weigh on me so not to do my duty in any way!

I meant to be such a help to John, such a real rest and comfort, and here I am a comparative burden already!

Nobody would believe what an effort it is to do what little I am able, – to dress and entertain, and order things.

It is fortunate Mary is so good with the baby. Such a dear baby!

And yet I cannot be with him, it makes me so nervous.

I suppose John never was nervous in his life. He laughs at me so about this wall- paper!

At first he meant to repaper the room, but afterwards he said that I was letting it get the better of me, and that nothing was worse for a nervous patient than to give way to such fancies.

He said that after the wall- paper was changed it would be the heavy bedstead, and then the barred windows, and then that gate at the head of the stairs, and so on.

‘You know the place is doing you good,' he said, ‘and really, dear, I don't care to renovate the house just for a three months' rental.'

‘Then do let us go downstairs,' I said, ‘there are such pretty rooms there.'

Then he took me in his arms and called me a blessed little goose, and said he would go down to the cellar, if I wished, and have it whitewashed into the bargain.

But he is right enough about the beds and windows and things.

It is an airy and comfortable room as any one need wish, and, of course, I would not be so silly as to make him uncomfortable just for a whim.

I'm really getting quite fond of the big room, all but that horrid paper.

Out of one window I can see the garden, those mysterious deep- shaded arbors, the riotous old- fashioned flowers, and bushes and gnarly trees.

Out of another I get a lovely view of the bay and a little private wharf belonging to the estate. There is a beautiful shaded lane that runs down there from the house. I always fancy I see people walking in these numerous paths and arbors, but John has cautioned me not to give way to fancy in the least. He says that with my imaginative power and habit of story- making, a nervous weakness like mine is sure to lead to all manner of excited fancies, and that I ought to use my will and good sense to check the tendency. So I try.

I think sometimes that if I were only well enough to write a little it would relieve the press of ideas and rest me.

But I find I get pretty tired when I try.

It is so discouraging not to have any advice and companionship about my work. When I get really well, John says we will ask Cousin Henry and Julia down for a long visit; but he says he would as soon put fireworks in my pillow- case as to let me have those stimulating people about now.

I wish I could get well faster.

But I must not think about that. This paper looks to me as if it knew what a vicious influence it had!

There is a recurrent spot where the pattern lolls like a broken neck and two bulbous eyes stare at you upside down.

I get positively angry with the impertinence of it and the everlastingness. Up and down and sideways they crawl, and those absurd, unblinking eyes are everywhere. There is one place where two breadths didn't match, and the eyes go all up and down the line, one a little higher than the other.

I never saw so much expression in an inanimate thing before, and we all know how much expression they have! I used to lie awake as a child and get more entertainment and terror out of blank walls and plain furniture than most children could find in a toy- store.

I remember what a kindly wink the knobs of our big, old bureau used to have, and there was one chair that always seemed like a strong friend.

I used to feel that if any of the other things looked too fierce I could always hop into that chair and be safe.

The furniture in this room is no worse than inharmonious, however, for we had to bring it all from downstairs. I suppose when this was used as a playroom they had to take the nursery things out, and no wonder! I never saw such ravages as the children have made here.

The wall- paper, as I said before, is torn off in spots, and it sticketh closer than a brother – they must have had perseverance as well as hatred.

Then the floor is scratched and gouged and splintered, the plaster itself is dug out here and there, and this great heavy bed which is all we found in the room, looks as if it had been through the wars.

But I don't mind it a bit – only the paper.

There comes John's sister. Such a dear girl as she is, and so careful of me! I must not let her find me writing.

She is a perfect and enthusiastic housekeeper, andhopes for no better profession. I verily believe she thinks it is the writing which made me sick!

But I can write when she is out, and see her a long way off from these windows.

There is one that commands the road, a lovely shaded winding road, and one that just looks off over the country. A lovely country, too, full of great elms and velvet meadows.

This wallpaper has a kind of subpattern in a different shade, a particularly irritating one, for you can only see it in certain lights, and not clearly then.

But in the places where it isn't faded and where the sun is just so – I can see a strange, provoking, formless sort of figure, that seems to skulk about behind that silly and conspicuous front design.

There's sister on the stairs!

Well, the Fourth of July is over! The people are all gone and I am tired out. John thought it might do me good to see a little company, so we just had mother and Nellie and the children down for a week.

Of course I didn't do a thing. Jennie sees to everything now.

But it tired me all the same.

John says if I don't pick up faster he shall send me to Weir Mitchell in the fall.

But I don't want to go there at all. I had a friend who was in his hands once, and she says he is just like John and my brother, only more so!

Besides, it is such an undertaking to go so far.

I don't feel as if it was worth while to turn my hand over for anything, and I'm getting dreadfully fretful and querulous.

I cry at nothing, and cry most of the time.

Of course I don't when John is here, or anybody else, but when I am alone.

And I am alone a good deal just now. John is kept in town very often by serious cases, and Jennie is good and lets me alone when I want her to.

So I walk a little in the garden or down that lovely lane, sit on the porch under the roses, and lie down up here a good deal.

I'm getting really fond of the room in spite of the wallpaper. Perhaps because of the wall-paper.

It dwells in my mind so!

I lie here on this great immovable bed – it is nailed down, I believe – and follow that pattern about by the hour. It is as good as gymnastics, I assure you. I start, we'll say, at the bottom, down in the corner over there where it has not been touched, and I determine for the thousandth time that I will follow that pointless pattern to some sort of a conclusion.

I know a little of the principle of design, and I know this thing was not arranged on any laws of radiation, or alternation, or repetition, or symmetry, or anything else that I ever heard of.

It is repeated, of course, by the breadths, but not otherwise.

Looked at in one way each breadth stands alone, the bloated curves and flourishes – a kind of ‘debased Romanesque' with delirium tremens – go waddling up and down in isolated columns of fatuity.

But, on the other hand, they connect diagonally, and the sprawling outlines run off in great slanting waves of optic horror, like a lot of wallowing seaweeds in full chase.

The whole thing goes horizontally, too, at least it seems so, and I exhaust myself in trying to distinguish the order of its going in that direction.

They have used a horizontal breadth for a frieze, and that adds wonderfully to the confusion.

There is one end of the room where it is almost intact, and there, when the crosslights fade and the low sun shines directly upon it, I can almost fancy radiation after all, – the interminable grotesques seem to form around a common centre and rush off in headlong plunges of equal distraction.

It makes me tired to follow it. I will take a nap I guess.

I don't know why I should write this.

I don't want to.

I don't feel able.

And I know John would think it absurd. But I must say what I feel and think in some way – it is such a relief!

But the effort is getting to be greater than the relief.

Half the time now I am awfully lazy, and lie down ever so much.

John says I mustn't lose my strength, and has me take cod liver oil and lots of tonics and things, to say nothing of ale and wine and rare meat.

Dear John! He loves me very dearly, and hates to have me sick. I tried to have a real earnest reasonable talk with him the other day, and tell him how I wish he would let me go and make a visit to Cousin Henry and Julia.

But he said I wasn't able to go, nor able to stand it after I got there; and I did not make out a very good case for myself, for I was crying before I had finished.

It is getting to be a great effort for me to think straight. Just this nervous weakness I suppose.

And dear John gathered me up in his arms, and just carried me upstairs and laid me on the bed, and sat by me and read to me till it tired my head.

He said I was his darling and his comfort and all he had, and that I must take care of myself for his sake, and keep well.

He says no one but myself can help me out of it, that I must use my will and self- control and not let any silly fancies run away with me.

There's one comfort, the baby is well and happy, and does not have to occupy this nursery with the horrid wallpaper.

If we had not used it, that blessed child would have! What a fortunate escape! Why, I wouldn't have a child of mine, an impressionable little thing, live in such a room for worlds.

I never thought of it before, but it is lucky that John kept me here after all, I can stand it so much easier than a baby, you see.

Of course I never mention it to them any more – I am too wise, – but I keep watch of it all the same.

There are things in that paper that nobody knows but me, or ever will.

Behind that outside pattern the dim shapes get clearer every day.

It is always the same shape, only very numerous.

And it is like a woman stooping down and creeping about behind that pattern. I don't like it a bit. I wonder – I begin to think – I wish John would take me away from here!

It is so hard to talk with John about my case, because he is so wise, and because he loves me so.

But I tried it last night.

It was moonlight. The moon shines in all around just as the sun does.

I hate to see it sometimes, it creeps so slowly, and always comes in by one window or another.

John was asleep and I hated to waken him, so I kept still and watched the moonlight on that undulating wallpaper till I felt creepy.

The faint figure behind seemed to shake the pattern, just as if she wanted to get out.

I got up softly and went to feel and see if the paper did move, and when I came back John was awake.

‘What is it, little girl?' he said. ‘Don't go walking about like that – you'll get cold.'

I thought it was a good time to talk, so I told him that I really was not gaining here, and that I wished he would take me away.

‘Why, darling!' said he, ‘our lease will be up in three weeks, and I can't see how to leave before.

‘The repairs are not done at home, and I cannot possibly leave town just now. Of course if you were in any danger, I could and would, but you really are better, dear, whether you can see it or not. I am a doctor, dear, and I know. You are gaining flesh and color, your appetite is better, I feel really much easier about you.'

‘I don't weigh a bit more,' said I, ‘nor as much; and my appetite may be better in the evening when you are here, but it is worse in the morning when you are away!'

‘Bless her little heart!' said he with a big hug, ‘she shall be as sick as she pleases! But now let's improve the shining hours by going to sleep, and talk about it in the morning!'

‘And you won't go away?' I asked gloomily.

‘Why, how can I, dear? It is only three weeks more and then we will take a nice little trip of a few days while Jennie is getting the house ready. Really, dear, you are better!'

‘Better in body perhaps -' I began, and stopped short, for he sat up straight and looked at me with such a stern, reproachful look that I could not say another word.

‘My darling,' said he, ‘I beg of you, for my sake and for our child's sake, as well as for your own, that you will never for one instant let that idea enter your mind! There is nothing so dangerous, so fascinating, to a temperament like yours. It is a false and foolish fancy. Can you not trust me as a physician when I tell you so?'

So of course I said no more on that score, and we went to sleep before long. He thought I was asleep first, but I wasn't, and lay there for hours trying to decide whether that front pattern and the back pattern really did move together or separately.

On a pattern like this, by daylight, there is a lack of sequence, a defiance of law, that is a constant irritant to a normal mind.

The color is hideous enough, and unreliable enough, and infuriating enough, but the pattern is torturing.

You think you have mastered it, but just as you get well underway in following, it turns a back- somersault and there you are. It slaps you in the face, knocks you down, and tramples upon you. It is like a bad dream.

The outside pattern is a florid arabesque, reminding one of a fungus. If you can imagine a toadstool in joints, an interminable string of toadstools, budding and sprouting in endless convolutions – why, that is something like it.

That is, sometimes!

There is one marked peculiarity about this paper, a thing nobody seems to notice but myself, and that is that it changes as the light changes.

When the sun shoots in through the east window – I always watch for that first long, straight ray – it changes so quickly that I never can quite believe it.

That is why I watch it always.

By moonlight – the moon shines in all night when there is a moon – I wouldn't know it was the same paper.

At night in any kind of light, in twilight, candlelight, lamplight, and worst of all by moonlight, it becomes bars! The outside pattern I mean, and the woman behind it is as plain as can be.

I didn't realize for a long time what the thing was that showed behind, that dim sub- pattern, but now I am quite sure it is a woman.

By daylight she is subdued, quiet. I fancy it is the pattern that keeps her so still. It is so puzzling. It keeps me quiet by the hour.

I lie down ever so much now. John says it is good for me, and to sleep all I can.

Indeed he started the habit by making me lie down for an hour after each meal.

It is a very bad habit I am convinced, for you see I don't sleep.

And that cultivates deceit, for I don't tell them I'm awake – O no!

The fact is I am getting a little afraid of John.

He seems very queer sometimes, and even Jennie has an inexplicable look.

It strikes me occasionally, just as a scientific hy – pothesis, – that perhaps it is the paper!

I have watched John when he did not know I was looking, and come into the room suddenly on the most innocent excuses, and I've caught him several times looking at the paper! And Jennie too. I caught Jennie with her hand on it once.

She didn't know I was in the room, and when I asked her in a quiet, a very quiet voice, with the most restrained manner possible, what she was doing with the paper – she turned around as if she had been caught stealing, and looked quite angry – asked me why I should frighten her so!

Then she said that the paper stained everything it touched, that she had found yellow smooches on all my clothes and John's, and she wished we would be more careful!

Did not that sound innocent? But I know she was studying that pattern, and I am determined that nobody shall find it out but myself!

*

Life is very much more exciting now than it used to be. You see I have something more to expect, to look forward to, to watch. I really do eat better, and am more quiet than I was.

John is so pleased to see me improve! He laughed a little the other day, and said I seemed to be flourishing in spite of my wall-paper.

I turned it off with a laugh. I had no intention of telling him it was because of the wall- paper – he would make fun of me. He might even want to take me away.

I don't want to leave now until I have found it out. There is a week more, and I think that will be enough.

I'm feeling ever so much better! I don't sleep much at night, for it is so interesting to watch developments; but I sleep a good deal in the daytime.

In the daytime it is tiresome and perplexing.

There are always new shoots on the fungus, and new shades of yellow all over it. I cannot keep count of them, though I have tried conscientiously.

It is the strangest yellow, that wall- paper! It makes me think of all the yellow things I ever saw – not beautiful ones like buttercups, but old foul, bad yellow things.

But there is something else about that paper – the smell! I noticed it the moment we came into the room, but with so much air and sun it was not bad. Now we have had a week of fog and rain, and whether the windows are open or not, the smell is here.

It creeps all over the house.

I find it hovering in the dining- room, skulking in the parlor, hiding in the hall, lying in wait for me on the stairs. It gets into my hair.

Even when I go to ride, if I turn my head suddenly and surprise it – there is that smell!

Such a peculiar odor, too! I have spent hours in trying to analyze it, to find what it smelled like.

It is not bad – at first, and very gentle, but quite the subtlest, most enduring odor I ever met.

In this damp weather it is awful, I wake up in the night and find it hanging over me.

It used to disturb me at first. I thought seriously of burning the house – to reach the smell.

But now I am used to it. The only thing I can think of that it is like is the color of the paper! A yellow smell.

There is a very funny mark on this wall, low down, near the mopboard. A streak that runs round the room. It goes behind every piece of furniture, except the bed, a long, straight, even smooch, as if it had been rubbed over and over.

I wonder how it was done and who did it, and what they did it for. Round and round and round – round and round and round – it makes me dizzy!

I really have discovered something at last.

Through watching so much at night, when it changes so, I have finally found out.

The front pattern does move – and no wonder! The woman behind shakes it!

Sometimes I think there are a great many women behind, and sometimes only one, and she crawls around fast, and her crawling shakes it all over.

Then in the very bright spots she keeps still, and in the very shady spots she just takes hold of the bars and shakes them hard.

And she is all the time trying to climb through. But nobody could climb through that pattern – it strangles so; I think that is why it has so many heads.

They get through, and then the pattern strangles them off and turns them upside down, and makes their eyes white!

If those heads were covered or taken off it would not be half so bad.

I think that woman gets out in the daytime!

And I'll tell you why – privately – I've seen her!

I can see her out of every one of my windows!

It is the same woman, I know, for she is always creeping, and most women do not creep by daylight.

I see her in that long shaded lane, creeping up and down. I see her in those dark grape arbors, creeping all around the garden.

I see her on that long road under the trees, creeping along, and when a carriage comes she hides under the blackberry vines.

I don't blame her a bit. It must be very humiliating to be caught creeping by daylight!

I always lock the door when I creep by daylight. I can't do it at night, for I know John would suspect something at once.

And John is so queer now, that I don't want to irritate him. I wish he would take another room! Besides, I don't want anybody to get that woman out at night but myself.

I often wonder if I could see her out of all the windows at once.

But, turn as fast as I can, I can only see out of one at one time.

And though I always see her, she may be able to creep faster than I can turn!

I have watched her sometimes away off in the open country, creeping as fast as a cloud shadow in a high wind.

If only that top pattern could be gotten off from the under one! I mean to try it, little by little.

I have found out another funny thing, but I shan't tell it this time! It does not do to trust people too much.

There are only two more days to get this paper off, and I believe John is beginning to notice. I don't like the look in his eyes.

And I heard him ask Jennie a lot of professional questions about me. She had a very good report to give.

She said I slept a good deal in the daytime.

John knows I don't sleep very well at night, for all I'm so quiet!

He asked me all sorts of questions, too, and pretended to be very loving and kind.

As if I couldn't see through him!

Still, I don't wonder he acts so, sleeping under this paper for three months.

It only interests me, but I feel sure John and Jennie are secretly affected by it.

Hurrah! This is the last day, but it is enough. John is to stay in town over night, and won't be out until this evening.

Jennie wanted to sleep with me – the sly thing! but I told her I should undoubtedly rest better for a night all alone.

That was clever, for really I wasn't alone a bit! As soon as it was moonlight and that poor thing began to crawl and shake the pattern, I got up and ran to help her.

I pulled and she shook, I shook and she pulled, and before morning we had peeled off yards of that paper.

A strip about as high as my head and half around the room.

And then when the sun came and that awful pattern began to laugh at me, I declared I would finish it to- day!

We go away to- morrow, and they are moving all my furniture down again to leave things as they were before.

Jennie looked at the wall in amazement, but I told her

merrily that I did it out of pure spite at the vicious thing.

She laughed and said she wouldn't mind doing it herself, but I must not get tired.

How she betrayed herself that time!

But I am here, and no person touches this paper but me, – not alive!

She tried to get me out of the room – it was too patent! But I said it was so quiet and empty and clean now that I believed I would lie down again and sleep all I could; and not to wake me even for dinner – I would call when I woke.

So now she is gone, and the servants are gone, and the things are gone, and there is nothing left but that great bedstead nailed down, with the canvas mattress we found on it.

We shall sleep downstairs to- night, and take the boat home tomorrow.

I quite enjoy the room, now it is bare again.

How those children did tear about here!

This bedstead is fairly gnawed!

But I must get to work.

I have locked the door and thrown the key down into the front path.

I don't want to go out, and I don't want to have anybody come in, till John comes.

I want to astonish him.

I've got a rope up here that even Jennie did not find. If that woman does get out, and tries to get away, I can tie her!

But I forgot I could not reach far without anything to stand on!

This bed will not move!

I tried to lift and push it until I was lame, and then I got so angry I bit off a little piece at one corner – but it hurt my teeth.

Then I peeled off all the paper I could reach standing on the floor. It sticks horribly and the pattern just enjoys it! All those strangled heads and bulbous eyes and waddling fungus growths just shriek with derision!

I am getting angry enough to do something desperate. To jump out of the window would be admirable exercise, but the bars are too strong even to try.

Besides I wouldn't do it. Of course not. I know well enough that a step like that is improper and might be misconstrued.

I don't like to look out of the windows even – there are so many of those creeping women, and they creep so fast.

I wonder if they all come out of that wall- paper as I did?

But I am securely fastened now by my well- hidden rope – you don't get me out in the road there!

I suppose I shall have to get back behind the pattern when it comes night, and that is hard!

It is so pleasant to be out in this great room and creep around as I please!

I don't want to go outside. I won't, even if Jennie asks me to.

For outside you have to creep on the ground, and everything is green instead of yellow.

But here I can creep smoothly on the floor, and my shoulder just fits in that long smooch around the wall, so I cannot lose my way.

Why there's John at the door!

It is no use, young man, you can't open it!

How he does call and pound!

Now he's crying for an axe.

It would be a shame to break down that beautiful door!

‘John dear!' said I in the gentlest voice, ‘the key is down by the front steps, under a plantain leaf!'

That silenced him for a few moments.

Then he said – very quietly indeed, ‘Open the door, my darling!'

‘I can't,' said I. ‘The key is down by the front door under a plantain leaf!'

And then I said it again, several times, very gently and slowly, and said it so often that he had to go and see, and he got it of course, and came in. He stopped short by the door.

‘What is the matter?' he cried. ‘For God's sake, what are you doing!'

I kept on creeping just the same, but I looked at him over my shoulder.

‘I've got out at last,' said I, ‘in spite of you and Jane! And I've pulled off most of the paper, so you can't put me back!'

Now why should that man have fainted? But he did, and right across my path by the wall, so that I had to creep over him every time!

The Rocking- Chair

A waving spot of sunshine, a signal light that caught the eye at once in a waste of commonplace houses, and all the dreary dimness of a narrow city street.

Across some low roof that made a gap in the wall of masonry, shot a level, brilliant beam of the just- setting sun, touching the golden head of a girl in an open window.

She sat in a high- backed rocking- chair with brass mountings that glittered as it swung, rocking slowly back and forth, never lifting her head, but fairly lighting up the street with the glory of her sunlit hair.

We two stopped and stared, and, so staring, caught sight of a small sign in a lower window – ‘Furnished Lodgings.' With a common impulse we crossed the street and knocked at the dingy front door.

Slow, even footsteps approached from within, and a soft girlish laugh ceased suddenly as the door opened, showing us an old woman, with a dull, expressionless face and faded eyes.

Yes, she had rooms to let. Yes, we could see them. No, there was no service. No, there were no meals. So murmuring monotonously, she led the way up- stairs. It was an ordinary house enough, on a poor sort of street, a house in no way remarkable or unlike its fellows.

She showed us two rooms, connected, neither better nor worse than most of their class, rooms without a striking feature about them, unless it was the great brass- bound chair we found still rocking gently by the window.

But the gold- haired girl was nowhere to be seen.

I fancied I heard the light rustle of girlish robes in the inner chamber – a breath of that low laugh – but the door leading to this apartment was locked, and when I asked the woman if we could see the other rooms she said she had no other rooms to let.

A few words aside with Hal, and we decided to take these two, and move in at once. There was no reason we should not. We were looking for lodgings when that swinging sunbeam caught our eyes, and the accommodations were fully as good as we could pay for. So we closed our bargain on the spot, returned to our deserted boarding- house for a few belongings, and were settled anew that night.

Hal and I were young newspaper men, ‘ penny- a- liners,' part of that struggling crowd of aspirants who are to literature what squires and pages were to knighthood in olden days. We were winning our spurs. So far it was slow work, unpleasant and ill- paid – so was squireship and pagehood, I am sure; menial service and laborious polishing of armor; long running afoot while the master rode. But the squire could at least honor his lord and leader, while we, alas! had small honor for those above us in our profession, with but too good reason. We, of course, should do far nobler things when these same spurs were won!

Now it may have been mere literary instinct – the grasping at ‘material' of the pot- boiling writers of the day, and it may have been another kind of instinct – the unacknowledged attraction of the fair unknown; but, whatever the reason, the place had drawn us both, and here we were.

Unbroken friendship begun in babyhood held us two together, all the more closely because Hal was a merry, prosaic, clear- headed fellow, and I sensitive and romantic.

The fearless frankness of family life we shared, but held the right to unapproachable reserves, and so kept love unstrained.

We examined our new quarters with interest. The front room, Hal's, was rather big and bare. The back room, mine, rather small and bare.

He preferred that room, I am convinced, because of the window and the chair. I preferred the other, because of the locked door. We neither of us mentioned these prejudices.

‘Are you sure you would not rather have this room?' asked Hal, conscious, perhaps, of an ulterior motive in his choice.

‘No, indeed,' said I, with a similar reservation; ‘you only have the street and I have a real "view" from my window. The only thing I begrudge you is the chair!'

‘You may come and rock therein at any hour of the day or night,' said he magnanimously. ‘It is tremendously comfortable, for all its black looks.'

It was a comfortable chair, a very comfortable chair, and we both used it a great deal. A very high- backed chair, curving a little forward at the top, with heavy square corners. These corners, the ends of the rockers, the great sharp knobs that tipped the arms, and every other point and angle were mounted in brass.

‘Might be used for a battering- ram!' said Hal.

He sat smoking in it, rocking slowly and complacently by the window, while I lounged on the foot of the bed, and watched a pale young moon sink slowly over the western housetops.

It went out of sight at last, and the room grew darker and darker till I could only see Hal's handsome head and the curving chair- back move slowly to and fro against the dim sky.

‘What brought us here so suddenly, Maurice?' he asked, out of the dark.

‘Three reasons,' I answered. ‘Our need of lodgings, the suitability of these, and a beautiful head.'

‘Correct,' said he. ‘Anything else?'

‘Nothing you would admit the existence of, my sternly logical friend. But I am conscious of a certain compul-sion, or at least attraction, in the case, which does not seem wholly accounted for, even by golden hair.'

‘For once I will agree with you,' said Hal. ‘I feel the same way myself, and I am not impressionable.'

We were silent for a little. I may have closed my eyes, – it may have been longer than I thought, but it did not seem another moment when something brushed softly against my arm, and Hal in his great chair was rocking beside me.

‘Excuse me,' said he, seeing me start. ‘This chair evidently "walks," I've seen 'em before.'

So had I, on carpets, but there was no carpet here, and I thought I was awake.

He pulled the heavy thing back to the window again, and we went to bed.

Our door was open, and we could talk back and forth, but presently I dropped off and slept heavily until morning. But I must have dreamed most vividly, for he accused me of rocking in his chair half the night, said he could see my outline clearly against the starlight.

‘No,' said I, ‘you dreamed it. You've got that rockingchair on the brain.'

‘Dream it is, then,' he answered cheerily. ‘Better a nightmare than a contradiction; a vampire than a quarrel! Come on, let's go to breakfast!'

We wondered greatly as the days went by that we saw nothing of our golden- haired charmer. But we wondered in silence, and neither mentioned it to the other.

Sometimes I heard her light movements in the room next mine, or the soft laugh somewhere in the house; but the mother's slow, even steps were more frequent, and even she was not often visible.

All either of us saw of the girl, to my knowledge, was from the street, for she still availed herself of our chair by the window. This we disapproved of, on principle, the more so as we left the doors locked, and her presence proved the possession of another key. No; there was the door in my room! But I did not mention the idea. Under the circumstances, however, we made no complaint, and used to rush stealthily and swiftly up- stairs, hoping to surprise her. But we never succeeded. Only the chair was often found still rocking, and sometimes I fancied a faint sweet odor lingering about, an odor strangely saddening and suggestive. But one day when I thought Hal was there I rushed in unceremoniously and caught her. It was but a glimpse – a swift, light, noiseless sweep – she vanished into my own room. Following her with apologies for such a sudden entrance, I was too late. The envious door was locked again.

Our landlady's fair daughter was evidently shy enough when brought to bay, but strangely willing to take liberties in our absence.

Still, I had seen her, and for that sight would have forgiven much. Hers was a strange beauty, infinitely attractive yet infinitely perplexing. I marveled in secret, and longed with painful eagerness for another meeting; but I said nothing to Hal of my surprising her – it did not seem fair to the girl! She might have some good reason for going there; perhaps I could meet her again.

So I took to coming home early, on one excuse or another, and inventing all manner of errands to get to the room when Hal was not in.

But it was not until after numberless surprises on that point, finding him there when I supposed him downtown, and noticing something a little forced in his needless explanations, that I began to wonder if he might not be on the same quest.

Soon I was sure of it. I reached the corner of the street one evening just at sunset, and – yes, there was the rhythmic swing of that bright head in the dark frame of the open window. There also was Hal in the street below. She looked out, she smiled. He let himself in and went up- stairs.

I quickened my pace. I was in time to see the movement stop, the fair head turn, and Hal standing beyond her in the shadow.

I passed the door, passed the street, walked an hour – two hours – got a late supper somewhere, and came back about bedtime with a sharp and bitter feeling in my heart that I strove in vain to reason down. Why he had not as good a right to meet her as I it were hard to say, and yet I was strangely angry with him.

When I returned the lamplight shone behind the white curtain, and the shadow of the great chair stood motionless against it. Another shadow crossed – Hal – smoking. I went up.

He greeted me effusively and asked why I was so late. Where I got supper. Was unnaturally cheerful. There was a sudden dreadful sense of concealment between us. But he told nothing and I asked nothing, and we went silently to bed.

I blamed him for saying no word about our fair mystery, and yet I had said none concerning my own meeting. I racked my brain with questions as to how much he had really seen of her; if she had talked to him; what she had told him; how long she had stayed.

I tossed all night and Hal was sleepless too, for I heard him rocking for hours, by the window, by the bed, close to my door. I never knew a rocking- chair to ‘walk' as that one did.

Towards morning the steady creak and swing was too much for my nerves or temper.

‘For goodness' sake, Hal, do stop that and go to bed!'

‘What?' came a sleepy voice.

‘Don't fool!' said I, ‘I haven't slept a wink to- night for your everlasting rocking. Now do leave off and go to bed.'

‘Go to bed! I've been in bed all night and I wish you had! Can't you use the chair without blaming me for it?'

And all the time I heard him rock, rock, rock, over by the hall door!

I rose stealthily and entered the room, meaning to surprise the ill- timed joker and convict him in the act.

Both rooms were full of the dim phosphorescence of reflected moonlight; I knew them even in the dark; and yet I stumbled just inside the door, and fell heavily.

Hal was out of bed in a moment and had struck a light.

‘Are you hurt, my dear boy?'

I was hurt, and solely by his fault, for the chair was not where I supposed, but close to my bedroom door, where he must have left it to leap into bed when he heard me coming. So it was in no amiable humor that I refused his offers of assistance and limped back to my own sleepless pillow. I had struck my ankle on one of those brass- tipped rockers, and it pained me severely. I never saw a chair so made to hurt as that one. It was so large and heavy and ill- balanced, and every joint and corner so shod with brass. Hal and I had punished ourselves enough on it before, especially in the dark when we forgot where the thing was standing, but never so severely as this. It was not like Hal to play such tricks, and both heart and ankle ached as I crept into bed again to toss and doze and dream and fitfully start till morning.

Hal was kindness itself, but he would insist that he had been asleep and I rocking all night, till I grew actually angry with him.

‘That's carrying a joke too far,' I said at last. ‘I don't mind a joke, even when it hurts, but there are limits.'

‘Yes, there are!' said he, significantly, and we dropped the subject.

Several days passed. Hal had repeated meetings with the gold- haired damsel; this I saw from the street; but save for these bitter glimpses I waited vainly.

It was hard to bear, harder almost than the growing estrangement between Hal and me, and that cut deeply. I think that at last either one of us would have been glad to go away by himself, but neither was willing to leave the other to the room, the chair, the beautiful unknown.

Coming home one morning unexpectedly, I found the dull- faced landlady arranging the rooms, and quite laid myself out to make an impression upon her, to no purpose.

‘That is a fine old chair you have there,' said I, as she stood mechanically polishing the brass corners with her apron.

She looked at the darkly glittering thing with almost a flash of pride.

‘Yes,' said she, ‘a fine chair!'

‘Is it old?' I pursued.

‘Very old,' she answered briefly.

‘But I thought rocking- chairs were a modern American invention?' said I.

She looked at me apathetically.

‘It is Spanish,' she said, ‘Spanish oak, Spanish leather, Spanish brass, Spanish -.' I did not catch the last word, and she left the room without another.

It was a strange ill- balanced thing, that chair, though so easy and comfortable to sit in. The rockers were long and sharp behind, always lying in wait for the unwary, but cut short in front: and the back was so high and so heavy on top, that what with its weight and the shortness of the front rockers, it tipped forward with an ease and a violence equally astonishing.

This I knew from experience, as it had plunged over upon me during some of our frequent encounters. Hal also was a sufferer, but in spite of our manifold bruises, neither of us would have had the chair removed, for did not she sit in it, evening after evening, and rock there in the golden light of the setting sun.

So, evening after evening, we two fled from our work as early as possible, and hurried home alone, by separate ways, to the dingy street and the glorified window.

I could not endure forever. When Hal came home first, I, lingering in the street below, could see through our window that lovely head and his in close proximity. When I came first, it was to catch perhaps a quick glance from above – a bewildering smile – no more. She was always gone when I reached the room, and the inner door of my chamber irrevocably locked.

At times I even caught the click of the latch, heard the flutter of loose robes on the other side; and sometimes this daily disappointment, this constant agony of hope deferred, would bring me to my knees by that door begging her to open to me, crying to her in every term of passionate endearment and persuasion that tortured heart of man could think to use.

Hal had neither word nor look for me now, save those of studied politeness and cold indifference, and how could I behave otherwise to him, so proven to my face a liar?

I saw him from the street one night, in the broad level sunlight, sitting in that chair, with the beautiful head on his shoulder. It was more than I could bear. If he had won, and won so utterly, I would ask but to speak to her once, and say farewell to both forever. So I heavily climbed the stairs, knocked loudly, and entered at Hal's ‘Come in!' only to find him sitting there alone, smoking – yes, smoking in the chair which but a moment since had held her too!

He had but just lit the cigar, a paltry device to blind my eyes.

‘Look here, Hal,' said I, ‘I can't stand this any longer. May I ask you one thing? Let me see her once, just once, that I may say good- bye, and then neither of you need see me again!'

Hal rose to his feet and looked me straight in the eye. Then he threw that whole cigar out of the window, and walked to within two feet of me.

‘Are you crazy,' he said. ‘I ask her! I! I have never had speech of her in my life! And you -' He stopped and turned away.

‘And I what?' I would have it out now whatever came.

‘And you have seen her day after day – talked with her – I need not repeat all that my eyes have seen!'

‘You need not, indeed,' said I. ‘It would tax even your invention. I have never seen her in this room but once, and then but for a fleeting glimpse – no word. From the street I have seen her often – with you!'

He turned very white and walked from me to the window, then turned again.

‘I have never seen her in this room for even such a moment as you own to. From the street I have seen her often – with you! '

We looked at each other.

‘Do you mean to say,' I inquired slowly, ‘that I did not see you just now sitting in that chair, by that window, with her in your arms?'

‘Stop!' he cried, throwing out his hand with a fierce gesture. It struck sharply on the corner of the chair- back. He wiped the blood mechanically from the three- cornered cut, looking fixedly at me.

‘I saw you,' said I.

‘You did not!' said he.

I turned slowly on my heel and went into my room. I could not bear to tell that man, my more than brother, that he lied.

I sat down on my bed with my head on my hands, and presently I heard Hal's door open and shut, his step on the stair, the front door slam behind him. He had gone, I knew not where, and if he went to his death and a word of mine would have stopped him, I would not have said it. I do not know how long I sat there, in the company of hopeless love and jealousy and hate.

Suddenly, out of the silence of the empty room, came the steady swing and creak of the great chair. Perhaps – it must be! I sprang to my feet and noiselessly opened the door. There she sat by the window, looking out, and – yes – she threw a kiss to some one below. Ah, how beautiful she was! How beautiful! I made a step toward her. I held out my hands, I uttered I know not what – when all at once came Hal's quick step upon the stairs.

She heard it, too, and, giving me one look, one subtle, mysterious, triumphant look, slipped past me and into my room just as Hal burst in. He saw her go. He came straight to me and I thought he would have struck me down where I stood.

‘Out of my way,' he cried. ‘I will speak to her. Is it not enough to see?' – he motioned toward the window with his wounded hand – ‘Let me pass!'

‘She is not there,' I answered. ‘She has gone through into the other room.'

A light laugh sounded close by us, a faint, soft, silver laugh, almost at my elbow.

He flung me from his path, threw open the door, and entered. The room was empty.

‘Where have you hidden her?' he demanded. I coldly pointed to the other door.

‘So her room opens into yours, does it?' he muttered with a bitter smile. ‘No wonder you preferred the "view"! Perhaps I can open it too?' And he laid his hand upon the latch.

I smiled then, for bitter experience had taught me that it was always locked, locked to all my prayers and entreaties. Let him kneel there as I had! But it opened under his hand! I sprang to his side, and we looked into – a closet, two by four, as bare and shallow as an empty coffin!

He turned to me, as white with rage as I was with terror. I was not thinking of him.

‘What have you done with her?' he cried. And then contemptuously – ‘That I should stop to question a liar!'

I paid no heed to him, but walked back into the other room, where the great chair rocked by the window.

He followed me, furious with disappointment, and laid his hand upon the swaying back, his strong fingers closing on it till the nails were white.

‘Will you leave this place?' said he.

‘No,' said I.

‘I will live no longer with a liar and a traitor,' said he.

‘Then you will have to kill yourself,' said I.

With a muttered oath he sprang upon me, but caught his foot in the long rocker, and fell heavily.

So wild a wave of hate rose in my heart that I could have trampled upon him where he lay – killed him like a dog – but with a mighty effort I turned from him and left the room.

When I returned it was broad day. Early and still, not sunrise yet, but full of hard, clear light on roof and wall and roadway. I stopped on the lower floor to find the landlady and announce my immediate departure. Door after door I knocked at, tried and opened; room after room I entered and searched thoroughly; in all that house, from cellar to garret, was no furnished room but ours, no sign of human occupancy. Dust, dust, and cobwebs everywhere. Nothing else.

With a strange sinking of the heart I came back to our own door.

Surely I heard the landlady's slow, even step inside, and that soft, low laugh. I rushed in.

The room was empty of all life; both rooms utterly empty.

Yes, of all life; for, with the love of a lifetime surging in my heart, I sprang to where Hal lay beneath the window, and found him dead.

Dead, and most horribly dead. Three heavy marks – blows – three deep, three-cornered gashes – I started to my feet – even the chair had gone!

Again the whispered laugh. Out of that house of terror I fled desperately.

From the street I cast one shuddering glance at the fateful window.

The risen sun was gilding all the housetops, and its level rays, striking the high panes on the building opposite, shone back in a calm glory on the great chair by the window, the sweet face, down- dropped eyes, and swaying golden head.

Old Water

The lake lay glassy in level golden light. Where the long shadows of the wooded bank spread across it was dark, fathomless. Where the little cliff rose on the eastern shore its bright reflection went down endlessly.

Slowly across the open gold came a still canoe, sent swiftly and smoothly on by well- accustomed arms.

‘How strong! How splendid! Ah! she is like a Valkyr!' said the poet; and Mrs Osgood looked up at the dark bulk with appreciative eyes.

‘You don't know how it delights me to have you speak like that!' she said softly. ‘I feel those things myself, but have not the gift of words. And Ellen is so practical.'

‘She could not be your daughter and not have a poetic soul,' he answered, smiling gravely.

‘I'm sure I hope so. But I have never felt sure! When she was little I read to her from the poets, always; but she did not care for them – unless it was what she called "story poetry." And as soon as she had any choice of her own she took to science.'

‘The poetry is there,' he said, his eyes on the smooth brown arms, now more near. ‘That poise! That motion! It is the very soul of poetry – and the body! Her body is a poem!'

Mrs Osgood watched the accurate landing, the strong pull that brought the canoe over the roller and up into the little boathouse. ‘Ellen is so practical!' she murmured. ‘She will not even admit her own beauty.'

‘She is unawakened,' breathed the poet – ‘Unawakened!' And his big eyes glimmered as with a stir of hope.

‘It's very brave of her, too,' the mother went on. ‘She does not really love the water, and just makes herself go out on it. I think in her heart she's afraid – but will not admit it. O Ellen! Come here dear. This is Mr Pendexter – the Poet.'

Ellen gave her cool brown hand; a little wet even, as she had casually washed them at the water's edge; but he pressed it warmly, and uttered his admiration of her skill with the canoe.

‘O that's nothing,' said the girl. ‘Canoeing's dead easy.'

‘Will you teach it to me?' he asked. ‘I will be a most docile pupil.'

She looked up and down his large frame with a somewhat questioning eye. It was big enough surely, and those great limbs must mean strength; but he lacked something of the balance and assured quickness which speaks of training.

‘Can't you paddle?' she said.

‘Forgive my ignorance – but I have never been in one of those graceful slim crafts. I shall be so glad to try.'

‘Mr Pendexter has been more in Europe than America,' her mother put in hastily, ‘and you must not imagine, my dear, that all men care for these things. I'm sure that if you are interested, my daughter will be very glad to teach you, Mr Pendexter.'

‘Certainly,' said Ellen. ‘I'll teach him in two tries. Want to start tomorrow morning? I'm usually out pretty early.'

‘I shall be delighted,' he said. ‘We will greet Aurora together.'

‘The Dawn, dear,' suggested her mother with an apologetic smile.

‘O yes,' the girl agreed. ‘I recognize Aurora, mama. Is dinner ready?'

‘It will be when you are dressed,' said her mother. ‘Put on your blue frock, dear – the light one.'

‘All right,' said Ellen, and ran lightly up the path.

‘Beautiful! Beautiful!' he murmured, his eyes following her flying figure. ‘Ah, madam! What it must be to you to have such a daughter! To see your own youth – but a moment passed – repeated before your eyes!' And he bent an admiring glance on the outlines of his hostess.

Mrs Osgood appeared at dinner in a somewhat classic gown, her fine hair banded with barbaric gold; and looked with satisfaction at her daughter, who shone like a juvenile Juno in her misty blue. Ellen had her mother's beauty and her father's strength. Her frame was large, her muscles had power under their flowing grace of line. She carried herself like a queen, but wore the cheerful unconscious air of a healthy schoolgirl, which she was.

Her appetite was so hearty that her mother almost feared it would pain the poet, but she soon observed that he too showed full appreciation of her chef's creations. Ellen too observed him, noting with frank disapproval that he ate freely of sweets and creams, and seemed to enjoy the coffee and liqueurs exceedingly.

‘Ellen never takes coffee,' Mrs Osgood explained, as they sat in the luxurious drawing room, ‘she has some notion about training I believe.'

‘Mother! I am training!' the girl protested. ‘Not officially – there's no race on; but I like to keep in good condition. I'm stroke at college, Mr Pindexter.'

‘Pendexter, dear,' her mother whispered.

The big man took his second demitasse, and sat near the girl.

‘I can't tell you how much I admire it,' he said, leaning forward. ‘You are like Nausicaa – like Atalanta – like the women of my dreams!'

She was not displeased with his open admiration – even athletic girls are not above enjoying praise – but she took it awkwardly.

‘I don't believe in dreams,' she said.

‘No,' he agreed, ‘No – one must not. And yet – have you never had a dream that haunts you – a dream that comes again?'

‘I've had bad dreams,' she admitted, ‘horrid ones; but not the same dream twice.'

‘What do you dream of when your dreams are terrible?'

‘Beasts,' she answered promptly. ‘Big beasts that jump at me! And I run and run – ugh!'

Mrs Osgood sipped her coffee and watched them. There was no young poet more promising than this. He represented all that her own girlhood had longed for – all that the highly prosperous mill- owner she married had utterly failed to give. If her daughter could have what she had missed!

‘They say those dreams come from our remote past,' she suggested. ‘Do you believe that, Mr Pendexter?'

‘Yes,' he agreed, ‘from our racial infancy. From those long buried years of fear and pain.'

‘And when we have that queer feeling of having been there before – isn't that the same thing?'

‘We do not know,' said he. ‘Some say it is from a moment's delay in action of one- half of the brain. I cannot tell. To me it is more mysterious, more interesting, to think that when one has that wonderful sudden sense of previous acquaintance it means vague memories of a former life.' And he looked at Ellen as if she had figured largely in his previous existence. ‘Have you ever had that feeling, Miss Osgood?'

The girl laughed rather shamefacedly. ‘I've had it about one thing,' she said. ‘That's why I'm afraid of water.'

‘Afraid of water! You! A water goddess!'

‘O, I don't encourage it, of course. But it's the only thing I ever was nervous about. I've had it from childhood – that horrid feeling!'

She shivered a little, and asked if he wouldn't like some music.

‘Ah! You make music too?'

She laughed gaily. ‘Only with the pianola – or the other machine. Shall I start it?'

‘A moment,' he said. ‘In a moment. But tell me, will you not, of this dream of something terrible? I am so deeply interested.'

‘Why, it isn't much,' she said. ‘I don't dream it, really – it comes when I'm awake. Only two or three times – once when I was about ten or eleven, and twice since. It's water – black, still, smooth water – way down below me. And I can't get away from it. I want to – and then something grabs me – ugh!'

She got up decidedly and went to the music stand. ‘If that's a relic of my past I must have been prematurely cut off by an enraged ape! Anyhow, I don't like water – unless it's wild ocean. What shall I play?'

He meant to rise next morning with the daylight, but failed to awaken; and when he did look out he saw the canoe shooting lightly home in time for breakfast.

She laughed at him for his laziness, but promised a lesson later, and was pleased to find that he could play tennis. He looked well in his white flannels, in fact his appearance was more admirable than his playing, and the girl beat him till he grew almost angry.

Mrs Osgood watched delightedly on occasions where watching was agreeable, and on other occasions she took herself off with various excuses, and left them much together.

He expressed to her privately a question as to whether he was not too heavy for the canoe, but she reassured him.

‘O, no, indeed, Mr Pendexter; it's a specially wide canoe, and has air chambers in it – it can't sink.' Her father had made it for her. ‘He's a heavy man himself, and loves canoeing.'

So the stalwart poet was directed to step softly into the middle, and given the bow paddle.

It grieved him much that he could not see his fair instructress, and he proposed that they change places.

‘No, indeed!' she said. ‘Trust you with the other paddle? – Not yet!'

Could he not at least face her, he suggested. At which she laughed wickedly, and told him he'd better learn to paddle forward before he tried to do it backward.

‘If you want to look at me you might get another canoe and try to follow,' she added, smiling; whereat he declared her would obey orders absolutely.

He sat all across the little rattan bow seat, and rolled up his sleeves as she did. She gave him the paddle, showed him how to hold it, and grinned silently as his mighty strokes swung them to right or left, for all her vigorous steering.

‘Not so hard!' she said. ‘You are stronger than I, and your stroke is so far out you swing me around.'

With a little patience he mastered the art sufficiently to wield a fairly serviceable bow paddle, but she would not trust him with the stern; and not all the beauties of the quiet lake consoled him for losing sight of her. Still, he reflected, she could see him. Perhaps that was why she kept him there in front! – and he sat straighter at the thought.

She did rather enjoy the well proportioned bulk of him, but she had small respect for his lack of dexterity, and felt a real dislike for the heavy fell of black hair on his arms and hands.

He tired of canoeing. One cannot direct speaking glances over one's shoulder, nor tender words; not with good effect, that is. At tennis he found her so steadily victor that he tired of that too. Golf she did not care for; horses he was unfamiliar with; and when she ran the car her hands and eyes and whole attention were on the machine. So he begged for walking.

‘You must having charming walks in these woods,' he said. ‘I own inferiority in many ways – but I can walk!'

‘All right,' she cheerily agreed, and tramped about the country with him, brisk and tireless.

Her mother watched breathlessly. She wholly admired this ox-eyed man with the velvet voice, the mouth so red under his soft mustache. She thought his poetry noble and musical beyond measure. Ellen thought it was ‘no mortal use.'

‘What on earth does he want to make over those old legends for, anyway!' she said, when her mother tried to win her to some appreciation. ‘Isn't there enough to write about today without going back to people who never existed anyhow – nothing but characters out of other people's stories?'

‘They are parts of the world's poetic material, my dear; folk- lore, race- myths. They are among our universal images.'

‘Well, I don't like poetry about universal images, that's all. It's like mummies – sort of warmed over and dressed up!'

‘I am so sorry!' said her mother, with some irritation. ‘Here we are honored with a visit from one of our very greatest poets – perhaps the greatest; and my own child hasn't sense enough to appreciate his beautiful work. You are so like your father!'

‘Well, I can't help it,' said Ellen. ‘I don't like those foolish old stories about people who never did anything useful, and hadn't an idea in their heads except being in love and killing somebody! They had no sense, and no courage, and no decency!'

Her mother tried to win her to some admission of merit in his other work.

‘It's no use, mama! You may have your poet, and get all the esthetic satisfaction you can out of it. And I'll be polite to him, of course. But I don't like his stuff.'

‘Not his "Lyrics of the Day," dear? And "The Woods"?'

‘No, mumsy, not even those. I don't believe he ever saw a sunrise – unless he got up on purpose and set himself before it like a camera! And woods! Why he don't know one tree from another!'

Her mother almost despaired of her; but the poet was not discouraged.

‘Ah! Mrs Osgood! Since you honor me with your confidence I can but thank you and try my fate. It is so beautiful, this budding soul – not opened yet! So close – so almost hard! But when its rosy petals do unfold -'

He did not, however, give his confidence to Mrs Osgood beyond this gentle poetic outside view of a sort of floricultural intent. He told her nothing of the storm of passion which was growing within him; a passion of such seething intensity as would have alarmed that gentle soul exceedingly and make her doubt, perhaps, the wisdom of her selection.

She remained in a state of eager but restrained emotion; saying little to Ellen lest she alarm her, but hoping that the girl would find happiness with this great soul.

The great soul, meanwhile, pursued his way, using every art he knew – and his experience was not narrow – to reach the heart of the brown and ruddy nymph beside him.

She was ignorant and young. Too whole- souled in her indifference to really appreciate the stress he labored under; much less to sympathize. On the contrary she took a mischievous delight in teasing him, doing harm without knowing it, like a playful child. She teased him about his tennis playing, about his paddling, about his driving; allowed that perhaps he might play golf well, but she didn't care for golf herself – it was too slow; mocked even his walking expeditions.

‘He don't want to walk!' she said gaily to her mother one night at dinner. ‘He just wants to go somewhere and arrange himself gracefully under a tree and read to me about Eloise, or Araminta or somebody; all slim and white and wavy and golden- haired; and how they killed themselves for love!'

She laughed frankly at him, and he laughed with her; but his heart was hot and dark within him. The longer he pursued and failed the fiercer was his desire for her. Already he had loved longer than was usual to him. Never before had his overwhelming advances been so lightly parried and set aside.

‘Will you take a walk with me this evening after dinner?' he proposed. ‘There is a most heavenly moon – and I cannot see to read to you. It must be strangely lovely – the moonlight – on your lake, is it not, Mrs Osgood?'

‘It is indeed,' she warmly agreed, looking disapprovingly on the girl, who was still giggling softly at the memory of golden- haired Araminta. ‘Take him on the cliff walk, Ellen, and do try to be more appreciative of beauty!'

‘Yes, mama,' said Ellen, ‘I'll be good.'

She was so good upon the moonlit walk; so gentle and sympathetic, and so honestly tried to find some point of agreement, that his feelings were too much for his judgment, and he seized her hand and kissed it. She pushed him away, too astonished for words.

‘Why, Mr Pendexter! What are you thinking of!'

Then he poured out his heart to her. He told her how he loved her – madly, passionately, irresistably. He begged her to listen to him.

‘Ah! You young Diana! You do not know how I suffer! You are so young, so cold! So heavenly beautiful! Do not be cruel! Listen to me! Say you will be my wife! Give me one kiss! Just one!'

She was young, and cold, and ignorantly cruel. She laughed at him, laughed mercilessly, and turned away.

He followed her, the blood pounding in his veins, his voice shaken with the intensity of his emotions. He caught her hand and drew her toward him again. She broke from him with a little cry, and ran. He followed, hotly, madly; rushed upon her, caught her, held her fast.

‘You shall love me! You shall!' he cried. His hands were hot and trembling, but he held her close and turned her face to his.

‘I will not!' she cried, struggling. ‘Let me go! I hate you, I tell you. I hate you! You are – disgusting!' She pushed as far from him as he could.

They had reached the top of the little cliff opposite the house. Huge dark pines hung over them, their wide boughs swaying softly.

The water lay below in the shadow, smooth and oil- black.

The girl looked down at it, and a sudden shudder shook her tense frame. She gave a low moan and hid her face in her hands.

‘Ah!' he cried. ‘It is your fate! Our fate! We have lived through this before! We will die together if we cannot live together!'

He caught her to him, kissed her madly, passionately, and together they went down into the black water.

‘It's pretty lucky I could swim,' said Ellen, as she hurried home. ‘And he couldn't. The poor man! O, the poor man! He must have been crazy!'

曼斯蒂夫人窗外的景色

/

曼斯蒂夫人窗外的景色谈不上多么引人注目，但至少对她来说，那景色是引人入胜、美丽动人的。曼斯蒂夫人所住之处是纽约一栋寄宿公寓三楼靠后的那个房间。在夜里，人行道上依旧摆放着灰桶[1]，要是昆图斯·库尔提乌斯[2]还活着，人行道砖石之间的缝隙大到他都会感觉吃惊不已[3]。曼斯蒂夫人已故的丈夫以前是一间规模庞大的批发商行里的售货员，因为她的独生女儿嫁到了加利福尼亚，也没钱长途跋涉来纽约探望母亲，所以丈夫死后，就只剩下曼斯蒂夫人孤身一人。或许曼斯蒂夫人也可以搬到西岸和她女儿团聚，可她们到目前为止已经分开多年，丝毫没有融入彼此社交圈的需求了。且长期以来，她俩的交流也仅限于几封敷衍的通信往来，女儿的信字里行间透露着冷漠，曼斯蒂夫人的信回得也困难——因为痛风，她的右手已经变得越来越僵硬。就算她强烈地渴望女儿能够陪伴在旁，可曼斯蒂夫人日渐虚弱的身体，让她就连从街上爬三层楼梯回到自己房内都感到恐惧，这样的状态肯定会让她在尝试如此漫长的旅途前夕犹豫不决，而或许就算不编造这些理由，她也早已理所当然地接受了自己得在纽约独自生活。

当然，她也算不上孤单，因为时不时地，还是会有一些朋友辛苦地爬楼，到她房间来，但是随着年纪的增长，她们来得也越来越少了。曼斯蒂夫人从来都不算是一个很热爱社交的人，丈夫还健在的那些日子里，他的陪伴对曼斯蒂夫人来说就绰绰有余了。多年来，她内心深处一直抱有能够回到乡村里生活的渴望，在那儿搭个鸡舍，再建个花园，但是随着年龄的增长，这个想法已渐渐淡去。这位不善言谈的老女人心中仅存的那一丝柔软之处，留给了植物和动物。或许就是这一丝柔软，让她对自己窗外的景色拥有如此炙热的情感。乍眼一看，这景色即便在最善于发现美的人眼中，恐怕都很难找到任何可取之处。

曼斯蒂夫人所处的有利位置是一个略微突出的弓形窗，她在这里种了一盆常春藤，还有一串看上去不太健康的鳞茎植物。从这里看出去，最先映入眼帘的是自己房间的后院，但她能瞥到的范围十分有限。当然，她还是能看到窗下臭椿树最顶端的那些枝干，也能知道每年荷包牡丹多早就在弯茎上挂出一簇簇粉红的心形花朵。

但她更感兴趣的是后面的院子。因为院子大部分和寄宿公寓相连，长期以来都是又脏乱又嘈杂，在一周的某些日子里，总会挂满各种各样的衣物和磨损的桌布。尽管如此，曼斯蒂夫人还是在自己所俯视的这片远景中找到了许多值得欣赏的地方。的确，院子里有很多石子瓦砾，人行道的缝隙间杂草丛生，春天的时候，除了晾衣绳上零零散散晾着的衣裳间露出的绿叶，没有任何荫蔽之处。曼斯蒂夫人不喜欢院子的这块地方，但她热爱其他部分——绿意盎然的那部分。凌乱的院子已经让她习以为常，那些破烂的木桶、空瓶子，还有没人打扫的小路也不再令她感到恼火。她拥有一种自我愉悦的能力，让自己可以沉浸在眼前景色中美好的那一面。

就在紧邻的圈地里，不是正有一棵木兰花在四月水蓝色的晴空下绽放出它那轮廓分明、洁白如雪的花朵？以及在不远处，每年一到五月，不是还有那淡紫色的紫藤花一浪接着一浪地从篱笆上冒出头来？更远的地方，一棵七叶树从它宽大的扇形叶片上举出了烛台一样淡黄色和粉色的花朵，而就在它对面的院子里，一到六月则会弥漫着丁香花那甜美的香气；它看起来并不打眼，尽管生长环境对它十分不利，却依旧不屈不挠。

如果说曼斯蒂夫人望向窗外，首先注意到的是自然景色，那么除此之外，窗外所有的房子和里面居住的人们的个性，对她来说，则更有吸引力。她非常不喜欢对面医生家最近挂上的那个芥末黄色的窗帘，不过，医生家后面那座房子的老砖块刷上一层新漆的时候，却令她脸上洋溢着喜悦。那座房子的住户并不经常在后窗露脸，可是透过窗户，总能看见他家的用人。曼斯蒂夫人多次表示那是一帮吵吵嚷嚷的荡妇，她了解她们的行为举止，且对此十分反感。但新粉刷房子里安静的厨师则得到了曼斯蒂夫人最深切的同情，女主人总是欺负她，而她在入夜后总会悄悄地去投喂流浪猫。有一次，曼斯蒂夫人的心情被疏忽的女佣给破坏了，女佣足足有两天忘记投喂交由她照看的鹦鹉。到了第三天，尽管右手患有痛风，曼斯蒂夫人还是拿起笔写了封信，信的开头是这样的：“夫人，你的鹦鹉已经三天没有吃饭了……”正在此时，健忘的女佣拿着一杯瓜子出现在了窗前。

但在曼斯蒂夫人更深的思绪中，最让她感到愉悦的是院子深处那道越发狭窄的深景。薄暮时分，当远处褐石尖顶看上去就像是和西边流动的黄晕融为一体时，她喜欢让自己的思绪迷走于多年前欧洲之行的那段模糊记忆当中。在她的想象里，那段回忆现已沦为一片关于朦胧尖塔和梦幻天空的苍白幻影。或许，曼斯蒂夫人内心深处实际上是个艺术家，在任何场合，她都能敏感地留意到普通人所注意不到的颜色变化。在早春的绿意中，她最喜欢的是下雪天的黄昏，在硫黄色天空的映衬下，那错落有致的树枝所拼凑出的黑色格子。她同样享受的还有三月份阳光灿烂的融雪天。每到这时，大地便会一点点从冰雪里探出脑袋，就像是一张白色吸墨纸上散落的墨迹。更美好的是那朦胧的树影，虽然还没长出叶子，但都臃肿起来，不像冬天那样利落。她甚至饶有兴致地观察着远处工厂烟囱的一尾轻烟。当工厂关闭、烟雾消失后，这片风景中也便少了一个细节。

曼斯蒂夫人长时间坐在窗边并不是无所事事。她有时候读书，也织过无数双袜子，可就如同大海包围着孤单的岛屿一样，窗外的景色才真正占据着她的生活，也定义了她的生活。当难得有客人来时，她依旧会沉浸在对面正在清洗的窗户中不愿回神，或者很难从对某位邻居花床中那些绿点点——不知道它们会不会长成风信子——的仔细观察中抽离，而与此同时，她还要假装对访客某个从未谋面的孙子的逸事表示关心。曼斯蒂夫人真正的陪伴来自院子里的居民：那些风信子、木兰花；那只绿色的鹦鹉；那个喂猫的女佣；在芥末黄色窗帘后学习到深夜的医生；还有一同冥想的知己——那飘浮在夕阳之中的教堂塔尖。

四月的一天，曼斯蒂夫人正坐在老地方，手边放着正在织的活儿，眼睛盯着窗外，圆圆的云朵散落在湛蓝色天空中。一阵敲门声后，她的房东太太走了进来。曼斯蒂夫人不太喜欢她的房东，可还是礼貌性地迎房东进了屋。可今天似乎比起往常更难让她把目光从窗外的蓝天和绽放的木兰花上转移到桑普森夫人那张无趣的脸上，曼斯蒂夫人清楚地意识到自己费了很大的力气才把注意力拉回来。

“桑普森夫人，木兰花今年比往年开得要早。”她罕见地因为冲动脱口而出，因为她很少会提到自己生活中感兴趣的事。首先，这话题恐怕对她的访客来说没有任何吸引力，其次，她缺乏表达的能力，就算想要表达也没有办法说出自己的内心感受。

“什么花，曼斯蒂夫人？”房东太太一边问，一边在房间里四处张望，想要找到曼斯蒂夫人说那句话的原因。

“隔壁院子的木兰花——在布莱克的院子里。”曼斯蒂夫人又说了一次。

“真的吗？我都不知道那里有棵木兰。”桑普森夫人一脸不在乎地说。曼斯蒂夫人吃惊地看着她——她竟然不知道隔壁院子有一棵木兰！

“对了，”桑普森夫人继续道，“说起布莱克夫人，我想起来了，房屋扩建下周就要开工了。”

“开什么工？”这次轮到曼斯蒂夫人问了。

“房屋扩建。”桑普森夫人朝着自己忽视的木兰花那个方向点了点头，“你肯定知道布莱克夫人要给她的房子扩建的事儿吧？曼斯蒂夫人，你肯定知道的。我听说一直要把房子扩建到院墙根那儿。我是不知道在这种困难时期她哪儿来的钱能支付得起这么大规模的扩建，但是她总是对盖房子很痴迷。她之前在十七号大街开了一所寄宿公寓，有一次在往外装拱形窗还是干什么的时候差点儿伤着自己，我以为那次能让她彻底断了盖房子的念头，但我猜这大概就像喝酒一样，是种病。无论如何，扩建工程星期一就开始了。”

曼斯蒂夫人脸色变得无比苍白。她说话总是很慢，所以房东太太没留意到她听完自己讲话之后漫长的停顿。最后曼斯蒂夫人说：“你知道扩建要盖多高吗？”

“这是最诡异的地方。扩建的部分要一直盖到和主楼的楼顶一样高，哎呀，怎么会这样？”

曼斯蒂夫人又停顿了一下。“这不会给你带来巨大的不便吗，桑普森夫人？”她问道。

“要我说的确会，但我说了也没有用。据我所知，如果有人想要扩建，没有哪条法律能够阻止他们。”曼斯蒂夫人听到后，安静了下来。“说了也没用，”桑普森夫人又重复了一次，“但如果我是教会成员，扩建的事要是把伊莱扎·布莱克的身体搞坏，我也不会替她难过。好吧，曼斯蒂夫人，再见啦，我很高兴你住得很舒服。”

很舒服——很舒服！剩下老妇人独自一人后，她又转身面对着窗户。那天的景色是多么的美丽啊！蔚蓝的天空上飘着朵朵白云，大地上的万物被天空映衬得那么明净祥和。臭椿刚披上一件淡淡的黄绿色新衣，风信子含苞欲放，而木兰花则比以往任何时候都更像是雪花石膏雕刻出的玫瑰花饰。很快地，紫藤花将要绽放，随后就是七叶树，但这都没她什么事儿了。在她的视线和它们之间，很快就会升起一堵泥灰砖墙，不久就连教堂的塔尖也会消失，而她那洋溢着幸福的世界将会被抹杀殆尽。曼斯蒂夫人把那天晚上送来的餐盘原封不动地退了回去。她在窗前徘徊，直到夕阳在风中消失于暗黄的暮色之中，随后她上床就寝，躺在床上却彻夜未眠。

第二天一大早，她就起床了，站在窗前。窗外下着雨，可即使透过斜挂着的薄纱，窗外的景色依旧散发着它独特的魅力——雨水对树木是十分有益的。她前一天就注意到臭椿上已积满了尘土。

“我当然也可以搬走。”曼斯蒂夫人大声地说，然后从窗口转过身来，环顾了一下她的房间。当然，她也能搬走，正如她也能活生生地被人把皮剥掉一样。但无论经历哪一样，她还能活下来的概率都是微乎其微的。这房间对于她的幸福而言，虽然远没有窗外景色来得重要，但也是她人生的一部分。她在这里住了十七年了，她知道墙纸上的每一处污渍、地毯上的每一个裂缝；光线以某种方式洒落在她的版画上，书架上所有的书本早已变得破旧不堪，她的鳞茎和常春藤已经习惯了它们的窗口，知道该靠着哪个方向更接近阳光。“我们都已经老得搬不动了。”她说。

那天下午就放晴了。外面湿漉漉又亮闪闪的，那一大片蓝色穿透破碎的残云再次现身，臭椿水光闪闪，花坛里的泥土看起来肥沃而温暖。今天是星期四，下个星期一房屋扩建的工程就要开始了。

星期天下午的时候，当布莱克夫人正在地下室忙着收集食材给寄宿客人准备晚餐之际，有人给她送来了一张卡片。这张嵌着黑边的卡片上写着曼斯蒂夫人的名字。

“桑普森夫人那里的一位寄宿客人，我猜可能是想搬家。好吧，黛娜，明年扩建完工后我可以给她一个房间，”布莱克夫人说，“告诉那位女士，我马上就上楼去。”

布莱克夫人发现曼斯蒂夫人站在长长的起居室里，里面摆放着许多小雕像和椅套。在这座房子里，她坐不下来。

布莱克夫人急忙弯下腰打开记账本，这个动作扬起了一团灰尘，然后她朝来客走去。

“很高兴见到你，曼斯蒂夫人，请坐。”女房东的声音十分洪亮，这嗓音绝对出自一位能够负担得起扩建的女人。曼斯蒂夫人没有办法，只能坐下。

“夫人，请问，我有什么能帮到你的吗？”布莱克夫人接着说，“我的房子现在都住满了，不过我打算扩建，而——”

“我想跟你说的就是关于那个扩建的事情。”曼斯蒂夫人突然开口说道，“我是个贫穷的女人，布莱克夫人，而我从来也没多快乐过。我必须先跟你说说我自己的事——这样才能让你理解。”

布莱克夫人吃了一惊，不过很快就镇静下来，顺从地听着这段突如其来的插话。

“我从来没有得到过我想要的，”曼斯蒂夫人接着说，“失望总是一个接着一个到来。多年以来，我一直想住到乡下去，我一直梦想着，可我们一直没能做到。我们的房子没有向阳的窗户，所以我所有的植物都死了。我女儿好多年前结婚搬走了——再说，她和我喜欢的东西从来都不一样。然后我的丈夫去世了，留下我孤单一人。这已经是十七年前的事了。我搬到桑普森夫人那儿，从那以后，我就一直住在那里。你也能看得出来，我变得有点儿虚弱了，而我也不经常出门，只有在天气好的时候，如果我觉得好一点儿才出去。所以你能够理解为什么我经常坐在我的窗户前——就是三楼的后窗。”

“好吧，曼斯蒂夫人，”布莱克夫人慷慨地说，“我向你保证，可以给你一间在后面的房间。新房间，就是扩——”

“但是我不想搬家，我不能搬家，”曼斯蒂夫人几乎要喊了起来，“而我来就是想告诉你，如果你扩建了房子，我的窗户就看不到任何景色了——没有任何景色！你明白吗？”

布莱克夫人以为自己碰到了一个疯子，而她总是听说疯子必须要哄着来。“我的天，我的天，”她一边说一边把椅子往后推了一点儿，“这太糟糕了，不是吗？为什么我从来没想到这一点。肯定的，曼斯蒂夫人，扩建会影响到你窗外的景色。”

“你真的懂？”曼斯蒂夫人惊了一下。

“我当然可以理解。而我对此也非常抱歉。但是，曼斯蒂夫人，你别担心。我想我们能够好好地把这件事给解决了。”

曼斯蒂夫人从她的座椅上站了起来，而布莱克夫人溜向了门口。

“你说解决是什么意思，难道你的意思是我能够说服你改变扩建的主意？噢，布莱克夫人，听我说，我银行里有两千美元的存款，而我能，我知道我能给你一千美元，如果——”曼斯蒂夫人停了下来，泪水滚落到她的脸颊上。

“好吧，好吧，曼斯蒂夫人，你不用担心。”布莱克夫人安抚地说道，“我肯定我们能够解决的。我很抱歉，不能继续待在这里和你聊下去，现在正是一天中最忙的时候，要准备晚——”

布莱克夫人的手已经伸到了门把上，但曼斯蒂夫人突然一下子用力抓住她的手腕。

“你没有给我一个确切的答复。你的意思是你接受了我的提议吗？”

“哎呀，曼斯蒂夫人，我会再考虑一下的，我肯定会的。我无论如何也不会惹你生气的——”

“但我听说施工明天就要开始了。”曼斯蒂夫人非常坚持。

布莱克夫人犹豫了一下：“明天不会开始的，我向你保证，我今天晚上就给那些工人传话。”曼斯蒂夫人把她的手腕抓得更紧了。

“你不会是在骗我吧？”她说。

“不——不，”布莱克夫人结结巴巴地说，“曼斯蒂夫人，你怎么能这么想我呢？”

慢慢地，曼斯蒂夫人紧握的手松开了，她从敞开的门走了出去。“一千美元——”她停在大厅里重复了一次，然后她自己走出门外，一瘸一拐地走下台阶，靠在铸铁栏杆上。

“我的老天爷，”布莱克夫人惊叹着关上了大厅的门，并把门闩上，“我以前从来不知道那个老妇人是个疯子！而她看起来非常安静，也很优雅。”

曼斯蒂夫人当晚睡得很好，但第二天一大早，她就被锤砸的声音吵醒了。她赶紧以最快的速度走到窗前，向外看，发现布莱克夫人的院子里到处都是工人。有的工人把砖块从厨房搬到院子里，其他人则开始动手拆除布莱克夫人房子每层楼都有的老式木阳台装饰。曼斯蒂夫人意识到自己被欺骗了。起初，她想把自己的烦恼告诉桑普森夫人，但很快一股深深的挫败感占据了她的心绪，她回到床上，不再理会外面所发生的一切。

不过到了下午，她觉得自己必须要了解最坏的那一步。她下了床，穿好了衣服。这对她来说是一项艰巨的任务，因为她的双手比往常更加僵硬，而那些钩子和纽扣似乎都在躲着她。

坐在窗前时，她看见窗外工人已经把阳台上半部分拆掉了，而砖块也比早上多了很多。其中一个男人——一个满脸浮肿的工人——捡起了一朵木兰花放在鼻子前闻了闻，然后把花丢在了地上。另一个男人，在搬砖的途中直接踩在这朵花上。

“吉姆，小心点，”一个男人对另外一个抽烟斗的男人喊道，“如果你把火柴扔到这些装满废纸的木桶附近，你还没能反应过来，可能就已经把这个危险的老房子给烧光了。”曼斯蒂夫人把头伸出窗外，看到在木阳台下有几个装了废纸的木桶，还有一些垃圾。

工程终于在暮色降临的时候停了下来。落日是如此完美，玫红色的余晖徘徊于西边的天际，让远处的教堂尖顶更加美轮美奂。当天色变暗的时候，曼斯蒂夫人拉下窗帘，以她一直以来有条不紊的方式点起了灯。她总是亲手把煤油装满再把灯点着，那壶煤油则一直存放在橱柜里一个锌盖架子上。煤油灯亮起来，充满灯光的房间立刻呈现出像平常一样宁静的样子。那些书本、画作以及植物，就像它们的主人一样，在又一个安静的夜晚要准备休息了。而曼斯蒂夫人就像往常一样，把扶手椅拉到桌子边上，开始织起袜子来。

这天夜晚，她没能睡着。变天了，屋外刮起了狂风，乌云密集，遮挡了空中的繁星。曼斯蒂夫人两三次起身，看向窗外，但是除了对面窗户里还亮着的那一两盏灯外，什么都看不清楚。最后这些灯光也熄灭了。曼斯蒂夫人一直在等这些灯光熄灭，此刻她穿起了衣服。她显然是非常着急，因为她只在睡衣外披了一件薄薄的晨衣，头上裹了一条围巾，然后打开壁橱的门，小心翼翼地拿出了那壶煤油。她把一把火柴塞进口袋，更加小心地打开了自己的房门。没过多久，在楼下大厅里汽油灯微弱灯光的引领下，她摸索着走下了黑暗的楼梯，最后到达了楼梯底层，开始更加艰难地朝着漆黑一片的地下室走去。不过她在这里可以移动得更自由一些，因为在这里被听到的风险要小一点儿，而她毫不迟疑地设法打开了通向院子的铁门。她从地下室走出来，当她在晾衣绳下颤抖地摸索前行时，一阵冷风突然袭来。

那天清晨三点钟的时候，一阵火警警报把消防车带到了布莱克夫人的门口，同样也把桑普森夫人那些受到惊吓的房客带到了他们的窗口。布莱克夫人房子后面的木阳台烧起来了，而曼斯蒂夫人也在这群观望着火势的人群当中，她穿着薄薄的晨衣，把头探出了敞开的窗户外边。

不过火很快就被扑灭了，房子里那些惊慌失措的住户，之前穿着单薄的衣服逃出来了，天亮时分又重新回到住处，发现除了碎掉的玻璃窗和被烟熏黑的屋顶之外，房子并没有什么大碍。事实上，这场火最大的受害人是曼斯蒂夫人，第二天早晨，人们发现她气喘吁吁的，患上了肺炎，正如所有人所说，以她这个年纪还穿着晨衣把身子伸出窗外，这个结果也是意料之中的。很容易就能看得出她病得很重，但谁也没想到医生的诊断结果会是如此严重。那天晚上聚集在桑普森夫人桌前的每个人脸色都非常凝重和不安。并没有任何一个房客十分了解曼斯蒂夫人，“她总是独来独往”，正如她们所说，似乎觉得自己比其他房客都要高上一等。但是有人死在这所房子里总归是不太好，正如有位夫人对另外一位所说：“我亲爱的，这也很有可能发生在你我身上。”

但这就发生在了曼斯蒂夫人身上，她正在慢慢死去，就像她曾经活过那样，就算不是孤单一人，也是孤独的。医生派来了一位训练有素的护士，而桑普森太太时不时踩着低沉的步子走过来看看。但对于曼斯蒂夫人来说，这两个人都像是梦中人物一样遥远而虚幻。一整天下来她什么话也没说，但当有人问她女儿住址的时候，她摇了摇头。有时候护士留意到她在聚精会神地听着什么声音，没能听到后，就又昏睡过去了。

第二天天亮的时候，她的状态更差了。护士叫来了桑普森夫人，当她俩朝着这老太太俯下身的时候，她们看到她的嘴唇在动。

“扶我起来，扶我下床。”她轻声说道。

她们用手臂把她撑起来，她用僵硬的手指指向窗户。

“噢，那扇窗户——她想要坐在窗户边。她以前在那里一坐就是一天，”桑普森夫人解释道，“我想，这对她也没什么坏处吧？”

“现在什么都无所谓了。”护士说。

她们把曼斯蒂夫人扶到窗边，把她放在她的椅子上。窗外天刚亮，是一个让人感到喜悦的春日黎明，虽然木兰花和七叶树还在暗影中沉睡，但教堂的尖顶早已染上了一层金色的光芒。布莱克夫人的院子里一片寂静。阳台上烧焦的木头还躺在掉下来的地方。很明显，自从那场火灾后，工人们还没有继续他们的工作。木兰花又开出了几朵雕塑般立体的花朵，窗外的景色毫发无伤。

曼斯蒂夫人呼吸起来很辛苦，每呼吸一次都更加困难。她试图让她们把窗户打开，可她们并没有听懂。如果她能尝一口窗外的空气，臭椿那沁人心脾的芳香，会让她放松很多。可至少窗外的风景还在——教堂尖顶现在金光灿灿的，天空的颜色已经从蓝灰变成湛蓝，一天的开始是从东边到西边一丝丝被点亮的，就连木兰花现在也晒到了阳光。

曼斯蒂夫人的头向后一倒，在微笑中离开了人世。就在那一天，房子的扩建工程又恢复了。

[1]十九世纪纽约人行道旁的灰桶用于丢弃炉灰和各种垃圾。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明的之外，均为译者注。）

[2]罗马历史学家，大概生于一世纪。

[3]昆图斯流传至今的作品少之又少，大部分内容都佚失了，这里用他来做类比，说明人行横道间的空隙之多、缝隙之大。——编者注